<sect1 id="ch09-reboot">
<title>Rebooting the system</title>
<?dbhtml filename="reboot.html" dir="chapter09"?>

<para>Now that all software has been installed, bootscripts have been created, 
it's time to reboot the computer. Before we reboot let's unmount
$LFS/proc and the LFS partition itself by running:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>umount $LFS/proc &amp;&amp;</userinput>
<userinput>umount $LFS</userinput></screen></para>

<para>And you can reboot your system by running something like:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>/sbin/shutdown -r now</userinput></screen></para>

<para>At the LILO: prompt make sure that you tell it to boot 
<emphasis>lfs</emphasis> and not the default entry which will boot your
host system again.</para>

<para>After you have rebooted, your LFS system is ready for use and you
can start adding your own software.</para>

<para>One final thing you may want to do is run lilo, now that you are
booted into LFS. This way you will put the LFS version of LILO in the MBR
rather than the one that's there right now from your host system.
Depending on how old your host distribution is, the LFS version may have
more advanced features you need/could use.</para>
 
<para>Either way, run the following to make the lilo version installed
on LFS active:</para>
 
<para><screen><userinput>/sbin/lilo</userinput></screen></para>
 
<para>If you are wondering: "Well, where to go now?" you'll be glad to
hear that someone has written an LFS hint on the subject at <ulink
url="&hints-root;afterlfs.txt">&hints-root;afterlfs.txt</ulink>.
On a same note, if you are not only newbie to LFS, but also
newbie to Linux in general, you may find the newbie hint at <ulink
url="&hints-root;newbie.txt">&hints-root;newbie.txt</ulink>
 very interesting.</para>
 
<para>Don't forget there are several LFS mailinglists you can subscribe
to if you are in need of help, advice, etc. See
<xref linkend="ch01-maillists"/> for more information.</para>
 
<para>Again, we thank you for using the LFS Book and hope you found this
book useful and worth your time.</para>

</sect1>

