<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>badblocks</command> searches a device (usually a disk
partition) for bad blocks.</para>

<para><command>blkid</command> is a command line utility to locate and
print block device attributes.</para>

<para><command>chattr</command> changes the attributes of files on a
second extended (ext2) filesystem.</para>

<para><command>compile_et</command> is an error table compiler. It
converts a table of error-code names and messages into a C source file
suitable for use with the com_err library.</para>

<para><command>debugfs</command> is a filesystem debugger. It can be
used to examine and change the state of an ext2 filesystem.</para>

<para><command>dumpe2fs</command> prints the super block and blocks group
information for the filesystem present on a given device.</para>

<para><command>e2fsck</command> is used to check, and optionally repair,
second extended (ext2) filesystems, and also ext3 filesystems.</para>

<para><command>e2image</command> is used to save critical ext2 filesystem
data to a file.</para>

<para><command>e2label</command> will display or change the filesystem
label on the ext2 filesystem present on a given device.</para>

<para><command>findfs</command> finds a file system by label or UUID.</para>

<para><command>fsck</command> is used to check, and optionally repair,
filesystems. By default it checks the filesystems listed in
<filename>/etc/fstab</filename></para>

<para><command>logsave</command> saves the output of a command in a logfile.</para>

<para><command>lsattr</command> lists the attributes of files on a second
extended filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mk_cmds</command> converts a table of command names
and help messages into a C source file suitable for use with the
<filename>libss</filename> subsystem library.</para>

<para><command>mke2fs</command> is used to create a second extended
filesystem on the given device.</para>

<para><command>mklost+found</command> is used to create a
<filename>lost+found</filename> directory on a second extended filesystem.
It pre-allocates disk blocks to this directory to lighten the task of e2fsck.</para>

<para><command>resize2fs</command> can be used to enlarge or shrink an
ext2 filesystem.</para>

<para><command>tune2fs</command> is used adjust tunable filesystem
parameters on a second extended filesystem.</para>

<para><command>uuidgen</command> creates new universally unique
identifiers (UUID). Each new UUID can reasonably be considered unique
among all UUIDs created, on the local system and on other systems, in the
past and in the future.</para>

<para><command>libblkid</command> contains routines for device
identification and token extraction.</para>

<para><command>libcom_err</command> is the common error display routine.</para>

<para><command>libe2p</command> is used by dumpe2fs, chattr, and lsattr.</para>

<para><command>libext2fs</command> contains routines to enable user-level
programs to manipulate an ext2 filesystem.</para>

<para><command>libss</command> is used by debugfs.</para>

<para><command>libuuid</command> contains routines for generating unique
identifiers for objects that may be accessible beyond the local system.</para>

</sect2>

