<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>autopoint</command> copies standard gettext infrastructure
files into a source package.</para>

<para><command>config.charset</command> outputs a system-dependent table of
character encoding aliases.</para>

<para><command>config.rpath</command> outputs a system-dependent set of
variables, describing how to set the runtime search path of shared libraries in an
executable.</para>

<para><command>gettext</command> translates a natural language message into
the user's language, by looking up the translation in a message catalog.</para>

<para><command>gettextize</command> copies all standard Gettext files into
the given top-level directory of a package, to begin internationalizing it.</para>

<para><command>hostname</command> displays a network hostname in various
forms.</para>

<para><command>msgattrib</command> filters the messages of a translation
catalog according to their attributes and manipulates the attributes.</para>

<para><command>msgcat</command> concatenates and merges the given
<filename>.po</filename> files.</para>

<para><command>msgcmp</command> compares two <filename>.po</filename>
files to check that both contain the same set of msgid strings.</para>

<para><command>msgcomm</command> finds the messages that are common to
to the given <filename>.po</filename> files.</para>

<para><command>msgconv</command> converts a translation catalog to a
different character encoding.</para>

<para><command>msgen</command> creates an English translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msgexec</command> applies a command to all translations of a
translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msgfilter</command> applies a filter to all translations of a
translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msgfmt</command> generates a binary message catalog from
from a translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>msggrep</command> extracts all messages of a translation
catalog that match a given pattern or belong to some given source files.</para>

<para><command>msginit</command> creates a new  <filename>.po</filename>
file, initializing the meta information with values from the user's
environment.</para>

<para><command>msgmerge</command> combines two raw translations into a
single file.</para>

<para><command>msgunfmt</command> decompiles a binary message catalog
into raw translation text.</para>

<para><command>msguniq</command> unifies duplicate translations in a
translation catalog.</para>

<para><command>ngettext</command> displays native language translations of a
textual message whose grammatical form depends on a number.</para>

<para><command>xgettext</command> extracts the translatable message lines
from the given source files, to make the first translation template.</para>

<para><command>libasprintf</command> defines the autosprintf class which
makes C formatted output routines usable in C++ programs, for use with the
&lt;string&gt; strings and the &lt;iostream&gt; streams.</para>

<para><command>libgettextlib</command> is a private library containing
common routines used by the various gettext programs. They're not meant for
general use.</para>

<para><command>libgettextpo</command> is used to write specialized
programs that process PO files. This library is used when the standard
applications shipped with gettext won't suffice (such as msgcomm, msgcmp,
msgattrib and msgen).</para>

<para><command>libgettextsrc</command> is a private library containing
common routines used by the various gettext programs. They're not meant for
general use.</para>

</sect2>

