<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>agetty</command> opens a tty port, prompts for a login name,
and then invokes the login program.</para>

<para><command>arch</command> reports the machine's architecture.</para>

<para><command>blockdev</command> allows you to call block device ioctls
from the command line.</para>

<para><command>cal</command> displays a simple calender.</para>

<para><command>cfdisk</command> is used to manipulate the partition table
of the given device.</para>

<para><command>chkdupexe</command> finds duplicate executables.</para>

<para><command>col</command> filters out reverse line feeds.</para>

<para><command>colcrt</command> is used to filter nroff output for terminals
that lack some capabilities such as overstriking and half-lines.</para>

<para><command>colrm</command> filters out the given columns.</para>

<para><command>column</command> formats a given file into multiple
columns.</para>

<para><command>ctrlaltdel</command> sets the function of the Ctrl+Alt+Del
 key combination, to a hard or a soft reset.</para>

<para><command>cytune</command> was used to tune the parameters of the
serial line drivers for Cyclades cards.</para>

<para><command>ddate</command> gives the Discordian date, or converts the
given Gregorian date to a Discordian one.</para>

<para><command>dmesg</command> dumps the kernel boot messages.</para>

<para><command>elvtune</command> can be used to tune the performance
and interactiveness of a block device.</para>

<para><command>fdformat</command> low-level formats a floppy disk.</para>

<para><command>fdisk</command> could be used to manipulate the partition
table of the given device.</para>

<para><command>fsck.cramfs</command> performs a consistency check on the
Cramfs filesystem on the given device.</para>

<para><command>fsck.minix</command> performs a consistency check on the
Minix filesystem on the given device.</para>

<para><command>getopt</command> parses options in the given command line.</para>

<para><command>hexdump</command> dumps the given file in hexadecimal, or
in another given format.</para>

<para><command>hwclock</command> is used to read or set the system's
hardware clock (also called the RTC or BIOS clock).</para>

<para><command>ipcrm</command> removes the given IPC resource.</para>

<para><command>ipcs</command> provides IPC status information.</para>

<para><command>isosize</command> reports the size of an iso9660
filesystem.</para>

<para><command>kill</command> terminates the specified process.</para>

<para><command>line</command> copies a single line.</para>

<para><command>logger</command> enters the given message into the system
log.</para>

<para><command>look</command> displays lines that begin with the given
string.</para>

<para><command>losetup</command> is used to set up and control loop devices.</para>

<para><command>mcookie</command> generates magic cookies, 128-bit random
hexadecimal numbers, for xauth.</para>

<para><command>mkfs</command> is used to build a filesystem on a device
(usually a harddisk partition).</para>

<para><command>mkfs.bfs</command> creates an SCO bfs filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mkfs.cramfs</command> creates a cramfs filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mkfs.minix</command> creates a Minix filesystem.</para>

<para><command>mkswap</command> initializes the given device or file to be
used as a swap area.</para>

<para><command>more</command> is a filter for paging through text one
screenful at a time. But less is much better.</para>

<para><command>mount</command> attaches the filesystem on the given device
to the given directory in the system's file tree.</para>

<para><command>namei</command> shows the symbolic links in the given
pathnames.</para>

<para><command>pg</command> displays a text file one screenful at a
time.</para>

<para><command>pivot_root</command> makes the given filesystem the new
root filesystem of the current process.</para>

<para><command>ramsize</command> could be used to set the size of the
RAM disk in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>rdev</command> could be used to query and set the root
device and other things in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>readprofile</command> reads kernel profiling information.</para>

<para><command>rename</command> renames the given files, replacing a given
string with another.</para>

<para><command>renice</command> is used to alter the priority of running
processes.</para>

<para><command>rev</command> reverses the lines of a given file.</para>

<para><command>rootflags</command> could be used to set the rootflags
in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>script</command> makes a typescript of a terminal
session, of everything printed to the terminal.</para>

<para><command>setfdprm</command> sets user-provided floppy disk
parameters.</para>

<para><command>setsid</command> runs the given program in a new session.</para>

<para><command>setterm</command> is used to set terminal attributes.</para>

<para><command>sfdisk</command> is a disk partition table manipulator.</para>

<para><command>swapdev</command> could be used to set the swap device
in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>swapoff</command> disables devices and files for paging
and swapping.</para>

<para><command>swapon</command> enables devices and files for paging
and swapping.</para>

<para><command>tunelp</command> is used to tune the parameters of the
line printer.</para>

<para><command>ul</command> is a filter for translating underscores into
escape sequences indicating underlining for the terminal in use.</para>

<para><command>umount</command> disconnects a filesystem from the
system's file tree.</para>

<para><command>vidmode</command> could be used to set the video mode
in a bootable image.</para>

<para><command>whereis</command> reports the location of binary, the
source, and the manual page for the given command.</para>

<para><command>write</command> sends a message to the given user. That is,
if that user has not disabled such messages.</para>

</sect2>

