<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<sect1 id="mksqoverview">
<title>Overview of mksquashfs</title>

<sect2 id="mksqusing">
<title>Using mksquashfs</title>

<para>
The <command>mksquashfs</command> tool can be used for creating new squashed file systems, as
well as for appending new data to existing squashed file systems.
</para>

<para>
The general format for <command>mksquashfs</command> from the command-line is:
</para>

<programlisting>
	bash# mksquashfs source1 source2 ... destination [options]
</programlisting>

<para>
<emphasis>source</emphasis> items can be files and directories with mixed relative/absolute paths;
<emphasis>destination</emphasis> can be regular files (thus, you will have a file system image on
your disk), or a block device, such as <filename>/dev/fd0</filename> or <filename>/dev/hda3</filename>.
</para>

<para>
When the new files are added to the new file system or appended to an existing one,
<command>mksquashfs</command> will automatically rename files with duplicate names:
if two or more files named <filename>text</filename> will appear in the same
resulting directory, the second file will be renamed to
<filename>text_1</filename>, third one to <filename>text_2</filename> and so on.
Additionally, duplicate files will be removed, so there will be only one physical instance.
</para>

<para>
If <emphasis>destination</emphasis> has a pre-existing SquashFS
file system on it, by default, the new <emphasis>source</emphasis> items will be appended to existing root directory.
Examine the options table below to force <command>mksquashfs</command> to overwrite the whole destination
and/or change the way new source items are added.
</para>

<para>
If a single source file or directory is given, it becomes the root in a newly created file system. If two
or more source files and/or directories are given, they will all become sub-items in the root of
the new file system.
</para>

<para>
See the next section for more details about <command>mksquashfs</command> options.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="mksqoptions">
<title>Command-line options</title>

<para>
All possible options for <command>mksquashfs</command> are shown in the table below.
</para>

<table frame="all">

<title><command>mksquashfs</command> command-line options</title>

<tgroup cols="2">

<thead>
<row>
<entry>Option</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>

<tbody>

<row>
<entry><command>-info</command></entry>
<entry>print files, their original size and compression ratio, as they are added to the file system</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-version</command></entry>
<entry>print the version, copyright and licence message</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-e &lt;files/directories to exclude&gt;</command></entry>
<entry>specify which files and/or directories to omit
from the new file system that is to be created</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-ef &lt;file&gt;</command></entry>
<entry>specify a <filename>file</filename> which contains the list of
files/directories to exclude</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-noI</command> or <command>-noInodeCompression</command></entry>
<entry>do not compress the inode table</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-noD</command> or <command>-noDataCompression</command></entry>
<entry>do not compress the data</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-b [block size]</command></entry>
<entry>use [block size] filesystem block size (32 Kbytes default) - this can be either 512, 1024, 2048, 4096, 8192, 16384 or 32768</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-nopad</command></entry>
<entry>do not pad the resulting file system to a multiple of 4 KBytes</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-be</command> or <command>-le</command></entry>
<entry>force a big or little endian file system, respectively</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-check-data</command></entry>
<entry>enable additional file system checks</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-keep-as-directory</command></entry>
<entry>if the source is a single directory, force this directory to be a subdirectory of the root in the created file system</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-noappend</command></entry>
<entry>if the destination file/device already contains a squashed file system, overwrite it, rather than append the new data to an existing file system.</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>-root-becomes [name]</command></entry>
<entry>can be used while appending to a pre-existing squashed file system, it will make a new root, and [name] directory will contain all pre-existing files/directories.
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>

</tgroup>

</table>

<para>
In most cases, you should leave all compression/block options by default, as they allow <command>mksquashfs</command> to achieve
the best possible compression ratios.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>
