<sect1 id="etc">
  <title>/etc</title>

  <para>This is the nerve center of your system, it contains all system
  related configuration files in here or in its sub-directories. A
  &#34;configuration file&#34; is defined as a local file used to control 
  the operation of a program; it must be static and cannot be an executable binary.
  For this reason, it&#39;s a good idea to backup this directory regularly. It will
  definitely save you a lot of re-configuration later if you re-install or
  lose your current installation. Normally, no binaries should be or are
  located here.</para>

  <para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/</term><listitem><para>This
  directory tree contains all the configuration files for the X Window System.
  Users should note that many of the files located in this directory are
  actually symbolic links to the /usr/X11R6 directory tree. Thus, the
  presence of these files in these locations can not be certain.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/XF86Config,
  /etc/X11/XF86Config-4</term><listitem><para>The &#39;X&#39; configuration
  file. Most modern distributions possess hardware autodetection systems that
  enable automatic creation of a valid file. Should autodetection fail a
  configuration file can also be created manually provided that you have
  sufficient knowledge about your system. It would be considered prudent not
  to attempt to type out a file from beginning to end. Rather, use common
  configuration utilities such as xf86config, XF86Setup and xf86cfg to create
  a workable template. Then, using suitable documentation commence
  optimization through intuition and/or trial and error. Options that can be
  configured via this file include X modules to be loaded on startup,
  keyboard, mouse, monitor and graphic chipset type. Often, commercial
  distributions will include their own X configuration utilities such as
  XDrake on Mandrake and also Xconfiguration on Redhat. Below is a sample X
  configuration file from the reference system</para>

<para><screen>
### BEGIN DEBCONF SECTION
# XF86Config-4 (XFree86 server configuration file) generated by dexconf, the
# Debian X Configuration tool, using values from the debconf database.
#
# Edit this file with caution, and see the XF86Config-4 manual page.
# (Type &#34;man XF86Config-4&#34; at the shell prompt.)
#
# If you want your changes to this file preserved by dexconf, only 
# make changes
# before the &#34;### BEGIN DEBCONF SECTION&#34; line above, and/or after the
# &#34;### END DEBCONF SECTION&#34; line below.
#
# To change things within the debconf section, run the command:
#   dpkg-reconfigure xserver-xfree86
# as root.  Also see &#34;How do I add custom sections to a dexconf-
# generated
# XF86Config or XF86Config-4 file?&#34; in /usr/share/doc/xfree86-
# common/FAQ.gz.

Section &#34;Files&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;unix/:7100&#34;                        
# local font server
        # if the local font server has problems, 
# we can fall back on these
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/misc&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/cyrillic&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi/:unscaled&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi/:unscaled&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/Type1&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/Speedo&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi&#34;
        FontPath        &#34;/usr/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;Module&#34;
        Load        &#34;GLcore&#34;
        Load        &#34;bitmap&#34;
        Load        &#34;dbe&#34;
        Load        &#34;ddc&#34;
        Load        &#34;dri&#34;
        Load        &#34;extmod&#34;
        Load        &#34;freetype&#34;
        Load        &#34;glx&#34;
        Load        &#34;int10&#34;
        Load        &#34;pex5&#34;
        Load        &#34;record&#34;
        Load        &#34;speedo&#34;
        Load        &#34;type1&#34;
        Load        &#34;vbe&#34;
        Load        &#34;xie&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;InputDevice&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Generic Keyboard&#34;
        Driver                &#34;keyboard&#34;
        Option                &#34;CoreKeyboard&#34;
        Option                &#34;XkbRules&#34;        &#34;xfree86&#34;
        Option                &#34;XkbModel&#34;        &#34;pc104&#34;
        Option                &#34;XkbLayout&#34;        &#34;us&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;InputDevice&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Configured Mouse&#34;
        Driver                &#34;mouse&#34;
        Option                &#34;CorePointer&#34;
        Option                &#34;Device&#34;                &#34;/dev/psaux&#34;
        Option                &#34;Protocol&#34;                &#34;NetMousePS/2&#34;
        Option                &#34;Emulate3Buttons&#34;        &#34;true&#34;
        Option                &#34;ZAxisMapping&#34;                &#34;4 5&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;InputDevice&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Generic Mouse&#34;
        Driver                &#34;mouse&#34;
        Option                &#34;SendCoreEvents&#34;        &#34;true&#34;
        Option                &#34;Device&#34;                &#34;/dev/input/mice&#34;
        Option                &#34;Protocol&#34;                &#34;ImPS/2&#34;
        Option                &#34;Emulate3Buttons&#34;        &#34;true&#34;
        Option                &#34;ZAxisMapping&#34;                &#34;4 5&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;Device&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Generic Video Card&#34;
        Driver                &#34;nv&#34;
#        Option                &#34;UseFBDev&#34;                &#34;true&#34;
        Option                &#34;UseFBDev&#34;                &#34;false&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;Monitor&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Generic Monitor&#34;
        HorizSync        30-38
        VertRefresh        43-95
        Option                &#34;DPMS&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;Screen&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Default Screen&#34;
        Device                &#34;Generic Video Card&#34;
        Monitor                &#34;Generic Monitor&#34;
        DefaultDepth        16
        SubSection &#34;Display&#34;
                Depth                1
                Modes                &#34;800x600&#34; &#34;640x480&#34;
        EndSubSection
        SubSection &#34;Display&#34;
                Depth                4
                Modes                &#34;800x600&#34; &#34;640x480&#34;
        EndSubSection
        SubSection &#34;Display&#34;
                Depth                8
                Modes                &#34;800x600&#34; &#34;640x480&#34;
        EndSubSection
        SubSection &#34;Display&#34;
                Depth                15
                Modes                &#34;800x600&#34; &#34;640x480&#34;
        EndSubSection
        SubSection &#34;Display&#34;
                Depth                16
                Modes                &#34;800x600&#34; &#34;640x480&#34;
        EndSubSection
        SubSection &#34;Display&#34;
                Depth                24
                Modes                &#34;800x600&#34; &#34;640x480&#34;
        EndSubSection
EndSection

Section &#34;ServerLayout&#34;
        Identifier        &#34;Default Layout&#34;
        Screen                &#34;Default Screen&#34;
        InputDevice        &#34;Generic Keyboard&#34;
        InputDevice        &#34;Configured Mouse&#34;
        InputDevice        &#34;Generic Mouse&#34;
EndSection

Section &#34;DRI&#34;
        Mode        0666
EndSection

### END DEBCONF SECTION
</screen></para>

  <para>As you can see, the layout of the file is quite simple
  and tends to be quite standard across most distributions. At the top are the
  locations of the various font files for X (note - X will not start if you do
  not specify a valid font), next is the &#34;Modules&#34; section. It details
  what modules are to be loaded upon startup. The most well known extensions
  are probably GLX (required for 3D rendering of graphics and games) and
  Xinerama which allows users to expand their desktop over several monitors.
  Next are the various &#34;Device&#34; sections which describe the type of
  hardware you have. Improper configuration of these subsections can lead to
  heartache and trauma with seemingly misplaced keys, bewitched mice and also
  constant flashing as X attempts to restart in a sometimes never ending loop.
  In most cases when all else fails the vesa driver seems to be able to
  initialise most modern video cards. In the &#34;Screen&#34; section it is
  possible to alter the default startup resolution and depth. Quite often it
  is possible to alter these attributes on the fly by using the alt-ctrl-+ or
  alt-ctrl- set of keystrokes. Lastly are the &#34;ServerLayout&#34; and
  &#34;DRI&#34; sections. Users will almost never touch the &#34;DRI&#34;
  section and only those who wish to utilise the Xinerama extensions of X will
  require having to change any of the ServerLayout options.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/Xmodmap</term><listitem><para>In
  general your default keyboard mapping comes from your X server setup. If
  this setup is insufficient and you are unwilling to go through the process
  of reconfiguration and/or you are not the superuser you&#39;ll need to use
  the xmodmap program. This is the utility&#39;s global configuration file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/xkb/</term><listitem><para>The
  various symbols, types, geometries of keymaps that the X server supports can
  be found in this directory tree.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/lbxproxy/</term><listitem><para>Low
  Bandwidth X (LBX) proxy server configuration files. Applications that would
  like to take advantage of the Low Bandwidth extension to X (LBX) must make
  their connections to an lbxproxy. These applications need know nothing about
  LBX, they simply connect to the lbxproxy as if it were a regular X server.
  The lbxproxy accepts client connections, multiplexes them over a single
  connection to the X server, and performs various optimizations on the X
  protocol to make it faster over low bandwidth and/or high latency
  connections. It should be noted that such compression will not increase the
  pace of rendering all that much. Its primary purpose is to reduce network
  load and thus increase overall network latency. A competing project called
  DXPC (Differential X Protocol Compression) has been found to be more
  efficient at this task. Studies have shown though that in almost all cases
  ssh tunneling of X will produce far better results than through any of
  these specialised pieces of software.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/proxymngr/</term><listitem><para>X
  proxy services manager initialisation files. proxymngr is responsible for
  resolving requests from xfindproxy (in the xbase-clients package) and other
  similar clients, starting new proxies when appropriate, and keeping track of
  all the available proxy services.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/xdm/</term><listitem><para>X
  display manager configuration files. xdm manages a collection of X servers,
  which may be on the local host or remote machines. It provides services
  similar to those provided by init, getty, and login on character-based
  terminals: prompting for login name and password, authenticating the user,
  and running a session. xdm supports XDMCP (X Display Manager Control
  Protocol) and can also be used to run a chooser process which presents the
  user with a menu of possible hosts that offer XDMCP display management. If
  the xutils package is installed, xdm can use the sessreg utility to register
  login sessions to the system utmp file; this, however, is not necessary for
  xdm to function.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/xdm/xdm-config</term><listitem><para>This
  is the master &#39;xdm&#39; configuration file. It determines where all
  other &#39;xdm&#39; configuration files will be located. It is almost
  certain to be left undisturbed.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/gdm/</term><listitem><para>GNOME
  Display Manager configuration files. gdm provides the equivalent of a
  &#34;login:&#34; prompt for X displays- it pops up a login window and starts
  an X session. It provides all the functionality of xdm, including XDMCP
  support for managing remote displays. The greeting window is written using
  the GNOME libraries and hence looks like a GNOME application- even to the
  extent of supporting themes! By default, the greeter is run as an
  unprivileged user for security.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf</term><listitem><para>This
  is the primary configuration file for GDM. Through it, users can specify
  whether they would like their system to automatically login as a certain
  user, background startup image and also if they would like to run their
  machine as somewhat of a terminal server by using the XDMCP protocol.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/fonts</term><listitem><para>Home
  of xfs fonts.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/fs/</term><listitem><para>X
  font server configuration files. xfs is a daemon that listens on a network
  port and serves X fonts to X servers (and thus to X clients). All X servers
  have the ability to serve locally installed fonts for themselves, but xfs
  makes it possible to offload that job from the X server, and/or have a
  central repository of fonts on a networked machine running xfs so that all
  the machines running X servers on a network do not require their own set of
  fonts. xfs may also be invoked by users to, for instance, make available X
  fonts in user accounts that are not available to the X server or to an
  already running system xfs.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/fs/config</term><listitem><para>This
  is the &#39;xfs&#39; initialisation file. It specifies the number of clients
  that are allowed to connect to the &#39;xfs&#39; server at any one time, the
  location of log files, default resolution, the location of the fonts, etc.</para>

<para><screen>	
# font server configuration file
# $Xorg: config.cpp,v 1.3 2000/08/17 19:54:19 cpqbld Exp $

# allow a maximum of 10 clients to connect to this font server
client-limit = 10
# when a font server reaches its limit, start up a new one
clone-self = on
# log messages to /var/log/xfs.log (if syslog is not used)
error-file = /var/log/xfs.log
# log errors using syslog
use-syslog = on
# turn off TCP port listening (Unix domain connections are still permitted)
no-listen = tcp
# paths to search for fonts
catalogue = /usr/lib/X11/fonts/misc/,/usr/lib/X11/fonts/cyrillic/,
/usr/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi/:unscaled,/usr/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi/:unscaled,
/usr/lib/X11/fonts/Type1/,/usr/lib/X11/fonts/CID,
/usr/lib/X11/fonts/Speedo/,/usr/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi/,
/usr/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi/
# in decipoints
default-point-size = 120
# x1,y1,x2,y2,...
default-resolutions = 100,100,75,75

# font cache control, specified in kB
cache-hi-mark = 2048
cache-low-mark = 1433
cache-balance = 70
</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/twm</term><listitem><para>Home
  of configuration files for twm. The original Tabbed Window Manager.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/xinit/</term><listitem><para>xinit
  configuration files. &#39;xinit&#39; is a configuration method of starting
  up an X session that is designed to used as part of a script. Normally, this
  is used at larger sites as part of a tailored login process.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/X11/xinit/xinitrc</term><listitem><para>Global
  xinitrc file, used by all X sessions started by xinit (startx). Its
  usage is of course overridden by a .xinitrc file located in the home
  directory of a user.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/adduser.conf</term><listitem><para>&#39;adduser&#39;
  configuration. The adduser command can create new users, groups and add
  existing users to existing groups. Adding users with adduser is much easier
  than adding them by hand. Adduser will choose appropriate UID and GID
  values, create a home directory, copy skeletal user configuration from
  /etc/skel, allow you to set an initial password and the GECOS field.
  Optionally a custom script can be executed after this commands. See
  adduser(8) and adduser.conf(5) for full documentation.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/adjtime</term><listitem><para>Has
  parameters to help adjust the software (kernel) time so that it matches the
  RTC.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/aliases</term><listitem><para>This
  is the aliases file - it says who gets mail for whom. It was originally
  generated by `eximconfig&#39;, part of the exim package distributed with
  Debian, but it may edited by the mail system administrator. See exim info
  section for details of the things that can be configured here. An aliases
  database file (aliases.db) is built from the entries in the aliases files by
  the newaliases utility.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/alternatives</term><listitem><para>It
  is possible for several programs fulfilling the same or similar functions to
  be installed on a single system at the same time. For example, many systems
  have several text editors installed at once. This gives choice to the users
  of a system, allowing each to use a different editor, if desired, but makes
  it difficult for a program to make a good choice of editor to invoke if the
  user has not specified a particular preference.</para><para>The alternatives
  system aims to solve this problem. A generic name in the filesystem is
  shared by all files providing interchangeable functionality. The
  alternatives system and the system administrator together determine which
  actual file is referenced by this generic name. For example, if the text
  editors ed(1) and nvi(1) are both installed on the system, the alternatives
  system will cause the generic name /usr/bin/editor to refer to /usr/bin/nvi
  by default. The system administrator can override this and cause it to refer
  to /usr/bin/ed instead, and the alternatives system will not alter this
  setting until explicitly requested to do so.</para><para>The generic name is
  not a direct symbolic link to the selected alternative. Instead, it is a
  symbolic link to a name in the alternatives directory, which in turn is a
  symbolic link to the actual file referenced. This is done so that the system
  administrator&#39;s changes can be confined within the /etc directory.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/apt</term><listitem><para>
This is Debian's next generation front-end for the dpkg package manager. It provides the apt-get utility and APT dselect method that provides a simpler, safer way to install and upgrade packages. APT features complete installation ordering, multiple source capability and several other unique features, see the Users Guide in /usr/share/doc/apt/guide.text.gz
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/apt/sources.list</term><listitem><para><screen>
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-7 (20020718)]/
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-6 (20020718)]/
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-5 (20020718)]/
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-4 (20020718)]/
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-3 (20020718)]/ 
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-2 (20020718)]/ 
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main
deb cdrom:[Debian GNU/Linux 3.0 r0 _Woody_ - Official i386 Binary-1 (20020718)]/ 
          unstable contrib main non-US/contrib non-US/main

# deb http://security.debian.org/ stable/updates main
</screen></para>

  <para>
  Contains a list of apt-sources from which packages may be installed via APT.
  </para>

  </listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>/etc/asound.conf</term><listitem><para>ALSA
  (Advanced Linux Sound Architecture) configuration file. It is normally
  created via alsactl or other third-party sound configuration utilities that
  may be specific to a distribution such as sndconfig from Redhat.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/at.deny</term><listitem><para>Users
  denied access to the at daemon. The &#39;at&#39; command allows user to
  execute programs at an arbitrary time.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/autoconf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  files for autoconf. &#39;autoconf&#39; creates scripts to configure source
  code packages using templates. To create configure from configure.in, run
  the autoconf program with no arguments. autoconf processes configure.ac with
  the m4 macro processor, using the Autoconf macros. If you give autoconf an
  argument, it reads that file instead of configure.ac and writes the
  configuration script to the standard output instead of to configure. If you
  give autoconf the argument -, it reads the standard input instead of
  configure.ac and writes the configuration script on the standard output.</para><para>The
  Autoconf macros are defined in several files. Some of the files are
  distributed with Autoconf; autoconf reads them first. Then it looks for the
  optional file acsite.m4 in the directory that contains the distributed
  Autoconf macro files, and for the optional file aclocal.m4 in the current
  directory. Those files can contain your site&#39;s or the package&#39;s own
  Autoconf macro definitions. If a macro is defined in more than one of the
  files that autoconf reads, the last definition it reads overrides the
  earlier ones.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/bash.bashrc</term><listitem><para>System
  wide functions and aliases&#39; file for interactive bash shells.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/bash_completion</term><listitem><para>Programmable
  completion functions for bash 2.05a.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/chatscripts/provider</term><listitem><para>This
  is the chat script used to dial out to your default service provider.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/cron.d,
  /etc/cron.daily, /etc/cron.weekly, /etc/cron.monthly</term><listitem><para>These
  directories contain scripts to be executed on a regular basis by the cron
  daemon.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/crontab</term><listitem><para>&#39;cron&#39;
  configuration file. This file is for the cron table to setup the automatic
  running of system routines. A cron table can also be established for
  individual users. The location of these user cron table files will be
  explained later on.</para>
<para><screen>
# /etc/crontab: system-wide crontab
# Unlike any other crontab you don&#39;t have to run the `crontab&#39;
# command to install the new version when you edit this file.
# This file also has a username field, that none of the other crontabs do.

SHELL=/bin/sh
PATH=/usr/local/sbin:/usr/local/bin:/sbin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/usr/bin

# m h dom mon dow user command
25 6 * * * root test -e /usr/sbin/anacron || run-parts --report /etc/cron.daily
47 6 * * 7 root test -e /usr/sbin/anacron || run-parts --report /etc/cron.weekly
52 6 1 * * root test -e /usr/sbin/anacron || run-parts --report /etc/cron.monthly
#
</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>/etc/csh.login</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .login file for csh(1). This file is sourced on all invocations of the
  shell. It contains commands that are to be executed upon login and sometimes
  aliases also.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/csh.logout</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .logout file for csh(1). This file is sourced on all invocations of the
  shell. It contains commands that are to be executed upon logout.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/csh.cshrc</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .cshrc file for csh(1). This file is sourced on all invocations of the
  shell. This file should contain commands to set the command search path,
  plus other important environment variables. This file should not contain
  commands that produce output or assume the shell is attached to a tty.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/cups</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  files for the Common UNIX Printing System (CUPS). Files here are used to
  define client-specific parameters, such as the default server or default
  encryption settings.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/deluser.conf</term><listitem><para>&#39;deluser&#39;
  configuration files. The deluser command can remove users and groups and
  remove users from a given group. Deluser can optionally remove and backup
  the user&#39;s home directory and mail spool or all files on the system
  owned by him. Optionally a custom script can also be executed after each of
  the commands.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/devfs</term><listitem><para>
  This daemon sets up the /dev filesystem for use. It creates required
  symbolic links in /dev and also creates (if so configured, as is the
  default) symbolic links to the "old" names for devices.
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/devfs/conf.d/</term><listitem><para>&#39;devfsd&#39;
  configuration files. This daemon sets up the /dev filesystem for use. It
  creates required symbolic links in /dev and also creates (if so configured,
  as is the default) symbolic links to the &#34;old&#34; names for devices.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/dhclient.conf,
  /etc/dhclient-script</term><listitem><para>&#39;dhclient&#39; configuration
  file and &#39;dhclient&#39; script files respectively. It configures your
  system so that it may act as a client on a DHCP based network. It is
  essential to connect to the Internet nowadays.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/dict.conf</term><listitem><para><screen>
#  /etc/dict.conf Written by Bob Hilliard &#60;hilliard@debian.org&#62;
#  1998/03/20.  Last revised Sun, 22 Nov 1998 18:10:04 -0500 This is
#  the configuration file for /usr/bin/dict.  In most cases only the
#  server keyword need be specified.  

#  This default configuration will try to access a dictd server on
#  the local host, failing that, it will try the public server.  In
#  many cases this will be slow, so you should comment out the line 
#  for the server that you don&#39;t want to use. To use any other 
#  server, enter its IP address in place of &#34;dict.org&#34;.  

#  Refer to the dict manpage (man dict) for other options that could
#  be inserted in here.

server localhost 
server dict.org
</screen></para>
<para>
dict  is  a  client  for  the  Dictionary  Server  Protocol  (DICT), a TCP transaction based
query/response protocol that provides access to dictionary definitions from a set of natural
language dictionary databases.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>/etc/dosemu.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for the Linux DOS Emulator. DOSEMU is a PC Emulator application that
  allows Linux to run a DOS operating system in a virtual x86 machine. This
  allows you to run many DOS applications. It includes the FreeDOS kernel,
  color text and full keyboard emulation (via hotkeys) via terminal,
  built-in X support, IBM character set font, graphics capability
  at the console with most compatible video cards, DPMI support so you can
  run DOOM, CDROM support, builtin IPX and pktdrvr support. Note -
  &#39;dosemu&#39; is simply a ported version of Corel&#39;s own PC-DOS.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/email-addresses</term><listitem><para>Part
  of the exim package. This file contains email addresses to use for outgoing
  mail. Any local part not in here will be qualified by the system domain as
  normal. It should contain lines of the form:
  
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>

  <para><screen>
  user: someone@isp.com
  otheruser: someoneelse@anotherisp.com
  </screen></para>
  
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  Exim  is an MTA that is considered to be rather easier to configure than smail or
  sendmail. It is a drop-in replacement for sendmail, mailq and rsmtp.
  Advanced features include the ability to reject connections from known spam
  sites, and an extremely efficient queue processing algorithm.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/esound.conf</term><listitem><para>ESD
  configuration files. The Enlightened sound daemon is designed to mix
  together several digitized audio streams for playback by a single device.
  Like nasd, artsd and rplay it also has the capability to play sounds
  remotely.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>/etc/exports</term><listitem><para>The
  control list of systems who want to access the system via NFS, a the list of
  directories that you would like to share and the permissions allocated on
  each share.</para>
  <para><screen>
  # /etc/exports: the access control list for filesystems which may be
  # exported to NFS clients.  See exports(5).
  ## LTS-begin ##

  #
  # The lines between the &#39;LTS-begin&#39; and the &#39;LTS-end&#39; were added
  # on: Sun Feb 23 05:54:17 EST 2003 by the ltsp installation script.
  # For more information, visit the ltsp homepage
  # at http://www.ltsp.org
  #

  /opt/ltsp/i386                  192.168.0.0/255.255.255.0(ro,no_root_squash)
  /var/opt/ltsp/swapfiles         192.168.0.0/255.255.255.0(rw,no_root_squash)

  #
  # The following entries need to be uncommented if you want
  # Local App support in ltsp
  #
  #/home                  192.168.0.0/255.255.255.0(rw,no_root_squash)

  ## LTS-end ##
</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>/etc/fdprm</term><listitem><para>Floppy
  disk parameter table. Describes what different floppy disk formats look
  like. Used by setfdprm.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/fstab</term><listitem><para>The
  configuration file for &#39;mount&#39; and now &#39;supermount&#39;. It
  lists the filesystems mounted automatically at startup by the mount -a
  command (in /etc/rc or equivalent startup file). Under Linux, also contains
  information about swap areas used automatically by swapon -a.</para>

  <variablelist><varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>
  <screen>
  # /etc/fstab: static file system information.
  #
  # The following is an example. Please see fstab(5) for further details.
  # Please refer to mount(1) for a complete description of mount options.
  #
  # Format:
  # &#60;file system&#62; &#60;mount point&#62; &#60;type&#62; &#60;options&#62; &#60;dump&#62; &#60;pass&#62;
  #
  # dump(8) uses the &#60;dump&#62; field to determine which file systems need
  # to be dumped. fsck(8) uses the &#60;pass&#62; column to determine which file
  # systems need to be checked--the root file system should have a 1 in 
  # this field, other file systems a 2, and any file systems that should
  # not be checked (such as MS-DOS or NFS file systems) a 0.
  #
  # The `sw&#39; option indicates that the swap partition is to be activated
  # with `swapon -a&#39;.
  /dev/hda2 none swap sw 0 0
  # The `bsdgroups&#39; option indicates that the file system is to be mounted
  # with BSD semantics (files inherit the group ownership of the directory
  # in which they live). `ro&#39; can be used to mount a file system read-only.
  /dev/hda3 / ext2 defaults 0 1 
  /dev/hda5 /home ext2 defaults 0 2
  /dev/hda6 /var ext2 defaults 0 2
  /dev/hda7 /usr ext2 defaults,ro 0 2
  /dev/hda8 /usr/local ext2 defaults,bsdgroups 0 2
  # The `noauto&#39; option indicates that the file system should not be mounted
  # with `mount -a&#39;. `user&#39; indicates that normal users are allowed to mount
  # the file system.
  /dev/cdrom /cdrom iso9660 defaults,noauto,ro,user 0 0
  /dev/fd0 /floppy minix defaults,noauto,user 0 0
  /dev/fd1 /floppy minix defaults,noauto,user 0 0
  # NFS file systems: server:
  /export/usr /usr nfs defaults 0 0
  # proc file system:
  proc /proc proc defaults 0 0
  </screen></para>
  </listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>

  </listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ftpaccess</term><listitem><para>Determines
  who might get ftp-access to your machine.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ftpchroot</term><listitem><para>List
  of ftp users that need to be chrooted.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ftpuser</term><listitem><para>List
  of disallowed ftp users.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/gateways</term><listitem><para>Lists
  gateways for &#39;routed&#39;.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/gettydefs</term><listitem><para>Configures
  console-logins.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/gnome-vfs-mime-magic</term><listitem><para>MIME
  magic patterns as used by the Gnome VFS library.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/group</term><listitem><para>Similar
  to /etc/passwd. It lists the configured user groups and who belongs to them.
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/group-</term><listitem><para>Old
  /etc/group file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/gshadow</term><listitem><para>Contains
  encrypted forms of group passwords.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/gshadow-</term><listitem><para>Old
  /etc/gshadow file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/hostname</term><listitem><para>Contains
  the hostname of your machine (can be fully qualified or not).</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/host.conf</term><listitem><para>Determines
  the search order for look-ups (usually hosts bind, i.e. &#34;check
  /etc/hosts first and then look for a DNS&#34;).</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/hosts</term><listitem><para>This
  file is used to define a system name and domain combination with a specific
  IP address. This file needs to always contain an entry for an IP address, if
  the machine is connected to the network.</para>
  
  <para><screen>
  ### etherconf DEBCONF AREA. DO NOT EDIT THIS AREA OR INSERT TEXT BEFORE IT.
  127.0.0.1 localhost ::1 localhost
  ip6-localhost ip6-loopback
  fe00::0 ip6-localnet
  ff00::0 ip6-mcastprefix
  ff02::1 ip6-allnodes
  ff02::2 ip6-allrouters
  ff02::3 ip6-allhosts
  192.168.0.99 debian.localdomain.com debian
  ### END OF DEBCONF AREA. PLACE YOUR EDITS BELOW; THEY WILL BE PRESERVED.
  192.168.0.1 ws001
  </screen></para>
  
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/hosts.allow</term><listitem><para>Part
  of the tcp-wrappers system to control access to your machine&#39;s services.
  It lists hosts that are allowed to access the system and specific daemons.</para>
  <para><screen>
  # /etc/hosts.allow: list of hosts that are allowed to access the
  # system.
  # See the manual pages hosts_access(5), hosts_options(5)
  # and /usr/doc/netbase/portmapper.txt.gz
  #
  # Example: ALL: LOCAL @some_netgroup
  # ALL: .foobar.edu EXCEPT terminalserver.foobar.edu
  #
  # If you&#39;re going to protect the portmapper use the name &#34;portmap&#34;
  # for the daemon name. Remember that you can only use the keyword
  # &#34;ALL&#34; and IP addresses (NOT host or domain names) for the
  # portmapper. See portmap(8) and /usr/doc/portmap/portmapper.txt.gz
  # for further information.
  bootpd: 0.0.0.0 in.tftpd: 192.168.0.
  portmap: 192.168.0.
  rpc.mountd: 192.168.0.
  rpc.nfsd: 192.168.0.
  gdm: 192.168.0.
  nasd: 192.168.0.
  </screen></para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/hosts.deny</term><listitem><para>part
  of the tcp-wrappers system to control access to your machine&#39;s services.
  It lists hosts that are not allowed to access the system.</para>
  <para><screen>
  # Example: ALL: some.host.name, .some.domain
  # ALL EXCEPT in.fingerd: other.host.name, .other.domain
  #
  # If you&#39;re going to protect the portmapper use the name &#34;portmap&#34;
  # for the daemon name. Remember that you can only use the keyword
  # &#34;ALL&#34; and IP addresses (NOT host or domain names) for the
  # portmapper. See portmap(8) and /usr/doc/portmap/portmapper.txt.gz
  # for further information.
  #
  # The PARANOID wildcard matches any host whose name does not match
  # its address. You may wish to enable this to ensure any programs
  # that don&#39;t validate looked up hostnames still leave understandable
  # logs. In past versions of Debian this has been the default.
  # ALL: PARANOID
  </screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/httpd</term><listitem><para>Apache
  configuration files. Apache is a versatile, high-performance HTTP server.
  The most popular server in the world, Apache features a modular design and
  supports dynamic selection of extension modules at runtime. Its strong
  points are its range of possible customization, dynamic adjustment of the
  number of server processes, and a whole range of available modules including
  many authentication mechanisms, server-parsed HTML, server-side includes,
  access control, CERN httpd metafiles emulation, proxy caching, etc. Apache
  also supports multiple virtual homing.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/identd.conf</term><listitem><para>TCP/IP
  IDENT protocol server. It implements the TCP/IP proposed standard IDENT user
  identification protocol (RFC 1413). identd operates by looking up specific
  TCP/IP connections and returning the username of the process owning the
  connection. It can also return other information besides the username.</para>

  <para><screen>
  # /etc/identd.conf - an example configuration file


  #-- The syslog facility for error messages
  # syslog:facility = daemon


  #-- User and group (from passwd database) to run as
  server:user = nobody

  #-- Override the group id
  # server:group = kmem

  #-- What port to listen on when started as a daemon or from /etc/inittab
  # server:port = 113

  #-- The socket backlog limit
  # server:backlog = 256

  #-- Where to write the file containing our process id
  # server:pid-file = "/var/run/identd/identd.pid"

  #-- Maximum number of concurrent requests allowed (0 = unlimited)
  # server:max-requests = 0

  #-- Enable some protocol extensions like "VERSION" or "QUIT"
  protocol:extensions = enabled

  #-- Allow multiple queries per connection
  protocol:multiquery = enabled

  #-- Timeout in seconds since connection or last query. Zero = disable
  # protocol:timeout = 120

  #-- Maximum number of threads doing kernel lookups
  # kernel:threads = 8

  #-- Maximum number of queued kernel lookup requests
  # kernel:buffers = 32

  #-- Maximum number of time to retry a kernel lookup in case of failure
  # kernel:attempts = 5



  #-- Disable username lookups (only return uid numbers)
  # result:uid-only = no

  #-- Enable the ".noident" file
  # result:noident = enabled

  #-- Charset token to return in replies
  # result:charset = "US-ASCII"

  #-- Opsys token to return in replies
  # result:opsys = "UNIX"

  #-- Log all request replies to syslog (none == don't)
  # result:syslog-level = none


  #-- Enable encryption (only available if linked with a DES library)
  # result:encrypt = no

  #-- Path to the DES key file (only available if linked with a DES library)
  # encrypt:key-file = "/usr/local/etc/identd.key"


  #-- Include a machine local configuration file
  # include = /etc/identd.conf
  </screen></para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/inetd.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  of services that are started by the INETD TCP/IP super server.
  &#39;inetd&#39; is now deprecated. &#39;xinetd&#39; has taken its place. See
  /etc/xinet.conf for further details.</para>
  
  <para><screen>
  # /etc/inetd.conf:  see inetd(8) for further information.
  #
  # Internet server configuration database
  #
  #
  # Lines starting with "#:LABEL:" or "#&lt;off&gt;#" should not
  # be changed unless you know what you are doing!
  #
  # If you want to disable an entry so it isn't touched during
  # package updates just comment it out with a single '#' character.
  #
  # Packages should modify this file by using update-inetd(8)
  #
  # &lt;service_name&gt; &lt;sock_type&gt; &lt;proto&gt; 
  # &lt;flags&gt; &lt;user&gt; &lt;server_path&gt;
  # &lt;args&gt;
  #
  #:INTERNAL: Internal services
  #echo	stream	tcp nowait root	internal
  #echo	dgram	udp wait root internal
  #chargen stream tcp	nowait root internal
  #chargen dgram udp	wait root internal
  discard stream tcp nowait root internal
  discard dgram	udp wait root internal
  daytime stream tcp nowait root internal
  #daytime dgram udp wait root internal
  time stream tcp nowait root internal
  #time dgram udp wait root internal

  #:STANDARD: These are standard services.
  ftp stream tcp nowait	root /usr/sbin/tcpd /usr/sbin/in.ftpd	
  telnet stream	tcp nowait telnetd.telnetd /usr/sbin/tcpd 
                                           /usr/sbin/in.telnetd

  #:MAIL: Mail, news and uucp services.
  smtp stream tcp nowait mail /usr/sbin/exim exim -bs
  imap2  stream  tcp nowait root /usr/sbin/tcpd /usr/sbin/imapd
  imap3  stream  tcp nowait root /usr/sbin/tcpd /usr/sbin/imapd

  #:INFO: Info services
  ident	stream tcp wait	identd /usr/sbin/identd	identd
  finger stream	tcp nowait nobody /usr/sbin/tcpd 
                                  /usr/sbin/in.fingerd

  #:BOOT: Tftp service is provided primarily for booting.  
  #Most sites run this only on machines acting as "boot servers."
  tftp dgram udp wait nobody /usr/sbin/tcpd 
                             /usr/sbin/in.tftpd -s /tftpboot
  </screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/init.d</term><listitem><para><screen>

Order of scripts run in /etc/rc?.d
==================================

0. Overview.

   All scripts executed by the init system are located in /etc/init.d.
   The directories /etc/rc?.d (? = S, 0 .. 6) contain relative links to
   those scripts. These links are named S&#60;2-digit-number&#62;&#60;
   original-name&#62; or K&#60;2-digit-number&#62;&#60;original-name&#62;.

   If a scripts has the &#34;.sh&#34; suffix it is a bourne shell script and
   MAY be handled in an optimized manner. The behaviour of executing the
   script in an optimized way will not differ in any way from it being
   forked and executed in the regular way.

   The following runlevels are defined:

   N       System bootup (NONE).
   S       Single user mode (not to be switched to directly)
   0       halt
   1       single user mode
   2 .. 5  multi user mode
   6       reboot

1. Boot.

   When the systems boots, the /etc/init.d/rcS script is executed. It
   in turn executes all the S* scripts in /etc/rcS.d in alphabetical
   (and thus numerical) order. The first argument passed to the
   executed scripts is &#34;start&#34;. The runlevel at this point is
   &#34;N&#34; (none).

   Only things that need to be run once to get the system in a consistent
   state are to be run. The rcS.d directory is NOT meant to replace rc.local.
   One should not start daemons in this runlevel unless absolutely
   necessary. Eg, NFS might need the portmapper, so it is OK to start it
   early in the boot process. But this is not the time to start the
   squid proxy server.

2. Going multiuser.

   After the rcS.d scripts have been executed, init switches to the
   default runlevel as specified in /etc/inittab, usually &#34;2&#34;.

   Init then executes the /etc/init.d/rc script which takes care of
   starting the services in /etc/rc2.d.

   Because the previous runlevel is &#34;N&#34; (none) the /etc/rc2.d/KXXxxxx
   scripts will NOT be executed - there is nothing to stop yet,
   the system is busy coming up.

   If for example there is a service that wants to run in runlevel 4
   and ONLY in that level, it will place a KXXxxxx script in
   /etc/rc{2,3,5}.d to stop the service when switching out of runlevel 4.
   We do not need to run that script at this point.
   
   The /etc.rc2.d/SXXxxxx scripts will be executed in alphabetical
   order, with the first argument set to &#34;start&#34;.

3. Switching runlevels.

   When one switches from (for example) runlevel 2 to runlevel 3,
   /etc/init.d/rc will first execute in alphabetical order all K
   scripts for runlevel 3 (/etc/rc3.d/KXXxxxx) with as first argument
   &#34;stop&#34; and then all S scripts for runlevel 3 (/etc/rc3.d/SXXxxxx)
   with as first argument &#34;start&#34;.

   As an optimization, a check is made for each &#34;service&#34; to see if
   it was already running in the previous runlevel. If it was, and there
   is no K (stop) script present for it in the new runlevel, there is
   no need to start it a second time so that will not be done.

   On the other hand, if there was a K script present, it is assumed the
   service was stopped on purpose first and so needs to be restarted.

   We MIGHT make the same optimization for stop scripts as well-
   if no S script was present in the previous runlevel, we can assume
   that service was not running and we don&#39;t need to stop it either.
   In that case we can remove the &#34;coming from level N&#34; special case
   mentioned above in 2). But right now that has not been implemented.

4. Single user mode.

   Switching to single user mode is done by switching to runlevel 1.
   That will cause all services to be stopped (assuming they all have
   a K script in /etc/rc1.d). The runlevel 1 scripts will then switch
   to runlevel &#34;S&#34; which has no scripts - all it does is spawn
   a shell directly on /dev/console for maintenance.

5. Halt/reboot

   Going to runlevel 0 or 6 will cause the system to be halted or rebooted,
   respectively. For example, if we go to runlevel 6 (reboot) first
   all /etc/rc6.d/KXXxxxx scripts will be executed alphabetically with
   &#34;stop&#34; as the first argument.

   Then the /etc/rc6.d/SXXxxxx scripts will be executed alphabetically
   with &#34;stop&#34; as the first argument as well. The reason is that there
   is nothing to start any more at this point - all scripts that are
   run are meant to bring the system down.

   In the future, the /etc/rc6.d/SXXxxxx scripts MIGHT be moved to
   /etc/rc6.d/K1XXxxxx for clarity.
</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>/etc/inittab</term><listitem><para>Boot-time
  system configuration/initialization script. Tells init how to handle
  runlevels. It sets the default runlevel. This is run first except when
  booting in emergency (-b) mode. It also enables a user to startup a getty
  session on an external device such as the serial ports. To add terminals or
  dial-in modem lines to a system, just add more lines to /etc/inittab, one
  for each terminal or dial-in line. For more details, see the manual pages
  init, inittab, and getty. If a command fails when it starts, and init is
  configured to restart it, it will use a lot of system resources: init starts
  it, it fails, init starts it, it fails, and so on. To prevent this, init
  will keep track of how often it restarts a command, and if the frequency
  grows to high, it will delay for five minutes before restarting again.
  /etc/inittab also has some special features that allow init to react to
  special circumstances. powerwait Allows init to shut the system down, when
  the power fails. This assumes the use of a UPS, and software that watches
  the UPS and informs init that the power is off. ctrlaltdel Allows init to
  reboot the system, when the user presses ctrl-alt-del on the console
  keyboard. Note that the system administrator can configure the reaction to
  ctrl-alt-del to be something else instead, e.g., to be ignored, if the
  system is in a public location. sysinit Command to be run when the system is
  booted. This command usually cleans up /tmp, for example. The list above is
  not exhaustive. See your inittab manual page for all possibilities, and for
  details on how to use the ones above. To set (or reset) initial terminal
  colours. The following shell script should work for VGA consoles: for n in 1
  2 4 5 6 7 8; do setterm -fore yellow -bold on -back blue -store &#62;
  /dev/tty$n done Substitute your favorite colors, and use /dev/ttyS$n for
  serial terminals. To make sure they are reset when people log out (if
  they&#39;ve been changed) replace the references to getty (or mingetty or
  uugetty or whatever) in /etc/inittab with references to /sbin/mygetty.
  #!/bin/sh setterm -fore yellow -bold on -back blue -store &#62; $1 exec
  /sbin/mingetty $@ An example /etc/inittab is provided below.</para>
  
  <para><screen>
  # /etc/inittab: init(8) configuration.
  # $Id$
  # The default runlevel. id:2:initdefault:
  # Boot-time system configuration/initialization script.
  # This is run first except when booting in emergency (-b) mode.
  si::sysinit:/etc/init.d/rcS
  # What to do in single-user mode.
  ~~:S:wait:/sbin/sulogin
  # /etc/init.d executes the S and K scripts upon change
  # of runlevel.
  #
  # Runlevel 0 is halt.
  # Runlevel 1 is single-user.
  # Runlevels 2-5 are multi-user.
  # Runlevel 6 is reboot.
  l0:0:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 0 l1:1:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 1
  l2:2:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 2 l3:3:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 3
  l4:4:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 4 l5:5:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 5
  l6:6:wait:/etc/init.d/rc 6
  # Normally not reached, but fallthrough in case of emergency.
  z6:6:respawn:/sbin/sulogin
  # What to do when CTRL-ALT-DEL is pressed.
  ca:12345:ctrlaltdel:/sbin/shutdown -t1 -a -r now
  # Action on special keypress (ALT-UpArrow).
  #kb::kbrequest:/bin/echo &#34;Keyboard Request
  #--edit /etc/inittab to let this work.&#34;
  # What to do when the power fails/returns.
  pf::powerwait:/etc/init.d/powerfail start
  pn::powerfailnow:/etc/init.d/powerfail now
  po::powerokwait:/etc/init.d/powerfail stop
  # /sbin/getty invocations for the runlevels.
  #
  # The &#34;id&#34; field MUST be the same as the last
  # characters of the device (after &#34;tty&#34;).
  #
  # Format:
  # &#60;id&#62;:&#60;runlevels&#62;:&#60;action&#62;:&#60;process&#62;
  #
  # Note that on most Debian systems tty7 is used by the X Window System,
  # so if you want to add more getty&#39;s go ahead but skip tty7 if you run X.
  #
  1:2345:respawn:/sbin/getty 38400 tty1 2:23:respawn:/sbin/getty 38400 tty2
  3:23:respawn:/sbin/getty 38400 tty3 4:23:respawn:/sbin/getty 38400 tty4
  5:23:respawn:/sbin/getty 38400 tty5 6:23:respawn:/sbin/getty 38400 tty6
  # Example how to put a getty on a serial line (for a terminal)
  #
  #T0:23:respawn:/sbin/getty -L ttyS0 9600 vt100 
  #T1:23:respawn:/sbin/getty -L ttyS1 9600 vt100
  # Example how to put a getty on a modem line.
  #
  #T3:23:respawn:/sbin/mgetty -x0 -s 57600 ttyS3

  Undocumented features
  
  The letters A-C can be used to spawn a daemon listed in /etc/inittab. For
  example, assuming you want to start getty on a port to receive a call, but
  only after receiving a voice call first (and not all the time). Furthermore,
  you want to be able to receive a data or a fax call and that when you get
  the voice message you&#39;ll know which you want. You insert two new lines
  in /etc/inittab, each with its own ID, and each with a runlevel such as A
  for data and B for fax. When you know which you need, you simply spawn the
  appropriate daemon by calling &#39;telinit A&#39; or &#39;telinit B&#39;.
  The appropriate getty is put on the line until the first call is received.
  When the caller terminates the connection, the getty drops because, by
  definition, on demand will not respawn. The other two letters, S and Q, are
  special. S brings you system to maintenance mode and is the same as changing
  state to runlevel 1. The Q is used to tell init to reread inittab. The
  /etc/inittab file can be changed as often as required, but will only be read
  under certain circumstances: -One of its processes dies (do you need to
  respawn another?) -On a powerful signal from a power daemon (or a command
  line) -When told to change state by telinit The Q argument tells init to
  reread the /etc/inittab file. Even though it is called the System V runlevel
  system runlevels 7-9 are legitimate runlevels that can be used if necessary.
  The administrator must remember to alter the inittab file though and also to
  create the required rc?.d files.</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/inputrc</term><listitem><para>Global
  inputrc for libreadline. Readline is a function that gets a line from a user
  and automatically edits it.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/isapnp.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for ISA based cards. This standard is virtually redundant in new
  systems. The &#39;isapnptools&#39; suite of ISA Plug-And-Play configuration
  utilities is used to configure such devices. These programs are suitable for
  all systems, whether or not they include a PnP BIOS. In fact, PnP BIOS adds
  some complications because it may already activate some cards so that the
  drivers can find them, and these tools can unconfigure them, or change their
  settings causing all sorts of nasty effects.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/isdn</term><listitem><para>ISDN
  configuration files.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/issue</term><listitem><para>Output
  by getty before the login prompt. Usually contains a short description or
  welcoming message to the system. The contents are up to the system
  administrator. Debian GNU/\s 3.0 \n \l</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/issue.net</term><listitem><para>Presents
  the welcome screen to users who login remotely to your machine (whereas
  /etc/issue determines what a local user sees on login). Debian GNU/%s 3.0 %h</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/kde</term><listitem><para>KDE
  initialization scripts and KDM configuration.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/kde/kdm</term><listitem><para>Location
  for the K Desktop Manager files. kdm manages a collection of X servers,
  which may be on the local host or remote machines. It provides services
  similar to those provided by init, getty, and login on character-based
  terminals: prompting for login name and password, authenticating the user,
  and running a session. kdm supports XDMCP (X Display Manager Control
  Protocol) and can also be used to run a chooser process which presents the
  user with a menu of possible hosts that offer XDMCP display management.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/kderc</term><listitem><para>System
  wide KDE initialization script. Commands here executed every time the KDE
  environment is loaded. It&#39;s a link to /etc/kde2/system.kdeglobals
  
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para> <screen>
  [Directories]
  dir_config=/etc/kde2
  dir_html=/usr/share/doc/kde/HTML
  dir_cgi=/usr/lib/cgi-bin
  dir_apps=/usr/share/applnk
  dir_mime=/usr/share/mimelnk
  dir_services=/usr/share/services
  dir_servicetypes=/usr/share/servicetypes
  [General]
  TerminalApplication=x-terminal-emulator
  </screen> </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ld.so.conf, /etc/ld.so.cache</term><listitem><para>
   
  <variablelist> 

  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>/etc/ld.so.conf is a file
  containing a list of colon, space, tab, newline, or comma separated
  directories in which to search for libraries. /etc/ld.so.cache containing an
  ordered list of libraries found in the directories specified in
  /etc/ld.so.conf. This file is not in human readable format, and is not
  intended to be edited.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>&#39;ldconfig&#39; creates the necessary
  links and cache (for use by the run-time linker, ld.so) to the most recent
  shared libraries found in the directories specified on the command line, in
  the file /etc/ld.so.conf, and in the trusted directories (/usr/lib and
  /lib). &#39;ldconfig&#39; checks the header and file names of the libraries
  it encounters when determining which versions should have their links
  updated. ldconfig ignores symbolic links when scanning for libraries.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>&#39;ldconfig&#39; will attempt to deduce the type of ELF libs (ie.
  libc5 or libc6/glibc) based on what C libs if any the library was linked
  against, therefore when making dynamic libraries, it is wise to explicitly
  link against libc (use -lc).</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>Some existing libs do not contain
  enough information to allow the deduction of their type, therefore the
  /etc/ld.so.conf file format allows the specification of an expected type.
  This is only used for those ELF libs which we can not work out. The format
  is like this &#34;dirname=TYPE&#34;, where type can be libc4, libc5 or
  libc6. (This syntax also works on the command line). Spaces are not allowed.
  Also see the -p option.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>Directory names containing an = are no
  longer legal unless they also have an expected type specifier.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para>&#39;ldconfig&#39; should normally be run by the super-user as it may
  require write permission on some root owned directories and files. It is
  normally run automatically at bootup or manually whenever new shared
  libraries are installed.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
  
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/usr/X11R6/lib</term><listitem><para>X libraries.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/usr/local/lib</term><listitem><para>Local libraries.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/lilo.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for the Linux boot loader &#39;lilo&#39;. &#39;lilo&#39; is the
  original OS loader and can load Linux and others. The &#39;lilo&#39; package
  normally contains lilo (the installer) and boot-record-images to install
  Linux, OS/2, DOS and generic Boot Sectors of other Oses. You can use Lilo to
  manage your Master Boot Record (with a simple text screen, text menu or
  colorful splash graphics) or call &#39;lilo&#39; from other boot-loaders to
  jump-start the Linux kernel.
  
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para> <screen>
  Prompt #Prompt user to select
  OS choice at boot timeout=300  # Amount of time to wait before default OS
                                 # started (in ms)
  default=Debian4 #Default OS to be loaded
  vga=normal #VGA mode
  boot=/dev/had #location of MBR
  map=/boot/map #location of kernel
  install=/boot/boot-bmp.b #File to be installed as boot sector
  bitmap=/boot/debian.bmp #LILO boot image 
  bmp-table=30p,100p,1,10 #Colours
  selectable bmp-colors=13,,0,1,,0 #Colours chosen
  lba32 #Required on most new systems to overcome
        #1024 cylinder problem
  image=/vmlinuz #name of kernel
  image label=Debian #a label
  read-only #file system to be mounted read only
  root=/dev/hda6 #location of root filesystem
  
  image=/boot/bzImage
  label=Debian4
  read-only
  root=/dev/hda6

  image=/mnt/redhat/boot/vmlinuz
  label=Redhat
  initrd=/mnt/redhat/boot/initrd-2.4.18-14.img
  read-only
  root=/dev/hda5
  vga=788
  append=&#34; hdc=ide-scsi hdd=ide-scsi&#34;
  
  image=/mnt/mandrake/boot/vmlinuz
  label=&#34;Mandrake&#34;
  root=/dev/hda7
  initrd=/mnt/mandrake/boot/initrd.img
  append=&#34;devfs=mount hdc=ide-scsi
  acpi=off quiet&#34;
  vga=788
  read-only

  other=/dev/hda2
  table=/dev/hda
  loader=/boot/chain.b
  label=FBSD
  other=/dev/hda1
  label=Windows
  table=/dev/hda
  
  other=/dev/fd0
  label=floppy unsafe
  </screen></para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/local.gen</term><listitem><para>This
  file lists locales that you wish to have built. You can find a list of valid
  supported locales at /usr/share/i18n/SUPPORTED. Other combinations are
  possible, but may not be well tested. If you change this file, you need to
  re-run locale-gen.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/locale.alias</term><listitem><para>Locale
  name alias data base.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/login.defs</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  control definitions for the login package. An inordinate number of
  attributes can be altered via this single file such as the location of mail,
  delay in seconds after a failed login, enabling display of fail log
  information, display of unknown username login failures, shell environment
  variables, etc....</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/logrotate.conf</term><listitem><para>The
  logrotate utility is designed to simplify the administration of log files on
  a system which generates a lot of log files. Logrotate allows for the
  automatic rotation compression, removal and mailing of log files. Logrotate
  can be set to handle a log file daily, weekly, monthly or when the log file
  gets to a certain size. Normally, logrotate runs as a daily cron job.</para>

<para><screen>
  # see "man logrotate" for details
  # rotate log files weekly
  weekly

  # keep 4 weeks worth of backlogs
  rotate 4

  # create new (empty) log files after rotating old ones
  create

  # uncomment this if you want your log files compressed
  #compress

  # packages drop log rotation information into this directory
  include /etc/logrotate.d

  # no packages own wtmp, or btmp -- we'll rotate them here
  /var/log/wtmp {
      monthly
      create 0664 root utmp
      rotate 1
  }

  /var/log/btmp {
      missingok
      monthly
      create 0664 root utmp
      rotate 1
  }

  # system-specific logs may be configured here
</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ltrace.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for ltrace (Library Call Tracer). It tracks runtime library calls in
  dynamically linked programs. &#39;ltrace&#39; is a debugging program which
  runs a specified command until it exits. While the command is executing,
  ltrace intercepts and records the dynamic library calls which are called by
  the executed process and the signals received by that process. It can also
  intercept and print the system calls executed by the program. The program to
  be traced need not be recompiled for this, so you can use it on binaries for
  which you don&#39;t have the source handy. You should install ltrace if you
  need a sysadmin tool for tracking the execution of processes.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/magic</term><listitem><para>Magic
  local data and configuration file for the file(1) command. Contains the
  descriptions of various file formats based on which file guesses the type of
  the file. Insert here your local magic data. Format is described in
  magic(5).</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mail.rc</term><listitem><para>Initialization
  file for &#39;mail&#39;. &#39;mail&#39; is an intelligent mail processing
  system which has a command syntax reminiscent of ed with lines replaced by
  messages. It's basically a command line version of Microsoft Outlook.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mailcap</term><listitem><para>&#39;metamail&#39;
  capabilities file. The mailcap file is read by the metamail program to
  determine how to display non-text at the local site. The syntax of a mailcap
  file is quite simple, at least compared to termcap files. Any line that
  starts with &#34;#&#34; is a comment. Blank lines are ignored. Otherwise,
  each line defines a single mailcap entry for a single content type. Long
  lines may be continued by ending them with a backslash character, \. Each
  individual mailcap entry consists of a content-type specification, a command
  to execute, and (possibly) a set of optional &#34;flag&#34; values.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mailcap.order</term><listitem><para>The
  mailcap ordering specifications. The order of entries in the /etc/mailcap
  file can be altered by editing the /etc/mailcap.order file. Each line of
  that file specifies a package and an optional mime type. Mailcap entries
  that match will be placed in the order of this file. Entries that don&#39;t
  match will be placed later.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mailname</term><listitem><para>Mail
  server hostname. Normally the same as the hostname.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/menu,
  /etc/menu-methods</term><listitem><para>The menu package was inspired by the
  install-fvwm2-menu program from the old fvwm2 package. However, menu tries
  to provide a more general interface for menu building. With the update-menus
  command from this package, no package needs to be modified for every X
  window manager again, and it provides a unified interface for both text-and
  X-oriented programs.</para><para>When a package that wants to add something
  to the menu tree gets installed, it will run update-menus in its postinstall
  script. Update-menus then reads in all menu files in /etc/menu/
  /usr/lib/menu and /usr/lib/menu/default, and stores the menu entries of all
  installed packages in memory. Once that has been done, it will run the
  menu-methods in /etc/menu-methods/*, and pipe the information about the menu
  entries to the menu-methods on stdout, so that the menu-methods can read
  this. Each Window Manager or other program that wants to have the debian
  menu tree, will supply a menu-method script in /etc/menu-methods/. This
  menu-method then knows how to generate the startup-file for that window
  manager. To facilitate this task for the window-manager maintainers, menu
  provides a install-menu program. This program can generate the startup files
  for just about every window manager.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mgetty+sendfax</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  files for use of mgetty as the interface on the serial port. The mgetty
  routine special routine has special features for handling things such as
  dial up connections and fax connections.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mime.types</term><listitem><para>MIME-TYPES
  and the extensions that represent them. This file is part of the
  &#34;mime-support&#34; package. Note: Compression schemes like
  &#34;gzip&#34;, &#34;bzip&#34;, and &#34;compress&#34; are not actually
  &#34;mime-types&#34;. They are &#34;encodings&#34; and hence must _not_ have
  entries in this file to map their extensions. The &#34;mime-type&#34; of an
  encoded file refers to the type of data that has been encoded, not the type
  of the encoding.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/minicom</term><listitem><para>&#39;minicom&#39;
  configuration files. &#39;minicom&#39; is a communication program which
  somewhat resembles the shareware program TELIX but is free with source code
  and runs under most unices. Features include dialling directory with
  auto-redial, support for UUCP-style lock files on serial devices, a separate
  script language interpreter, capture to file, multiple users with individual
  configurations, and more.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/modules</term><listitem><para>List
  of modules to be loaded at startup.</para>

  <para><screen>
  # /etc/modules: kernel modules to load at boot time.
  #
  # This file should contain the names of kernel modules that are
  # to be loaded at boot time, one per line. Comments begin with
  # a &#34;#&#34;, and everything on the line after them are ignored.
  unix
  af_packet
  via-rhine
  cmpci
  ne2k-pci
  nvidia
  </screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/modules.conf</term><listitem><para><screen>
  ### This file is automatically generated by update-modules"
  #
  # Please do not edit this file directly. If you want to change or add
  # anything please take a look at the files in /etc/modutils and read
  # the manpage for update-modules.
  #
  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/0keep
  # DO NOT MODIFY THIS FILE!
  # This file is not marked as conffile to make sure if you upgrade modutils
  # it will be restored in case some modifications have been made.
  #
  # The keep command is necessary to prevent insmod and friends from ignoring
  # the builtin defaults of a path-statement is encountered. Until all other
  # packages use the new `add path'-statement this keep-statement is essential
  # to keep your system working
  keep

  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/0keep

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/actions
  # Special actions that are needed for some modules

  # The BTTV module does not load the tuner module automatically,
  # so do that in here
  post-install bttv insmod tuner
  post-remove bttv rmmod tuner


  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/actions

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/aliases
  # Aliases to tell insmod/modprobe which modules to use 

  # Uncomment the network protocols you don't want loaded:
  # alias net-pf-1 off		# Unix
  # alias net-pf-2 off		# IPv4
  # alias net-pf-3 off		# Amateur Radio AX.25
  # alias net-pf-4 off		# IPX
  # alias net-pf-5 off		# DDP / appletalk
  # alias net-pf-6 off		# Amateur Radio NET/ROM
  # alias net-pf-9 off		# X.25
  # alias net-pf-10 off		# IPv6
  # alias net-pf-11 off		# ROSE / Amateur Radio X.25 PLP
  # alias net-pf-19 off		# Acorn Econet

  alias char-major-10-175	agpgart
  alias char-major-10-200	tun
  alias char-major-81	bttv
  alias char-major-108	ppp_generic
  alias /dev/ppp		ppp_generic
  alias tty-ldisc-3	ppp_async
  alias tty-ldisc-14	ppp_synctty
  alias ppp-compress-21	bsd_comp
  alias ppp-compress-24	ppp_deflate
  alias ppp-compress-26	ppp_deflate

  # Crypto modules (see http://www.kerneli.org/)
  alias loop-xfer-gen-0	loop_gen
  alias loop-xfer-3	loop_fish2
  alias loop-xfer-gen-10	loop_gen
  alias cipher-2		des
  alias cipher-3		fish2
  alias cipher-4		blowfish
  alias cipher-6		idea
  alias cipher-7		serp6f
  alias cipher-8		mars6
  alias cipher-11		rc62
  alias cipher-15		dfc2
  alias cipher-16		rijndael
  alias cipher-17		rc5


  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/aliases

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/ltmodem-2.4.18
  # lt_drivers: autoloading and insertion parameter usage
  alias char-major-62 lt_serial
  alias /dev/tts/LT0  lt_serial
  alias /dev/modem lt_serial
  # options lt_modem vendor_id=0x115d device_id=0x0420 Forced=3,0x130,0x2f8
  # section for lt_drivers ends

  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/ltmodem-2.4.18

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/paths
  # This file contains a list of paths that modprobe should scan,
  # beside the once that are compiled into the modutils tools
  # themselves.


  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/paths

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/ppp
  alias /dev/ppp          ppp_generic
  alias char-major-108    ppp_generic
  alias tty-ldisc-3       ppp_async  
  alias tty-ldisc-14      ppp_synctty
  alias ppp-compress-21   bsd_comp   
  alias ppp-compress-24   ppp_deflate
  alias ppp-compress-26   ppp_deflate

  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/ppp

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/setserial
  #
  # This is what I wanted to do, but logger is in /usr/bin, which isn't
  # loaded when the module is first loaded into the kernel at boot time!
  #
  #post-install serial /etc/init.d/setserial start | 
  #logger -p daemon.info -t "setserial-module reload"
  #pre-remove serial /etc/init.d/setserial stop | 
  #logger -p daemon.info -t "setserial-module uload"
  #
  alias /dev/tts          serial
  alias /dev/tts/0        serial
  alias /dev/tts/1        serial
  alias /dev/tts/2        serial
  alias /dev/tts/3        serial
  post-install serial /etc/init.d/setserial modload > /dev/null 2> /dev/null
  pre-remove serial /etc/init.d/setserial modsave  > /dev/null 2> /dev/null

  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/setserial

  ### update-modules: start processing /etc/modutils/arch/i386
  alias parport_lowlevel parport_pc
  alias char-major-10-144 nvram
  alias binfmt-0064 binfmt_aout
  alias char-major-10-135 rtc

  ### update-modules: end processing /etc/modutils/arch/i386
  </screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/modutils</term><listitem><para>These
  utilities are intended to make a Linux modular kernel manageable for all
  users, administrators and distribution maintainers.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mtools</term><listitem><para>Debian
  default mtools configuration file. The mtools series of commands work with
  MS-DOS files and directories on floppy disks. This allows you to use Linux
  with MS-DOS formatted diskettes on DOS and Windows systems.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/manpath.conf</term><listitem><para>This
  file is used by the man_db package to configure the man and cat paths. It is
  also used to provide a manpath for those without one by examining their PATH
  environment variable. For details see the manpath(5) man page.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mediaprm</term><listitem><para>Was
  formally named /etc/fdprm. See /etc/fdprm for further details.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/motd</term><listitem><para>The
  message of the day, automatically output after a successful login. Contents
  are up to the system administrator. Often used for getting information to
  every user, such as warnings about planned downtimes. Linux
  debian.localdomain.com 2.4.18 #1 Sat Mar 15 00:17:39 EST 2003 i686 unknown
  Most of the programs included with the Debian GNU/Linux system are freely
  redistributable; the exact distribution terms for each program are described
  in the individual files in /usr/share/doc/*/copyright Debian GNU/Linux comes
  with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by applicable law.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/mtab</term><listitem><para>List
  of currently mounted filesystems. Initially set up by the bootup scripts,
  and updated automatically by the mount command. Used when a list of mounted
  filesystems is needed, e.g., by the df command. This file is sometimes a
  symbolic link to /proc/mounts.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/networks</term><listitem><para>List
  of networks that the system is currently located on. For example,
  192.168.0.0.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/nsswitch.conf</term><listitem><para>System
  Database/Name Service Switch configuration file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/oss.conf</term><listitem><para>OSS
  (Open Sound System) configuration file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/pam.d/</term><listitem><para>This
  directory is the home of the configuration files for PAMs, Pluggable
  Authentication Modules.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/postfix/</term><listitem><para>Holds
  your postfix configuration files. Postfix is now the MTA of choice among
  Linux distributions. It is sendmail-compatible, offers improved speed over
  sendmail, ease of administration and security. It was originally developed
  by IBM and was called the IBM Secure Mailer and is used in many large
  commercial networks. It is now the de-facto standard.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ppp/</term><listitem><para>The
  place where your dial-up configuration files are placed. More than likely to
  be created by the text menu based pppconfig or other GUI based ppp
  configuration utilities such as kppp or gnome-ppp.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/pam.conf</term><listitem><para>Most
  programs use a file under the /etc/pam.d/ directory to setup their PAM
  service modules. This file is and can be used, but is not recommended.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/paper.config</term><listitem><para>Paper
  size configuration file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/papersize</term><listitem><para>Default
  papersize.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/passwd</term><listitem><para>This
  is the &#39;old&#39; password file, It is kept for compatibility and
  contains the user database, with fields giving the username, real name, home
  directory, encrypted password, and other information about each user. The
  format is documented in the passwd man(ual) page.</para>

<para><screen>
root:x:0:0:root:/root:/bin/bash daemon:x:1:1:daemon:/usr/sbin:/bin/sh
bin:x:2:2:bin:/bin:/bin/sh sys:x:3:3:sys:/dev:/bin/sh
sync:x:4:100:sync:/bin:/bin/sync games:x:5:100:games:/usr/games:/bin/sh
man:x:6:100:man:/var/cache/man:/bin/sh lp:x:7:7:lp:/var/spool/lpd:/bin/sh
mail:x:8:8:mail:/var/mail:/bin/sh news:x:9:9:news:/var/spool/news:/bin/sh
uucp:x:10:10:uucp:/var/spool/uucp:/bin/sh proxy:x:13:13:proxy:/bin:/bin/sh
postgres:x:31:32:postgres:/var/lib/postgres:/bin/sh
www-data:x:33:33:www-data:/var/www:/bin/sh
backup:x:34:34:backup:/var/backups:/bin/sh
operator:x:37:37:Operator:/var:/bin/sh
list:x:38:38:SmartList:/var/list:/bin/sh irc:x:39:39:ircd:/var:/bin/sh
gnats:x:41:41:Gnats Bug-Reporting System (admin):/var/lib/gnats:/bin/sh
nobody:x:65534:65534:nobody:/home:/bin/sh
binh:x:1000:1000:,,,:/home/binh:/bin/bash
identd:x:100:65534::/var/run/identd:/bin/false
sshd:x:101:65534::/var/run/sshd:/bin/false gdm:x:102:101:Gnome Display
Manager:/var/lib/gdm:/bin/false
telnetd:x:103:103::/usr/lib/telnetd:/bin/false
dummy:x:1001:1001:,,,:/home/dummy:/bin/bash
</screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/passwd-</term><listitem><para>Old
  /etc/passwd file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/printcap</term><listitem><para>Printer
  configuration (capabilities) file. The definition of all system printers,
  whether local or remote, is stored in this file. Its layout is similar to
  that of /etc/termcap but it uses a different syntax.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/profile</term><listitem><para>Files
  and commands to be executed at login or startup time by the Bourne or C
  shells. These allow the system administrator to set global defaults for all
  users.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/profile.d</term><listitem><para>Shells
  scripts to be executed upon login to the Bourne or C shells. These scripts
  are normally called from the /etc/profile file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/protocols</term><listitem><para>Protocols
  definitions file. It describes the various DARPA Internet protocols that are
  available from the TCP/IP subsystem. It should be consulted instead of using
  the numbers in the ARPA include files or resorting to guesstimation. This
  file should be left untouched since changes could result in incorrect IP
  packages.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/pcmcia</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  files for PCMCIA devices. Generally only useful to laptop users.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/reportbug.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for reportbug. Reportbug is primarily designed to report bugs in the
  Debian distribution. By default it creates an e-mail to the Debian bug
  tracking system at mit@bugs.debian.org with information about the bug. Using
  the -bts option you can report bugs to other servers also using ddebbugs
  such as KDE.org. It is similar to bug but has far greater capabilities while
  still maintaining simplicity.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/rc.boot or /etc/rc?.d</term><listitem><para>These directories contain all the files necessary to control system services and configure runlevels. A skeleton file is provided in /etc/init.d/skeleton</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/rcS.d</term><listitem><para>The
  scripts in this directory are executed once when booting the system, even
  when booting directly into single user mode. The files are all symbolic
  links, the real files are located in /etc/init.d/. For a more general
  discussion of this technique, see /etc/init.d/README.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/resolv.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  of how DNS is to occur is defined in this file. It tells the name resolver
  libraries where they need to go to find information not found in the
  /etc/hosts file. This always has at least one nameserver line, but
  preferably three. The resolver uses each in turn. More than the first three
  can be included but anything beyond the first three will be ignored. Two
  lines that appear in the /etc/resolv.conf file are domain and search. Both
  of these are mutually exclusive options, and where both show up, the last
  one wins. Other entries beyond the three discussed here are listed in the
  man pages but aren&#39;t often used.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/rmt</term><listitem><para>This
  is not a mistake. This shell script (/etc/rmt) has been provided for
  compatibility with other Unix-like systems, some of which have utilities
  that expect to find (and execute) rmt in the /etc directory on remote
  systems.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/rpc</term><listitem><para>The
  rpc file contains user readable names that can be used in place of rpc
  program numbers. Each line has the following information: -name of server
  for the rpc program -rpc program number -aliases Items are separated by any
  number of blanks and/or tab characters. A ``#&#39;&#39; indicates the
  beginning of a comment; characters up to the end of the line are not
  interpreted by routines which search the file.</para>

  <para><screen>
  # /etc/rpc:
  # $Id$
  #
  # rpc 88/08/01 4.0 RPCSRC; from 1.12   88/02/07 SMI

  portmapper	100000	portmap sunrpc
  rstatd		100001	rstat rstat_svc rup perfmeter
  rusersd		100002	rusers
  nfs		100003	nfsprog
  ypserv		100004	ypprog
  mountd		100005	mount showmount
  ypbind		100007
  walld		100008	rwall shutdown
  yppasswdd	100009	yppasswd
  etherstatd	100010	etherstat
  rquotad		100011	rquotaprog quota rquota
  sprayd		100012	spray
  3270_mapper	100013
  rje_mapper	100014
  selection_svc	100015	selnsvc
  database_svc	100016
  rexd		100017	rex
  alis		100018
  sched		100019
  llockmgr	100020
  nlockmgr	100021
  x25.inr		100022
  statmon		100023
  status		100024
  bootparam	100026
  ypupdated	100028	ypupdate
  keyserv		100029	keyserver
  tfsd		100037 
  nsed		100038
  nsemntd		100039
  pcnfsd		150001
  amd		300019	amq
  sgi_fam		391002
  ugidd		545580417
  bwnfsd          788585389
  </screen></para>
  
  </listitem></varlistentry>
 
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/samba</term><listitem><para>Samba
  configuration files. A &#39;LanManager&#39; like file and printer server for
  Unix. The Samba software suite is a collection of programs that implements
  the SMB protocol for unix systems, allowing you to serve files and printers
  to Windows, NT, OS/2 and DOS clients. This protocol is sometimes also
  referred to as the LanManager or NetBIOS protocol.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/sane.d</term><listitem><para>Sane
  configuration files. SANE stands for &#34;Scanner Access Now Easy&#34; and
  is an application programming interface (API) that provides standardized
  access to any raster image scanner hardware (flatbed scanner, hand-held
  scanner, video- and still-cameras, frame-grabbers, etc.). The SANE API is
  public domain and its discussion and development is open to everybody. The
  current source code is written for UNIX (including GNU/Linux) and is
  available under the GNU General Public License (the SANE API is available to
  proprietary applications and backends as well, however).</para><para>SANE is
  a universal scanner interface. The value of such a universal interface is
  that it allows writing just one driver per image acquisition device rather
  than one driver for each device and application. So, if you have three
  applications and four devices, traditionally you&#39;d have had to write 12
  different programs. With SANE, this number is reduced to seven: the three
  applications plus the four drivers. Of course, the savings get even bigger
  as more and more drivers and/or applications are added.</para><para>Not only
  does SANE reduce development time and code duplication, it also raises the
  level at which applications can work. As such, it will enable applications
  that were previously unheard of in the UNIX world. While SANE is primarily
  targeted at a UNIX environment, the standard has been carefully designed to
  make it possible to implement the API on virtually any hardware or operating
  system.</para><para>While SANE is an acronym for ``Scanner Access Now
  Easy&#39;&#39; the hope is of course that SANE is indeed sane in the sense
  that it will allow easy implementation of the API while accommodating all
  features required by today&#39;s scanner hardware and applications.
  Specifically, SANE should be broad enough to accommodate devices such as
  scanners, digital still and video cameras, as well as virtual devices like
  image file filters.</para><para>If you&#39;re familiar with TWAIN, you may
  wonder why there is a need for SANE. Simply put, TWAIN does not separate the
  user-interface from the driver of a device. This, unfortunately, makes it
  difficult, if not impossible, to provide network transparent access to image
  acquisition devices (which is useful if you have a LAN full of machines, but
  scanners connected to only one or two machines; it&#39;s obviously also
  useful for remote-controlled cameras and such). It also means that any
  particular TWAIN driver is pretty much married to a particular GUI API (be
  it Win32 or the Mac API). In contrast, SANE cleanly separates device
  controls from their representation in a user-interface. As a result, SANE
  has no difficulty supporting command-line driven interfaces or
  network-transparent scanning. For these reasons, it is unlikely that there
  will ever be a SANE backend that can talk to a TWAIN driver. The converse is
  no problem though: it would be pretty straight forward to access SANE
  devices through a TWAIN source. In summary, if TWAIN had been just a little
  better designed, there would have been no reason for SANE to exist, but
  things being the way they are, TWAIN simply isn&#39;t SANE.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/securetty</term><listitem><para>Identifies
  secure terminals, i.e., the terminals from which root is allowed to log in.
  Typically only the virtual consoles are listed, so that it becomes
  impossible (or at least harder) to gain superuser privileges by breaking
  into a system over a modem or a network. 
  
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para><screen> 
  # /etc/securetty: list of terminals on which root is allowed to login.
  # See securetty(5) and login(1).
  console

  # Standard consoles
  tty1
  tty2
  tty3
  tty4
  tty5
  tty6
  tty7
  tty8
  tty9
  tty10
  tty11
  tty12

  # Same as above, but these only occur with devfs devices
  vc/1
  vc/2
  vc/3
  vc/4
  vc/5
  vc/6
  vc/7
  vc/8
  vc/9
  vc/10
  vc/11
  vc/12
  </screen> </para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/sensors.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for libsensors. A set of libraries designed to ascertain current
  hardware states via motherboard sensor chips. Useful statistics such as core
  voltages, CPU temperature can be determined through third party utilities
  that make user of these libraries such as &#39;gkrellm&#39;. If you do not
  wish to install these packages you may also utilise the /proc filesystem
  real-time nature.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/sudoers</term><listitem><para>Sudoers
  file. This file must be edited with the &#39;visudo&#39; command as root.
  The sudo command allows an authenticated user to execute an authorized
  command as root. Both the effective UID and GID are set to 0 (you are
  basically root). It determines which users are authorized and which commands
  they are authorized to use. Configuration of this command is via this file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/shadow</term><listitem><para>Shadow
  password file on systems with shadow password software installed (PAMs).
  Shadow passwords move the encrypted password from /etc/passwd into
  /etc/shadow; the latter is not readable by anyone except root. This makes it
  more difficult to crack passwords.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/shadow-</term><listitem><para>Old
  /etc/shadow file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/sysctl.conf</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  file for setting system variables, most notably kernel parameters.
  &#39;sysctl&#39; is a means of configuring certain aspects of the kernel at
  run-time, and the /proc/sys/ directory is there so that you don&#39;t even
  need special tools to do it!</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/security</term><listitem><para>Essential
  to security. This subdirectory allows administrators to impose quota limits,
  access limits and also to configure PAM environments.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/serial.conf</term><listitem><para>Serial
  port configuration. Changeable parameters include speed, baud rate, port,
  irq and type.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/services</term><listitem><para>A
  definition of the networks, services and the associated port for each
  protocol that are available on this system. For example, web services (http)
  are assigned to port 80 by default.
  
  # /etc/services:
  # $Id$
  #
  # Network services, Internet style
  #
  # Note that it is presently the policy of IANA to assign a single
  # well-known port number for both TCP and UDP; hence, most entries
  # here have two entries even if the protocol doesn&#39;t support UDP
  # operations. Updated from RFC 1700, ``Assigned Numbers&#39;&#39; (October
  # 1994). Not all ports are included, only the more common ones.
  echo 7/tcp
  echo 7/udp
  discard 9/tcp sink null
  discard 9/udp sink null
  systat 11/tcp users
  daytime 13/tcp daytime
  13/udp netstat
  15/tcp qotd
  17/tcp quote msp
  18/tcp # message send protocol
  msp 18/udp # message send protocol
  chargen 19/tcp ttytst source
  chargen 19/udp ttytst source
  ftp-data 20/tcp
  ftp 21/tcp
  fsp 21/udp  fspd
  ssh 22/tcp # SSH Remote Login Protocol
  ssh 22/udp # SSH Remote Login Protocol
  telnet 23/tcp
  # 24 - private smtp 
  25/tcp mail
  # 26 - unassigned
  time 37/tcp timserver
  time 37/udp timserver
  rlp 39/udp resource # resource location
  nameserver 42/tcp name # IEN 116
  whois 43/tcp nicname
  re-mail-ck 50/tcp # Remote Mail Checking Protocol
  re-mail-ck 50/udp # Remote Mail Checking Protocol
  domain 53/tcp nameserver # name-domain server domain 53/udp
  nameserver netbios-ns 137/tcp # NETBIOS Name Service netbios-ns 137/udp
  netbios-dgm 138/tcp # NETBIOS Datagram Service
  netbios-dgm 138/udp
  netbios-ssn 139/tcp # NETBIOS session service
  netbios-ssn 139/udp
  x11 6000/tcp x11-0 # X windows system
  x11 6000/udp x11-0 # X windows system
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/shells</term><listitem><para>Lists
  trusted shells. The chsh command allows users to change their login shell
  only to shells listed in this file. ftpd, the server process that provides
  FTP services for a machine, will check that the user&#39;s shell is listed
  in /etc/shells and will not let people log in unless the shell is listed
  there. There are also some display managers that will passively or actively
  (dependent upon on distribution and display manager being used) refuse a
  user access to the system unless their shell is one of those listed here.
  
  <variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term></term><listitem>
  <para><screen>
  # /etc/shells: valid login shells
  /bin/ash
  /bin/bash
  /bin/csh
  /bin/sh
  /usr/bin/es
  /usr/bin/ksh 
  /bin/ksh
  /usr/bin/rc
  /usr/bin/tcsh
  /bin/tcsh
  /usr/bin/zsh
  /bin/sash
  /bin/zsh
  /usr/bin/esh
  </screen></para></listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/skel/</term><listitem><para>The
  default files for each new user are stored in this directory. Each time a
  new user is added, these skeleton files are copied into their home
  directory. An average system would have: .alias, .bash_profile, .bashrc and
  .cshrc files. Other files are left up to the system administrator.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/sysconfig/</term><listitem><para>This
  directory contains configuration files and subdirectories for the setup of
  system configuration specifics and for the boot process, like
  &#39;clock&#39;, which sets the timezone, or &#39;keyboard&#39; which
  controls the keyboard map. The contents may vary drastically depending on
  which distribution and what utilities you have installed. For example, on a
  Redhat or Mandrake based system it is possible to alter an endless array of
  attributes from the default desktop to whether DMA should be enabled for
  your IDE devices. On our Debian reference system though this folder is
  almost expedient containing only two files hwconf and soundcard which are
  both configured by the Redhat utilities hwconf and sndconfig respectively.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/slip</term><listitem><para>Configuration
  files for the setup and operation of SLIP (serial line IP) interface.
  Generally unused nowadays. This protocol has been superceded by the faster
  and more efficient PPP protocol.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/screenrc</term><listitem><para>This
  is the system wide screenrc. You can use this file to change the default
  behavior of screen system wide or copy it to ~/.screenrc and use it as a
  starting point for your own settings. Commands in this file are used to set
  options, bind screen functions to keys, redefine terminal capabilities, and
  to automatically establish one or more windows at the beginning of your
  screen session. This is not a comprehensive list of options, look at the
  screen manual for details on everything that you can put in this file.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/scrollkeeper.conf</term><listitem><para>A
  free electronic cataloging system for documentation. It stores metadata
  specified by the http://www.ibiblio.org/osrt/omf/ (Open Source Metadata
  Framework) as well as certain metadata extracted directly from documents
  (such as the table of contents). It provides various functionality
  pertaining to this metadata to help browsers, such as sorting the registered
  documents or searching the metadata for documents which satisfy a set of
  criteria.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/ssh</term><listitem><para>&#39;ssh&#39;
  configuration files. &#39;ssh&#39; is a secure rlogin/rsh/rcp replacement
  (OpenSSH). This is the portable version of OpenSSH, a free implementation of
  the Secure Shell protocol as specified by the IETF secsh working group.
  &#39;ssh&#39; (Secure Shell) is a program for logging into a remote machine
  and for executing commands on a remote machine. It provides secure encrypted
  communications between two untrusted hosts over an insecure network. X11
  connections and arbitrary TCP/IP ports can also be forwarded over the secure
  channel. It is intended as a replacement for rlogin, rsh and rcp, and can be
  used to provide applications with a secure communication channel. It should
  be noted that in some countries, particularly Iraq, and Pakistan, it may be
  illegal to use any encryption at all without a special permit.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/syslog.conf</term><listitem><para>Lists
  where log files should go, what messages are written to them and the level
  of verbosity. It is also now possible to filter based on message content,
  message integrity, message encryption (near future), portability and better
  network forwarding.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/termcap</term><listitem><para>The
  terminal capability database. Describes the &#34;escape sequences&#34; by
  which various terminals can be controlled. Programs are written so that
  instead of directly outputting an escape sequence that only works on a
  particular brand of terminal, they look up the correct sequence to do
  whatever it is they want to do in /etc/termcap. As a result most programs
  work with most kinds of terminals.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/timezone</term><listitem><para>local
  timezone.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>/etc/updatedb.conf</term><listitem><para>Sets
  environment variables that are used by updatedb which therefore configures
  the database for &#39;locate&#39;, a utility that locates a pattern in a
  database of filenames and returns the filenames that match.</para>

  <para><screen>
  # This file sets environment variables which are used by updatedb

  # filesystems which are pruned from updatedb database
  PRUNEFS="NFS nfs afs proc smbfs autofs auto iso9660 ncpfs coda devpts ftpfs"
  export PRUNEFS
  # paths which are pruned from updatedb database
  PRUNEPATHS="/tmp /usr/tmp /var/tmp /afs /amd /alex /var/spool"
  export PRUNEPATHS
  # netpaths which are added
  NETPATHS=""
  export NETPATHS
  </screen></para>
  </listitem></varlistentry>
  
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/vga</term><listitem><para>The
  configuration file for the svgalib is stored in this directory. svgalib
  provides graphics capabilities to programs running on the system console,
  without going through the X Window System. It uses direct access to the
  video hardware to provide low-level access to the standard VGA and SVGA
  graphics modes. It only works with some video hardware; so use with caution.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/vim</term><listitem><para>Contains
  configuration files for both vim and its X based counterpart gvim. A wide
  range of options can be accessed though these two files such as automatic
  indentation, syntax highlighting, etc....</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/xinetd.d/</term><listitem><para>The
  original &#39;inetd&#39; daemon has now been superceded by the much improved
  &#39;xinetd&#39;. &#39;inetd&#39; should be run at boot time by
  /etc/init.d/inetd (or /etc/rc.local on some systems). It then listens for
  connections on certain Internet sockets. When a connection is found on one
  of its sockets, it decides what service the socket corresponds to, and
  invokes a program to service the request. After the program is finished, it
  continues to listen on the socket (except in some cases). Essentially, inetd
  allows running one daemon to invoke several others, reducing load on the
  system. Services controlled via xinetd put their configuration files here.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/zlogin</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .zlogin file for zsh(1). This file is sourced only for login shells. It
  should contain commands that should be executed only in login shells. It
  should be used to set the terminal type and run a series of external
  commands (fortune, msgs, from, etc.)</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/zlogout</term><listitem><para>Commands
  to be executed upon user exit from the zsh. Its control is system-wide
  but the .zlogout file for zsh(1) does override it in terms of importance.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/zprofile</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .zprofile file for zsh(1). This file is sourced only for login shells (i.e.
  Shells invoked with &#34;-&#34; as the first character of argv[0], and
  shells invoked with the -l flag.)</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/zshenv</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .zshenv file for zsh(1). This file is sourced on all invocations of the
  shell. If the -f flag is present or if the NO_RCS option is set within this
  file, all other initialization files are skipped. This file should contain
  commands to set the command search path, plus other important environment
  variables. This file should not contain commands that produce output or
  assume the shell is attached to a tty.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry><term>/etc/zshrc</term><listitem><para>System-wide
  .zshrc file for zsh(1). This file is sourced only for interactive shells. It
  should contain commands to set up aliases, functions, options, key bindings,
  etc.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist></para>

  <para>Compliance with the FSSTND requires that the following directories, or
  symbolic links to directories are required in /etc:</para>

  <para><screen>
  opt       Configuration for /opt
  X11       Configuration for the X Window system (optional)
  sgml      Configuration for SGML (optional)
  xml       Configuration for XML (optional)

  The following directories, or symbolic links to directories must be in /etc,
  if the corresponding subsystem is installed:

  opt       Configuration for /opt

  The following files, or symbolic links to files, must be in /etc if the
  corresponding subsystem is installed (it is recommended that files be
  stored in subdirectories of /etc/ rather than directly in /etc:

  csh.login   Systemwide initialization file for C shell logins (optional)
  exports     NFS filesystem access control list (optional)
  fstab       Static information about filesystems (optional)
  ftpusers    FTP daemon user access control list (optional)
  gateways    File which lists gateways for routed (optional)
  gettydefs   Speed and terminal settings used by getty (optional)
  group       User group file (optional)
  host.conf   Resolver configuration file (optional)
  hosts       Static information about host names (optional)
  hosts.allow Host access file for TCP wrappers (optional)
  hosts.deny  Host access file for TCP wrappers (optional)
  hosts.equiv List of trusted hosts for rlogin, rsh, rcp (optional)
  hosts.lpd   List of trusted hosts for lpd (optional)
  inetd.conf  Configuration file for inetd (optional)
  inittab     Configuration file for init (optional)
  issue       Pre-login message and identification file (optional)
  ld.so.conf  List of extra directories to search for shared libraries 
              (optional)
  motd        Post-login message of the day file (optional)
  mtab        Dynamic information about filesystems (optional)
  mtools.conf Configuration file for mtools (optional)
  networks    Static information about network names (optional)
  passwd      The password file (optional)
  printcap    The lpd printer capability database (optional)
  profile     Systemwide initialization file for sh shell logins (optional)
  protocols   IP protocol listing (optional)
  resolv.conf Resolver configuration file (optional)
  rpc         RPC protocol listing (optional)
  securetty   TTY access control for root login (optional)
  services    Port names for network services (optional)
  shells      Pathnames of valid login shells (optional)
  syslog.conf Configuration file for syslogd (optional) 

  mtab does not fit the static nature of /etc: it is excepted for historical
  reasons. On some Linux systems, this may be a symbolic link to /proc/mounts,
  in which case this exception is not required.

  /etc/opt : Configuration files for /opt
  Host-specific configuration files for add-on application software packages
  must be installed within the directory /etc/opt/&#60;subdir&#62;, where 
  &#60;subdir&#62; is the name of the subtree in /opt where the static data
  from that package is stored.

  No structure is imposed on the internal arrangement of /etc/opt/&#60;subdir&#62;.
  If a configuration file must reside in a different location in order for the
  package or system to function properly, it may be placed in a location other
  than /etc/opt/&#60;subdir&#62;.

  The rationale behind this subtree is best explained by refering to the
  rationale for /opt.

  /etc/X11 : Configuration for the X Window System (optional)
  /etc/X11 is the location for all X11 host-specific configuration. This
  directory is necessary to allow local control if /usr is mounted read only.

  The following files, or symbolic links to files, must be in /etc/X11 if the
  corresponding subsystem is installed:

  Xconfig    The configuration file for early versions of XFree86 (optional)
  XF86Config The configuration file for XFree86 versions 3 and 4 (optional)
  Xmodmap    Global X11 keyboard modification file (optional)

  Subdirectories of /etc/X11 may include those for xdm and for any other
  programs (some window managers, for example) that need them.

  /etc/X11/xdm holds the configuration files for xdm. These are most of the
  files previously found in /usr/lib/X11/xdm. Some local variable data for
  xdm is stored in /var/lib/xdm.

  It is recommended that window managers with only one configuration file
  which is a default .*wmrc file must name it system.*wmrc (unless there is
  a widely-accepted alternative name) and not use a subdirectory. Any window
  manager subdirectories must be identically named to the actual window 
  manager binary.

  /etc/sgml : Configuration files for SGML (optional)
  Generic configuration files defining high-level parameters of the SGML
  systems are installed here. Files with names *.conf indicate generic
  configuration files. File with names *.cat are the DTD-specific centralized
  catalogs, containing references to all other catalogs needed to use the 
  given DTD. The super catalog file catalog references all the centralized
  catalogs.

  /etc/xml : Configuration files for XML (optional)
  Generic configuration files defining high-level parameters of the XML
  systems are installed here. Files with names *.conf indicate generic
  configuration files. The super catalog file catalog references all the
  centralized catalogs.		  
  </screen></para>

</sect1>
