<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY About-The-Author SYSTEM "About-the-Author.xml">
<!ENTITY Contributors SYSTEM "Contributors.xml">
<!ENTITY Disclaimer   SYSTEM "Disclaimer.xml">
<!ENTITY Donations SYSTEM "Donations.xml">
<!ENTITY Feedback     SYSTEM "Feedback.xml">
<!ENTITY GFDL         SYSTEM "fdl.xml">
<!ENTITY Foreward SYSTEM "Foreward.xml">
<!ENTITY The-Root-Directory SYSTEM "The-Root-Directory.xml">
<!ENTITY bin SYSTEM "bin.xml">
<!ENTITY boot SYSTEM "boot.xml">
<!ENTITY dev SYSTEM "dev.xml">
<!ENTITY etc SYSTEM "etc.xml">
<!ENTITY home SYSTEM "home.xml">
<!ENTITY initrd SYSTEM "initrd.xml">
<!ENTITY lib SYSTEM "lib.xml">
<!ENTITY lostfound SYSTEM "lostfound.xml">
<!ENTITY media SYSTEM "media.xml">
<!ENTITY mnt SYSTEM "mnt.xml">
<!ENTITY opt SYSTEM "opt.xml">
<!ENTITY proc SYSTEM "proc.xml">
<!ENTITY root SYSTEM "root.xml">
<!ENTITY sbin SYSTEM "sbin.xml">
<!ENTITY srv SYSTEM "srv.xml">
<!ENTITY tmp SYSTEM "tmp.xml">
<!ENTITY usr SYSTEM "usr.xml">
<!ENTITY var SYSTEM "var.xml">
<!ENTITY Glossary SYSTEM "Glossary.xml">
<!ENTITY Signals SYSTEM "Signals.xml">
<!ENTITY Sources SYSTEM "Sources.xml">
]>

<book>

<bookinfo>
<title>Linux Filesystem Hierarchy</title>
<subtitle>Version 0.65</subtitle>
<pubdate>2004-07-30</pubdate>

<author>
<firstname>Binh</firstname>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<affiliation>
<address>
<email>dtbnguyen(at)gmail(dot)com</email>
</address>
</affiliation>
</author>

<abstract>
<para>
This document outlines the set of requirements and guidelines for file and directory placement under the Linux operating system according to those of the FSSTND v2.3 final (January 29, 2004) and also its actual implementation on an arbitrary system. It is meant to be accessible to all members of the Linux community, be distribution independent and is intended to discuss the impact of the FSSTND and how it has managed to increase the efficiency of support interoperability of applications, system administration tools, development tools, and scripts as well as greater uniformity of documentation for these systems.
</para>

<para>Alternatives form of this document are available at:</para> 

<para><ulink url="http://elibrary.fultus.com/covers/technical/linux/guides/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/cover.html">
http://elibrary.fultus.com/covers/technical/linux/guides/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/cover.html</ulink></para>
<para>Fultus Corporation helps writers and companies to publish, promote,
market, and sell books and eBooks. Fultus combines traditional self-publishing
practices with modern technology to produce paperback and hardcover
print-on-demand (POD) books and electronic books (eBooks).
Fultus publishes works (fiction, non-fiction, science fiction, mystery,
...) by both published and unpublished authors. We enable you to
self-publish easily and cost-effectively, creating your book as
a print-ready paperback or hardcover POD book or as an electronic
book (eBook) in multiple eBook's formats. You retain all rights
to your work. We provide distribution to bookstores worldwide. And all
at a fraction of the cost of traditional publishing.
We also offer corporate publishing solutions that enable businesses to
produce and deliver manuals and documentation more efficiently and
economically. Our use of electronic delivery and print-on-demand technologies
reduces printed inventory and saves time.</para>

<!--

<para>
<ulink url="http://www.indialinux.org/">
	http://www.indialinux.org/</ulink>	
IndiaLinux.org - For an India with Open Source and Open Minds
</para>

-->

<para>Please inform the author as to whether you would like to create a
an alternative form of this document so that he can include 
you in this list. Also note that the author considers breaches 
of copyright to be extremely serious. He will pursue all claims 
to the fullest extent of the law.</para>

</abstract>

<legalnotice>
<para>Copyright 2003 Binh Nguyen</para>
<para>Trademarks are owned by their owners.</para>
<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
Version 1.2; with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts,
and with no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in
the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
</legalnotice>
</bookinfo>

<preface> <title>Source and pre-formatted versions available</title>
<para>The source code and other machine readable formats
of this book can be found on the Internet at the
Linux Documentation Project home page <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>
The latest version of this document can be found at
<ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/">
http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/</ulink>
</para>
</preface>

<chapter>
<title>Linux Filesystem Hierarchy</title>

&Foreward;
&The-Root-Directory;
&bin;
&boot;
&dev;
&etc;
&home;
&initrd;
&lib;
&lostfound;
&media;
&mnt;
&opt;
&proc;
&root;
&sbin;
&usr;
&var;
&srv;
&tmp;
</chapter>

&Glossary;
&Signals;
&Sources;
&About-The-Author;
&Contributors;
&Disclaimer;
&Donations;
&Feedback;
&GFDL;

</book>
