<sect1 id="mnt">
  <title>/mnt</title>

  <para>This is a generic mount point under which you mount your filesystems
  or devices. Mounting is the process by which you make a filesystem available
  to the system. After mounting your files will be accessible under the
  mount-point. This directory usually contains mount points or sub-directories
  where you mount your floppy and your CD. You can also create additional
  mount-points here if you wish. Standard mount points would include
  /mnt/cdrom and /mnt/floppy. There is no limitation to creating a mount-point
  anywhere on your system but by convention and for sheer practicality do not
  litter your file system with mount-points. It should be noted that some
  distributions like Debian allocate /floppy and /cdrom as mount points while
  Redhat and Mandrake puts them in /mnt/floppy and /mnt/cdrom respectively.</para>

  <para>
  However, it should be noted that as of FSSTND version 2.3 the purpose of this 
  directory has changed.
  </para>

  <para>
  <screen>
  This directory is provided so that the system administrator may temporarily
  mount a filesystem as needed. The content of this directory is a local issue
  and should not affect the manner in which any program is run.

  This directory must not be used by installation programs: a suitable temporary
  directory not in use by the system must be used instead.
  </screen>
  </para>

  <sect2 id="mount-and-umount"><title>Mounting and unmounting</title>
  <para>Before one can use a filesystem, it has to be <glossterm>mounted</glossterm>.
  The operating system then does various bookkeeping things to make sure that
  everything works. Since all files in UNIX are in a single directory tree,
  the mount operation will make it look like the contents of the new
  filesystem are the contents of an existing subdirectory in some already
  mounted filesystem.</para> <para>The mounts could be done as in the
  following example: 
  <screen> 
  <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mount /dev/hda2 /home</userinput> 
  <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mount /dev/hda3 /usr</userinput>
  <prompt>$</prompt> 
  </screen>
  The <command>mount</command> command takes two
  arguments. The first one is the device file corresponding to the disk or
  partition containing the filesystem. The second one is the directory below
  which it will be mounted. After these commands the contents of the two
  filesystems look just like the contents of the <filename>/home</filename>
  and <filename>/usr</filename> directories, respectively. One would then say
  that ``<filename>/dev/hda2</filename> <glossterm>is mounted on</glossterm>
  <filename>/home</filename>&#39;&#39;, and similarly for
  <filename>/usr</filename>. To look at either filesystem, one would look at
  the contents of the directory on which it has been mounted, just as if it
  were any other directory. Note the difference between the device file,
  <filename>/dev/hda2</filename>, and the mounted-on directory,
  <filename>/home</filename>. The device file gives access to the raw contents
  of the disk, the mounted-on directory gives access to the files on the disk.
  The mounted-on directory is called the <glossterm>mount point</glossterm>.</para>
  <para>Linux supports many filesystem types. <command>mount</command> tries
  to guess the type of the filesystem. You can also use the <option>-t fstype</option>
  option to specify the type directly; this is sometimes necessary, since the
  heuristics <command>mount</command> uses do not always work. For example, to
  mount an MS-DOS floppy, you could use the following command: </para>
  <screen>
  <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mount -t msdos /dev/fd0 /floppy</userinput>
  <prompt> $</prompt>
  </screen> 
  <para>The mounted-on directory need not be empty,
  although it must exist. Any files in it, however, will be inaccessible by
  name while the filesystem is mounted. (Any files that have already been
  opened will still be accessible. Files that have hard links from other
  directories can be accessed using those names.) There is no harm done with
  this, and it can even be useful. For instance, some people like to have
  <filename>/tmp</filename> and <filename>/var/tmp</filename> synonymous, and
  make <filename>/tmp</filename> be a symbolic link to <filename>/var/tmp</filename>.
  When the system is booted, before the <filename>/var</filename> filesystem
  is mounted, a <filename>/var/tmp</filename> directory residing on the root
  filesystem is used instead. When <filename>/var</filename> is mounted, it
  will make the <filename>/var/tmp</filename> directory on the root filesystem
  inaccessible. If <filename>/var/tmp</filename> didn&#39;t exist on the root
  filesystem, it would be impossible to use temporary files before mounting
  <filename>/var</filename>.</para> <para>If you don&#39;t intend to write
  anything to the filesystem, use the <option>-r</option> switch for
  <command>mount</command> to do a <glossterm>read-only mount</glossterm>.
  This will make the kernel stop any attempts at writing to the filesystem,
  and will also stop the kernel from updating file access times in the inodes.
  Read-only mounts are necessary for unwritable media, e.g., CD-ROMs.</para>
  <para>The alert reader has already noticed a slight logistical problem. How
  is the first filesystem (called the <glossterm>root filesystem</glossterm>,
  because it contains the root directory) mounted, since it obviously
  can&#39;t be mounted on another filesystem? Well, the answer is that it is
  done by magic.</para> <para>For more information, see the kernel source or
  the Kernel Hackers&#39; Guide. </para> <para>The root filesystem is
  magically mounted at boot time, and one can rely on it to always be mounted.
  If the root filesystem can&#39;t be mounted, the system does not boot. The
  name of the filesystem that is magically mounted as root is either compiled
  into the kernel, or set using LILO or <command>rdev</command>.</para>
  <para>The root filesystem is usually first mounted read-only. The startup
  scripts will then run <command>fsck</command> to verify its validity, and if
  there are no problems, they will <glossterm>re-mount</glossterm> it so that
  writes will also be allowed. <command>fsck</command> must not be run on a
  mounted filesystem, since any changes to the filesystem while
  <command>fsck</command> is running <emphasis>will</emphasis> cause trouble.
  Since the root filesystem is mounted read-only while it is being checked,
  <command>fsck</command> can fix any problems without worry, since the
  remount operation will flush any metadata that the filesystem keeps in
  memory.</para> <para>On many systems there are other filesystems that should
  also be mounted automatically at boot time. These are specified in the
  <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file; see the fstab man page for details on
  the format. The details of exactly when the extra filesystems are mounted
  depend on many factors, and can be configured by each administrator if need
  be.</para> <para>When a filesystem no longer needs to be mounted, it can be
  unmounted with <command>umount</command>.</para> <para>It should of course
  be <command>unmount</command>, but the n mysteriously disappeared in the
  70s, and hasn&#39;t been seen since. Please return it to Bell Labs, NJ, if
  you find it.</para> <para><command>umount</command> takes one argument:
  either the device file or the mount point. For example, to unmount the
  directories of the previous example, one could use the commands</para>
  <screen>
  <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>umount /dev/hda2</userinput>
  <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>umount /usr</userinput>
  <prompt>$</prompt>
  </screen>
  <para>See the man page for further instructions on how to use the command.
  It is imperative that you always unmount a mounted floppy.
  <emphasis>Don&#39;t just pop the floppy out of the drive!</emphasis> Because
  of disk caching, the data is not necessarily written to the floppy until you
  unmount it, so removing the floppy from the drive too early might cause the
  contents to become garbled. If you only read from the floppy, this is not
  very likely, but if you write, even accidentally, the result may be
  catastrophic.</para> <para>Mounting and unmounting requires super user
  privileges, i.e., only root can do it. The reason for this is that if any
  user can mount a floppy on any directory, then it is rather easy to create a
  floppy with, say, a Trojan horse disguised as <filename>/bin/sh</filename>,
  or any other often used program. However, it is often necessary to allow
  users to use floppies, and there are several ways to do this:
  <itemizedlist> <listitem><para>Give the users the root password. This is
  obviously bad security, but is the easiest solution. It works well if there
  is no need for security anyway, which is the case on many non-networked,
  personal systems.</para></listitem> <listitem><para>Use a program such as
  <command>sudo</command> to allow users to use mount. This is still bad
  security, but doesn&#39;t directly give super user privileges to everyone.
  <footnote><para>It requires several seconds of hard thinking on the
  users&#39; behalf. Furthermore <command>sudo</command> can be configured to
  only allow users to execute certain commands. See the sudo(8), sudoers(5),
  and visudo(8) manual pages. </para></footnote> </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Make the users use <command>mtools</command>, a package for
  manipulating MS-DOS filesystems, without mounting them. This works well if
  MS-DOS floppies are all that is needed, but is rather awkward otherwise.
  </para></listitem> <listitem><para>List the floppy devices and their
  allowable mount points together with the suitable options in
  <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>.</para></listitem> </itemizedlist>The last
  alternative can be implemented by adding a line like the following to the
  <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file: </para>
  <para><screen>
  /dev/fd0 /floppy
  msdos user,noauto 0 0
  </screen></para>
  <para>The columns are: device file to
  mount, directory to mount on, filesystem type, options, backup frequency
  (used by <command>dump</command>), and <command>fsck</command> pass number
  (to specify the order in which filesystems should be checked upon boot; 0
  means no check).</para> <para>The <option>noauto</option> option stops this
  mount to be done automatically when the system is started (i.e., it stops
  <command>mount -a</command> from mounting it). The <option>user</option>
  option allows any user to mount the filesystem, and, because of security
  reasons, disallows execution of programs (normal or setuid) and
  interpretation of device files from the mounted filesystem. After this, any
  user can mount a floppy with an msdos filesystem with the following command:
  </para><para>
  <screen> 
  <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mount /floppy</userinput>
  <prompt>$</prompt>
  </screen>
  </para><para>The floppy can (and needs to, of course) be
  unmounted with the corresponding <command>umount</command> command.</para>
  <para>If you want to provide access to several types of floppies, you need
  to give several mount points. The settings can be different for each mount
  point. For example, to give access to both MS-DOS and ext2 floppies, you
  could have the following to lines in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>:
  </para>
  <para><screen>
  /dev/fd0 /dosfloppy msdos user,noauto 0 0 /dev/fd0
  /ext2floppy ext2 user,noauto 0 0
  </screen></para>
  <para>For MS-DOS
  filesystems (not just floppies), you probably want to restrict access to it
  by using the <option>uid</option>, <option>gid</option>, and
  <option>umask</option> filesystem options, described in detail on the
  <command>mount</command> manual page. If you aren&#39;t careful, mounting an
  MS-DOS filesystem gives everyone at least read access to the files in it,
  which is not a good idea.</para></sect2>
  
</sect1>
