<chapter id="/sbin">
  <title>/sbin</title>
    <para>Linux discriminates between 'normal' executables and those used for system maintenance or administrative tasks. The latter reside either here or - the less important ones - in /usr/sbin. Locally installed system administration programs should be placed into /usr/local/sbin. Programs executed after /usr is known to be mounted (when there are no problems) are generally placed into /usr/sbin. This directory contains all the binaries that are essential to the working of the system. These include system administration as well as maintenance and hardware configuration programs. You may find lilo, fdisk, init, ifconfig, etc here. These are the essential programs that are required by all the users. Another directory that contains system binaries is /usr/sbin. This directory contains other binaries of use to the system administrator. This is where you will find the network daemons for your system along with other binaries that only the system administrator has access to, but which are not required for system maintenance and repair. For obvious security reasons, these directories are never part of normal user's $PATHs, only of roots (PATH is an environment variable that controls the sequence of locations that the sytem will attempt to look in for commands).
    </para>

    <para>
    FSSTND compliance requires that the following commands, or symbolic links to commands,
    are required in /sbin.
    </para>

    <para><screen>shutdown Command to bring the system down.</screen></para>
			
    <para>The following files, or symbolic links to files, must be in /sbin if the corresponding subsystem is installed:
    </para>

	<para>
	<screen>
       fastboot   Reboot the system without checking the disks (optional)
       fasthalt   Stop the system without checking the disks (optional)
       fdisk      Partition table manipulator (optional)
       fsck       File system check and repair utility (optional)
       fsck.*     File system check and repair utility for a specific filesystem (optional)
       getty      The getty program (optional)
       halt       Command to stop the system (optional)
       ifconfig   Configure a network interface (optional)
       init       Initial process (optional)
       mkfs       Command to build a filesystem (optional)
       mkfs.*     Command to build a specific filesystem (optional)
       mkswap     Command to set up a swap area (optional)
       reboot     Command to reboot the system (optional)
       route      IP routing table utility (optional)
       swapon     Enable paging and swapping (optional)
       swapoff    Disable paging and swapping (optional)
       update     Daemon to periodically flush filesystem buffers (optional)
       </screen>
       </para>
       
	</chapter>
