<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<chapter id="chap_02"><title>Quickstart</title>
<abstract>
<para>In order to get the most out of this guide, we will immediately start with a practical chapter on connecting to the Linux system and doing some basic things.</para>
<para>We will discuss:</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Connecting to the system</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Disconnecting from the system</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Text and graphic mode</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Changing your password</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Navigating through the file system</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Determining file type</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Looking at text files</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Moving and deleting files</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</abstract>
<sect1 id="sect_02_01"><title>Logging in, activating the user interface and logging out</title>
<sect2 id="sect_02_01_01"><title>Introduction</title>
<para>In order to work on a Linux system directly, you will need to provide a user name and password.  You always need to authenticate to the system.  As we already mentioned in the exercise from <xref linkend="chap_01" />, most PC-based Linux systems have two basic modes for a system to run in: either quick and sober in text console mode, which looks like DOS with mouse, multitasking and multi-user features, or in graphical console mode, which looks better but eats more system resources.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sect_02_01_02"><title>Graphical mode</title>
<para>When you see something in a window, you're in graphical mode.</para>
<para>To log in, make sure the mouse pointer is in the login window, provide your user name and password to the system and click OK or press [ENTER].</para>
<note><title>Careful with that root account!</title>
<para>It is generally considered a bad idea to connect (graphically) using the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user name, the system adminstrator's account, since the use of graphics includes running a lot of extra programs, in root's case with a lot of extra permissions.  To keep all risks as low as possible, use a normal user account to connect graphically.  But there are enough risks to keep this in mind as a general advice, for all use of the root account: only log in as root when extra privileges are required.</para>
</note>
<para>After entering your user name/password combination, it can take a little while before the graphical environment is started, depending on the CPU speed of your computer and the software used.</para>
<para>To continue, you will need to open a <emphasis>terminal window</emphasis> or <emphasis>xterm</emphasis> for short (X being the name for the underlying software supporting the graphical environment).  This program can be found in the Utilities or Internet menu, depending on what window manager you are using.  There might be icons that you can use as a shortcut to get an xterm window as well, and clicking the right mouse button on the desktop background will usually present you with a menu containing a terminal window application.</para>
<para>While browsing the menus, you will notice that a lot of things can be done without entering commands via the keyboard.  For most users, the good old point-'n'-click method of dealing with the computer will do.  But this guide is for future network and system administrators, who will need to meddle with the heart of the system.  They need a stronger tool than a mouse to handle all the tasks they will face.  This tool is the shell, and when in graphical mode, we activate our shell by opening a terminal window.</para>
<para>The terminal window is your control panel for the system.  Almost everything that follows is done using this simple but powerful text tool.  A terminal window should always show a command prompt when you open one.  This terminal shows a standard prompt, which displays the user's login name, the name of the machine which this terminal commands, and the current working directory:</para>
<figure><title>Terminal window</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/xterm.eps" format="EPS"></imagedata>
</imageobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/xterm.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>Later we will discuss prompts and their behavior in detail.</para>
<para>To disconnect from the system in graphical mode, you need to close all terminal windows and other applications.  After that, hit the logout icon or find <emphasis>Log Out</emphasis> in the menu.  Closing everything is not really necessary, and the system can do this for you, but session management will put all currently open applications back on your screen when you connect again, which takes longer and is not always the desired effect.</para>
<para>When you see the login screen again, asking to enter user name and password, logout was successful.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="sect_02_01_03"><title>Text mode</title>
<para>You know you're in text mode when the whole screen is black, showing (in most cases white) characters.  A text mode login screen typically shows some information about the machine you are working on, the name of the machine and a prompt waiting for you to log in:</para>

<screen>

RedHat Linux Release 7.2 (Enigma)

blast login: _




</screen>
<para>The login is different from a graphical login, in that you have to hit the [ENTER] key after providing your user name.  Then you should enter your password, followed by another [ENTER].  You won't see any indication that you are entering something, not even an asterisk, and you won't see the cursor move.  But this is normal on Linux and is done for security reasons.</para>
<para>When the system has accepted you as a valid user, you may get some more information, called the <emphasis>message of the day</emphasis>, which can be anything and is not displayed when opening a graphical terminal.  But after that, you will be given a shell, indicated with the same prompt that you would get in graphical mode.</para>
<para>Logging out is done by entering the <command>logout</command> command, followed by [ENTER].  You are successfully disconnected from the system when you see the login screen again.</para>
<note><title>Don't hit the power button!</title>
<para>Don't power-off the computer after logging out.  It is not meant to be shut off without application of the proper procedures for halting the system.  Powering it off without going through the halting process might cause severe damage!</para></note>
<para>Now that we know how to connect to and disconnect from the system, we're ready for our first commands.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="sect_02_02"><title>Absolute basics</title>
<sect2 id="sect_02_02_01"><title>The commands</title>
<para>These are the quickies, which we need to get started, and we will discuss them later in more detail:</para>
<table frame="all">
<title>Quickstart commands</title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Command</entry>
<entry>Meaning</entry>
</row>
</thead>

<tbody>

<row>
<entry><command>ls</command></entry>
<entry><para>Displays a list of files in the current working directory, like the <command>dir</command> command in DOS</para></entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>cd <filename>directory</filename></command></entry>
<entry><para>change directories</para></entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry><command>passwd</command></entry>
<entry>change the password for the current user</entry>
</row>   

<row>
<entry><command>file <filename>filename</filename></command></entry>
<entry>display file type of file with name <filename>filename</filename></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>cat <filename>textfile</filename></command></entry>
<entry>throws content of <filename>textfile</filename> on the screen</entry>
</row>
<row><entry><command>pwd</command></entry>
<entry>display present working directory</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>exit</command> or <command>logout</command></entry>
<entry>leave this session</entry>
</row>   
<row>
<entry><command>man <option>command</option></command></entry>
<entry>read man pages on <command>command</command></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>info <option>command</option></command></entry>
<entry>read Info pages on <command>command</command></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><command>apropos <option>string</option></command></entry>
<entry>search the <emphasis>whatis</emphasis> database for strings</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sect_02_02_02"><title>General remarks</title>
<para>In Linux, like in UNIX, directories are separated using forward slashes, like the ones used in web addresses (URLs).  We will discuss directory structure indepth later.</para>
<para>The symbols . and .. have special meaning when directories are concerned.  We will try to find out about those during the exercises, and more in the next chapter.</para>
<para>Try to avoid logging in with or using the system administrator's account, <emphasis>root</emphasis>.  Besides doing your normal work, most tasks, including checking the system, collecting information etc., can be executed using a normal user account with no special permissions at all.  If needed, for instance when creating a new user or installing new software, the preferred way of obtaining root access is by switching user IDs, see <xref linkend="sect_03_02_01" /> for an example.</para>  
<para>Almost all commands in this book can be executed without system administrator priviledges.  In most cases, when issuing a command or starting a program as a non-privileged user, the system will warn you or prompt you for the root password when root access is required.  Once you've done, leave the application or session that gives you root privileges immediately.</para>
<para>Reading documentation should become your second nature.  Especially in the beginning, it is important to read system documentation, manuals for basic commands, HOWTOs and so on.  Since the amount of documentation is so enormous, it is impossible to include all related documentation.  This book will try to guide you to the most appropriate documentation on every subject discussed, in order to stimulate the habit of reading the man pages.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="sect_02_02_03"><title>The man pages</title>
<para>A lot of beginning users fear the man (manual) pages, because they are an overwhelming source of documentation.  They are, however, very structured, as you will see from the example below on: <command>man <option>man</option></command>.</para>
<para>Reading man pages is usually done in a terminal window when in graphical mode, or just in text mode if you prefer it.  Type the command like this at the prompt, followed by enter:</para>
<screen>
yourname@yourcomp ~&gt; man man
</screen>
<para>The documentation for <command>man</command> will be displayed on your screen after you press enter:</para>  
<screen>
man(1)                                                         man(1)



NAME
 man - format and display the on-line manual pages
 manpath - determine user's search path for man pages

SYNOPSIS
 man [-acdfFhkKtwW] [--path] [-m system] [-p string] [-C config_file]
 [-M pathlist] [-P pager] [-S section_list] [section] name ...


DESCRIPTION
 man formats and displays the on-line manual pages.  If you specify
 section, man only looks in that section of the manual.  
 name is normally the name of the manual page, which is typically the 
 name of a  command, function, or file.  However, if name contains a 
 slash (/) then man interprets it as a file specification, so that you
 can do man ./foo.5 or even man /cd/foo/bar.1.gz.

 See  below  for  a  description  of where man looks for the manual
 page files.

OPTIONS
 -C  config_file
lines 1-27
</screen>
<para>Browse to the next page using the space bar.  You can go back to the previous page using the b-key.  When you reach the end, <command>man</command> will quit and you get the prompt back, or type q if you want to leave the man page before reaching the end.</para>
<para>Each man page usually contains a couple of standard sections, as we can see from the <command>man <option>man</option></command> example:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The first line contains the name of the command you are reading about, and the id of the section in which this man page is located.  The man pages are ordered in chapters.  Commands are likely to have multiple man pages, for example the man page from the user section, the man page from the system admin section, and the man page from the programmer section.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The name of the command and a short description are given, which is used for building an index of the man pages.  You can look for any given search string in this index using the <command>apropos</command> command.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The synopsis of the command provides a technical notation of all the options and/or arguments this command can take.  You can think of an option as a way of executing the command.  The argument is what you execute it on.  Some commands have no options or no arguments.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>A longer description of the command is given.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Options with their descriptions are listed.  Options can usually be combined.  If not so, this section will tell you about it.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Environment describes the shell variables that influence the behavior of this command (not all commands have this).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sometimes sections specific to this command are provided, such as the CAT PAGES section in the example.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>A reference to other man pages is given in the SEE ALSO section.  In between parentheses is the number of the man page section in which to find this command.  Experienced users often switch to the SEE ALSO part using the <command>/</command> command followed by the search string SEE and [ENTER].</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Usually there is also information about known bugs (anomalies) and where to report new bugs you may find.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>There might also be author and copyright information.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Some commands have multiple man pages.  For instance, the <command>passwd</command> command has a man page in section 1 and another in section 5.  By default, the man page with the lowest number is shown.  If you want to see another section than the default, specify it after the <command>man</command> command:</para>
<cmdsynopsis><command>man <option>5</option> passwd</command></cmdsynopsis>
<para>If you want to see all man pages about a command, one after the other, use the <option>-a</option> to man:</para>
<cmdsynopsis><command>man <option>-a</option> passwd</command></cmdsynopsis>
<para>This way, when you reach the end of the first man page and press <keycap>SPACE</keycap> again, the man page from the next section will be displayed.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sect_02_02_04"><title>More info</title>
<sect3 id="sect_02_02_04_01"><title>The Info pages</title>
<para>In addition to the man pages, you can read the info pages about a command, using the <command>info</command> command.  These usually contain more recent information and are somewhat easier to use.  The man pages for some commands refer to the info pages.</para>
<para>Get started with <command>info <option>info</option></command>.  Use the arrow keys to browse trough the text and move the cursor on a line starting with an asterisk, containing the keyword about which you want info.  Use the p- and n-keys to go to the previous or next subject.  The space bar will move you one page further, no matter whether this starts a new subject or an info page for another command.  Use <keycap>q</keycap> to quit.  The <command>info</command> program has more information.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sect_02_02_04_02"><title>The whatis and apropos commands</title>
<para>A short index of explanations for commands is available using the <command>whatis</command> command, like in the examples below:</para>
<screen>
[your_prompt] whatis ls
ls                   (1)  - list directory contents
</screen>
<para>This displays short information about a command, and the first section in the collection of man pages that contains an appropriate page.</para>
<para>If you don't know where to get started and which man page to read, <command>apropos</command> gives more information.  Say that you don't know how to start a browser, then you could enter the following command:</para>
<screen>
another prompt&gt; apropos browser
Galeon [galeon](1)  - gecko-based GNOME web browser
lynx           (1)  - a general purpose distributed information browser 
	            for the World Wide Web
ncftp          (1)  - Browser program for the File Transfer Protocol
opera          (1)  - a graphical web browser
pilot          (1)  - simple file system browser in the style of the 
		    Pine Composer
pinfo          (1)  - curses based lynx-style info browser
pinfo [pman]   (1)  - curses based lynx-style info browser
viewres        (1x)  - graphical class browser for Xt
</screen>
<para>After pressing enter you will see that a lot of browser related stuff is on your machine: not only web browsers, but also file and FTP browsers, and browsers for documentation.  If you have development packages installed, you may also have the accompanying man pages dealing with writing programs having to do with browsers.  Generally, a command with a man page in section one, so one marked with <quote>(1)</quote>, is suitable for trying out as a user.  The user who issued the above <command>apropos</command> might consequently try to start the commands <command>galeon</command>, <command>lynx</command> or <command>opera</command>, since these clearly have to do with browsing the world wide web.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sect_02_02_04_03"><title>The --help option</title>
<para>Most GNU commands support the <option>--help</option>, which gives a short explanation about how to use the command and a list of available options.  Below is the output of this option with the <command>cat</command>:</para>
<screen>
userprompt: cat --help
Usage: cat [OPTION] [FILE]...
Concatenate FILE(s), or standard input, to standard output.

  -A, --show-all           equivalent to -vET
  -b, --number-nonblank    number nonblank output lines
  -e                       equivalent to -vE
  -E, --show-ends          display $ at end of each line
  -n, --number             number all output lines
  -s, --squeeze-blank      never more than one single blank line
  -t                       equivalent to -vT
  -T, --show-tabs          display TAB characters as ^I
  -u                       (ignored)
  -v, --show-nonprinting   use ^ and M- notation, 
			   except for LFD and TAB
      --help     display this help and exit
      --version  output version information and exit

With no FILE, or when FILE is -, read standard input.

Report bugs to &lt;bug-textutils@gnu.org&gt;.
</screen>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sect_02_02_04_04"><title>Exceptions</title>
<para>Some commands don't have separate documentation, because they are part of another command.  <command>cd</command>, <command>exit</command>, <command>logout</command> and <command>pwd</command> are such exceptions.  They are part of your shell program and are called <emphasis>shell builtin</emphasis> commands.  For information about these, refer to the man or info page of your shell.  Most beginning Linux users have a Bash shell.  See <xref linkend="sect_03_02_03_02" /> for more about shells.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sect_02_03"><title>Exercises</title>
<para>Most of what we learn is by making mistakes and by seeing how things can go wrong.  These exercises are made to get you to read some error messages.  The order in which you do these exercises, is important.</para>
<sect2 id="sect_02_03_01"><title>Connecting and disconnecting</title>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Determine whether you are working in text or in graphical mode.</para>
<para>I am working in text/graphical mode.  (cross out what's not applicable)</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Log in with the user name and password you made for yourself during the installation.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Log out.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Log in again, using a non-existent user name</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="sect_02_03_02"><title>Passwords</title>
<para>Log in again with your user name and password.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Change your password into <emphasis>P6p3.aa!</emphasis> and hit the [ENTER] key.</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Try again, this time enter a password that is ridiculously easy, like <emphasis>123</emphasis> or <emphasis>aaa</emphasis>.</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Try again, this time don't enter a password but just hit the [ENTER] key.</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Try the command <command>psswd</command> instead of <command>passwd</command></para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="sect_02_03_03"><title>Directories</title>
<para>These are some exercises to help you get the feel.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Enter the command <command>cd <filename>blah</filename></command></para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Enter the command <command>cd <filename>..</filename></command></para>
<para>Mind the space between "cd" and ".."!  Use the <command>pwd</command> command.</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>List the directory contents with the <command>ls</command> command.</para>
<para>-&gt; What do you see?</para>
<para>-&gt; What do you think these are?</para>
<para>-&gt; Check using the <command>pwd</command> command.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Enter the <command>cd</command> command.</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Repeat step 2 two times.</para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Display the content of this directory.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Try the command <command>cd <filename>root</filename></command></para>
<para>-&gt; What happens?</para>
<para>-&gt; To which directories do you have access?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Repeat step 4.</para>
<para>Do you know another possibility to get where you are now?</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sect_02_03_04"><title>Files</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Change directory to <filename>/</filename> and then to <filename>etc</filename>.  Type <command>ls</command>; if the output is longer than your screen, make the window longer, or try [SHIFT]+[Page Up] and [SHIFT]+[Page Down].</para>
<para>The file <filename>inittab</filename> contains the answer to the first question in this list.  Try the <command>file</command> command on it.</para>
<para>-&gt; The file type of my <filename>inittab</filename> is  .....</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Use the command <command>cat <filename>inittab</filename></command> and read the file.</para>
<para>-&gt; What is the default mode of your computer?</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Return to your home directory using the <command>cd</command> command.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Enter the command <command>file .</command></para>
<para>-&gt; Does this help to find the meaning of "."? </para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Can you look at "." using the <command>cat</command> command?</para>
<para></para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Display help for the <command>cat</command> program, using the <option>--help</option> option.  Use the option for numbering of output lines to count how many users are listed in the file <filename>/etc/passwd</filename>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sect_02_03_05"><title>Getting help</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Read <command>man <option>intro</option></command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Read <command>man <option>ls</option></command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Read <command>info <option>passwd</option></command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Read <command>apropos <option>pwd</option></command></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Try <command>man</command> or <command>info</command> on <command>cd</command>.</para>
<para>-&gt; How would you find out more about <command>cd</command>? </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
