<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY chap1 SYSTEM "chap1.xml">
<!ENTITY chap2 SYSTEM "chap2.xml">
<!ENTITY chap3 SYSTEM "chap3.xml">
<!ENTITY chap4 SYSTEM "chap4.xml">
<!ENTITY chap5 SYSTEM "chap5.xml">
<!ENTITY chap6 SYSTEM "chap6.xml">
<!ENTITY chap7 SYSTEM "chap7.xml">
<!ENTITY chap8 SYSTEM "chap8.xml">
<!ENTITY chap9 SYSTEM "chap9.xml">
<!ENTITY chap10 SYSTEM "chap10.xml">
<!ENTITY app1 SYSTEM "app1.xml">
<!ENTITY app2 SYSTEM "app2.xml">
<!ENTITY app3 SYSTEM "app3.xml">
<!ENTITY app4 SYSTEM "app4.xml">
<!ENTITY gloss SYSTEM "gloss.xml">
]>

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Introduction to Linux</title>
    <subtitle>A Hands on Guide</subtitle>

<authorgroup>
      <author>
	<firstname>Machtelt</firstname>
	<surname>Garrels</surname>
	<affiliation>
<orgname>CoreSequence.com
</orgname>
<address>
<email>tille@coresequence.com</email>
</address>
	</affiliation>
      </author>
</authorgroup>

<edition>Version 3.0.3 Last updated 20030325</edition>
<keywordset>
      <keyword>Linux</keyword>
      <keyword>Beginners</keyword>
      <keyword>linux</keyword>
      <keyword>start</keyword>
      <keyword>Getting started</keyword>
      <keyword>guide</keyword>
      <keyword>Guide</keyword>
      <keyword>Exercises</keyword>
      <keyword>exercises</keyword>
</keywordset>
</bookinfo>

<preface>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section id="intro_01">
<title>Why this guide?</title>

<para>Many people still believe that learning Linux is difficult, or that only experts can understand how a Linux system works.  Though there is a lot of free documentation available, the documentation is widely scattered on the Web, and often confusing, since it is usually oriented toward experienced UNIX or Linux users.   Today, thanks to the advancements in development, Linux has grown in popularity both at home and at work.  The goal of this guide is to show people of all ages that Linux can be simple and fun, and used for all kinds of purposes.</para>

</section>

<section id="intro_02">
<title>Who should read this book?</title>

<para>
This guide was created as an overview of the Linux Operating System, geared toward new users as an exploration tour and getting started guide, with exercises at the end of each chapter.  For more advanced trainees it can be a desktop reference, and a collection of the base knowledge needed to proceed with system and network administration.  This book contains many real life examples derived from the author's experience as a Linux system and network administrator, trainer and consultant.  We hope these examples will help you to get a better understanding of the Linux system and that you feel encouraged to try out things on your own.</para>
<para>Everybody who wants to get a CLUE, a Command Line User Experience, with Linux (and UNIX in general) will find this book useful.</para>
</section>

<section id="intro_03">
<title>New versions of this guide</title>

<para>This document is published in the Guides section of the Linux Documentation Project collection (<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>).  The most recent edition is also available at  <ulink url="http://tille.soti.org/training/tldp/">http://tille.soti.org/training/tldp/</ulink>.</para>
</section>

<section id="intro_04">
<title>Revision History</title>
<para>
<revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>2002-12-29</date>
	<authorinitials>MG</authorinitials>
        <revremark>Initial release for TLDP</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>2003-01-22</date>
	<authorinitials>MG</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Bug fixes;
removed some more too RedHat specific stuff;
corrected minor errors;
moved most recent version to decent URL;
improved tar section, added something about jar.</revremark>
      </revision>
	<revision>
        <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
        <date>2003-02-28</date>
        <authorinitials>MG</authorinitials>
        <revremark>ps a bit better explained;
more in getting started: --help, whatis, apropos explained;
more on find;
chmod and umask still contained a couple of errors and incompletenesses;
resized images that were too large to be printed;
resized oversized text boxes for better print quality;
updated glossary.</revremark>
      </revision>	
        <revision>
        <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
        <date>2003-03-26</date>
        <authorinitials>MG</authorinitials>
        <revremark>grep and escape characters; 
exporting variables; 
more consequent about security issues; 
init and cron revised; 
window and desktop managers explanation; 
removed some more too RedHat specific stuff; 
added piece about (x)inetd; 
local authentication;
text conversions and encoding;
graphical help, graphical file managers, note on internet connections;
spellcheck.
</revremark>
      </revision>
</revhistory>
</para>
</section>

<section id="intro_05">
<title>Contributions</title>

<para>
Many thanks to all the people who shared their experiences.  And especially to the Belgian Linux users, among them my husband, for hearing me out every day and always being generous in their comments.</para>
<para>Also a special thought for Tabatha Persad for doing a really thorough revision, spell check and styling, and to Eugene Crosser for marking the errors that we two looked over.</para>
<para>And thanks to all the readers who helped to pick out the last errors, unclear definitions and typos by going through the trouble of mailing me all their remarks.</para>
<para>Finally, a big thank you for the volunteers who are currently translating this document in French, Swedish, German and more.  It is a big work that should not be underestimated; I admire your braveness.</para>
</section>

<section id="intro_06">
<title>Feedback</title>

<para>
Missing information, missing links, missing characters?  Mail it to the maintainer of this document: <address><email>tille@coresequence.com</email></address>
</para>
<para>Don't forget to check with the <ulink url="http://tille.soti.org/training/tldp/">latest version</ulink> first!</para>
</section>

<section id="intro_07">
<title>Copyright information</title>

<para>Copyright &copy; 2002  Machtelt Garrels.</para>
<para> Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being <quote>New versions of this document</quote>, <quote>Contributions</quote>, <quote>Feedback</quote> and <quote>Copyright information</quote>, with no Front-Cover Texts and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in <xref linkend="app4" /> entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.</para>

<para>The author and publisher have made every effort in the preparation of this book to ensure the accuracy of the information.  However, the information contained in this book is sold without warranty, either express or implied.  Neither the author nor the publisher nor any dealer or distributor will be held liable for any damages caused or alleged to be caused either directly or indirectly by this book.</para>

<para>The logos, trademarks and symbols used in this book are the properties of their respective owners.</para>
</section>

<section id="intro_08">
<title>What do you need?</title>
<para>You will require a computer and a medium containing a Linux distribution.  Most of this guide applies to all Linux distributions - and UNIX in general.  Apart from time, there are no further specific requirements.</para>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Installation-HOWTO/">Installation HOWTO</ulink> contains helpful information on how to obtain Linux software and install it on your computer.  Hardware requirements and coexistence with other operating systems are also discussed.</para>

</section>

</preface>

<toc></toc>

&chap1;
&chap2;
&chap3;
&chap4;
&chap5;
&chap6;
&chap7;
&chap8;
&chap9;
&chap10;
&app1;
&app2;
&app3;
&app4;
&gloss;
</book>
