<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" []>
<book id="hLinux-Media-Guide">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Guide to Managing Media and Public Relations in the Linux Community
	</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/LPI.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
      <author>
	<firstname>Sheldon</firstname>
	<surname>Rose</surname>
      <address>
<email>sheldon (at) sackepr (dot) com</email>
	<affiliation>
          <jobtitle>Public Relations Counsel</jobtitle>
          <orgname><ulink url="http://www.lpi.org">Linux Professional Institute</ulink></orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </address>
    </author>

    <pubdate>2004-01-08</pubdate>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright &copy; 2005 by Linux Professional Institute. This material may be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v1.0 or later (the latest version is presently available at <ulink url="http://www.opencontent.org/openpub/"/>). Distribution of the work or derivative of the work in any standard (paper) book form is prohibited unless prior permission is obtained from the copyright holder.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <revhistory id="revhistory">
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>2005-04-21</date>
	<authorinitials>TM</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Update to correct links, update copyright notice</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2003-12-02</date>
	<authorinitials>SR</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial Release, reviewed by TM at LDP.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <abstract><para>This guide provides useful information on how to generate
  positive public relations and news media coverage for Linux.</para></abstract>

  </bookinfo>
  <toc></toc>
  <chapter id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section id="who_should_read">
      <title>Who Should Be Reading This Guide?</title>
      <para>This document is intended for people who want to learn
  practical and cost-effective ways to raise the profile of an
  organization or promote new programs.</para>
      <para>This guide provides useful information on how to generate
  positive public relations and news media coverage for Linux. By
  no means does the guide intend to teach all there is to know
  about public and media relations, but it does support you in
  building and maintaining a healthy public image.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="what_is">
      <title>What is Public Relations?</title>
      <para>You have news to share&mdash;information that
  would benefit the Linux community. You have some idea of the
  people you want to reach with your news and views. Now the
  problem becomes: How to reach them in the most effective way? The
  better the communications between you and your audience, the
  higher the profile of your organization.</para>
      <para>Generating publicity is not as complex as you might think.
  Most of the success of public relations centers on knowing what
  to do and when. Implementing these initiatives can dramatically
  increase awareness of your business.</para>
      <para>Public relations (PR) is often confused with advertising,
  merchandising, promotion, or any of a dozen other buzz words in
  the marketing communications vocabulary. (By the way, 
  <emphasis>marketing communications</emphasis> is a broad term that          encompasses all of these disciplines.)</para>
      <para>Public relations is about doing something newsworthy that
  you want to communicate, and then telling your audience (or very
  likely, several audiences) what you have done.</para>
      <para>One of the most common public relations vehicles is the
  brief <quote>New Product</quote> announcement
  you see in magazines and trade publications. Often only a few
  lines or a paragraph in length, these announcements herald the
  launch of future products or services. These short announcements
  are typically triggered by a new product release, which may be
  accompanied by various forms of communications such as internal
  announcements to the organization's employees
  and external news releases to the media, stockholders, user
  community, and other groups. News releases trigger a chain of
  events that result in visibility.</para>
      <para>There are some important terms that may help you understand
  public relations.  <emphasis role="bold">News media</emphasis>
  refers to all the places where people read or hear about news,
  including newspapers, magazines, television, radio, and the
  Internet.</para>
      <para>A <emphasis role="bold">news release</emphasis>, sometimes        referred to as a press release, is a printed or
  electronic document issued by organizations who want to
  communicate news to editors, journalists, industry writers, or
  other media groups. Journalists write about the story for
  publication (if it is considered newsworthy), while editors
  control whether the story actually appears in a newspaper,
  magazine, website, or broadcast.</para>
      <para>A news release contains important facts, quotes from key
  people, dates that the news happened (or will happen), and
  contacts for additional information. The news release is concise
  and usually runs no longer than two pages.</para>
      <para>Public relations, then, can be thought of as the process
  that delivers your news to the people you want to reach through a
  broad, influential, and far-reaching news media community.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="pr_vs_advertising">
      <title>How Public Relations Differs from Advertising</title>
      <para>International humorist Stephen Leacock defined advertising
  as: <quote>the science of arresting the human
  intelligence long enough to get money from it.</quote> But
  the textbook definition of advertising is: <quote>a
  form of persuasion that informs people about the goods and
  services they can purchase.</quote></para>
      <para>Advertising is very different from public relations. One
  key difference is that you always pay for the space and time of
  an advertisement (or commercial, which is an insert appearing on
  radio, television, or the Internet). By contrast, editorial
  coverage generated through public relations is not paid for by
  the organization issuing the news release. The media will pick up
  and publish the story because they consider it newsworthy, not as
  a paid advertisement.</para>
      <para>Another crucial difference is that, in advertising, you
  have virtually full control over the message. Because you are
  paying for advertising, the ad or commercial runs your exact text
  (called copy), provided the copy complies with generally
  acceptable standards for advertising. In the case of public
  relations, the media outlet you are targeting is under no
  obligation to run the story in any form. If a media outlet does
  decide to run the story, an editor will generally rewrite the
  news release, or use pertinent information from the news release
  to create the news. (For instance, your news release might be
  used as part of a larger story on players in your industry or
  profession.) In addition, you have no control over when the
  release or news will run. All decisions are made by the
  editor.</para>
      <para>As you can see, public relations is a cost-effective way of
  getting your story out. Taking the trouble to write effective
  news releases and to build a relationship with the relevant media
  will, in time, pay dividends in the form of exposure and
  prestige. Best of all, public relations probably costs less than
  a single advertisement.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="what_pr_can_do">
      <title>What Public Relations Can Do</title>
      <para>Since public relations communicates your messages through
  the news media, all the power of the media is brought to bear
  when the public&mdash;those viewers, listeners, or
  readers you want to reach&mdash;learns about your
  news.</para>
      <para>Think of what this means: high interest level, credibility,
  implied objectivity, and possibly implied endorsement by the
  journalist or publication reporting the information. There is
  also an urgency conveyed when news is reported in the
  media&mdash;and that news has the potential to reach
  a tremendously large audience.</para>
      <para>With exposure comes awareness. An important goal of public
  relations&mdash;in any medium&mdash;is to make people aware of what 
  your organization is, what it offers, and what it does. Never
  underestimate the value of such awareness. In flashier terms, 
  it's called <emphasis>buzz.</emphasis></para>
      <para>Creating awareness for your organization is important for
  the development and utilization of its programs and initiatives.
  You must inform the public and educational and training
  institutions about what you offer and how you can meet their
  needs. Public relations is probably the most valuable tool in
  accomplishing this. A well-implemented public relations
  initiative will help present your organization's offerings to their best
  advantage.</para>
      <para>Public and news media relations also positions you to enter
  new marketplaces and exposes new Linux programs to new
  audiences&mdash;all without the expense associated
  with an advertising program. A sustained public relations program
  allows you to ensure your programs are in front of appropriate
  decision-makers. This continuous flow of information creates a
  constant awareness and a constant influx of
  inquiries&mdash;especially when integrated with
  other powerful marketing communications tools such as brochures,
  trade shows, and so on.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>The Benefits of a Public and Media Relations Program</title>
      <para>Public relations is vitally necessary, perhaps even
  critical, in today's competitive marketplace.
  There are many ways a sustained public relations program can
  benefit your organization:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Public relations should not be a <quote>we
      will do it if we have the time and resources</quote>
      kind of effort. A sustained initiative can build your
      organization's profile in the news media
      and the local community.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Editorial coverage gives your organization better
      stakeholder attention compared to paid advertisements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Editorial copy generated through effective public
      relations is far more believable and credible than paid
      advertising, due to media objectivity. Recent studies in
      North America suggest that positive editorial coverage
      generates up to nine times more visibility than paid
      advertising.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Public relations is an economical means of promoting
      your organization.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Regular and effective news releases can make your
      organization a <quote>news media
      source</quote> on the state of Linux. It is critical to
      develop relationships with the news media in the same way it
      is a good idea to develop other kinds of friendships in the
      community. Writers and reporters are always looking for
      reliable and respected sources to quote.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Regular media exposure legitimizes your
      organization's work and enhances its
      reputation. There is a subtle but nonetheless real perception
      that mention in a newspaper or on television must be
      important. Media coverage communicates to the business
      community that your organization's qualifications and programs are
      worthy of <quote>a serious look.</quote></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>You must also be cautious when dealing with media outlets.
  Being overconfident or overly aggressive in trying to place
  stories with the news media can have damaging results. It is a
  lot easier to lose goodwill than to gain it back. The safest
  position is to understand what you are doing, work hard to
  accomplish predetermined and realistic goals, be courteous and
  respectful when dealing with your media contacts, and expect some
  disappointments along the way. After all, hard as you may try,
  the results of your public and news media relations initiatives
  are never predictable. But if planned and implemented correctly,
  the benefits are enormous. <xref linkend="planning"></xref> explains how
  to determine what you really want to accomplish.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="planning">
    <title>Public and Media Relations Planning</title>
    <para>When you want to promote your organization, you are
  provided with a variety of options. The first step is to develop
  a plan. You must determine the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>What do you want to accomplish?</emphasis>
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Who do you want to reachneeds to know about your
        organization?</emphasis>
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>What do you want to say??</emphasis>
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>What kind of information is
        newsworthy?</emphasis>
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section id="what_accomplish">
      <title>What Do You Want to Accomplish?</title>
      <para>The first and most important step in public relations
  planning is to understand and define what you want to accomplish
  through public relations. What are your objectives? Just as
  importantly, how will you determine (measure) your success in
  accomplishing these objectives? Creating a list of concrete goals
  can help you maintain direction in your efforts.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="who_needs_know">
      <title>Who Needs to Know About Your Organization?</title>
      <para>Now that you know what you want to do, the second step is
  to determine who you need to talk to.</para>
      <para>The best way to gain insight into this question is to look
  from the other side of the communications channel: Of all the
  people that your organization deals with, who do you need to tell
  about new programs and products? Often your most important
  contacts will be your current and future partners, IT
  professionals in your local area, human resource managers,
  training and development personnel, and organizations offering
  competing products.</para>
      <para>To reach your organization's public
  relations goals, there are many key audiences and stakeholders
  that your organization should regularly communicate with to gain
  higher visibility. The following list details a few of the most
  important audiences:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">News media.</emphasis>
      Includes print, radio, television, and Internet outlets for
      business news, information technology news especially related
      to Linux and open source, vertical media (directed at a
      people with similar interests such as a hobby or business),
      human resources, colleges and universities, and organizations
      and enterprises dealing with Linux or Linux information
      management solutions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">IT professionals.</emphasis>
      Includes practicing IT professionals, students, and prospects
      such as people considering a career change.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Influencers.</emphasis>
      </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Other LPI affiliates.</emphasis>
      </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Business partners and
      suppliers.</emphasis>
      Includes communicating to strategic partners such as
      independent software vendors, training providers, and
      suppliers, which helps your organization become a valued
      business partner to these groups, each of which bring
      specific value to your business.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="what_to_say">
      <title>What Do You Want to Say?</title>
      <para>The third step in public relations planning is to
  understand what you want to say. To attain your objectives, it is
  critically important to maintain message consistency when
  delivering you organization's messages,
  vision, mission, and core values to your target audiences.
  Consistency creates a stronger impression and helps people
  remember your core messages.</para>
      <para>Although a given message may be <quote>tweaked</quote> or
  <quote>massaged</quote> for different audiences,
  the core messages should not vary.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="newsworthy_info">
      <title>What Kind of Information is Newsworthy?</title>
      <para>These are examples of great happenings that generate
  interest.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Locations and launches.</emphasis>
      This kind of news is obvious. For instance, a new branch of
      your organization may have just opened, and you want to make
      people aware of the new location and offerings. Also, if you
      are launching a new product or have hired a local figure
      well-known to the Linux community, these things are of great
      interest to the public.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Industry developments and human
      interest.</emphasis>
      Sometimes newsworthy information is a little less obvious.
      Every day happenings can be in the news. Whenever there are
      changes or new developments in the industry, this clearly
      presents an opportunity for positive exposure and media
      coverage in appropriate publications. For instance, how and
      why the change is being undertaken may become a story in
      itself. Perhaps the change is being driven by a dynamic Linux
      guru, worthy of a magazine profile. Sometimes these stories
      are called <quote>case studies</quote> and
      typically are given favourable consideration by editors
      because of their considerable human interest appeal.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Numerical data and trends.</emphasis>
      Society is fascinated with numbers. The more impressive or
      interesting the figures (relative to competitors and the rest
      of the industry), the more likely media outlets are to use
      those numbers in their reporting. 
      </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Organizational announcements.</emphasis>
      Notable changes in staff or volunteers are another way of
      getting media exposure. The more important the position, the
      more newsworthy organizational announcements become.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Partnerships.</emphasis>
      Especially partnerships with far-reaching effects across the
      industry create a major news story.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Industry recognition.</emphasis>
      When your organization wins an award or is recognized by
      peers, let the world know!</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The bottom line is that you can find news in almost any
  event. Your responsibility is to ensure that your organization
  becomes known and respected by editors, journalists, educators,
  and other stakeholders with whom you are communicating. Remember,
  the more respected your organization is, the more (and better)
  coverage you are likely to receive. The determining factor in
  that judgment will be the audience&mdash;the
  readers, viewers, and listeners who you reach.</para>
      <para>Effective and well-organized public relations efforts
  require news releases and correspondences to reach an appropriate
  editor. <xref linkend="contacting_media"></xref> details what you need 
  to do to get news media contacts and, ultimately, positive
  visibility.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="contacting_media">
    <title>Contacting the News Media</title>
    <para>All contacts with the news media create an impression of
  you and your organization that carries into the public
  perception. Creating and updating a media contact database is the
  first step towards developing good relationships with editors and
  writers. When you are contacting editors, remember that editors
  are busy professionals, so being polite and to-the-point are
  vitally important. Customizing your pitch for different editors
  and types of media will also give your information a better
  chance of being published. Effective media contacts will make
  your public relations campaign a success for your organization
  and the publications that you are featured in.</para>
    <section id="creating_contact_db">
      <title>Creating a Media Contact Database</title>
      <para>You cannot underestimate the importance of maintaining and
  continually updating a database of editorial contacts who have an
  explicit or implied interest in Linux and your organization.
  Directories available in your local reference library list
  publications of every description, giving the full particulars of
  their readership, editorial staff (often with contact
  information), circulation, publication frequency, areas of
  coverage, and other relevant information. Consulting these
  directories is the first step towards building your media
  database.</para>
      <para>Time must be spent in researching names and contact
  information for your database. You will need to know the
  audiences of each publication, names of key editors, these
  editors' responsibilities, the dates of
  special-focus issues concerning Linux, and more. This information
  will allow you to do a better job of targeting your news to the
  right media contacts. For instance, there may be occasions when
  you want your news to reach certain editors but not others. Your
  news may only concern a portion of your database, such as the
  educational community. Your research (and later, direct
  experience) will tell you that only certain editors will be
  interested. In short, there is a lot of homework to be done
  identifying the news media related to your area and learning the
  specifics about them. The more information your database
  contains, the more valuable the information will be to
  you.</para>
      <para>Before you contact any editor, you need to know where to
  call, email, or write. Fortunately, there are dozens of published
  directories of editorial contacts. While you could easily spend
  thousands of dollars buying or subscribing to them, you do not
  need to. As mentioned above, your library probably has several
  subscriptions on hand.</para>
      <para>Some of the more popular directories for North American and
  international contacts include the following news media
  organizations. There is likely a membership fee (depending on the
  service level requested) to access the databases of these
  groups.</para>
      <table frame="all">
	<title>News Media Organizations</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colnum="1"/>
	  <colspec colnum="2"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">Media Group</entry>
              <entry align="left">Web Address</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">Bacon's Directories</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.bacons.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">Bowden's</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.bowdens.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">Burrelle's/Luce</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.burrellesluce.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">BusinessWire</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.businesswire.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">Canada Newswire</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.newswire.ca"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">CCN Matthews</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.ccnmatthews.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">Media Map</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.mediamap.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">PR Newswire</entry>
              <entry align="left"><ulink url="www.prnewswire.com"></ulink></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>Another way to find local media contacts and organizations
  is to look in your local telephone directories. Here are some
  categories to start you on your way (your local Yellow Pages may
  list these under different headings):</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Broadcasting companies</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>News publications</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>News services</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Newspaper feature syndicates</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Newspapers</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Publishers - periodicals and magazines</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Radio stations</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Television stations</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Once you have created a list of potential editors to
  contact, find out as much as you can about their publication,
  coverage areas, and special interests. Become familiar with their
  publication, their website, or their broadcast. Get to know the
  beats (coverage areas) of specific reporters.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="maintaining_db">
      <title>Maintaining Your Database</title>
      <para>Whether you keep your editorial contact information in an
  electronic database (such as an ACT or DBF file) or in a
  traditional Rolodex, your contact information <emphasis>must</emphasis>
  be kept up-to-date. Editors come and go, reporters are reassigned
  to new beats, and publications merge or create spin-offs. You
  need to stay on top of these changes. Review your media contact
  list at least every three to four months. Contact appropriate
  people in each organization to get updates of names, email
  addresses, and phone numbers. Through this exercise you may
  discover new targets to whom you can pitch your story.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="contacting_editors">
      <title>Contacting the Editors</title>
      <section id="intro_letter">
        <title>Letter of Introduction</title>
        <para>When contacting an editor for the first time, you should
  take pains to get your relationship off to a good start. This is
  best accomplished by sending a well-crafted letter (or email) of
  introduction prior to issuing your first news release.</para>
        <para>Even if you have been involved in media relations in
  another capacity, a letter of introduction can help establish a
  <quote>new era</quote> of cooperation between
  you (in your new public relations role) and the editor. After
  all, a successful public and media relations program is all about
  relationships&mdash;successful ones.</para>
        <para>What must your letter accomplish? Consider your goals
  carefully, because this letter can do a great deal for your
  organization.</para>
        <para>First, reaching the right editor or reporter is extremely
  important. Then, you will want to get that editor's help in identifying other
  professionals who may be interested in receiving and conveying
  Linux news. These professionals include freelance writers (who
  write speculatively or on assignment, then sell specific stories
  to publications), editors in related areas (business and feature
  editors), industry spokespeople, and so on. Your letter also
  needs to articulate why this editor will likely be interested in
  your organization's story and why his or her
  audience will be interested.</para>
        <para>The primary purpose for the letter of introduction is to
  open the lines of communication and to make yourself or your
  designated spokesperson available. Be sure to give your full name
  and contact information. 
  <emphasis role="bold">Most importantly, do not forget to include
  your email and website addresses.</emphasis>
  Email is the preferred method of communication in the
  journalistic community. Make corresponding and dealing with you
  easy for your media contacts. This is critical to the success of
  any media and public relations program.</para>
        <para>If you include broadcast in your public relations program,
  you will need to adjust the terminology accordingly. Instead of
  editors, you will be corresponding with news directors and
  producers; instead of readers, you will be referring to
  listeners, viewers, or an audience. No matter what their job
  description is, remember that you are dealing with actual people.
  The more personable you are in your correspondence, the more
  likely you are to see results.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="using_phone">
        <title>Using the Phone</title>
        <para>Regardless of the size and scope of your media relations
  program, look for an opportunity to directly contact at least
  some of the editors and journalists important to your
  organization. The telephone is a tremendous ally in any public
  relations program. A phone call establishes person-to-person
  contact, lends credibility to your public relations effort, and
  helps your contact to associate a name to the news releases you
  subsequently send to them. A few moments on the phone, either as
  a prelude or a follow-up to a news release, not only draws
  attention to your organization but can also impart a sense of
  immediacy and urgency that may provide the edge you need to
  acquire editorial coverage of your story.</para>
        <para>When calling an editor, always immediately identify
  yourself and your organization. Next, ask if the editor is on
  deadline. If their answer is <quote>Yes,</quote>
  don't tie up their time but offer to call back
  in a day or two and then do so. Editors are known for their
  extraordinary memory&mdash;they never forget a
  nuisance or a courtesy.</para>
        <para>If the editor is not on deadline, then state immediately
  why you are calling, saying something like this:</para>
        <blockquote>
          <para><quote>Hello, I'm (name) with (my organization), and I'm 
  calling to alert you to our announcement of (news topic). I want you to know
  that I'm available to you for any additional information or an interview, 
  now or any time in the future. Give me a call at (phone number) or email 
  me at (email address).</quote></para>
        </blockquote>
        <para>Look what the dialogue above accomplishes. You have
  identified yourself and your organization, stated your business
  succinctly, and offered your services as a liaison. Now let the
  editor decide what to do. If they seem to want to get off the
  phone quickly, don't worry. They may have
  something urgent demanding their attention or a story that needs
  to be filed immediately. You can always call back or have the
  editor return your call later. Listen carefully to the
  editor's recommendations for calling them at
  another time.</para>
        <para>While most editors and reporters are busy, they are seldom
  rude (in fact, the contrary) and usually cooperative. If the
  editor asks why you are calling, or has other questions, be
  prepared to answer. As in any business situation, always do your
  homework. If necessary, write down potential questions and
  answers and rehearse beforehand. Nothing irritates a busy editor
  or reporter more than dealing with a public relations
  representative who is unprepared to answer basic
  questions.</para>
        <para>If you cannot answer all the questions, promise to find the
  answers and send the information by email. 
  <emphasis>Be sure to do this in a timely fashion.</emphasis>
  Editors appreciate quick responses and will give more attention
  to people who can give them the information they are seeking in a
  timely manner. This is a very important consideration.</para>
        <para>If the editor gives you a <quote>No thanks, not
  interested</quote> response&mdash;which may
  happen quite frequently at the beginning&mdash;you
  should ask if there is someone else on staff who would be
  interested in your information. If there is time, and the editor
  seems receptive to sharing information (listen carefully to their
  tone of voice and phone manner), you might also ask if there is
  anything special about Linux they are looking for, now or in the
  future. After all, the less you waste of each
  other's time, the more productive your
  relationship will be.</para>
        <para>Once editors know of you and your organization, there may
  be times when they contact you directly. For example, the
  publications you have targeted may occasionally feature an
  editorial focus on Linux. Check the editorial calendars of these
  publications on a regular basis. Periodicals plan their issues
  two to three months in advance of the publication date, so you
  need to be proactive in pitching (telling) your
  organization's story ahead of time. Editorial
  calendars are often made available on the
  publication's website. They are also usually
  available free of charge from the
  publication's advertising department. If all
  else fails, contacting the publication's
  editorial assistant and making a polite request should yield
  positive results.</para>
        <para>Another important way to use the phone is to find out who
  you should be contacting at a specific publication. The
  receptionist is usually cooperative and very knowledgeable about
  this. You may end up talking to a lot of different people before
  you get the answers you need, but public relations is far more
  effective when you deliver your news to the right people.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="making_pitch">
      <title>Making the Pitch</title>
      <para><quote>The Pitch</quote> (that is,
  <quote>selling</quote> your story) has changed
  over the years. Pitching is often not done just by regular mail,
  telephone, or even fax anymore. These days, most contacts are
  made through email.</para>
      <para>Before sending anything, you should try to find out how a
  particular editor or journalist likes to receive pitches and in
  what format the pitch should be presented. In-depth database
  research on numerous publications and reporters is available from
  companies like LexisNexis and Dow Jones and can be a real asset
  to public relations professionals looking for contact
  preferences.</para>
      <para>Every editor or journalist has their own preferences for
  receiving news releases and pitches. Knowing whether to call,
  fax, or email makes a world of difference&mdash;and
  may even be the difference between getting your news read and
  covered, and not. While sending the same email to 20 editors is
  quick, easy, and painless, your pitch may not get the attention
  your organization deserves.</para>
      <para>Though e-mail has simplified and certainly quickened the
  transfer of information between public relations professionals
  and their media contacts, email has some drawbacks. Email is not
  as personal as a phone call, as quick as glancing over a fax, or
  as formal as a letter sent by post. The ease and ubiquity of
  email can sometimes make building a working relationship with
  certain editors or journalists more difficult.</para>
      <para>For example, a particular Bloomberg reporter (who shall
  remain anonymous) does not like receiving pitches by email. In
  her words: <quote>Email tells a one-sided story in
  its pitch. It makes it impossible to ask questions regarding some
  uncertain aspects.</quote> Because of this, this reporter
  prefers to be contacted by phone. She will only read and accept
  email if the email relates to her beat and covers all the points
  she wants covered.</para>
      <para>David Andelman of the New York Daily News prefers receiving
  pitches and news releases by fax, which he can read instantly
  without having to print them out. <quote>I am
  [always] getting an abundance of press news,</quote> he
  says. <quote>But at least with faxes, I can filter
  through them easier and quicker than I can with emails, deciding
  what is trash and what I can use. Don't waste
  my time. We are a daily paper.</quote></para>
      <para>Samuel Brittan, an economic commentator with the Financial
  Times in London, likes old-fashioned snail mail.
  <quote>There are problems which occur with email, be
  it privacy issues, bounce-backs, or just an
  over-abundance,</quote> he says. <quote>I simply
  prefer to be mailed directly through the postal
  service.</quote></para>
      <para>Carrie Donovan, an editorial assistant for The Washington
  Post, states: <quote>Initially, I prefer postal mail
  pitches, since I receive artwork and photos for stories. Images
  sent via email tends to be problematic, either too small for us
  to run or it may look bit-mapped (jagged-looking).</quote>
  She also observes that emailed releases are more likely to have
  missing information, something as seemingly obvious as an address
  to an event. Like most media professionals, Ms. Donovan wants all
  the facts delivered coherently and comprehensively. Failure of a
  public relations representative to do this is enough to turn her
  off completely.</para>
      <para>Whatever method you use to correspond with an editor or
  reporter, always remember that media people are 
  <emphasis>extremely</emphasis>
  busy. After all, they live and die by deadlines. Although you may
  want to know if your contact has received your pitch or news
  release, phoning them is generally not recommended. Most editors
  don't have the time to answer follow-up calls
  or engage in lengthy conversation. This again underscores the
  importance of giving them all the information in one
  <quote>neat and clean</quote> delivery. As Mr.
  Andelman bluntly states, <quote>We aren't idiots. If you faxed it to us and you
  didn't get an error message back, you know we
  received it just fine. And if we decide to use it, chances are we
  will contact you for more information.</quote></para>
      <para>First impressions count. The best advice we can give when
  you are dealing with a news editor for the first time is to
  tailor the pitch specifically to that editor's
  beat. Then sit back and hope for the best. Although this approach
  sounds unpredictable, this is the nature of public
  relations.</para>
      <para>By corresponding with editors in the way they prefer (which
  may not be the easiest or most convenient way for you), you will
  set a good impression for your organization. With persistence and
  good manners, you may eventually become an authority to whom
  journalists and editors willingly turn for commentary.</para>
      <section id="getting_editor_attention">
        <title>Getting the Editor's Attention</title>
        <para>Editors pride themselves on keeping current with the latest
  developments in their field. Indeed, being current is a central
  aspect of their jobs and practically inescapable, considering the
  mountains of information delivered to their desktops. Since they
  take this responsibility very seriously, most editors
  read&mdash;or at least scan&mdash;every
  single release that comes in.</para>
        <para>The big read usually begins as an accompaniment to the
  morning cup of coffee. Editors will read the
  release's headline, perhaps scan a paragraph
  or two, and decide whether the piece works for their
  publications. Since so much depends on passing this preliminary
  test, we will discuss in Chapter 4 how to give your release the
  best chance of being <quote>picked up.</quote></para>
        <para>Not every news release will contain earth-shattering news.
  In fact, many will be written mainly to keep the
  organization's name in front of the editors.
  Nonetheless there will be times when an item will be particularly
  newsworthy, timely, or significant to at least one editor. That
  is the time to pick up the phone and bring the item to their
  attention. Editors are sensitive to significant announcements and
  do not want to miss them any more than you want them missed, so
  calling is appropriate on these occasions. However, there are a
  few caveats.</para>
        <para>First, remember <emphasis>never</emphasis> to call during the editor's
  <quote>deadline time</quote> of the day, week,
  or month. Note these periods in your contact database. Secondly,
  use the phone strategically. Do not phone too often or for
  trivial news&mdash;that is equivalent to
  <quote>crying wolf.</quote> If you will be
  making several important announcements within a short period, let
  the editor know you will be doing this instead of calling
  separately about each item. Only pick up the phone when all of
  your ducks are in a row; that is, when the information is ready
  to be released, and you are prepped and primed to answer
  questions. Finally, remember that any phone call should be brief
  and to the point, with additional information sent by email (or
  whatever format the editor has stipulated).</para>
        <para>Using the telephone intelligently and to maximum effect
  will demonstrate your public relations savvy and professionalism.
  This, in turn, will increase your
  organization's credibility, increasing the
  likelihood that your news will be picked up.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="pitching_media">
      <title>Pitching for Different Media</title>
      <para>The news release, the most common way in which you will
  communicate news, mostly serves print-based media such as
  newspapers, magazines, and the Internet. Pitching stories for
  television and radio will be somewhat different.</para>
      <section id="print_based_media">
        <title>Print-based Media</title>
        <para>Every publication has a lead time for accepting releases
  and pitches. Generally, daily and weekly newspapers have quite
  short lead times, while monthly or quarterly magazines may have a
  lead time of several months. Each publication will also have
  requirements regarding text and graphic formats. For instance,
  they may accept only plain-text documents with no formatting or
  require graphical files (such as photos) to be submitted in a
  particular file type and resolution.</para>
        <para>Although you do not need to become an expert in desktop
  publishing and print production, having a general knowledge of
  these areas will be extremely beneficial. Familiarize yourself
  with commonly used text formats (such as Microsoft Word for print
  and HTML for the Internet) and graphical formats (such as eps,
  jpeg, and gif). For important communications, you may wish to
  engage the services of a copy editor, graphic designer, or other
  publishing professional.</para>
        <para>The Internet today works similarly to the print media.
  Speed is paramount for this medium. News can be posted
  immediately, without waiting for the printing presses to roll.
  Space limitations are not as much of a concern as they are for
  print, and the online edition will often publish stories that do
  not fit in the printed edition.</para>
        <para>Naturally, online editors prefer to receive your news
  electronically. Targeting the right online editors can result in
  almost immediate posting of your news. Be sure to build
  relationships with online editors as you would for print editors.
  The online world is a growing segment that you simply cannot
  afford to ignore.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="tv_radio">
        <title>Television and Radio</title>
        <para>Studies show that television has replaced newspapers as the
  primary medium from which people get their news. These studies
  also found that TV news had a much higher credibility rating than
  newspaper coverage. Thus, specialty TV programs may offer an
  excellent opportunity for communicating your story. Such shows
  may include: local TV news shows, programs produced by community
  TV stations, business or information technology shows, and
  educational shows.</para>
        <para>Because television emphasizes visuals, you should look for
  stories and angles that permit interesting or engaging video
  footage. (There is nothing duller than â$=talking
  heads.â$) TV news producers and editors like action,
  especially fast-paced action. They also favor stories with a
  local twist. Try and localize your story, which means making the
  news relevant and appealing geographically to the television
  station concerned.</para>
        <para>Radio interviews are another excellent vehicle for
  publicizing your organization and activities. Contact your local
  radio station and pitch yourself as an interview candidate to the
  news director or assignment editor. Know that you must have a
  compelling and convincing answer to the question,
  <quote>Why should our listeners be interested?</quote></para>
        <para>In <xref linkend="working_with_media"></xref>, we further explore 
  the characteristics of different media, so that you can customize your 
  pitches to each one.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="working_with_media">
    <title>Working with the Media</title>
    <para>In this part, we look at how to motivate the news media to
  use your stories. We will review the duties of editors and
  producers, the characteristics of different news media, and the
  ways in which your organization can increase the chances of
  gaining visibility. We will see how to create news media interest
  in your story, not only through the information contained in your
  release, but also through contact with the editors. We will try
  to create a better understanding of the
  editors' side of the public relations channel
  with some insight into the little things&mdash;and
  the big things&mdash;that editors look for.</para>
    <section id="editor_duties">
      <title>Duties of an Editor</title>
      <para>The eventual success of your organization's public and media relations
  efforts depends mainly on how often your news releases are issued
  and, more importantly, how often the news they contain is
  selected to run. The latter decision is in the hands of a person
  whose title is usually <emphasis>editor</emphasis>. Understanding an editor's 
  job will help you do your job better.</para>
      <para>Can you name the editor of your local computer magazine or
  local newspaper? The editor is a very important ally in public
  relations. The editor (whose title might also be 
  <emphasis>managing editor</emphasis> or <emphasis>editor in chief</emphasis>) 
  has overall responsibility for the publication's content. Below him or her,
  depending on the periodical's size, are
  subject editors who are assigned to specific beats (often called
  <quote>departments</quote>). These editors
  oversee the content for their departments. Sometimes each editor
  has additional staff, such as reporters, freelancer writers,
  photographers, copy writers, copy editors, etc.</para>
      <para>The information contained in news releases is the primary
  source of information for most editors. Newsworthy releases are
  selected and edited or worked into an article. The selected
  releases are the lucky ones; most never see the light of day.
  When you consider that the editor at a daily publication receives
  upwards of 500 news releases on any given day, gauging the
  statistical possibility of an individual release being picked up
  for coverage is easy.</para>
      <section id="newspaper_editors">
        <title>Newspaper Editors</title>
        <para>Newspapers don't mean just the regular
  daily newspapers targeted at the general public. There are
  special-interest newspapers for business, computers, information
  technology, telecommunications, and other fields. The specialty
  papers may run weekly instead of daily, but, like their daily
  counterparts, they are primarily news-driven rather than
  feature-driven (which is more the case with magazines).</para>
        <para>Newspaper editors reject many more releases than they use.
  The larger the paper's circulation or the more
  active the area being covered, the more releases the editor has
  to sort through.</para>
        <para>Most newspapers have a space budget, which is not to be
  confused with a financial budget. The space budget consists of
  the total number of pages printed, divided between advertising
  and news articles. Advertisements are the lifeblood of a
  newspaper; ads consistently provide the largest portion of
  income. The ads must be accommodated first, after which the
  issue's remaining space is allocated to
  specific stories and departments by the key editors.</para>
        <para>The selection of news releases to cover is based on the
  editor's personal and professional judgment.
  The main factor in that judgment can be summed up in a single
  word: <quote>newsworthiness</quote>.
  Unfortunately, newsworthiness is defined by individual
  editor's opinions. Newsworthy stories are
  generally those that offer the most information with the most
  urgency to the most people.</para>
        <para>If a news release issued on particular day is not covered
  in the following day's paper, this does not
  mean the news will not appear at all. Releases not considered
  newsworthy enough to appear in a weekday edition may be suitable
  for the weekend paper, where there is more room and less emphasis
  on breaking news. Even if a news item is selected for use, the
  article may still get pulled at the last minute. Perhaps an
  advertiser cancelled a large insert just prior to deadline,
  necessitating a layout change, or a big story emerged late in the
  day. When this happens, more expendable news is
  sacrificed.</para>
        <para>What happens to releases that aren't
  selected for immediate coverage? Some are kept for future use,
  but more likely they are sent into the
  editor's trash can.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="magazine_editors">
        <title>Magazine Editors</title>
        <para>Magazines operate very much like newspapers, with
  departments, editors, space budgets, and advertising, but
  magazines differ in a few important ways.</para>
        <para>The potential lifespan of a news release is much longer for
  a magazine. A monthly publication might not use your news for
  several months. Depending on the printing and preparation
  schedule, your release could appear as soon as a week or two
  after you send the release or as late as six-months later. The
  nice thing is that whenever your news appears, the information
  remains in front of the reader for a full month instead of just
  one day.</para>
        <para>The editorial focus and format of a magazine are usually
  more specialized than those of newspapers. <quote>Focus</quote> refers to 
  the subjects a magazine covers; for instance, <emphasis>Linux Journal</emphasis>
  focuses on Linux in general while <emphasis>ComputerWorld</emphasis>
  might focus on Linux in the enterprise. <quote>Format</quote> refers to the 
  way in which a magazine's news and information is
  presented, usually as a particular mix of regular columns,
  articles, features (main stories), shorter pieces, and editorials
  (opinion pieces). Magazine stories don't have
  to be as <quote>newsy</quote> as newspaper
  stories. To a greater degree, a magazine researches and creates
  news rather than relying on current events.</para>
        <para>General-interest magazines try to appeal to a large segment
  of the population. (Examples are <emphasis>Macleans, Readers'
  Digest,</emphasis> and <emphasis>People.</emphasis>)
  Special-interest magazines target a limited, well-defined
  community of readers who share a particular interest along with
  associated activities and concerns. Special-interest magazines
  are good targets for the Linux community, especially those
  focusing on Linux, operating systems, storage, security,
  computers, and information technology.</para>
        <para>Whether special interest or general interest, the closer
  your news release relates to the audience of a publication and
  the greater the impact on that audience, the more likely an
  editor will choose your news to publish. The key factors are
  editorial relevance and appeal to the publication's target audience.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="target_other_media">
      <title>Targeting Other Medias</title>
      <para>In television and radio news shows, news editors, some
  reporters, and even anchors have input on the news to be aired.
  In other types of shows, often the producer decides which stories
  to cover in future broadcasts. Segment producers will produce the
  individual stories for a broadcast, while assistant producers may
  perform specialized functions, such as finding interview
  subjects.</para>
      <section id="target_tv">
        <title>Television</title>
        <para>The same considerations of <quote>newsworthiness</quote> discussed for
  newspapers apply to television broadcast news, with the added
  element of visuals. There are several types of TV programming you
  will want to consider. These include educational and
  informational programs, local and community news programs, and
  perhaps a business program. Understand the types of shows being
  produced and aired in your regional area, and then pitch your
  story for an in-studio interview or a feature.</para>
        <para>Ensuring that you are pitching the right story to the right
  TV program staffer will be discussed later in this guide.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="target_radio">
        <title>Radio</title>
        <para>Radio time for news stories is very limited. Usually there
  is only enough time for headlines and summaries of the
  day's top stories, but radio still has great
  opportunities for your organization.</para>
        <para>Some radio stations offer expanded news coverage and
  features (this is sometimes called <quote>foreground
  programming</quote>). Most Linux news has a better chance of
  getting coverage or an interview in news programming than in
  regular programming. The best chance of all lies in targeting an
  all-news station. Approximately 45 minutes of each hour are
  devoted to news, sports, weather, special reports, and features.
  (The remaining 15 minutes are for commercials.) All-news radio
  stations operate more like a magazine or newspaper, with specific
  departments and editors, more producers, more reporters, and
  therefore, more available resources. Stories that interest a
  significant portion of their listening community or that appeal
  to deep-pocketed sponsors will be given the most attention. You
  could pitch a <quote>Linux for business</quote>
  type of story. Even if your underlying goal is to promote your
  organization, the story or interview must avoid advertising or
  commercial overtones of any kind. Nothing kills the news
  media's credibility faster or turns off
  listeners more than inappropriate jingoism.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="target_talk_shows">
        <title>Talk Shows</title>
        <para>Talk shows, whether on television or radio, are excellent
  vehicles for covering a wide variety of topics. Talk shows often
  invite industry experts to be commentators or participants in a
  panel discussion. In addition, these shows often have phone-in
  segments, inviting listeners to ask questions or make comments.
  These characteristics make the talk show an ideal forum for
  raising your organization's visibility.</para>
        <para>For these programs, there is usually an assistant producer
  responsible for lining up interesting guests, as well as a
  producer who coordinates the overall process. Both email and
  telephone contact with the assistant producer can prove
  rewarding. The host, interviewer, or moderator of the show does
  not usually choose the guests or have final say in who appears.
  Unless instructed otherwise, contacting the assistant producer or
  producer is best.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="selling_to_media">
      <title><quote>Selling</quote> Your Story to the Media</title>
      <para>Clearly, editors and producers have to know the interests
  of their audiences. Often this knowledge comes from the
  editors' strong identification with their
  readers, which can develop into an almost paternal attitude.
  Editors are constantly making decisions about what their readers
  will and won't see&mdash;any
  editor would correctly say that is their job. Part of this
  judgment is based on what the editor feels the readers are
  currently interested in, and part is based on what the editor
  feels the readers <emphasis>should</emphasis> or <emphasis>will</emphasis>
  be interested in. An astute editor keeps their sights as much on
  the future as on the present.</para>
      <para>Keep in mind that the role of the news media has never been
  confined to just reporting the news, but also includes analysis
  and interpretation. Analysis and interpretation are considered
  the domain of <quote>experts,</quote> which
  presents a perfect opportunity for specialists in your
  organization to share their knowledge and bring visibility to
  your organization.</para>
      <para>Editors, being journalists, abide by the five Ws tradition
  of reporting: who, what, where, when, and why (with an unofficial
  <quote>how</quote>tagging along).
  Always include clear, engaging answers to the five Ws in all news
  releases. Also, you can use the five Ws as a guideline for how to
  most effectively catch the attention of editors.</para>
      <para><emphasis>The way</emphasis> in which you present this information 
  is crucial to being accepted by an editor as newsworthy for their audience. 
  You have to <quote>tell a story,</quote> make the news
  interesting and relevant, and choose an appropriate time and
  place to present the story.</para>
      <section id="selling_who">
        <title>Who</title>
        <para><quote>Who</quote> usually consists of your
  organization, spokespersons, and authorities quoted in your news
  releases. Your organization and those speaking as representatives
  must be presented as professional, authoritative, influential,
  and with strong credentials for speaking on matters related to
  your industry. By positioning your organization in this way, you
  have a much better chance of generating visibility and
  prestige.</para>
        <para>The goal is to make your organization a recognized
  authority in your field. With this distinction, any time you
  issue a statement, your news will draw the attention of editors
  whose readers are interested in the specific work you do. All
  things being equal, the more influential your spokesperson, the
  better the chance your news has of being selected.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="selling_what">
        <title>What</title>
        <para>The <quote>what</quote> is the subject of
  your release&mdash;a new application, a new
  appointment, or any interesting event you choose to announce.
  Naturally, unusual or exciting announcements have a better chance
  of being covered. Anything you can do to make your story stand
  out from the ordinary will be viewed as a refreshing change and
  will increase the chance of your story being published.</para>
        <para>If the <quote>what</quote> in your story
  is a personnel appointment (either paid or volunteer), look for
  some human interest in either the person or the job at hand. If
  this person is a well-known Linux expert or a pillar of their
  local community, all the better. The more noteworthy the
  individual, the more newsworthy the story.</para>
        <para>If the <quote>what</quote> is an event
  such as a Linux trade show, that is a plus. Editors regard events
  as more urgent and newsworthy than other announcements.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="selling_where">
        <title>Where</title>
        <para>The <quote>where</quote> of your release
  plays a key role. As you begin to understand public relations,
  you will appreciate the role of staging events to generate news.
  Since the media appreciates visuals, try to produce events with
  images as well as a pertinent story.</para>
        <para>In planning a pitch or a release, ensure that you clearly
  indicate the address of every event you hope to have reporters
  attend. Reporters' time is wasted if they have
  to call for directions to every event. A special media contact
  person is a good idea to have at all events. This person can
  prevent reporters from missing important or visual parts of
  events. Be aware of upcoming events or activities that you might
  be able to capitalize on or borrow interest from. Again, the goal
  is promote the unusual, the unique, the unexpected that will
  pique the editor's curiosity or sense of
  humor&mdash;and get your story into print.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="selling_when">
        <title>When</title>
        <para>Remember that for most organizations,
  <quote>when</quote> can be just about any time.
  There is no need to wait for once-a-year events (like trade
  shows) to provide news. With creative thinking, you can come up
  with news stories that capitalize on current events. For example,
  news about the economy and what proprietary operating systems
  cost organizations to run can provide a background for Linux
  news. New computer applications running on Linux also present
  rich opportunities.</para>
        <para><quote>When</quote> is extremely important
  in terms of releasing the news. For instance, if you are
  publicizing special events or trade show appearances, you want to
  allow ample time for an editor to assign a reporter to cover the
  story (if the news is deemed of interest). If the editor
  doesn't have enough time to assign a reporter
  to cover your event, you can count on no reporters being
  available.</para>
        <para>Fortunately, though, while timing is critically important,
  avoiding bad timing is easy. The first rule is always to provide
  a reasonable amount of advance notice. For news-breaking media
  such as radio, television, and some newspapers, two days is an
  absolute minimum, and a week is more prudent. For magazines and
  trade journals, one to two weeks is the minimum in most cases,
  and three to four weeks is even better.</para>
        <para>The second rule is to use your common sense and avoid
  scheduling pitches when you know the editor is on deadline or is
  involved with other events. Also avoid periods when the editor is
  working with little or no support staff (such as when reporters
  are away at an important trade show). Generally, business hours
  between 9:30 a.m. and 2:00 p.m. is best, since this gives
  reporters time to write and file their stories. Mondays and
  Fridays are always more difficult than midweek, but
  don't be afraid to ask if the editor prefers
  specific days.</para>
        <para>If you are requesting reporters attend and cover an event,
  never ask the editor to confirm their attendance. The editor will
  not appreciate the pressure, and besides they cannot guarantee
  they will have the resources (reporters and camera operators) at
  the appointed time. News changes by the second. A reporter may be
  ready to go to your event and, at the last minute, be reassigned
  to something else. This happens all the time, so
  don't take the rejection personally.</para>
        <para>If you show respect for the editor's
  time, they will appreciate your consideration and may be more
  likely to cover at least some of your stories.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="selling_why">
        <title>Why</title>
        <para>So far, we have discussed <emphasis>who</emphasis>
  the news media is interested in, <emphasis>what</emphasis>
  news is most likely to be covered, and <emphasis>where</emphasis>
  and <emphasis>when</emphasis> you are going to make your pitch. 
  Now, in looking at the <quote>why</quote> of your
  organization's story, we will address two questions. First, 
  <emphasis>why</emphasis> did your news item come to pass, and second, 
  <emphasis>why</emphasis> should an editor (and their readers, listeners, 
  or viewers) find your event newsworthy?</para>
        <para>Unless there is something terribly interesting about the
  who, what, where, or when, <quote>why</quote> is
  the single most compelling factor available to an editor in
  determining newsworthiness. Why is the news important to the
  audience? Why do they need to know about this? Why is your
  particular event unusual or out of the ordinary?</para>
        <para>Most organization's activities can be
  analyzed in terms of their cause and/or their effect. The more
  you can identify causes or effects in your story, the better
  chance your organization has of receiving coverage. As an
  example, if there is a trend of Linux being increasingly used in
  the enterprise, there must be a reason why. Giving the editor
  just a few of these reasons can make your story more newsworthy
  than just a simple, bland announcement. Even including some
  statistics to support your why will likely have a tremendous
  effect.</para>
        <para>The same principle holds true for something as seemingly
  mundane as a new personnel selection. Why was there a vacancy?
  Why was this person selected to fill the spot? Adding either or
  both pieces of information to the release greatly increases the
  news interest.</para>
        <para>One of the cardinal rules of media and public relations is: 
  <quote>Never promote features, always promote
  benefits.</quote> A feature is any specific aspect that
  makes a product or service unique; features belong to products or
  services. A benefit is an advantage gained by the user in
  selecting a specific product or service; benefits belong to
  users. What a product or service does is nowhere near as
  meaningful as why there is some advantage or benefit to the
  user.</para>
        <para>You don't need to completely ignore
  describing features, but you do need to present them in the
  context of their benefits to the end user. The reason for doing
  this is simple. Readers are potential users, and the better job
  you do of relating to the user, the more you will attract
  readers. Readers, as we already know, are the
  editor's Holy Grail.</para>
        <para>If your release is about an event, there are numerous
  <quote>whys</quote> you need to address. Why
  now? Why is your organization involved or being a sponsor? Why
  would anyone want to come to the event?</para>
        <para>Be proactive and open in sharing the causes and anticipated
  effects of these accomplishments. Don't leave
  the editor wondering: <quote>So what?</quote>
  Failing to provide answers to why your activity is news is a
  sure-fire way of getting your release
  <quote>filed</quote> in the recycle bin.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="selling_how">
        <title>How</title>
        <para>Cause and effect, and explaining why your news is
  happening, will very naturally lead to the
  <quote>how</quote> of your story. How did this
  come to pass? How are you accomplishing this? How did your
  organization decide to embark on this new and exciting
  initiative? How will this change affect people and the
  marketplace? Describing the <emphasis>hows</emphasis>
  gives color and interest to your story.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="dos_donts">
      <title>Do's and Don'ts When Dealing with the News Media</title>
      <para>When pitching your organization's story to news editors, there are 
  fundamental do's and don'ts that you as a public relations
  professional should follow.</para>
      <section id="dealing_do">
        <title>Do's</title>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis> introduce yourself to different media 
  editors, journalists, and freelancers by sending them an email note or by 
  inviting them out for coffee or lunch. Bring along some background information 
  or a few pages from your website to explain what your organization is
  all about.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis>
  follow up after the meeting with thank-you note, mentioning that
  you will be in touch as appropriate. This is important to set the
  stage for future dialogue.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis>
  let them know what your goals are and what special events, news,
  or programs you have coming up.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis> 
  send out news releases by email about two weeks in advance, when
  you have a special event planned. Send a follow-up email a few
  days later. Phone again at a convenient time before the event to
  suggest a possible meeting or interview at the event. The bigger
  the event, the more advance notice should be given.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis>  
  tailor your pitch for the needs of each medium. For example, set
  up plenty of photo opportunities for television media,
  human-interest stories for print, and interviews for
  radio.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis>
  give them the name of someone who has a personal experience to
  tell. Remember that the media loves a good story. Real life
  stories engage readers and makes for better copy than just
  statistics relating to Linux and open source.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Do</emphasis>
  ensure that you or your designated spokesperson is available for
  interviews at a moment's notice; otherwise
  much of your efforts will be in vain. Both of you, of course,
  should do your homework and rehearse questions and answers in
  advance. You should have facts, statistics, and anecdotes in your
  head, ready to use.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="dealing_donts">
        <title>Don'ts</title>
        <para><emphasis>Don't</emphasis>
  send out a pitch or news release with vague, general statements.
  Your story has to show not tell, and you must convince the editor
  to cover the news that promotes your organization rather someone
  else's. Getting editorial coverage is fiercely competitive.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Don't</emphasis>
  ever tell the media what you want from them. Instead, ask them
  about the kinds of stories they're looking
  for, or if there are any other reporters in their newsroom who
  would be interested in Linux and open source. By learning what
  they want, you can tailor your communications to get what 
  <emphasis>you</emphasis> want.</para>
        <para><emphasis>Don't</emphasis>
  underestimate the importance of less prominent media like
  community newspapers, cable TV, trade journals, and
  special-interest newsletters. Look at the entire spectrum of news
  media for different angles.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="monitoring_coverage">
      <title>Monitoring Media Coverage</title>
      <para>It is essential to keep abreast of the news being printed
  or broadcast about your organization, your competition, and the
  industry as a whole. A comprehensive public and media relations
  program must track public perception of Linux, stay informed of
  industry trends, and understand the impact of evolving
  legislation on your community.</para>
      <para>If you have time to spare, you can monitor news coverage
  yourself by typing key words (such as the name of your
  organization) into popular web search engines such as Google and
  AltaVista. However, this will track only online citations. A more
  reliable tracking method is to use a media monitor service or a
  clipping service. The website 
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://dmoz.org/News/Services/Media_Monitoring/">
    http://dmoz.org/News/Services/Media_Monitoring/</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  provides a long list of media monitoring services, some of which
  are provided in the Appendix.</para>
      <para>In <xref linkend="news_releases"></xref> we will examine the parts of a 
  news release and discuss what can make your releases stand out from the
  crowd.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="news_releases">
    <title>News Releases&mdash;the Major Communications Tool</title>
    <section id="writing_releases">
      <title>Writing News Releases</title>
      <para>Who, what, where, when, why, and
  how&mdash;these are the six critical ingredients of
  all news releases. But don't forget, a little
  spice can make your news release stand out from the crowd. In
  this part, you will learn how to write a professional-looking
  news release, the most important tool in any public relations
  program.</para>
      <section id="headline">
        <title>The Headline</title>
        <para>The headline is the first thing&mdash;and
  sometimes the only thing&mdash;an editor will read.
  Releases are often rejected as a result of a weak
  headline.</para>
        <para>Create headlines with impact. The most effective words in a
  news release headline are eye-catching words like <quote>announces</quote> and
  <quote>new.</quote> Comparative words like <quote>better</quote> or
  <quote>more</quote> can also draw attention to your article. The headline is the
  <quote>hook</quote> that lures editors and reporters into reading more. Headlines
  must be compelling.</para>
        <para>Many public relations novices make the mistake of
  embellishing their headlines. Your organization has to earn the
  respect of editors. Nobody owes you a reading. Too much
  information, or confusing information, is a turnoff. Most
  importantly, you should never sacrifice accuracy for the sake of
  a flashy headline.</para>
        <para>Here are some guidelines for writing headlines:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Determine the most significant benefit your most
      important reader will derive from the news.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Try and state those benefits in seven words or
      less.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Ask yourself if your statement is meaningful to someone
      not closely involved with your business.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>When actually writing the headline, try to achieve the
  greatest impact using the fewest words. Your headline
  doesn't need to be quite as dramatic as a
  newspaper headline. Editors are looking for information in the
  headline, so try to at least include who, what, and why. Whatever
  the headline, you must accurately reflect the content that
  follows.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="first_para">
        <title>The First Paragraph</title>
        <para>Many news releases are accepted or rejected on the basis of
  the headline and first paragraph or two. These introductory
  paragraphs are often all an editor will have time to read. Many
  releases are rejected due a simple downfall: failure to include
  any <emphasis>news</emphasis> in the first paragraph.</para>
        <para>An important news-writing concept is 
  <emphasis role="bold">collapsible copy.</emphasis>
  Collapsible copy reads well from the beginning to the end of any
  given paragraph. The information is <quote>chunked</quote> to stand on its 
  own, if need be. Each sentence could be pulled from the news release and
  used as a quotation. This type of copy should be used as
  extensively as possible in all paragraphs.</para>
        <para>Editors expect to see the five Ws covered in the first few
  sentences. Here's an example:</para>
        <blockquote>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">NEW YORK &mdash; January 22,
  2003 &mdash;</emphasis>The Linux Professional Institute (LPI) 
  (<citetitle><ulink url="http://www.lpi.org/">www.lpi.org</ulink></citetitle>),
  the premier professional certification program for the Linux
  community, and UnitedLinux LLC 
  (<citetitle><ulink url="http://www.unitedlinux.com/">www.unitedlinux.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>), an industry initiative to streamline Linux development and
  certification around a global, uniform distribution, have signed
  a cooperative agreement to market a UnitedLinux professional
  certification program.</para>
          <para>Under the memorandum of understanding, LPI and UnitedLinux
  will work jointly to create new UnitedLinux specific exams which,
  when passed together with the current LPI Levels 1 and 2 exams,
  will lead to two new UnitedLinux certifications. The new exams
  are expected to be available during the first quarter of
  2003.</para>
        </blockquote>
        <para>Let's look more closely at this example. The <emphasis>where</emphasis>
  and <emphasis>when</emphasis> of this and most releases are specified in the 
  <emphasis role="bold">slug</emphasis> (<quote>New York &mdash; January 22,
  2003</quote>). The <emphasis>who</emphasis> is LPI and UnitedLinux. The 
  <emphasis>what</emphasis> is signing a cooperative agreement. The 
  <emphasis>why</emphasis> is marketing a UnitedLinux professional certification
  program. And the <emphasis>how</emphasis>
  is LPI and UnitedLinux working jointly to create new UnitedLinux-specific
  exams.</para>
        <para>These two paragraphs alone communicate the essential points
  of this announcement,. In print, there may not be enough space
  for more than this. Some special-interest journals devote a
  column or a page to announcements, which are printed verbatim
  from the news release. Unless the announcement is deemed more
  newsworthy, this may be all the coverage you get.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="middle_paras">
        <title>The Middle Paragraphs</title>
        <para>Limited space in publications and time in broadcasting
  means the first paragraph <emphasis>may</emphasis>
  get covered. Paragraphs should always be ordered by importance
  for two important reasons.</para>
        <para>First, editors read through releases quickly and often will
  not finish entire releases. You must consider what things are
  most important, and place them next in the release. Often, a
  statement from your spokesperson explaining the expected impacts
  on the marketplace or something related can be catchy enough to
  be quoted. Follow this with the next most important thing, and so on
  to the end of the release.</para>
        <para>Second, sequence frequently indicates importance (unless
  the story is an in-depth feature that can establish pacing and
  shape). Stacking your news, in what some editors call the
  <quote>inverted pyramid,</quote> can show
  editors the relative importance of your details. By following the
  inverted pyramid, you will make the editor's
  job easier and also accomplish your goal of getting the most
  critical information covered.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="fine_details">
        <title>Final Details</title>
        <para>You need to mark the end of your news release, so that
  editors know there is no further news. In journalism, this is
  traditionally done by putting <quote>-30-</quote> or
  <quote>-end-</quote> on a new, centered
  line, after the last line of copy, as follows:</para>
        <para>
<screen>                              -30-                     </screen>
      </para>
        <para>After ending the release, it is important to include the  
  <emphasis role="bold">boilerplate</emphasis>&mdash;
  standard, reusable background information
  about the organization issuing the news and contact information
  for editorial follow-up. The boilerplate includes the
  organization's web address where the editor
  can go for further details. Boilerplates can be reviewed and
  revised periodically, but they should maintain consistency.
  Wildly different boilerplates are unprofessional from one release
  to the next.</para>
        <para>Below is an example of boilerplate and contact
  information.</para>
        <blockquote>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">About Linux Professional Institute</emphasis>
      </para>
          <para>The Linux Professional Institute (LPI) develops
  professional certification for the Linux operating system
  independent of software vendors or training providers.
  Established as an international non-profit organization in 1999
  by the Linux community, LPI develops accessible,
  internationally-recognized certification programs which have
  earned the respect of vendors, employers and administrators.
  LPI's activities involve hundreds of
  volunteers and professionals throughout the world in many
  different capacities, and the group encourages active public
  involvement through mailing lists and its website at 
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.lpi.org/">www.lpi.org</ulink>.
  </citetitle>
  LPI's multi-level program of exams is
  administered globally through Virtual University Enterprises
  (VUE) and Prometric testing centers. LPI's
  major financial sponsors are Platinum Sponsors Caldera
  International (NASDAQ:CALD), IBM (NYSE:IBM), Linuxcare, Maxspeed,
  SGI (NYSE:SGI), SuSE Linux AG and TurboLinux as well as Gold
  Sponsors Hewlett-Packard (NYSE:HWP) and Wave Technologies.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Contact:</emphasis></para>
          <para>Sheldon Rose</para>
          <para>Sacke &amp; Associates Inc.</para>
          <para>416-218-1102, ext 2191</para>
          <para>sheldonr@sackepr.com</para>
        </blockquote>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="good_bad_releases">
      <title>What Makes a News Release Good (or Bad)</title>
      <para>Print editors and journalists are notoriously overworked
  and underpaid. A well-written news release will often be used
  word for word, with maybe a few changes for <quote>objectivity</quote> or 
  to accommodate the publication's format.</para>
      <para>The editorial staff at the <emphasis>Los Angeles Times</emphasis>
  says this about news releases:</para>
      <para>A good news release is a concise, complete description of
  an upcoming event; a timely report of an event has just occurred;
  notification of important personnel or procedural changes in an
  organization; or other news or feature tips.</para>
      <para>Bad releases&mdash;the ones that don't get used&mdash; often have
  these common mistakes:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lack of a local angle.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Insufficient or inaccurate information (who, what,
       when, where, why, how).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Failure to include contact information for the
       organization.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verbosity. (Try to keep the release to one or two
       pages, but balance brevity against failure to include
       necessary information.)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lack of timeliness&mdash;the
       editor's deadline has passed or the news
       is released too long after the event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Writing a news release does not have to be painful. What
  you need is a little time to gather all the facts: the who, what,
  when, where, why and how (and any additional information
  necessary to support).</para>
      <para>Sometimes your news won't be used right
  away or in the form you provided. A writer may need time to
  rewrite your outline into a news story. Or, if a feature is being
  developed on Linux, the writer may use many sources for depth and
  objectivity. They may use quotable quotes, first-person
  anecdotes, statistics, and causes and effects from your releases
  as well as those of your competitors.</para>
      <para>Deadlines are hugely important because the news media
  cannot delay publication or broadcasting.
  Don't bother editors with untimely
  information. If you can't pitch your story in
  time, wait for another opportune moment to come around.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="top_ten_tips">
      <title>Top Ten Tips for Writing Releases</title>
      <para>To summarize what we have said so far, here are ten tips
  for writing an excellent news release.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Use an active headline to grab the
      editor's attention.</emphasis></para>
          <para>The headline makes your release stand out. Keep the
  headline short, active, and descriptive, with the most positive
  spin. Write <quote>Jane Doe Named Person of the
  Year</quote> instead of <quote>Jane Doe Gets
  Award.</quote></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Put the most important information at the
      beginning.</emphasis></para>
          <para>This is a tried and true rule of journalism. Remember that
  the first two paragraphs should contain the salient facts of who,
  what, when, where, why, and how. Don't bury
  good information at the end.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Avoid exaggeration and unsubstantiated claims.</emphasis></para>
          <para>A news editor can smell a sales pitch a mile away. Instead
  of making over-inflated statements, provide real, usable
  information. Find legitimate ways to set your organization apart,
  and stress those points.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Write in an active, engaging, and concise style.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Use language that conveys your excitement about the news.
  If your release is boring or passively written, the editor may
  conclude the news itself is not very meaningful or you are not a
  good candidate for an interview. Interesting equals
  newsworthy.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Keep your release to two pages or less.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Generally, if you can't state your
  message in two pages, you are not getting to the point fast
  enough. Editors are always looking for concise, easy-to-read
  releases that can be thrown onto a website or squeezed into a
  leftover space in a page layout. For highly important news with
  many details, you can include a third page, but this should be
  done sparingly.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Include a contact.</emphasis></para>
          <para><emphasis>Every</emphasis>
  news release should include a contact person who the media can
  reach for more information. This contact is your spokesperson and
  must be familiar with all the news in the release. They should be
  prepared to answer questions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Keep jargon to the minimum.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Avoid using highly technical terms and buzzwords familiar
  only to Linux insiders. Jargon can date quickly, and complicated
  language irritates people who don't know what
  you mean. Your goal is to tell your story to as wide an audience
  as possible, not to unduly limit the audience. Even
  special-interest publications mostly write in plain language and
  only use jargon and acronyms generally familiar to their
  readers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Stress <quote>benefits, benefits,
      benefits.</quote></emphasis></para>
          <para>This falls under the category of <quote>show,
  don't tell.</quote> Avoid claiming something is <quote>unique</quote> or
  <quote>the best</quote> when you can't substantiate this. Instead, provide
  specific examples of benefits, supported by evidence and anecdotes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Be specific and detailed.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Marcia Yudkin, author of 
  <emphasis>Six Steps to Free Publicity,</emphasis>
  talks about the <quote>Yes, but what <emphasis>is</emphasis>
  it?</quote> syndrome. Nothing is more irritating than seeing
  constant references to a product name or service name, but no
  information on what that product or service is. The reader needs
  to be able to visualize a new product or understand what a
  service offers. This is particularly critical for launches
  (announcements of new offerings). You should ask someone
  unfamiliar with your product or service to read your release and
  then describe the product or service in their own words.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Proofread!</emphasis></para>
          <para>This is easily forgotten, but extremely important. Always
  proofread your work before issuing the final release. Better yet,
  give the document to someone else (perhaps a copy editor) who can
  readily spot spelling and grammatical errors. Nothing signals
  unprofessionalism more than a typo-filled communication.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="distributing_release">
      <title>Distributing the News Release</title>
      <para>Your media contact database is your best source for
  editors, journalists, and freelancers who should receive your
  news, but if you want to include a broader range of news media
  targets, you may consider using one of the many news release
  distribution services available. Asking one or two of your news
  media contacts will likely reveal a creditable service. These
  services can be expensive, so base your decision on how broad an
  appeal your news has.</para>
      <para>In North America, the more popular distribution services
  include:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>PR Newswire (
      <citetitle>
        <ulink url="http://www.prnewswire.com/">
        www.prnewswire.com</ulink>
      </citetitle>
      )</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Canada Newswire (
      <citetitle>
        <ulink url="http://www.newswire.ca/">
        www.newswire.ca</ulink>
      </citetitle>
      )</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>BusinessWire (
      <citetitle>
        <ulink url="http://www.businesswire.com/">
        www.businesswire.com</ulink>
      </citetitle>
      )</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>These firms will customize your distribution based on the
  subject matter, and can target specific media such as technology
  editors, medical editors, daily news editors, and so on. A
  customer service representative will explain your options and the
  cost involved.</para>
      <para>News releases are very important in a public relations
  campaign. News releases give editors and the public a glimpse
  into your company. When these documents are done professionally,
  your organization will receive the recognition you deserve.
  Remember, though, that news releases are not the only tool of
  public relations professionals. In our next chapter, we will
  examine the variety of other tools that can be used.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="other_pr_tools">
    <title>Other Public Relations Tools</title>
    <para>The news release is the most important form of written
  communications used by a public relations professional, but not
  the only one. There are many other public relations tools that
  should be used when appropriate.</para>
    <para>News releases may suffice for most news stories, but other,
  lengthier forms of communication can give in-depth coverage of an
  interesting news item. Feature articles, bylined articles, and
  emails may be written to provide human interest appeal, to
  explore topics and issues in more depth, to raise your
  organization's profile in the local community,
  or for other reasons.</para>
    <section id="feat_articles">
      <title>Feature Articles</title>
      <para>Feature articles, which explore a subject at length, are
  not constrained by the tight deadlines of regular news articles.
  Features may be submitted at any time, depending on the
  editor's needs. Features often stem from a
  regular news item.</para>
      <para>Imagine that the Linux operating system has been
  successfully implemented at a large organization in your
  community. This story is newsworthy, but begin to look for
  <quote>the rest of the story.</quote> What
  difficulties did they experience in the transition, or what part
  did your organization play in their implementation? This could be
  the start of a feature article.</para>
      <para>More research and creativity will go into a feature story,
  but the must still be accurate. You will provide more facts, more
  statistics, more examples and anecdotes, and more analysis than
  in a news release. You can humanize and dramatize what may appear
  unexciting at first glance (a Linux implementation). You can
  openly focus on a particular angle or viewpoint, so long as you
  avoid outright advertising. Readers dislike advertorials
  masquerading as <quote>articles,</quote> and no
  editor will accept an article that blatantly sells.</para>
      <para>Another bonus is that editors are quite open to features,
  because they provide much needed content for filling an issue.
  When the feature is written by a reliable source and does not
  require payment (unlike a commissioned article), the article
  becomes a real asset.</para>
      <para>All writing needs to engage the reader. The first sentence
  or two must be compelling enough for the editor to read on.
  Features require a strong lead&mdash;something to
  hook your target audience. A headline or a photograph may
  help.</para>
      <para>For a feature, you have a wide repertoire of leads to
  choose from. Some leads are designed to startle and shock, some
  will excite readers' curiosity, some will
  vividly describe a real or imagined scenario, and some will
  succinctly state the nature of the story.</para>
      <para>The body of the feature then unfolds in a logical sequence,
  and ends with a strong and memorable close. Every feature will be
  different, depending on the subject, the anticipated audience,
  and the skill of the writer. Reading features written by others
  in the Linux community is a good way to learn and pick up
  possible story ideas.</para>
      <para>You can direct a feature to the <quote>feature
  editor</quote> at a daily newspaper or your targeted trade
  magazines. Before going to the trouble of writing the article,
  you should pitch the idea to see if the publication has any
  interest at all. The pitch should include an outline, an
  estimated length (number of words), and a description of
  illustrations or photos you can supply. You could also include a
  selected portfolio of previously published articles about your
  organization.</para>
      <para>The upfront consultation is invaluable. Since the editor
  knows their readership better than you do, they might suggest an
  angle of specific interest to their readers and indicate where
  this piece might fit in their publishing schedule. The more
  complete your package, the more seriously your work will be
  considered.</para>
      <para>Another possibility is to plant the story idea with the
  editor, and let the publication take care of writing the feature.
  In this case, you can supply expertise and interview
  subjects.</para>
      <para>Whatever your approach, keep in mind that the ultimate goal
  is to generate favorable coverage and visibility for your
  organization.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="byline_articles">
      <title>Bylined Articles</title>
      <para>A byline is the line showing the
  author's name at the beginning of an article.
  Basically, a bylined article is attributed to a source rather
  than being anonymous.</para>
      <para>Bylined articles can be any length, and they tend to based
  on opinion. They articulate views and opinions that are clearly
  the writer's own, without requiring objectivity.</para>
      <para>Issues, trends, and predictions regarding Linux and open
  source are ideal subjects for bylined articles. Moreover,
  forward-looking pieces are of high interest. Editors are always
  looking for <quote>the next thing</quote> to tell their readers about.</para>
      <para>Opinion articles are important to position your
  organization as the leader and trendsetter in your field. To be a
  guru is to be watched, quoted, respected, and followed. Editors
  like highlighting celebrated members of the community because
  they sell more issues.</para>
      <para>Gauging the interest of the news media is very important.
  What's hot? What are they writing about? Check
  the topics listed in their editorial calendars. Try to match
  their interests to the activities of your organization in the
  community. Then start writing your opinion piece.</para>
      <para>Typically, the author of a bylined article should be your
  organization's designated spokesperson and
  acknowledged authority for the media. That might be you or a
  senior official. Sometimes a public relations professional will
  ghost-write the piece for the spokesperson, whose name will
  appear on the article. When this occurs, the article must closely
  reflect the spokesperson's views and ideas. In
  other words, he or she <quote>owns</quote> the
  ideas expressed in the article, not the writer.</para>
      <para>An added bonus of by-lined articles is that they can be
  adapted into speeches for possible speaking opportunities.
  Conversely, any speech can be written as a by-lined
  article.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="email_writing">
      <title>Email Writing</title>
      <para>Another effective way to communicate to a targeted audience
  is through an email campaign. The effectiveness of a good email
  should not be underestimated. Some fundraising experts, for
  example, can raise thousand of dollars with an effective email
  campaign. Exceptional letters have obtained contracts, sold
  properties, and landed jobs.</para>
      <para>Emails can be targeted to a specific audience for much less
  than you would spend on a regular mail campaign. Every email is
  an opportunity to effectively communicate to your target
  audience. For example, your organization might want to target
  recent graduates of local computer training courses with
  opportunities in their area. You will need to obtain the names
  and email addresses of recent graduates from the institutions
  offering those programs. Cooperation with their institution can
  often be established if you provide something in return, such as
  a reciprocal link on your website, a mention in your newsletter,
  or even free advertising.</para>
      <para>Hopefully, your email campaign will generate interest in
  your organization and your programs. Be mindful of potentially
  spamming your intended audience&mdash;this could
  have a negative impact.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="misc_tools">
      <title>Miscellaneous Communications Tools</title>
      <para>There are numerous other communication tools you can use in
  a public relations effort. Here are just a few
  suggestions:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A speech at a Linux trade show.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A presentation at a local training institution or
      career development conference.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A brochure or flyer describing the work your company
      does.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A white paper describing the benefits of your
      company's work, posted on your website.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A newsletter or email newsletter describing your
      organization's activities and
      achievements, aimed at current and prospective users.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>An advertisement placed in targeted magazines.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Special events such as open houses and
      <quote>media information</quote> days.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Regular tours of your facility.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The possibilities are limited only by your time, resources,
  and budget.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="emphasize_core_msgs">
      <title>Don't Forget Emphasizing Core Messages</title>
      <para>In all your public relations initiatives,
  don't lose sight of your core messages
  (described in <xref linkend="planning"></xref>). These messages are the
  <quote>essence</quote> of your organization,
  defining your identity for users, the media, and the general
  public. Remember that the core messages should be woven into
  everything you do as a public relations representative.
  Consistency creates a bigger impact for your audience.</para>
      <para>In the next chapter, we will look at how to use a trade
  show as a valuable tool for promoting your organization.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="trade_show">
    <title>Working the Trade Show</title>
    <para>Speaking engagements at appropriate industry functions will
  garner increased visibility and media coverage. One of the
  easiest ways to gain credibility is to participate as actively as
  possible in trade shows, industry gatherings, and seminars. You
  must choose these events carefully, distinguishing between those
  that are worthwhile and those too small to matter. Keep in mind,
  the larger the gathering, the more competitive the speaking
  application process.</para>
    <section id="speaking_opps">
      <title>Arranging Speaking Opportunities</title>
      <para>Arranging possible speaking opportunities takes
  considerable effort and involves a long lead time. In most
  instances, you must be in contact with the conference organizers
  at least nine to ten months in advance of the show. You may even
  find that a sponsorship is required to be considered as a
  possible presenter.</para>
      <para>First, do your research regarding relevant conferences that
  are being planned in your area in the months ahead. The website
  of the event organizer or of the conference itself is often a
  good place to start looking for information. Contact the
  organizers to find out their needs and application requirements
  for possible speakers.</para>
      <para>Also, consider other venues in addition to trade shows
  focusing on Linux and open source. For example, you could offer
  your services as a speaker to human resources or computer
  training communities.</para>
      <para>The key to successful participation is similar to pitching
  to the news media. You must understand your audience, you must
  have a compelling topic, and you must be ready and willing to
  impart your knowledge and experience of the industry. Most
  importantly, your presentation has to teach something to someone,
  and not just be a commercial for your organization or Linux. Give
  the audience the satisfaction of having really learned something
  from your presentation, and show organizers will want to have you
  as a presenter at their next show.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="getting_attention">
      <title>Getting Media Attention at Trade Shows</title>
      <para>If you want publicity while exhibiting at a trade show,
  don't do what too many other organizations do.
  During the show, they wait patiently at their booth until they
  spot a reporter coming down the aisle. Then, if the reporter
  stops at its booth, the exhibitor moves in with the same tired
  pitch used on everybody else who walks by.</para>
      <para>If this has been your approach in the past, now is the time
  to change. Waiting until the show begins is already too late to
  capture the news media's attention. You should
  now understand that establishing strong news media relationships
  weeks or even months in advance can pay off when the show
  begins.</para>
      <para>Begin by finding out which news media will be covering the
  show. The best way to get that information is from the
  show's public relations department. Ask them
  if they can give you the names of print, broadcast, and online
  media they are targeting. This information is important to know,
  so that you don't pitch the same story ideas
  as the show organizers.</para>
      <para>If you discover the organizers are pitching an idea that
  fits well with your organization's objectives,
  ask if they could include your business as an example in their
  pitch.</para>
      <para>Check the editorial calendars of both the publications that
  will be covering the show and other publications that might have
  an interest. (A computer magazine, for example, is a prime target
  for a large Linux conference.) Many publications will issue a
  special report before or after the show takes place. The report
  may be a section within an issue or even an entire special
  edition. If you cannot glean this information from the calendar,
  you should call the publication and ask.</para>
      <para>The special reports present ripe opportunities for media
  coverage. Pitch story ideas that may become part of the special
  report to your media contacts.</para>
      <para>Prepare a compelling news release describing the most
  interesting thing that your organization will be doing at the
  show. Mention awards, impressive results, or endorsements by
  Linux experts&mdash;anything that will snag the
  media's attention. Include the line
  <quote>For more information or to arrange an
  interview, contact:</quote> as part of your contact
  information at the end.</para>
      <para>In devising your strategy to get media coverage at the
  show, always position your organization as
  <quote>part of the solution,</quote> not as a
  mere attendee.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="planning_trade_show">
      <title>Planning for a Trade Show</title>
      <para>Planning for trade shows needs to start at least a few
  months in advance. If you wish to have a significant presence at
  strategic or influential show, you should plan to set up a booth,
  either on your own or with a key partner. Booth space is limited
  and must be reserved in advance. Usually a fee is involved, which
  varies according to square footage and location on the exhibition
  floor. Designing the portable booth can take a few months, so
  plan ahead.</para>
      <para>Here are some tips for getting maximum benefit from your
  trade show appearances.</para>
      <section id="pre_show">
        <title>Before the Show</title>
        <para>A major trade show requires considerable advance
  preparation and, if you aren't ready, can
  present a logistical nightmare. You must develop a solid plan and
  monitor your progress vigilantly.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Evaluate and select trade shows carefully.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Participating in a show can require a major investment of
  time, money, and resources. Be tough in your evaluation of a
  show's worthiness. Are the attendees likely
  customers for your organization? Exposure to a few hundred very
  qualified targets is better than exposure to thousands of
  generalists who are very unlikely to be interested in your
  business.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Read the show manual.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Before you do anything, contact the organizers of the show
  to find the show's manual. Everything you need
  to know about the show should be there, including a proposed or
  final schedule, registration information and forms, floor plans,
  exhibit specifications, invitations for potential speakers, and
  other important details.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Identify your goals.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Be specific about the things you want to accomplish as a
  result of your participation in the show. Do you want to increase
  visibility, gain exposure to a large number of customers who
  might be interested in your products, or check out the
  competition? Concrete goals are important to determine the value
  of the trade show to your organization.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Define measurements of success.</emphasis></para>
            <para>For each goal, determine a way to measure its success. Make
  these measurements as specific as possible. You could plan to
  hand out 1000 brochures, obtain contact information for at least
  200 prospects, and take a key editor out to lunch. These
  benchmarks will help you decide whether the show was worth the
  expense.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Put your show plan in writing.</emphasis></para>
            <para>The plan should include a workable schedule, a
  comprehensive list of preparation activities, and an individual
  assigned for each task. You cannot leave things to chance, or
  else Murphy's Law (Whatever can go wrong, will go wrong.) will surely
  prevail!</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Develop a key message for your booth exhibit.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Like good advertising, a good exhibit clearly communicates
  one major message. This draws in more prospects to your booth
  than an unfocused cacophony of messages.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Design an open, inviting booth.</emphasis></para>
            <para>An open booth design, with no tables obstructing access,
  invites attendees to come in. Your logo should be big enough to
  be seen from a good distance. Maximize <quote>walking
  around</quote> space by mounting brochure displays on walls.
  Use interesting graphics to draw people's
  attention. For demos, laptops and flat-screen monitors are
  space-efficient. If space permits, provide comfortable chairs to
  encourage prospects to linger. A portable booth should be
  reasonably easy to set up and take down.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Advertise your show participation.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Use tag lines such as: <quote>see us at Booth
  1525 at the Linux World Conference</quote> in news releases
  and other communications leading up to the show (even if those
  releases are about something unrelated). Write a news release
  announcing show-related news. Invite editors to stop by the
  booth, or set up appointments between them and your
  spokespeople.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Order all necessary supplies, including brochures and
      giveaways.</emphasis></para>
            <para>If your marketing collateral needs to be updated or
  redesigned, take care of this early. You don't
  want to run the risk of having no brochures to hand out. Design forms for 
  filling out prospect information&mdash;clear forms eliminate
  guesswork. Consider giveaways to generate attention and a sense of
  fun. These don't have to be expensive. Pens
  with your web address and a catchy slogan can be very
  effective.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Design PowerPoint presentations and demos for the
      booth.</emphasis></para>
            <para>These will draw attendees to your booth and help them learn
  more about your business. Presentations will allow you to
  communicate information to many prospects at once.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Create a unique identity for your booth staff.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Decide on the dress code for your staff. Matching blazers,
  T-shirts, or even boutonnieres will make your representatives
  easily identifiable.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Train your exhibit staff before each show.</emphasis></para>
            <para>This is very important! Your staff needs to know what is
  expected of them. They need to be briefed on all new programs and
  initiatives that should be emphasized. They must know how to run
  the demos and presentations, and they should know some basic
  trouble shooting. Nothing looks more unprofessional then demos
  that don't work.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="during_show">
        <title>During the Show</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Set up a rotating booth schedule for your staff.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Your staff needs breaks for lunch and relaxing. They will
  be more cheerful if they don't have stay at the booth all day long.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Remind staff to record all prospect information.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Encourage your staff to record everything they can learn
  about a prospect's needs and experience with
  Linux. Stress the importance of getting phone numbers and email
  addresses. (Creating an information form as suggested above will
  make this easier.)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Encourage staff to greet people warmly and smile!</emphasis></para>
            <para>Amazingly, this is often forgotten. An inviting attitude
  can give a valuable first impression. The staff should avoid
  having their backs to the entrance, or taking phone calls while
  on duty. A friendly greeting to passersby may encourage them to
  stop rather than simply walk by. Staff who are uniformly
  courteous and helpful, knowledgeable about all aspects of the
  industry, and responsive to requests will make a very good
  impression.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="post_show">
        <title>After the Show</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Send requested literature immediately.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Send requested material within 24 hours. A quick response
  is your second opportunity to make a favorable impression. (Your
  performance in the booth is the first.)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Include a teaser on the envelope or in the email
      subject line.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Be sure to mention your organization's
  name and the name of the conference on the outside of the
  envelope or in the email subject line, so they know your letter
  is not junk mail.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Help your prospects take the next step.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Make sure your literature packages make responding easy for
  prospects by including your web address and information on the
  opportunities available to them.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Keep track of your prospects.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Nothing signals the success of your trade-show effort
  better than having prospects purchase your products or having the
  media spotlight your efforts. Keep a record of the customers who
  found out about your products through the trade show. Use these
  results to demonstrate the show's return on investment.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Analyze <quote>lessons learned.</quote></emphasis></para>
            <para>After each show, evaluate what went well and what
  didn't. Critique each aspect of the show and
  ask others for comments. Pay special attention to feedback
  regarding communication to prospective customers. The
  <quote>lessons learned</quote> will help improve
  your efforts in future shows.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Next, we will review the major topics we have covered in
  this guide to public relations. This final chapter will serve as
  a quick reference guide to the major elements of public
  relations. Use this guide to develop a successful public
  relations campaign.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="quick_maximizing_tips">
    <title>Quick Tips for Maximizing Coverage</title>
    <para>To conclude this public relations guide, we give you quick
  tips for maximizing your opportunities for media overage. This
  chapter provides a quick reference guide to many of the major
  points we've covered. If you've appreciated the importance of the
  previous chapters, these pointers will be a valuable
  summary.</para>
    <section id="howto_maximize">
      <title>How to Maximize Media Coverage</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Have a strategy.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Tailor your strategy for each public relations opportunity.
  Think about the audience you want to reach and how to create
  excitement. An effective part of your strategy should be to
  enforce your organization's core messages in
  all news releases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Have a good story.</emphasis></para>
          <para>A news story must have a compelling beginning, middle, and
  end. Journalists recognize a strong story within seconds, so tell
  your story quickly and succinctly.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Know your audience.</emphasis></para>
          <para>You wouldn't follow up on a potential
  business opportunity without knowing something about their
  business, so don't call the news media
  blindly. Before you pitch to any media outlet, study their work.
  Read the publication, watch the show, and listen to the radio
  broadcast. Get familiar with the characteristics of the media
  outlet you are targeting. Find out about their main audience and
  their likes and dislikes. (Internet message boards are good for
  this.)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Invest in relationships.</emphasis></para>
          <para>The more you know about the media organization and your
  target editor, the better and more confidently you can pitch to
  them. Building relationships <emphasis>now</emphasis>
  means editors will be more likely to take your call when
  you've got an important story to tell. Best of
  all, even if they can't offer you coverage on
  this particular story, they may refer you to another reporter who
  can. As with any relationship, building trust is critical. Keep
  your promises, and be on time. Be upfront about what you can and
  can't do. You might not be able to do
  everything, but reporters will appreciate your honesty.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Think before you speak.</emphasis></para>
          <para>A word of caution: <emphasis>everything</emphasis>
  you say to a reporter is on the record, regardless of
  disclaimers. You are representing your organization at all times.
  The impression that you give has a definite impact on how the
  media views your organization.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Monitor your media coverage.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Media coverage shows your success. As a media relations
  expert, the end goal is always positive media coverage for your
  organization. When your organization is spotlighted in major
  media outlets, you bring attention and respect to your
  business.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Look for a unique angle.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Look for personal stories that can spur news media
  interest. For instance, if a local school board is considering
  Linux to save money, focus your story on the human interest
  angle. Unusual stories and angles that affect a
  media's audience are more likely to get media
  coverage than mundane ones.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Know your story inside and out.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Research your story carefully. This allows you to revise your pitch 
  if the editor has specific needs. You also must be able to answer any questions
  that the editor may have.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Be persistent.</emphasis></para>
          <para>There is a fine line between being persistent and annoying,
  but if you have a good story and know your audience, it is fine
  to make contact attempts until you get feedback from a
  reporter.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Follow up.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Many potential leads are lost because public relations
  people fail to follow through. If a reporter tells you to call
  back another time, make sure you do! Also, if a reporter
  doesn't answer your email immediately, do not
  assume they are not interested. They might not have had time to
  respond to the large volume of emails they receive.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Be creative.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Infusing your media relations plans with innovative
  thinking produces stronger, more effective results, so avoid
  recycling the same old news releases and fact sheets.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Find information.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Do you sometimes feel like you just
  can't write the news release? This blockage
  often indicates you don't have enough
  information. Do outside research. Interview an industry analyst.
  Get another perspective. This investigation can lead to the
  information for a great story.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Study and adopt good writing skills.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Use a journalistic approach. Look carefully at how
  reputable publications like <emphasis>The New York Times</emphasis>
  or <emphasis>The Wall Street Journal</emphasis>
  structure a story. What is the lead? What kind of quotes do they
  use? Study different types of stories. Features, appointment
  announcements, news articles, and opinion pieces can all be
  useful in your public relations campaign. Often, you will see the
  most important information is in the lead and that the rest of
  the story follows. This inverted pyramid style is usually the
  best way to organize an article.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Eliminate jargon and techno-speak.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Buzzwords are like bees&mdash;they can be
  highly irritating. Write with clear language, and avoid
  clichés, which are another sign of weak writing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Expect results.</emphasis></para>
          <para>Media coverage means increased visibility, which
      exposes your organization to more prospective customers. The
      more people you can reach, the better the impact will be on
      your organization.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>Finally, the success of your media relations efforts means
  success for <emphasis>you</emphasis>
  in the dynamic, engaging, challenging, and creative business of
  public relations.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <appendix id="app_1">
    <title>Monitoring Media Coverage</title>
    <para>Monitoring the media coverage of your organization is a
  vital part of tracking your success, but can be extremely time
  consuming. A more efficient and reliable tracking method is to
  use a media monitor service or a clipping service. The website 
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://dmoz.org/News/Services/Media_Monitoring/">
    http://dmoz.org/News/Services/Media_Monitoring/</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  provides a long list of media monitoring services, some of which
  are provided here.</para>
    <section id="monitor_clipping_services">
      <title>Media Monitor Services and Clipping Services</title>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">AirCheck News Taping</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.airchecknews.com/">
    www.airchecknews.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a full-service broadcast monitor providing national and
  local news segments and reports.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Advance Media Information</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.amiplan.com/">www.amiplan.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is database of events for the next 18 months, continually
  updated by a team of journalists and broadly divided into news
  and entertainment. Each item is integrated with a press
  directory, listing essential information, including telephone
  numbers and email addresses.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Bacon's</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.bacons.com/">www.bacons.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a public relations supplier of media directories, media
  software, press clippings, Internet clipping, media lists and
  news release distribution.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Medialink Worldwide</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.medialink.com/">
    www.medialink.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a television and radio news monitoring and clipping
  service.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Burrelle's/Luce Information
  Services</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://burrellesluce.com/">http://burrellesluce.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a premier monitoring service for quick and comprehensive
  print, broadcast, and Internet information.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">ClipGenius</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.clipgenius.com/">
    www.clipgenius.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a clipping service specializing in public relations news and
  newspaper clips as well as web and press clipping.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">ConfirMedia</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.confirmedia.com/">
    www.confirmedia.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) monitors content broadcast on radio and television.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">CustomScoop</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.customscoop.com/">
    www.customscoop.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is an online agency delivering a daily customized clipping
  service that draws from online editions of major wires and daily
  papers, TV and radio stations, smaller daily and weekly
  newspapers, magazines, trade journals, and new media
  publications. Free trial available.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Cutters</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.cutters.com/">
    www.cutters.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a Singapore-based press clipping service with particular
  emphasis on business and information technology news. Also
  provides tracking on electronic media.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">CyberAlert</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.cyberalert.com/">
    www.cyberalert.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) offers fully-automated Internet monitoring and clipping of
  content in web publications, sites, message boards, and news
  groups.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">E-mmediate Clipping Service</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.e-mmediateclippings.com/">
    www.e-mmediateclippings.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) offers web delivery of articles from Montana newspapers.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">JA Media Services</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.jamedia.com/">www.jamedia.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) offers broadcast television and radio monitoring, and news
  clipping and transcription services</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Media Source</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.memphismediasource.com/">
    www.memphismediasource.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a full-service TV news monitoring and digital video
  production company, offering local broadcast monitoring for 120
  U.S. cities and all major national networks.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Mediatrack</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.mediatrack.co.uk/">
    www.mediatrack.co.uk/</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) provides international media evaluation, analysis, and
  measurement, campaign evaluation, competitor analysis, and media
  research nationally or globally.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Metro Monitor</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.metromonitor.com/">
    www.metromonitor.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a professional broadcast news monitoring and news clipping
  service monitoring over 300 U.S. stations.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Multivision, Inc.</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.multivisioninc.com/">
    www.multivisioninc.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a media monitor specializing in hard-to-find coverage and
  markets along with digital delivery of broadcast clips.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">News Index Delivered</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.newsindex.com/delivered.html">
    www.newsindex.com/delivered.html</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) monitors hundreds of daily news sources, and provides keyword
  search-based email clippings daily.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">News Power Online</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.enewspower.com/">
    www.enewspower.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) provides comprehensive solutions to your information
  needs.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">NewsNow Digital Intelligence</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.newsnow.co.uk/di">
    www.newsnow.co.uk/di</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) tracks news about your company, searching over 3500 sites every
  few minutes for relevant stories.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">New Media Intelligence</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.newmediaintelligence.com/">
    www.parallel54.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) (previously known as Parallel54) provides research services including monitoring of newsgroups, media sites and other publicly accessible online content.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">PLCom News Services</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.plcom.net/news/index.php3">
    www.plcom.net/news/index.php3</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) offers customized media monitoring and analysis, automated news
  feeds, and newspaper and TV news abstracts delivered on the web
  with encryption security.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Postech</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.postech.com/">www.postech.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a design engineering and manufacturing firm specializing in
  broadcasting, data acquisition, and telecommunications
  industries.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Quickscan</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.quickscan.net/">
    www.quickscan.net</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a software company that provides database software and
  technical support to professional news monitoring
  companies.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">SDS Media</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.sds-web.co.uk/">
    www.sds-web.co.uk</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) scans all U.K. newspapers and trade magazines to daily extract
  and deliver relevant articles to hundreds of clients.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Smart Brief</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.smartbrief.com/">www.smartbrief.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) provides free, email based news summaries and other content
  for industry associations, professional organizations, advocacy
  groups, and their constituents.</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Video Monitoring Services</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.vidmon.com/">www.vidmon.com</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) is a broadcast information retrieval service</para>
      <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Videowatch</emphasis>
  (
  <citetitle>
    <ulink url="http://www.videowatch.org/">
    www.videowatch.org</ulink>
  </citetitle>
  ) monitors news and news magazine broadcasts, maintains a 60-day
  archive, and sends broadcasts to you on videotape.</para>
    </section>
  </appendix>
</book>
