  <chapter id="aboutthisguide">
    <title>About this Guide</title>
    <section id="purpose">
      <title>About this Guide</title>
      <para>This document was started on Aug 26, 1999 by Mark
      F. Komarinski after two day's worth of frustration getting tools
      to work. If even one LDP author is helped by this, then I did my
      job.</para>  
      <para>
        The newest version of this document can be found at the LDP
        homepage
        <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>.
        The original DocBook, HTML, and other formats can be found there.
      </para>
      <para>There are many ways to contribute to the Linux movement
      without actually writing code.  One of the most important is
      writing documentation, allowing each person to share their
      knowledge with thousands of others around the world.  This Guide
      is designed to help you get familiar with how the LDP works, and
      what tools you'll need to write your own HOWTO.</para>
    </section> 

	<!-- Because I haven't decided where to put it, the 
			About The LDP
		section has become an entity. Currently the file starts with a
		<section>
	-->
	&tldp;
	<!-- End of section about The LDP -->

    <section id="feedback">
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>Comments on this Guide may be directed to the LAG coordinator
      (<email>mkomarinski@wayga.org</email>).</para> 
    </section>

    <section id="copyrights">
      <title>Copyrights and Trademarks</title>
      <para>Copyright 1999-2002 Mark F. Komarinski, David C. Merrill, Jorge Godoy</para>
      <para>
         Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
	 under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
	 any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
	 Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
	 Texts. A copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "GNU
	 Free Documentation License".
       </para>
    </section>

<!-- The Acknowledgements section should be moved to the end according
	to the LDP Author Guide Text -->
  &thankyous;

<!-- Document conventions -->
  &conventions;

</chapter>