<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
  <chapter id="aboutthisguide">
    <title>About this Guide</title>
    <section id="purpose">
      <title>About this Guide</title>
      <para>This document was started on Aug 26, 1999 by Mark
      F. Komarinski after two day's worth of frustration getting tools
      to work. If even one LDP author is helped by this, then I did my
      job.</para>
		<para>
			Version 4 of this document was released in early 2004 by Emma Jane
			Hogbin. A complete overhaul of the document was done to separate
			the authoring HOWTOs from the technical HOWTOs. The review took
			approximately eight months.
		</para>
      <para>
        The newest version of this document can be found at the LDP
        homepage
        <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>.
        The original DocBook, HTML, and other formats can be found there.
      </para>
      <para>
		There are many ways to contribute to the Linux movement
      that do not require the ability to produce software. One such way is
		to write documentation. The availability of
		easy-to-understand, technically accurate documentation can make a
		world of difference to someone who is struggling with Linux
		software. This Guide is designed to help you research and write a 
		HOWTO which can be submitted to the LDP. The appendices also include
		sample templates, markup tips and information on how to transform
		your document from DocBook to another format (such as HTML) for
		easier proofreading.
		</para>
    </section> 

	<!-- Because I haven't decided where to put it, the 
			About The LDP
		section has become an entity. The file is contained within section
		tags.
	-->
	&tldp;
	<!-- End of section about The LDP -->

    <section id="feedback">
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>
		Send feedback to <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>. Please reference the title
		of this document in your email. Please note: you must <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">be subscribed</ulink>
		in order to send email to the list.
		</para>
    </section>

    <section id="copyrights">
      <title>Copyrights and Trademarks</title>
      <para>Copyright 1999-2002 Mark F. Komarinski, David C. Merrill, Jorge Godoy</para>
      <para>
         Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
	 under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
	 any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
	 Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
	 Texts. A copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled
	 <quote>GNU Free Documentation License.</quote>
       </para>
    </section>

<!-- The Acknowledgements section should be moved to the end according
	to the LDP Author Guide Text -->
  &thankyous;

<!-- Document conventions -->
  &conventions;

</chapter>
