<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<chapter id="distribution">
    <title> Distributing your documentation </title>

    <section id="beforeyoudistribute">
      <title> Before you distribute </title>
      <para> Before you distribute your code to millions of potential
      readers there are a few things you should do. </para> 
      <para> 
		First, be sure to spell-check your document. Most
      utilities that you would use to write your documentation will have plug-ins to
      perform a spell check. If not, there's always the
		<application>aspell</application>
      program. There's a smidge more about this program over in <xref
		linkend="ag-spellcheck" />.
		</para> 

      <para> Second, get someone to review your documentation for
      factual correctness.  You can also ask for general
      comments.  The documentation that is
      published by the LDP needs to be as factually correct as
      possible, as there are millions of Linux users that may be
      reading it. If you're part of a larger mailing list talking
      about the subject, ask others from the list to help you
      out. </para>

      <para> Third, create a web site where you can distribute your
      documentation. This isn't required, but is helpful for people to
      find the original location of your document. </para>

      <section id="validatecode">
		<title>Validate Your Document</title>

		<para>
                  There is more information about how to do this over in the
                  DocBook section. Check out <xref linkend="tools-validate" />
                  for more help with validating your document.
		</para>
    	</section>
    
    <section id="makingcopyright">
      <title> Copyright and Licensing issues </title>
      <para> In order for an LDP document to be accepted by the LDP,
      it must be licensed to conform to the "LICENSE REQUIREMENTS"
      section of the LDP Manifesto located at <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html</ulink>.
      As an author, you may retain the copyright and add other
      restrictions (for example, you must approve any translations or
      derivative works). </para>

      <para> We recommend using the <ulink 
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GNU Free Documentation 
      License (GFDL)</ulink> or the <ulink 
      url="http://opencontent.org/openpub/">Open Publication License 
      (OPL)</ulink> <emphasis>without</emphasis> options A and B.  If
      you choose, you can get DocBook markups of both the GNU GPL
      and the GNU FDL from <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp/licenses.html">
      the GNOME Documentation Project</ulink>.  You can then merely
      include the license in its entirety in your document. A
		DocBook-formatted copy of the license is available in
		<xref linkend="templates"/>.
		</para>
      
      <para>If you choose to use a boilerplate copyright, simply copy it
      into your source code under a section called <quote>Copyright
      and Licenses</quote> or similar. Also include a copyright
      statement of your own (since you still own it). If you are a new
      maintainer of an already-existing HOWTO, you must include the
      previous copyright statements of the previous author(s) and the
      dates they maintained that document. </para> 

      <para>You'll note that the licensing for the LDP Author Guide
      requires notification to the author of any derivative works or
      translations.  I also explicitly place any source code (aside
      from the markup language the Guide was written in) under the GPL. If your
      HOWTO includes bits of source code that you want others to use,
      you may do the same.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="crediting-ack">
      <title>The <quote>Acknowledgements</quote> section</title>

      <para>Your document should have an <quote>Acknowledgements</quote> section,
      in which you mention everyone who has contributed to your document in
      any meaningful way. You should include translators and converters, as well as
      people who have sent you lots of good feedback, perhaps the person who taught
      you the knowledge you are now passing on, and anybody else who was instrumental
      in making the document what it is. Most authors put this section at the end
      of their document.</para>
    
	 <para>When someone else assists in the production of an
	 LDP document,
    you should give them proper attribution, and there are DocBook tags
    designed to do this. This section will show you the tags you should
    use, as well as other ways of giving credit where credit is due.
    Crediting editors is easy - there is already an
    <sgmltag class="starttag">editor</sgmltag>tag in DocBook.
    But there are two special cases where you need to credit someone,
    but DocBook doesn't provide a special tag. These are <emphasis>translators</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>converters</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>A <emphasis>converter</emphasis> is someone
    who performs a source code conversion, e.g., from HTML to DocBook SGML.
    Source code conversions help the LDP achieve long term goals for meta-data,
    and allow us to produce documentation in many different output formats.</para>

    <para>Translators take your original document and translate it into other
    human-readable languages, e.g., from English to Japanese, or from German
    to English. Each translation allows many more people all over the world
    to make use of your document, and helps Linux achieve the ultimate goal -
    Total World Domination(tm)!</para>

		<para>
		We recommend that 
		you acknowledge converters in the comment for the
      initial version released in the new format, and 
		we recommend that you credit translators in each 
		version which they have translated.</para>

	<note><para>For more information on how to add these credits using DocBook
		please read <xref linkend="metadata-markup" />
	</para></note>
	</section>
	
	</section> <!-- beforeyoudistribute -->
    
	 <section id="submission">
      <title> Submission to LDP </title>
      <para> Once your LDP document has been carefully reviewed, you
      can release your document to the LDP. Send an e-mail with the
      source code as an attachment (you may gzip it if you like)
      to <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. </para>

		<para>
		If your document is a new document it will be reviewed by LDP
		volunteers and checked against the following points:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>License and Copyright</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				For a DocBook-formatted copy of the GFDL please visit the
				templates section: <xref linkend="templates" />
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Metadata</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				For more information on how to add these credits using DocBook
			please read <xref linkend="metadata-markup" />
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Abstract</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				This section must clearly define the scope of your
				document. Example markup is given in the templates
				section.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
			<term>Spelling</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>

			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Grammar</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>

			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Technical accuracy</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				If your document has already been reviewed by others for
				its technical accuracy, please include a note in your
				email to <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email> to this effect.
				For example: "I have submitted this document to the
				debian-laptop mailing list and have received positive
				feedback on the technical details." Or something.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Clarity of text</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>

			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Organiztion of material</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>

			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Type of markup</term>
			<listitem>
			<para>

			</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

		<para>
			For more information on what the reviewers will be looking
			for, please read the <ulink
			url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/index.html">Linux Documentation Project Reviewer
			HOWTO</ulink>. 
		</para>

      <para> Be sure to include the name of your HOWTO in the subject
      line, and use the body to outline changes you've made and attach
      your HOWTO. This allows the maintainers to do their jobs faster,
      so you will not have to wait for your HOWTO to be updated on the
      LDP web site. If you don't hear anything in 5 calendar days,
      please follow up with an e-mail to make sure things are still in
      process. </para> 

      <para>If your HOWTO contains extras, such as graphics or a
      special catalog, create a .tar.gz file with all the files in it
      including the .xml source code and mail it as an attachment to
      the submit list.</para>

      <para>If you are using the LDP CVS tree while developing
      your document, the LDP will still need to be notified when your
      document is ready to be published. E-mail should be sent to
      <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. Indicate
      the title of your document and the relative path to the
      file(s) in the LDP CVS tree within your message. </para>

		<para>
		To get a CVS account please refer to: <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/cvs/">http://tldp.org/cvs/</ulink>
		</para>
    </section>

	 <section id="compilations">
	 <title>Publishing Compilations of LDP Documents</title>
    <para>
	 	If you are interested in publishing a collection of
		LDP documents, please visit <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html#pub">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html#pub</ulink>
		for more information.
	</para>
	</section>

		
</chapter> 
