<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<chapter id="distribute">
<title>Distributing Your Documentation</title>

<section id="pre-distribute">
<title>Before Distributing Your Documentation</title>
	<para>
		Before you distribute your documentation, there are a few more
		things that you will need to check and possibly add to your document.
	</para>

	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Spelling and Grammar Check</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		You can read more about helper applications in <xref
		linkend="ag-spellcheck" />. You should also check your document for
		its overall flow and clarity.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Abstract and Other Meta Data</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Add a short paragraph which clearly defines the scope of your
		document.
		For more information on how to add this information using DocBook
		please read <xref linkend="metadata-markup" />
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Acknowledgments</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Give credit where credit is due. For more information about when to
		give credit, read <xref linkend="crediting-ack" />.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>License and Copyright</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		The LDP distributes documents, however, the author maintains the
		copyright on the document. All documents accepted by the LDP must
		contain a license and copyright notice. You can read more about this
		in <xref linkend="doc-copyright" />.
		You may also want to add a Disclaimer, but this is optional. More
		about this in <xref linkend="doc-disclaimer" />.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term>Validate the Markup</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		If you are submitting a DocBook or LinuxDoc document, make sure the
		markup is valid. Read why in <xref linkend="why-validate" />.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Obtain Peer Reviews</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		You may want to have others review your document before
		submitting it to the LDP. Ask people for a <ulink
		url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/peerreview.html">Peer
		Review</ulink> and/or a <ulink
		url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/techreview.html">Technical
		Accuracy Review</ulink>. Since not all mailing lists will respond favorably 
		to attachments, you may wish to set up a temporary web site which houses your
		document. Note: this is absolutely <emphasis>not</emphasis> required.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>

<section id="doc-licensing">
      <title>Licensing and Copyright</title>
      <para> In order for a document to be accepted by the LDP,
      it must be licensed and conform to the <quote>LICENSE
		REQUIREMENTS</quote> section of the LDP Manifesto located at <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html</ulink>.
		</para>

      <para> We recommend using the <ulink 
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GNU Free Documentation 
      License (GFDL)</ulink>, one of the <ulink
		url="http://www.creativecommons.org/license">Creative Commons
		Licenses</ulink> (such as <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-Share-Alike</ulink>), or the LDP license (currently under review). The full text of the license must be included in your document, including the title and version of the license you are using. The LDP will not accept new documents that do not meet licensing requirements.</para>

		<warning>
			<title>Debian-compatible licenses</title>
			<para>The Debian package maintainer for LDP documents has divided the LDP documents into those with a <quote>free</quote> license and those with a <quote>non-free</quote> license. For a summary of this list, please read <ulink url="https://wiki.debian.org/DFSGLicenses">Debian License Summaries</ulink>. Currently the Artistic License, BSD License and the GNU General Public License are listed as <quote>free</quote>. These licenses will also be accepted by the LDP. The definition of <quote>non-free</quote> has not been made transparent. By choosing another license that has any kind of restriction on redistribution or whether or not the document may be modified, your document <emphasis>may</emphasis> be put into the <quote>non-free</quote> package instead of the <quote>free</quote> package. We are working with Debian to clarify how these decisions are made.</para>
		</warning>
		
		<para>A DocBook-formatted copy of the license is available in <xref linkend="templates"/>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			For more information about open source documentation and
			licensing, please check <xref linkend="ref-licenses" />.
		</para>
		
		<section id="doc-copyright">
		<title>Copyright</title>
      <para>As an author, you may retain the copyright and add other
      restrictions (for example: require approval for any translations or
      derivative works). If you are a new
      maintainer of an already-existing HOWTO, you must include the
      previous copyright statements of the previous author(s) and the
      dates they maintained that document. </para>
		</section>
	 
	 <section id="doc-disclaimer">
		<title>Disclaimer</title>
		<para>If you would like to include a disclaimer, you may choose
		to use the following:</para>
		<blockquote>
		&disclaimer;
		</blockquote>
	 </section>

	<section id="doc-sourcecode">
		<title>Licensing source code</title>
      <para>If your HOWTO includes bits of source code that you want others to use,
      you may choose to release the source code under GPL.</para>
	</section>
</section>

<section id="crediting-ack">
	<title>Acknowledgments</title>

   <para>Your document should have an <quote>Acknowledgments</quote> section,
      in which you mention everyone who has contributed to your document in
      any meaningful way. You should include translators and converters, as well as
      people who have sent you lots of good feedback, perhaps the person who taught
      you the knowledge you are now passing on, and anybody else who was instrumental
      in making the document what it is. Most authors put this section at the end
      of their document.
	</para>
    
	 <para>When someone else assists in the production of an
	 LDP document,
    you should give them proper attribution, and there are DocBook tags
    designed to do this. This section will show you the tags you should
    use, as well as other ways of giving credit where credit is due.
    Crediting editors is easy - there is already an
    <sgmltag class="starttag">editor</sgmltag>tag in DocBook.
    But there are two special cases where you need to credit someone,
    but DocBook doesn't provide a special tag. These are <emphasis>translators</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>converters</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>A <emphasis>converter</emphasis> is someone
    who performs a source code conversion, for instance from HTML to DocBook XML.
    Source code conversions help the LDP achieve long term goals for meta-data,
    and allow us to distribute documentation in many different formats.</para>

    <para>Translators take your original document and translate it into other
    human-readable languages, from English to Japanese for example, or from German
    to English. Each translation allows many more people all over the world
    to make use of your document and of the Linux operating system!</para>

		<para>
		We recommend that 
		you acknowledge converters in the comment for the
      initial version released in the new format, and 
		we recommend that you credit translators in each 
		version which they have translated.</para>

	<note><title>Acknowledgments translated in DocBook</title><para>For more information on how to add these credits using DocBook
		please read <xref linkend="metadata-markup" />
	</para></note>
</section>

<section id="ag-review">
<title>TLDP Review Process</title>

<para>
	Before your document is accepted to the LDP collection it will undergo
	at least three formal reviews. These reviews include a <ulink
	url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/techreview.html">technical accuracy
	review</ulink>, a <ulink
	url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/languagereview.html">language
	review</ulink> and a <ulink
	url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/metadatareview.html">metadata
	review</ulink>. All new documents must pass these reviews
	before being accepted into the collection.
</para>

<para>
	When you feel your document is finished, email a copy to the submit 
	mailing list (<email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>). Please include the title of your document and
	<quote>Final Review Required</quote> in the subject line of your email. 
	A team of volunteers will be assigned to your document for each of the
	reviews. It may take up to a week to gather a team who is qualified to review your document.
	Typically the technical review happens first, followed by the language
	review and finally the metadata review. Your reviewers will read your document give you feedback on
	whether or not they think your document is ready for publication in the
	LDP collection.
</para>

<para>
	Your reviewers may have specific points that must be changed. Once you
	have made the changes submit your document back to your review team.
	They will review the document again and advise you on whether or not
	your document is ready for inclusion in the LDP collection. You may
	need to undergo several edits before your document is ready. Or it may
	not require any additional work. Be prepared to make at least one round
	of changes for both the technical and language reviews. Ideally this
	exchange will happen in the LDP's <ulink
	url="http://cvs.tldp.org">CVS</ulink> to better track each of the
	changes that are made, and keep track of the most current version of
	your document.
</para>

<para>
	Once your document has passed both the technical and language reviews,
	you may submit it by following the instructions in <xref
	linkend="submission" />.
</para>

<tip>
<title>Comparing Two Source Files</title>
<para>Your reviewer may make changes directly to your source file, or they may put their suggestions in a separate email. If they are working with the source file directly, and your document is using DocBook XML, you may find <application>XMLdiff</application> useful to see the changes that your reviewer has made to your source file. It is a python tool that figures out the differences between two similar XML files, in the same way the <application>diff</application> utility compares text files.</para>

<para>XMLdiff is available from <ulink url="http://www.logilab.org/projects/xmldiff" />.</para>
</tip>

<para>
	For more information on what the reviewers will be looking for, please
	read the <ulink
	url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/index.html">Linux Documentation Project Reviewer HOWTO</ulink>. 
</para>
</section>

<section id="submission">
	<title>Submission to LDP for publication</title>
		<note><title>The final step</title><para>
			This section contains information on what to do after your
			document has received both a technical and language review by the
			LDP volunteers.
		</para></note>

		<para>
			As part of the review process a Review Coordinator will add your
			document to the CVS (including any associated image files) and
			notify the submit mailing list that your document is ready for
			publication.
		</para>

		<para>
			If you do not already have a CVS account, please apply for one
			when your document is submitted for publication. You can apply
			for an account contacting LDP CVS master Sergiusz <ulink url="mailto:ser@gnu.org" />
		</para>
<!--
		
      <para> Once your LDP document has been carefully reviewed, you
      can release your document to the LDP. Send an e-mail with the
      source code as an attachment (you may gzip it if you like)
      to <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. </para>

      <para> Be sure to include the name of your work in the subject
      line, and use the body to outline changes you've made and attach
      your document's source code. This allows the maintainers to do their jobs faster, and
		means your revised document will appear on the site faster.
      If you haven't heard anything in 5 calendar days,
      please follow up with an e-mail to make sure things are still in
      process. </para> 

      <para>If your text contains extras, such as graphics or a
      special catalog, create a .tar.gz file with all the files in it,
      including the XML source code, and mail it as an attachment to
      the submit list.</para>

      <para>If you are using the LDP CVS tree while developing
      your document, the LDP will still need to be notified when your
      document is ready to be published. E-mail should be sent to
      <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. Indicate
      the title of your document and the relative path to the
      file(s) in the LDP CVS tree within your message. </para>

		<para> To get a CVS account please refer to: <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/cvs/">http://tldp.org/cvs/</ulink>
		</para>
    </section>
	 <section id="compilations">
	 <title>Publishing Compilations of LDP Documents</title>
    <para>
		If you are interested in publishing a collection of
		LDP documents, please visit <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html#pub">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html#pub</ulink>
		for more information.
	</para>
	</section>
	-->
</section>
</chapter>
