<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<chapter id="sg-maintaining">
    <title>Maintaining Your HOWTO</title>
    
  <para>
      Just because your document has now been published doesn't mean your
      job is done. Linux documentation needs regular maintenance to make sure it
      is up to date, and to improve it in response to readers' ideas
      and suggestions. TLDP is a living, growing body of knowledge,
      not just a publish-and-forget-it static entity.
  </para>
    
	<para>
		Add relevant mailing lists to your document where people
		can get support. If you have the time, follow these
		mailing lists yourself to stay up-to-date on the
		latest information.
   </para>
  
  <para>
      Put your email address in the document, and politely request
      feedback from your readers. Once you are officially published,
      you will begin to receive notes with suggestions.
		Some of these emails will be very valuable. Create a 
		folder in your mail program for
		incoming suggestions--when the time is right review
		the folder and make updates to your document. If you
		are following a related mailing list you may also
		choose to save a copy of important emails from the list to
		this folder.
	</para>
		
	<note><title>We're not a free support service, but...</title><para>
	Some people who email you will request personal
	assistance.	You should feel free to decline personal 
	assistance if you cannot spare the time. Writing a 
	contribution to the LDP does not commit you to a lifetime
   of free support for anyone on the net; however, do try
	to reply to all requests and suggest a mailing list that
	will (hopefully) be able to provide support to your reader.
	</para></note>


	<section id="fixingerrors">
		<title>Fixing Errors</title>
		<para>
			If you find an error in your own document, please fix it
			and re-submit it. You can re-submit your files by emailing
			them to <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. If you've been
			using the CVS, you can simply <command>cvs commit</command> your revised document
			and then send an email saying the new version is ready for
			distribution. Remember to update the revision history at the
			top of the document.
		</para>

		<para>
			If you find an error in someone else's document please
			contact the author of the document, or the LDP 
        coordinator at <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email> (<ulink
		  url="http://tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">subscription
		  required</ulink>) and
        mention the problem and how you think it needs to be
        fixed. 
		</para> 

		<note><title>Taking over unmaintained documentation</title><para>
			For more information on how to deal with unmaintained
			documents, please read:
			<ulink
			url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">Unmaintained</ulink>
			(includes a list of steps to take to take over
			<quote>ownership</quote> of unmaintained documents, and a
			list of unmaintained documents).
		</para></note>
	</section>
		
</chapter>
