<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<chapter id="sg-maintaining">
<title>Maintenance</title>
    
<section id="sg-maintaining-support">
<title>Maintaining Your Document</title>
  <para>Just because your document has now been published does not mean your
      job is done. Linux documentation needs regular maintenance to make sure it
      is up to date, and to improve it in response to readers' ideas
      and suggestions. TLDP is a living, growing body of knowledge,
      not just a publish-and-forget-it static entity.</para>
    
	<para>Add relevant mailing lists to your document where people
		can get support. If you have the time, follow these
		mailing lists yourself to stay up-to-date on the
		latest information.</para>
  
  <para>Put your email address in the document, and politely request
      feedback from your readers. Once you are officially published,
      you will begin to receive notes with suggestions.
		Some of these emails will be very valuable. Create a 
		folder in your mail program for
		incoming suggestions--when the time is right review
		the folder and make updates to your document. If you
		are following a related mailing list you may also
		choose to save a copy of important emails from the list to
		this folder.</para>
		
	<note><title>We are not a free support service, but...</title><para>
	Some people who email you will request personal
	assistance.	You should feel free to decline personal 
	assistance if you cannot spare the time. Writing a 
	contribution to the LDP does not commit you to a lifetime
   of free support for anyone on the net; however, do try
	to reply to all requests and suggest a mailing list that
	will (hopefully) be able to provide support to your reader.
	</para></note>
	</section>
	
	<section id="fixingerrors">
		<title>Fixing Errors</title>
		
		<section id="fix-own">
		<title>Fixing Your Own Documents</title>
		<para>If you find an error in your own document, please fix it and re-submit the document. If you do not have GitHub access, you can send an e-mail to <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email> with notification that you have changes and a volunteer will work with you to handle the change. </para>
			
		<para>If you are using GitHub, you can commit your changes to your local repository and then generate a pull request to have it added to the central repository.</para>

		<para>Remember to update the revision history at the top of the document.</para>
		</section>

		<section id="fix-other">
		<title>Fixing Other Documents in the Collection</title>
		<para>If you find an error in someone else's document please contact the author of the document with the correction. If you do not hear back from the author within a <quote>reasonable</quote> amount of time, please email the LDP coordinator at <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email> (<ulink url="http://tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">subscription required</ulink>) and describe the problem and how you think it needs to be fixed. If the license permits, you may be asked to make the change directly to the document. If the problems are serious, the document may be removed from the collection, or moved to the <quote>Unmaintained</quote> section.</para> 

		<note>
		<title>Taking over unmaintained documentation</title>
		<para>For more information on how to deal with unmaintained documents, please read: <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">Unmaintained</ulink> (includes a list of steps to take to take over <quote>ownership</quote> of unmaintained documents, and a list of unmaintained documents).</para>
		</note>
	</section>
</section>

</chapter>
