<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->

    <chapter id="ag-markup">
      <title>Markup</title>

		<section id="markup">
		<title>Markup: A General Overview</title>
	
      <para>
	To explain what markup is, we must first take a look at
	what SGML, XML and Linuxdoc and DocBook are.
      </para> 
		
		<para>The Standard Generalized Markup Language (SGML)
      is a way of embedding information about a document
	  into the text of the document. SGML is not a markup
	  language itself, it is a <quote>metalanguage</quote>
	  from which other markup languages are created
	  (e.g. HTML and DocBook). Documents are stored in SGML
	  format using a specific Document Type Definition--a
	  controlled vocabulary. These documents may then be
	  <quote>transformed</quote> into a variety of other
	  types of documents such as PDFs, HTML pages, plain text
	  (etc!). The advantage of using SGML means you can use an
	  automated transformation to convert your document into
	  whatever format you may need.</para>

	  <para>Instead of defining things like colors, font
	  sizes and other specific formatting rules you define the
	  structure of the document. This is done with a series of
	  tags which are wrapped around content.  The controlled
	  vocabulary consists of <quote>elements</quote> which
	  describes what the content is. This block of text, for
	  example, is a paragraph. In DocBook notation I have wrapped
	  the block of text with the start tag &lt;para&gt; and then
	  the end tag &lt;/para&gt;. In HTML, a sub-set of SGML,
	  this would be done with the element &lt;p&gt;. Although
	  there are many similarities between DocBook and HTML,
	  DocBook contains hundreds of elements and is considered
	  a much more descriptive vocabulary.</para>

	  <note><para>Steve Champeon does a great job of
	  explaining this (from an HTML perspective but with
	  an example of DocBook markup) in his article <ulink
	  url="http://hotwired.lycos.com/webmonkey/02/42/index4a.html">The
	  Secret Life of Markup</ulink>.</para></note>

      <para>There are really three parts to an SGML document:</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
      First there is the content. As a TLDP author it is good
      to remember
	  that this is the most important piece. Many authors will
	  write the content first and add their markup later. Content
	  may include both plain text and graphics. For more
	  information about writing your content read: FIXME
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>
	  To describe the structure of the content a controlled
	  vocabulary added on top of the content. It is used to
	  distinguish different kinds of content: paragraphs,
	  lists, tables, warnings (and so on).	This is also known
	  as document <quote>markup</quote> and is typically what
	  people are referring to when they talk about SGML, XML
	  and HTML.  </para>

	  <para> The rules that define the structure of a document
	  are known as a Document Type Definition (DTD). Depending
	  on what kind of document you are writing, you will use
	  a different set of rules. The rules include the required
	  elements (tagset) and the order in which they must appear.
	  This document was written in DocBook version 4.2 (although
	  that version will likely change over time).  For more
	  information about marking up your document read: FIXME
		</para></listitem>

		<listitem><para>
      Finally the document is transformed to another type of
	  document and formatted for displayed. This is controlled
	  through the Document Style Semantics and Specification
	  Language (DSSSL).
      The DSSSL tells the program doing the transformation how to
      convert the raw markup into something that a human can read.
	  </para>

	  <para>For example: The DSSSL instructions may specify that
	  an RTF document should have all <sgmltag>title</sgmltag>s
	  transformed into 14 point
      bold type; however, the instructions for an HTML
	  document may convert that same <sgmltag>title</sgmltag>
	  into an &lt;h1&gt; HTML element.</para> <para> For more
	  information about transforming your document to other
	  document formats read <xref linkend="transformations"/>.
	  </para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      <para>
	The eXtensible Markup Language (XML) is a sub-set of
	SGML. Like
		SGML it is also a metalanguage and defines the
		rules of how a controlled vocabulary (DTD) can be
		used. Both SGML and XML documents must point to a DTD
		for the rules about a document's structure. DocBook
		is a DTD which is available in both SGML and XML
		formats. Although the element names do not change
		between the two there are slight differences in how
		the markup is applied. The LDP has chosen to store
		its documents in XML format using the DocBook DTD.
		(Other markup languages are accepted by the LDP. See
		<xref linkend="templates"/> for more information.)
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="docbook-why">
      <title>DocBook: What it is and why we use it</title> 
		
		<para>DocBook provides for more
      than just formatting. You can automatically build indexes,
      tables of contents, and links within the document or to
      outside. You can also transform
	  your DocBook document into a variety of formats including:
	  LaTeX, info, text, HTML, and RTF.  From these basic
	  formats, you can
      then create other formats such as MS Word, PostScript, PDF
      and so on. If you prefer to work in Lyx you can write in
	  Tex format, export to DocBook and then transform to any
	  of the formats mentioned above.
      DocBook, unlike other formats, is more concerned about
	  describing a document's structure than detailing how it
	  will be displayed.
      </para>

      <para> Although there are other DTDs used to write
      documentation,
	  there are a few reasons not to use them.</para>

	  <itemizedlist> <listitem><para> DocBook is the most
	  popular DTD, being
      used by more than a dozen major open source projects from
      GNOME to Python to FreeBSD.
	  </para></listitem> <listitem><para> The tools for DocBook
	  are more developed than others.  DocBook support is
	  included in most Linux distributions, allowing you to
	  send raw files to be processed at the receiver's end.
	  </para></listitem> <listitem><para> And finally, DocBook
	  has an extensive set of tags (over 300 in all) which is
	  very useful when you are trying to describe the content
	  of a document.  (Fortunately for new authors the majority
	  of them do not need to be used for simple documentation.)
	  </para></listitem> </itemizedlist>

	  <para>Still not convinced? Eric
	  Raymond has written a <ulink
	  url="http://en.tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-Demystification-HOWTO/">DocBook
	  Demystification HOWTO</ulink> which may help.  </para>

	  <para>
			Convinced, but still not comfortable with the thought of
			working with DocBook? Give David Lawyer's <ulink
			url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Howtos-with-LinuxDoc.html">Howtos-with-LinuxDoc-mini-HOWTO</ulink>
			a try.
	  </para>

    </section>

  <section id="docbookxml">
    <title>Why XML?</title> <para>
      While tools for writing XML are not as developed as those
      for SGML, there are a few reasons why you may want to start
      writing in XML:
    </para>

    <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
	  <listitem>
		<para>
		  It's the format preferred by The LDP.
		</para>
	  </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Libraries for handling XML files are developing at a
	  rapid pace.  These utilities may make it easier for new
	  authoring tools to become available.
	</para>
      </listitem> <listitem>
	<para>
	  Many popular word processing programs are now creating
	  XML output.  While it may not be DocBook XML, this does
	  make it easier for application writers to either add
	  DocBook XML support, or provide some method of translating
	  between their format and DocBook XML.
	</para>
      </listitem> <listitem>
	<para>
	  Everyone else is doing it.  While this might not be a
	  real reason, it allows the LDP to keep up-to-date with
	  similar projects.  Tools, procedures, and issues can be
	  worked out in a common framework.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
		Still not convinced? Fortunately the LDP does
		accept a number of other file formats.	Lists of
		formats that
	 the LDP accepts is listed in <xref linkend="templates"/>
    </para>
  </section>

	 <section id="acceptedversions">
      <title>DocBook Versions</title> 
		&ldp-markup;

		<para>
			For an overview of HOWTO DocBook check out:
				<xref linkend="ref-docbook" />,
				<xref linkend="using-docbook" />,
				and <xref linkend="x2docbook" />
				from this guide.
		</para>
	 
	 </section>
<!--
<section id="doctype">
<title>DocBook Documents: Inserting a DOCTYPE</title>

      <para>When writing your DocBook header, it should look like
      this:</para> 

<screen>
<sgmltag class="starttag">!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"</sgmltag> 
</screen>

<section id="html2db">
	<title>HTML to DocBook</title>
	<para>
		If your document is already written in HTML, you may want to try
		<application>html2db</application> to convert your document.
		More information is available from <ulink
		url="http://www.cise.ufl.edu/~ppadala/tidy/" />.
	</para>
</section>
-->

</chapter>
