<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Authoring TLDP Documents: An Introduction</title>

<!-- 
	This comment can be deleted after an appropriate amount of time.
	Section 2.1 The LDP
	Moved this back into Chapter One - About this guide

	Section 2.2, 2.3, 2.4 DocBook and XML
	Moved this to two other sections: Markup and one of the
	Appendices on Converting Documents to DocBook XML.
-->

	<section id="newauthors">
	<title>Contributing to The LDP</title>
	 <para>So you want to help out but you are not sure where to start? Here
	 are a few suggestions to help get you on your way:
	 </para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Join the discuss mailing list (more in <xref
		linkend="mailinglists"/>). You can introduce yourself with a message
		about yourself including the topics you are interested in writing
		about. Please scan through the list of <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/HOWTO-INDEX/howtos.html">existing documents</ulink>, 
		<ulink url="http://tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">documents in
		progress</ulink> and <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained
		documents</ulink> before you post. While the members of the
		discuss list will have ideas on how you can contribute, it is good
		to have your own ideas as well.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Check the <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained
		HOWTOs</ulink> and see if there is a subject that you know about and
		can continue documenting.</para>
		
		<para>If you think the subject is out of date and no longer
		important to the Linux community, please email the discuss list and
		explain why you think the document should be marked as
		<quote>obsolete.</quote> Include the title of the document, and the
		URL as part of your post to the discussion list.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Email an author who is working on a subject comparable to the one
		you would like to write about. Ask if they would like help with
		their document--perhaps there is an additional section that you
		could contribute to an existing document? Or a new feature that is
		available for the latest kernel?
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	</section>

<section id="process">
<title>Summary of The LDP Process</title>
<para>
	The following section outlines the process of creating and/or
	maintaining a document for the Linux Documentation Project. This
	section includes all steps--some of which may not be relevant to your
	specific document.
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
	The first thing all new authors should do is join the discussion
	mailing list at <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">http://lists.tldp.org</ulink>.
	Authors who are interested in taking over the maintenance of someone
	else's document should also join this list. 
   This is to make sure the LDP knows who is working on what documentation.
	For more information about the mailing lists, please read <xref
	linkend="mailinglists" />.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
	Email the discuss mailing list. Briefly introduce yourself and the topic you
	plan to write about. For more information about writing proposals,
	please read <xref linkend="propose" />
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
	Write your document. You may choose whatever format you feel most
	comfortable in. If it is not one of the formats accepted by the LDP a
	volunteer will convert it for you. For more information on writing
	technical documentation, please read <xref linkend="write" />.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
	If you are adding your own markup, you may also want to join the
	docbook mailing list.
	For more information about the LDP DocBook list please read 
		<xref linkend="mailinglists"/>.
	If you would like to start with a template, you may find the templates in 
	<xref linkend="templates" /> useful. There is also a general
	introduction to markup in <xref linkend="ag-markup" /> and a section
	full of examples at <xref linkend="using-docbook" />.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
	Submit your document for technical and language reviews. Do this by
	emailing your document to <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. In the
	subject line be sure give the title of the document. In the body of the
	email say that you are ready for the review process. Outline any
	additional reviews your document may have already received. You should
	be assigned a reviewer within the week. The reviews may take an
	additional week each. For more information about this process, please
	read <xref linkend="distribute" />.
</para>
<para>
	If your document is not already in DocBook or LinuxDoc format, a
	reviewer will convert it for you.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
	After applying the comments from your reviewers, you may send your revised version to the
	submit list for final submission. Again, be sure to include the title
	of the document in the subject line. In the body of your email be sure
	to say that your document has already gone through the review process.
	For more information about your final submission to the LDP, please
	read <xref linkend="submission" />
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

      <tip><title>If you don't submit your document in DocBook format</title><para>
			The volunteer adding markup to your document may choose any 
			accepted markup language. The Author Guide, however,
			will refer only to DocBook. If you are submitting plain text or
			some other format, please let the LDP know if you prefer to
			maintain your document in either LinuxDoc or DocBook, which are the accepted formats for end-results.
      </para></tip>

</section>

    <section id="mailinglists">
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>
      <para>You can subscribe to the following mailing lists:</para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>First is <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>, which is the main
      discussion group of the LDP.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Another is the <email>docbook@en.tldp.org</email> list, which is for
      questions about DocBook use including markup and transformations.  If you run into
      trouble with a particular markup tag, you can send your question
      here for answers.</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <para>You can subscribe to either list by sending a request 
	  message to either <email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> or 
	  <email>docbook-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.   The subject of your message should read 
      <quote>subscribe</quote> (no quotes). To
      remove yourself from the list, send an E-mail with the subject of
      <quote>unsubscribe</quote> to
	  <email>discuss-unsubscribe@en.tldp.org</email> or
	  <email>docbook-unsubscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

      <para>
        If you are interested in DocBook beyond the simple markup of your
		  LDP document, you may want to consider joining one of the <ulink
		  url="http://www.oasis-open.org/">OASIS</ulink> DocBook mailing
		  lists. Please see <ulink
		  url="http://docbook.org/mailinglist/index.html">http://docbook.org/mailinglist/index.html</ulink>
		  for more information.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
