<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Authoring TLDP Documents: An Introduction</title>

<!-- 
	This comment can be deleted after an appropriate amount of time.
	Section 2.1 The LDP
	Moved this back into Chapter One - About this guide

	Section 2.2, 2.3, 2.4 DocBook and XML
	Moved this to two other sections: Markup and one of the
	Appendices on Converting Documents to DocBook XML.
-->

	<section id="newauthors">
	<title>Contributing to The LDP</title>
	 <para>So you want to help out but you are not sure where to start? Here
	 are a few suggestions to help get you on your way:
	 </para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Find something you would like to write about, and start writing!
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Check the <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained
		HOWTOs</ulink> and see if there is a subject that you know about and
		can continue documenting.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Join the discuss mailing list (more in <xref
		linkend="mailinglists"/>), and post a message about yourself,
		including the subject that you would like to write about.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Email a volunteer who is working on a subject comparable to the one you would like to write about. 
		Visit the
		<ulink url="http://tldp.org/vlist.html">Volunteer and 
		Contacts</ulink> page on the LDP web site for a list of volunteers.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
		Email <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email> and let them know you would 
		like to help.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	</section>

    <section id="process">
      <title>Summary of The LDP Process</title>
      <para>If you are new to the LDP and want to pick up an
      unmaintained document or write a new one, join the discussion
      mailing list at
      <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">http://lists.tldp.org</ulink>.
      This is to make sure the LDP knows who is working on what
      documentation.</para> 
      
	  <para>Once that part is complete, you may write your
      documentation <emphasis>in the format of your
		choice</emphasis> and submit a draft to
      <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. The draft will
      be reviewed by an LDP volunteer. In a few short days you will
      get the draft and comments from the volunteer.  After applying
      the comments, you may send this version to the submit list
      again for final submission into the LDP. Review criteria are available
	  in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">LDP Reviewer 
	  HOWTO</ulink>. You should read the LDP  Reviewer HOWTO
	 yourself before
	  submitting your documentation. (Don't worry, the Reviewer HOWTO pretty short
	  compared to this guide.)</para> 

      <note><title>Review Types</title>
        <para>
          Reviewers:  Please consult the <ulink
		  url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">LDP Reviewer HOWTO</ulink> for 
		  information about each of the different types of reviews.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>  <!--please check these changes for correctness!-->
		At this point, if you wrote your document in another format, an LDP volunteer will translate 
      it into some form of markup language.  The markup language format
		that is currently preferred is Docbook XML, see <xref linkend="ag-markup" />. Your reviewer will send the finished document to you.  In this guide, we assume the return format is Docbook XML.  All subsequent revisions of your document to the LDP
		must be in the same format.  If you have markup questions, you may ask the
      volunteer who assisted you, or ask the LDP DocBook list. For
		more information about the LDP DocBook list please read 
		<xref linkend="mailinglists"/>.
	</para>

      <tip><title>If you don't submit your document in DocBook format</title><para>
			The volunteer adding markup to your document may choose any 
			accepted markup language. The Author Guide, however,
			will refer only to DocBook. If you are submitting plain text or
			some other format, please let the LDP know if you prefer to
			maintain your document in either LinuxDoc or DocBook, which are the accepted formats for end-results.
      </para></tip>  <!--end of stuff needing check-->

	<para>
		Of course, you can also do the markup to your initial document
		yourself, but remember that it is not required. There are lots of
		templates to get you started in <xref linkend="templates" />.
	</para>

    </section>

    <section id="mailinglists">
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>
      <para>You can subscirbe to the following mailing lists:</para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>First is <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>, which is the main
      discussion group of the LDP.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Another is the <email>docbook@en.tldp.org</email> list, which is for
      questions about DocBook use including markup and transformations.  If you run into
      trouble with a particular markup tag, you can send your question
      here for answers.</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <para>You can subscribe to either list by sending a request 
	  message to either <email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> or 
	  <email>docbook-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.   The subject of your message should read 
      <quote>subscribe</quote> (no quotes). To
      remove yourself from the list, send an E-mail with the subject of
      <quote>unsubscribe</quote> to
	  <email>discuss-unsubscribe@en.tldp.org</email> or
	  <email>docbook-unsubscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

      <para>
        If you are interested in DocBook beyond the simple markup of your
		  LDP document, you may want to consider joining one of the <ulink
		  url="http://www.oasis-open.org/">OASIS</ulink> DocBook mailing
		  lists. Please see <ulink
		  url="http://docbook.org/mailinglist/index.html">http://docbook.org/mailinglist/index.html</ulink>
		  for more information.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
