<!-- 
        <!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
	$Id$
-->		  

<chapter id="propose">
<title>Writing Your Proposal</title>

<section id="sg-subject">
<title>Choosing a Subject</title>

<para>
	It is likely that if you are reading the Author Guide, you already have a
	subject in mind. The idea may have come from your own frustrations in
	trying to get something to work; or maybe you are already writing or
	have written documentation for other purposes and you want to submit
	it to the LDP. 
	For example, if you posted a question to a mailing list
	and it took many posts to resolve the problem -- that might be an incentive to write documentation. 
</para>	
<para>
	Regardless of how you picked your subject, it is important that the LDP
	community understand why your documentation should be included in its
	collection. If someone has requested documentation, or you worked
	with a mailing list to resolve a problem you should include the details in
	your proposal to the LDP discuss mailing list. It may help others to
	understand the need for your specific document.
</para>
</section>

<section id="scope">
<title>Scope of Your Document</title>
<para>
	Now that you've got a subject, you will need to decide the
	<emphasis>scope</emphasis> of the document. The scope or subject area
	should be:
</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>          
            <title>Clearly defined.</title>

            <para>
              Define the boundaries of your
              subject area before you begin. Do not repeat information that is in
				  another HOWTO and do not leave gaps of information between
				  your HOWTO and someone else's HOWTO.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        
		<listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Not too broad, and not too narrow.</title>
              <para>
                If you try to cover too much information you may sacrifice depth. 
				It is better to cover a small subject area in detail than to cover a large subject
                area poorly. Linux tools are known for doing exactly one
                thing and doing that one thing <emphasis>well</emphasis>. 
                Similarly, your HOWTO should cover one subject and cover it
                <emphasis>well</emphasis>.
              </para>
          </formalpara>

          <para>
			 	If the scope of your proposed document is very narrow, it might be better to
				include your information as part of another HOWTO.
            This makes it easier for readers to find the HOWTO they need. 
				Search the LDP repository for topics which relate to your
				document. If you find a document which is a good match, email the author
				and ask them if they would like to include your contribution.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Undocumented.</title>
            
            <para>
              Before documenting a particular subject, always do a web
				  search (and specifically a search within the LDP documents)
				  to see if your topic is already covered in another
				  document. If it is, refer to the other document instead of
				  duplicating the information within your own document. You
				  may wish to include a brief summary of information that
				  can be found in other documents. 
            </para>
          </formalpara>
      
          <para>
            If the HOWTO already in place is insufficient or needs updating, 
            contact the author and offer to help.  See also <xref linkend="unmaintained" /> for taking over old or unmaintained documents.</para> 

		<para>
	    Most authors appreciate any help offered.  Additionally, sending
		 comments and remarks to the author is usually regarded both as a
		 reassurance and a reward: to the author, feedback is the ultimate proof that writing the documentation was not a pointless effort.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Pre-approved by the LDP.</title>
            
            <para>
              Before you proceed with your HOWTO, post to the discuss list
              and get some feedback from other LDP volunteers. Checking with the
              list <emphasis>before</emphasis> you begin can save you headaches
              <emphasis>later</emphasis>.
            </para>
          
		  </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

<note><title>Stay in touch!</title><para>
 	Joining the discuss list and following
    it regularly, even if you never post, is a good way to stay current
    on the activities, needs and policies of the LDP.
</para></note>

<section id="typesofdocs">
<!-- Sub-Section added by EJH: August 12, 2003 -->
	<title>Documentation Templates</title>
	<para>
	After you've decided the scope of your document you
	should start to consider the type of document that you will write. There are
	a number of different LDP documentation templates:
	Guides, HOWTOs, man pages and FAQs. Rahul Sundaram
	describes their scope in the <ulink
	url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/LDP-FAQ/index.html">Linux Documentation
	Project (LDP) FAQ</ulink>. Here is a brief overview of what they are
	with pointers on how you can get started writing your own:	
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
		<formalpara>
		<title>Guides</title>
		<para>A guide covers a broad subject and is quite long. The Author
		Guide (this document) is a guide. Other guides include: 
		<ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/index.html">Introduction to Linux: A hands on
		guide</ulink>,
		<ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/index.html">The Linux Kernel
		Module Programming Guide</ulink>, etc. A full list of guides is
		available from: <ulink url="http://tldp.org/guides.html">Linux Project 
		Documentation Guides</ulink>. Guides use the <quote>book</quote>
		templates located in <xref linkend="templates"/>.
		</para>
		</formalpara>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
		<formalpara>
		<title>HOWTOs</title>
		<para>A HOWTO is typically a set of instructions that outlines,
		step-by-step, how a specific task is accomplished. Examples of
		HOWTOs are: 
			<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/CDROM-HOWTO/index.html">CDROM-HOWTO</ulink>
			<ulink
			url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Module-HOWTO/index.html">Module-HOWTO</ulink>.
		A full list of HOWTOs is available from: <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/HOWTO-INDEX/howtos.html">Single List of
		HOWTOs</ulink> (warning: it's a BIG page). HOWTOs typically use the
		<quote>article</quote> template and are output to multiple HTML
		pages by default.
		Templates are available in <xref linkend="templates"/>.
		</para>
		</formalpara>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
		<formalpara>
		<title>man pages</title>
		<para>man (Manual) pages are the standard form of help available for many
		linux applications and utilities. They can be viewed by typing
		<command>man applicationname</command> at a prompt. A full list of man
		pages is available from: 
		<ulink url="http://tldp.org/docs.html#man">Linux Man Pages</ulink>.
		Since man pages are bundled with software there is no LDP template
		at this time.</para>
		</formalpara>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
		<formalpara>
		<title>FAQs</title>
		<para>FAQs (Frequently Asked Questions) are a list of questions and
		answers to help prevent new users from asking the same questions
		over and over again.
		A full list of FAQs is available from: <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/">Linux Documentation Project
		FAQs</ulink>. FAQs typically use the <quote>article</quote>
		template with some specific DocBook elements to form the
		Question/Answer structure.
		You can find a template for writing a FAQ in <xref linkend="templates" />.
		</para>
		</formalpara>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note><title>mini-HOWTOs and HOWTOs</title><para>
		The LDP no longer distinguishes between HOWTOs and mini-HOWTOs. All
		previously written mini-HOWTOs have been included in longer HOWTOs.
		All new documents must be at least HOWTO in length.  This means the
		documents should cover a bigger subject area rather than a small one. If
		your document is very small you may wish to submit it for inclusion
		in another, larger HOWTO that already exists. If you're not sure
		what size your document is, email the discuss list and ask for
		feedback.
	</para></note>
	
</section> <!-- end of types of docs -->
</section> <!-- end of choosing a subject -->

<section id="unmaintained">
<title>Unmaintained and Out-of-date Documents</title>

<para>
  If you wish to become the <quote>owner</quote> for an unmaintained document there are
  several steps you must go through.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	   Contact the author. Make sure the author no longer 
wishes to maintain the document in question. Note that the E-mail address 
shown may no longer be valid. In that case, try a <ulink
url="http://google.com">search</ulink> for the 
author. If the original author of a document cannot be found after a <quote>good-faith</quote> effort, 
let us know (<email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>--<ulink
url="http://tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">subscription
required</ulink>).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
      Determine if a more up-to-date copy of the document exists, outside
of what is available on the LDP. If so, try to secure a copy for yourself
to work on.
   	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
      Inform the LDP which document you would like to maintain, so that we can
track who is working on what and prevent duplication of effort. We also
suggest that you join the LDP general discussion list
(<email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>). This step is also required for new
documents.
	</para></listitem>   

    <listitem><para> 
	Submit the document to the LDP with any intended modifications. Make
sure to continue to reference the original author somewhere within the
document (Credits, Revision History, etc.). Once the document is
re-submitted, we will remove the entry from the list of unmaintained
documents.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<note><title>Feedback wanted</title><para>Some of unmaintained documents may be outdated, or the content may be
covered in another (actively maintained) HOWTO. If that is the situation,
contact us (preferably on the discuss mailing list) and let us know.</para></note>
	
</section>
  
<section id="sg-outline">
    <title>Developing an Outline</title>
    
    <para>
      Before you actually begin writing, prepare an outline.
      An outline will help you to get a clear picture of the subject matter
      and allow you to concentrate on one small part of the HOWTO
      at a time.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Unless your HOWTO is exceptionally small, your outline will probably
      be multilevel.
      When developing a multilevel outline, the top level should contain general
      subject areas, and sub-headings should be more detailed and specific.
      Look at each level of your outline independently,
      and make sure it covers all key areas of the subject matter. Sub-headings
      should cover all key areas of the heading under which they fall.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Each item in your outline should follow the item before it,
      and lead into the item that comes next. For example, a HOWTO about a particular
      program shouldn't have a section on <emphasis>configuration</emphasis>
      before one on <emphasis>installation</emphasis>.</para>
	  
	  <para>You may choose to use the following outline for a HOWTO about
	  using a specific program:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>development history</para></listitem>
		
	  <listitem><para>where to download the software from</para></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><para>how to install the software</para></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><para>how to configure the software</para></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem><para>how to use the software</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
	
	<para>You may find it helpful to try a little <quote>card
	sorting</quote> at this stage of the writing process. Write all of your mini
	subject areas onto pieces of paper. Now sort these pieces of paper into
	main headings and their sub-sections. It may help to shuffle the slips of
	paper before you start. This will help to give you a fresh set of eyes
	while working.
	</para>
	
    <para>
      When you are comfortable with your outline, look it over once more,
      with a critical eye. Have you covered every relevant topic in
      sufficient detail? Have you not wandered beyond the scope of the document?
      It is a good idea to show your outline to others (including The LDP
	  discuss list) to get some feedback.
      Remember: it is much easier to reorganize your document at the outline stage 
	  than doing this after writing it. 
    </para>
    
	<tip><title>Writing a HOWTO made easy</title>
		<para>
		For help writing your HOWTO outline, and getting a head start on
		the markup of your document, check out <ulink
		url="http://www.nyx.net/~sgjoen/The_LDP_HOWTO_Generator.html">The LDP HOWTO
		Generator</ulink>.  Note that this is for generating HOWTOs.  Templates for FAQs and Guides are available in <xref linkend="templates" />.
	</para></tip>
	 
    <note><title>You're not alone</title>
      <para>
        You might have noticed a theme developing here.
        Just like Free software, Free documentation is best when you
        <quote>release early, release often.</quote> The discuss list includes
        many experienced LDP authors, and you would be wise to seek their
        advice when making decisions about your contribution.
      </para>
    </note>
</section>

<section id="research">
<!-- Section added by EJH: August 12, 2003 -->
<title>Research</title>
	<para>
	  While you are working on your outline you will most likely research 
	  your topic--especially to confirm the document you are about to 
	  write does not yet exist! Here are a few pointers that will keep
	  you from pulling out your hair later:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
			<title>Compile your resources as you research.</title>
			<para>It is almost guaranteed you will not remember where to
			find a critical piece of information when you need it most. It
			will help to bookmark important (and even not so important)
			pages as you go. Make sure the bookmark's title reflects why the
			page is important to you.
			If there are multiple key ideas in one page, you may want to bookmark the
			same page with different titles.</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
			<title>Assume your most important resource will disappear.</title>
			<para>The dreaded <quote>Error 404: Page not found</quote>. Even if you have
			bookmarked a page it may not be there when you return to it. If
			a page contains a really critical piece of information: make a
			copy. You may do this by creating a text file with the title of 
			the document, the author's name, the page's URL and the text of 
			the page into a text file on your computer. You might also
			choose to <quote>print</quote> the file to a PDF (save as or convert to PDF format will
			capture the original URL on the page if you're using a smart
			browser).</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
			<title>Start your <quote>Resources</quote> page now.</title>
			<para>As you find pages of interest add them to a Resources
			document. You may do this by exporting your bookmarks or by
			keeping a separate text file with the Resources sorted by
			sub-category. A little effort now will save you a lot of time
			later.</para>
			</formalpara>

			<para>
				There is more information about the DocBook markup of
				bibliographies in <xref linkend="doc-bib" />.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
			<title>Write down subject areas as you go.</title>
			<para>If you are card sorting you may find it particularly
			useful to write topic cards as you find pages that cover that
			specific topic. At the top of the card write the subject area.
			In the main area of the card write a few notes about what you
			might cover under this topic--include the titles of pages that
			contain important information. If a sub-topic gets too big you
			may want to divide it into multiple cards.</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
			<title>Separate generic information from version-specific
			information.</title>
			<para>A new version of the software that you describe might be released the day after you release your document.
			Other things, like where to download
			the software, won't change. Alternatively, you may 
			choose to document old problems with specific software as a way
			of encouraging readers to upgrade to the latest version available:
			<quote>Version X of the software is known for a specific bug.
			The bug was fixed as of Version Y.</quote>
			</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
	
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
			<title>Save all related emails.</title>
			<para>People will often have interesting insight into the
			problem that you are writing about. Any questions that are asked
			about your topic should be addressed in the final document. If
			you are writing about software make sure to ask people what
			system they are using. Add information in your document about
			which system configurations your instructions have been tested
			on. (Having lots of friends with moderately different
			configurations can be very beneficial!)
			All of these personal experiences can add
			greatly to your final documentation.</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</section>
</chapter>
