<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->

<section id="submission">
	<title>Submission to LDP</title>
      <para> Once your LDP document has been carefully reviewed, you
      can release your document to the LDP. Send an e-mail with the
      source code as an attachment (you may gzip it if you like)
      to <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. </para>

		<tip><para>
			For more information on what the reviewers will be looking
			for, please read the <ulink
			url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/index.html">Linux Documentation Project Reviewer
			HOWTO</ulink>. 
		</para></tip>

      <para> Be sure to include the name of your HOWTO in the subject
      line, and use the body to outline changes you've made and attach
      your HOWTO. This allows the maintainers to do their jobs faster, and
		means your revised HOWTO will appear on the site faster.
      If you haven't heard anything in 5 calendar days,
      please follow up with an e-mail to make sure things are still in
      process. </para> 

      <para>If your HOWTO contains extras, such as graphics or a
      special catalog, create a .tar.gz file with all the files in it
      including the .xml source code and mail it as an attachment to
      the submit list.</para>

      <para>If you are using the LDP CVS tree while developing
      your document, the LDP will still need to be notified when your
      document is ready to be published. E-mail should be sent to
      <email>submit@en.tldp.org</email>. Indicate
      the title of your document and the relative path to the
      file(s) in the LDP CVS tree within your message. </para>

		<para> To get a CVS account please refer to: <ulink
		url="http://tldp.org/cvs/">http://tldp.org/cvs/</ulink>
		</para>
    </section>

	 <section id="compilations">
	 <title>Publishing Compilations of LDP Documents</title>
    <para>
		If you are interested in publishing a collection of
		LDP documents, please visit <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html#pub">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html#pub</ulink>
		for more information.
	</para>
	</section>
