<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<chapter id="write">
<title>Write</title>

  <section id="sg-writingstyle">
    <title>Writing the Text</title>
    
    <para>
      By now you should have organized your document; you collected bits of raw information
      and inserted them into the outline.
      Your next challenge is to massage all of the raw data you've collected 
	  into a readable, entertaining and understandable whole. If you are
	  working from an existing document make sure any new pieces of
	  information are in the best possible places.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      It has taken quite a bit of work to get to the point where you can
      actually start writing, hasn't it? Well, the hard work begins to pay
      off for you now. At this stage, you can begin to really use your
      imagination and creativity to communicate this heap of information. 
		Don't be too clever though! Your readers are already struggling with 
		new concepts--do not make them struggle to understand your language
		as well.
    </para>

	<para>
	  There are a number of classic guides to writing--many
	  of which are available on-line. 
	  Their language will
	  seem old, but the messages are still valuable to authors today.
	  These are listed in <xref linkend="ref-techwriting" />. Also listed in the
	  resources section are a variety of sites that have 
	  information specific to technical writing.
	</para> 
	
	<para>
	  The Author Guide wouldn't be complete without
	  mentioning the Plain Language movement. Although
	  directed at simplifying government documents, <ulink
	  url="http://www.blm.gov/nhp/NPR/pe_toc.html">Writing user-friendly
	  documents</ulink> is quite useful. It includes before and after
	  writing samples. There's also a 
	  	<ulink
	  url="http://www.web.net/~plain/PlainTrain/IntroducingPlainLanguage.html">PlainTrain 
	  writing tutorial</ulink>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  And any document that discusses writing for the web wouldn't be complete without
	  a nod toward <ulink url="http://www.useit.com">useit.com</ulink>.
	  The following articles may be of specific interest:
	  <itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.useit.com/papers/webwriting/">Writing for the Web</ulink></para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><ulink url="http://useit.com/alertbox/20030811.html">Information pollution</ulink></para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><ulink url="http://useit.com/alertbox/9703b.html">Be Succinct! (Writing for the Web)</ulink></para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  There are many, many resources for writing web
	  documents--a quick web search for <quote>web
	  writing</quote> will find lots of resources. 
	  Don't get too distracted, though: the ultimate goal is to
	  write, not to read about writing!
	</para>

	<section id="writing-style">
	<!-- Section Added by ejh: August 12, 2003 -->
    <title>Writing Style and Style Guides</title>
	<para>
	  There are a number of industry style guides which define how language
	  should be used in documents. A common example for American English is
	  the <ulink
	  url="http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/">Chicago Manual
	  of Style</ulink>. It defines things like: whether a period (.) should be inside or
	  outside of <quote>quotes</quote>; and the format for citing 
	  another document. A style guide helps to keep documents
	  consistent--most corporations will follow a style guide to 
	  format media releases and other promotional material. 
	  Style guides mays also define how words should be spelled 
	  (is it color or colour?).
	</para>
	<para>
	  The LDP does not require a specific style
	  guide; however, you should use a consistent style throughout your
	  document. Your document should be spell checked for a single
	  language (e.g. American English vs. British English).
	  The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">Reviewer's HOWTO</ulink> currently lists a number of
	  conventions for LDP documents and it is as close as it
	  gets to an official LDP Style Guide.
	</para>

<tip><title>A personal glossary</title>
<para>It helps to make a list of terms that you were new to you when you
first started researching and writing your document. You can refer to this
list while writing the text. You may also want to include it as a glossary in
your final document.
</para></tip>

	<para>
	  You can save yourself a lot of time in the editing phase if you
	  decide how you will write your document ahead of time. If you are
	  taking over someone else's document you may need to either: modify
	  your own style to fit the current document; or edit the
	  document so that it melds with the style you would like to
	  use from now on.
	</para>

    <para>
      From a writing style perspective, use of the
	  first-person in a HOWTO adds to its charm--an attribute most 
	  other documentation sorely lacks. Don't be afraid 
	  to speak for yourself--use the word <quote>I</quote> to 
	  describe your personal experiences and opinions.
    </para>
	</section>
   
    <section id="writing-resources">
	<title>On-line Writing Resources</title>

	<para>
      In the <xref linkend="ref-techwriting" />
      section, you will find a list of resources that cover the subject
      better than this guide could hope to. Consult them, and follow their
      advice.
    </para>
	</section> <!-- writing-resources -->
  </section> <!-- sg-writingstyle -->
  
  <section id="sg-editing">
    <title>Edit and Proofread the Text</title>
    
    <para>
      Once you've written the text of your HOWTO, it is time 
	  to polish and refine it. Good editing can make the 
	  difference between a good HOWTO and a great one.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      One of the goals of editing is to remove <emphasis>[extraneous]</emphasis> material that
      has crept its way into your document.
      You should go through your HOWTO carefully, and ruthlessly
      delete anything that does not contribute to the reader's understanding
      of the subject matter. It is natural for writers to go off on tangents
      while in the process of writing. Now is the time to correct that. It
	  often helps to leave a bit of time between when you write a document
	  and when you edit it.
    </para>

	<para>
	  Make sure that the content of every section matches the title
	  precisely. It's possible that your original subject heading
	  is no longer relevant. If you've strayed from your original heading
	  it could mean one of the following: the original title was poorly
	  worded, the new material should actually go in a different section,
	  or the new material is not really necessary for your document. If you
	  need to change a title, check to see if the original subject heading 
	  is still important. If it is, make sure that topic is covered somewhere
	  else in the document.
	</para>
    
    <para>
      When editing and proofing your work, check for obvious mistakes, 
      such as spelling errors and typos. You should also check for deeper, but
      less obvious errors as well, such as <quote>holes</quote> in the
      information. If you are creating a set of instructions it may
	  help to test them on a new machine. Sometimes there
	  are packages that need to be installed which you've forgotten to
	  mention in your documentation, for instance.
	</para> 
	
	<para>
      When you are completely satisfied with the quality and accuracy of
      your work, forward it to someone else for third-party proofing.
      You will be too close to the work to see fundamental flaws.
	  Have others test the instructions as
	  well. Make sure they follow exactly what you have written. Ask anyone
	  who tests your documentation to make specific notes in any places
	  where they didn't follow your instructions (and the reason why they
	  didn't follow them). For example: <quote>I skipped step 2 because I
	  already have the required packages installed.</quote>
    </para>
    
    <para>
      In a sense, editing is like code review in software development.
      Having a programmer review their own code doesn't make much sense,
	  and neither does having a writer edit their own document.
      Recruit a friend, or write the discuss list 
	  to find a volunteer to proofread before submitting your document. You
	  may also want to submit your document to a mailing list that is
	  relevant to your document's topic. List members should be able to
	  help check the facts, clarity of your instructions and language of 
	  the document.
    </para>

    <note><title>Native speaker?</title>
      <para>
        If you are writing in a language in which you are not fluent,
        find an editor who is. Technical
        documentation, more than any other type of writing, must use
        extremely precise grammar and vocabulary. Misuse of language
		makes your document less valuable.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="tools-writing">
  <title>Tools for Writing, Editing and Maintaining your Document</title>
  <caution><title>Reminder</title><para>
  You do <emphasis>not</emphasis> need to submit your
  initial document to the LDP in anything more than plain text!  Other open 
  submission formats are accepted as well, for instance OpenOffice documents, 
  RTF files or HTML.  The LDP volunteers will convert your document to DocBook 
  for you. Once it has been converted you will need to maintain your document 
  in DocBook format, but that should be obvious.
  </para></caution>

  <section id="ag-edittools">
  <title>Editing Tools</title>
  <para>
  	You may use any word processing or text editing tool to write your
	initial document. When you get to the markup stage you may want to use
	a text editor which recognizes DocBook files. At a minimum a program
	which adds syntax highlighting to your markup will make life a lot
	easier. For a description of editors which can handle DocBook files
	please skip to <xref linkend="tools-edit" />.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section id="cvs-brief">
  <title>Concurrent Versions System (CVS)</title>
	&cvs-why;

	 <para>
	 	For more information on how to use CVS to maintain your LDP
		documents, please read <xref linkend="cvs" />.
	 </para>
  </section> <!-- cvs -->
  
  <section id="ag-spellcheck">
      <title>Spell Check</title>

		<para>
			Some writing tools will come with their own built-in spell
			check tools. This list is only if your application does not
			have a spell check option. 
		</para>

		<variablelist>
		<title>Spell Check Software</title>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>
			<application>aspell</application>
			<ulink url="http://aspell.sourceforge.net" />
		</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
        This spell check application can work around XML tags. By
		distinguishing between content and markup aspell is able to check
		your content and ignore the bits it shouldn't be looking at. If you
		are getting spelling errors in your markup tags you may be using an
		old version and should upgrade.
		</para>
		<para>The <command>aspell</command> command comes with the <application>aspell</application> package, included on most Linux distributions.  Use the command as follows:</para>
<cmdsynopsis><command>aspell <option>-c</option> <filename>file</filename></command></cmdsynopsis>
<para>An interactive user interface allows for fast and easy correction of errors.  Use the <option>--help</option> to read more about <command>aspell</command> features.</para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	
		<varlistentry>
		<term>
			<application>ispell</application>
			 <ulink url="http://www.cs.hmc.edu/~geoff/ispell.html" />	
		</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			Similar to <application>aspell</application>, but tries to spell
			check your markup tags. If you have a choice, use
			<application>aspell</application>, if not,
			<application>ispell</application> is a very acceptable substitute.
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section> <!-- end of spell check -->


  </section> <!-- end writing-tools -->
</chapter>
