<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->

    <para>
	 	The LDP provides optional CVS access to its authors. This enables
		collaborative writing and has the following positive effects:
    </para>

    <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
      <listitem>
        <para> CVS will keep an off-site backup of your documents. In
        the event that you hand over a document to another author,
        they can just retrieve the document from CVS and continue
        on. In the event you need to go back to a previous version of
        a document, you can retrieve it as well.  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>However difficult from an organizational point of view, it's great to have multiple people working on the same
        document.  CVS enables you to do this. You can have CVS tell you what changes were made by another author 
        while you were editing your copy, and
        integrate those changes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CVS keeps a log of what changes were made. These logs (and
        a date stamp) can be placed automatically inside your documents
		  when they are published.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> CVS can be combined with scripts to automatically
      update the LDP web site with new documentation as it's written
      and submitted. This is not in place yet, but it is a goal. 
		Currently, CVS updates signal the HOWTO coordinator to
      update the LDP web page, meaning that if you use CVS, you're not
      required to e-mail your XML code. (Although you do
      still need to send the submit list an email when you
      are ready for your document to be published, because the whole publishing process has not been fully automated yet.) </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

<note><title>Access to our CVS repository</title>
<para>Only authors with at least three submissions get access to our CVS, see <xref linkend="cvs" />.</para>
</note>
