  <section id="cvs">
    <title> CVS </title>
    <para> 
      The LDP is providing CVS access to authors. There are a few
      good reasons for this:
    </para> 

    <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
      <listitem>
        <para> CVS will keep an off-site backup of your documents. In
        the event that you hand over a document to another author,
        they can just retrieve the document from CVS and continue
        on. In the event you need to go back to a previous version of
        a document, you can retrieve it as well.  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> It's great to have many people working on the same
        document. You can have CVS tell you what changes were made
        while you were editing your copy by another author, and
        integrate those changes in.  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CVS keeps a log of what changes were made. These logs (and
        a date stamp) can be placed automatically inside the document
        when you use some special tags that get processed before the
        SGML processor.  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> It can provide for a way for a program to automatically
      update the LDP web site with new documentation as it's written
      and submitted. This is not in place yet, but it is a potential
      goal. Currently, CVS updates signal the HOWTO coordinator to
      update the LDP web page, meaning that if you use CVS, you're not
      required to e-mail your SGML code. </para> 
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para> If you're completely new to CVS, there are a few web pages
    you may want to look at which can help you out: </para> 

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> <ulink
        url="http://www.sourcegear.com/CVS/Docs/blandy">http://www.sourcegear.com/CVS/Docs/blandy</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> <ulink
        url="http://www.loria.fr/~molli/cvs/doc/cvs_toc.html">http://www.loria.fr/~molli/cvs/doc/cvs_toc.html</ulink></para> 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="getaccount">
      <title> Getting a CVS account </title>
      <para> First you'll need to get an account at the LDP's CVS
      Repository. This is pretty much the root directory that is used
      by CVS, with various projects (HOWTOs, mini HOWTOs, etc.)
      created as subdirectories of it. </para> 
      <para> You will need to create a hashed password and userid for
      your account. The hashed password allows you to send an
      encrypted password to the CVS group without them needing to know
      your password. You can do this with the following command, from
      bash (or sh): </para> 

      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>echo your_password | perl -e "print crypt(&lt;&gt;,\
join '',('.', '/', 0..9, 'A'..'Z', 'a'..'z')[rand 64, rand 64]),\"\n\""</command>
</screen>

      <para>Take the output of this command, and send it with your
      proposed userid to
      <email>pld-cvs@pld.org.pl</email>. Your unique
      CVSROOT directory will be created and you'll get an e-mail with
      a response. When you get your response, log into your CVSROOT
      and make sure everything is set up properly: </para> 

      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>export CVSROOT=:pserver:<replaceable>your_userid</replaceable>@cvs.linuxdoc.org:/cvsroot</command>
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>cvs -d $CVSROOT login</command>
</screen>

      <para> (Replace the <replaceable>your_userid</replaceable> with what
      you were sent in the response e-mail). </para> 
      <para> You will be asked for your password, and then be given
      access to the CVS Repository in read-write mode. Once you've
      used <command moreinfo="none">cvs login</command> once and have
      been given access to the system, your password is stored in
      <filename moreinfo="none">.cvspass</filename> and you will not
      have to use <command moreinfo="none">cvs login</command>
      again. Just set the CVSROOT and continue on. You can get the
      entire repository with this command:  </para> 

      <screen>
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>cvs get LDP</command>
</screen>

      <para> Or you can get the SGML source for your own document with
      these commands: </para> 

      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>cvs get LDP/howto/docbook/YOUR-HOWTO.sgml</command>
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>cvs get
guide/docbook/YOURGUIDE</command> 
</screen>
    </section>

    <section id="othercvsnotes">
      <title> Other CVS repository notes </title>

      <section id="anoncvs">
        <title> Anonymous CVS access </title>
        <para> Anonymous CVS access is available for those who do not
        require an account (such as those wishing to publish LDP
        documents). This repository is read-only: </para> 

        <screen>
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>cvs -d :pserver:cvs@anoncvs.linuxdoc.org:/cvsroot login</command>
</screen>

        <para> As a password, use cvs. You can then get LinuxDoc
        modules as above. Note that changes to the anoncvs site may be
        a half an hour behind the main site. </para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="cvsweb">
        <title> CVS Files via web </title>
        <para> You can access the CVS repository via the web at <ulink
        url="http://cvsview.linuxdoc.org/index.cgi/?cvsroot=Linuxdoc">http://cvsview.linuxdoc.org/index.cgi/?cvsroot=Linuxdoc</ulink>.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="cvsgraphics">
        <title> Graphical access to CVS </title>
        <para> There are graphical interfaces to CVS, and you can get
        a list of them at <ulink
        url="http://freshmeat.net/appindex">http://freshmeat.net/appindex</ulink>.
        Search for CVS. </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="commoncvscommands">
      <title>Common CVS Commands</title>

      <section id="updatingcvs">
        <title>Updating files and CVS </title>
        <para> CVS has a special tag, <emphasis>$Id&dollar;</emphasis>, that you
        can use to automatically insert the date and version directly
        into the document. After committing, CVS will turn this tag into
        <emphasis>$Id$
        </emphasis>. By including this tag in your document, you
        can have that automatically change each time you change the
        file, allowing the revision mark to increment each time. </para> 
        <para> When you're ready to upload changes to the CVS server,
        use the command <command moreinfo="none">cvs ci -m
        &quot;comment&quot; YOUR-HOWTO.sgml</command>. The -m
        &quot;comment&quot; isn't necessary, but if you don't include
        it, you'll be brought into the editor (usually vi, or whatever
        your <envar>EDITOR</envar> environment variable is) and be given
        the chance to add a comment about the changes. </para> 
        <para> You can follow more of the CVS discussion on the
        discuss list. </para>
        <para>If you are using the LDP CVS tree while developing your
        document, the LDP will need to be notified when your
        document is ready to be published. E-mail should be sent to
        <email>submit@linuxdoc.org</email>. Indicate within the message
        the title of your document and the relative path to the
        file(s) in the LDP CVS tree. </para>
      </section>

      <section id="addnewcvs">
        <title>Adding new files</title>
        <para>
          If your document contains graphics or multiple files, you
          may come to a point where you need to add new files to
          your cvs repository.
        </para>
        <para>
          To do this, make sure that your HOWTO is in its own directory.
          You may want to coordinate with the people at
          <email>submit@linuxdoc.org</email> to ensure you can
          add graphics or other files to your HOWTO.
        </para>
        <para>
          Once this is set up, use <command>cvs get</command> to get
          the latest copy of your HOWTO.  In most cases, the command
          will be similar to <command>cvs get LDP/howto/docbook/YOUR-HOWTO/</command>
          assuming that your CVSROOT is set.
        </para>
        <para>
          Copy in the files that you want to add to the repository.
          The command <command>cvs add <replaceable>filename</replaceable></command>
          will tell the CVS server that you want to add
          <replaceable>filename</replaceable> to the repository.
          You can now use <command>cvs commit</command> to commit
          the changes to the CVS server.  When finished, the files
          are now part of the repository.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tagrelease">
        <title>Creating Tag Releases</title>
        <para>
          Occasionally, you may want to create what you call a stable
          release.  This is an effective way to signal to the
          LDP coordinator that your document is ready for release.
          This tag release indicates a specific version of your
          HOWTO.  This allows you to continue creating new versions
          of your HOWTO without them being accidentally put
          on the web site.
        </para>
        <para>
          The downside of creating a stable (or tag) release is that
          it uses the current version of the files - the last
          ones submitted.  Use <command>cvs commit</command> to
          make sure that your files are synced up, then use
          <command>cvs -q tag <replaceable>Release-x_y</replaceable></command>.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can replace the <replaceable>Release-x_y</replaceable> with
          whatever you like.  However, to create a wall between CVS revisions
          and tag releases, the tag release nust start with a letter,
          and contain letters, numbers, hyphens, or underscores.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="recovery">
        <title>Recovering old versions</title>
        <para>
          There you are, typing away, when you screw up.  Real bad.
          Doesn't matter what it is, but suffice it to say that you've
          toasted not only the version on your local drive, but
          created a new version on the CVS server.  What you need
          to do is go back in time and resurrect and older
          version of your file.
        </para>
        <para>
          To do this, you'll need to know the version number of the
          file you want to retrieve. <command>cvs diff</command>
          will give a list of revisions if there are differences.  You
          can pick the revision number, subtract one, and that is
          probably the revision you want to look at.
        </para>
        <para>
          The command <command>cvs -Q update -p -r <replaceable>revision</replaceable></command>
          <replaceable>filename</replaceable> will output to stdout
          the contents of the <replaceable>revision</replaceable> version
          of <replaceable>filename</replaceable>.  You can pipe it to
          <command>more</command> or redirect the output to a file.
          Conveniently, you can redirect stdout to a file called
          <replaceable>filename</replaceable>.  Your local file
          is now the revision you want, and <command>cvs update
          </command> will update the CVS server with the new (old)
          version of <replaceable>filename</replaceable>.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

