    <section id="docbook">
      <title>DocBook</title>
      <para>
        To explain what DocBook is, we must first take a look
        at what SGML and XML are, and their relationship to DocBook.
      </para>
      <para>The Standard Generalized Markup Language (SGML) is a
      way of embedding information about a document
	  into the text of the document. SGML is not a markup language
	  itself, it is a <quote>metalanguage</quote> from which other markup
	  languages are created (e.g. HTML and DocBook). Documents are stored
	  in SGML format using a specific Document Type Definition--a
	  controlled vocabulary. These documents may then be
	  <quote>transformed</quote> into a variety of other types of documents
	  such as PDFs, HTML pages, plain text (etc!). The advantage of using
	  SGML means you can use an automated transformation to convert your
	  document into whatever format you may need.</para>

	  <para>Instead of defining things like colors, font sizes and other specific
	  formatting rules you define the structure of the document. This is
	  done with a series of tags which are wrapped around content. 
	  The controlled vocabulary consists of <quote>elements</quote> which
	  describes what the content is. This block
	  of text, for example, is a paragraph. In DocBook notation I have
	  wrapped the block of text with the start tag &lt;para&gt; and then
	  the end tag &lt;/para&gt;. In HTML, a sub-set of SGML, this would be
	  done with the element &lt;p&gt;. Although there are many similarities
	  between DocBook and HTML, DocBook contains hundreds of elements and
	  is considered a much more descriptive vocabulary.</para>
	  
	  <note><para>Steve
	  Champeon does a great job of explaining this (from an HTML
	  perspective but with an example of DocBook markup) in his article
	  <ulink url="http://hotwired.lycos.com/webmonkey/02/42/index4a.html">The
	  Secret Life of Markup</ulink></para></note>

      <para>There are really three parts to an SGML document:</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
      First there is the content. As a TLDP author it is good to remember
	  that this is the most important piece. Many authors will write the
	  content first and add their markup later. Content may include both
	  plain text and graphics. For more information about writing your
	  content read: FIXME
		</para></listitem>
	  
	  	<listitem><para>
	  To describe the structure of the content a controlled vocabulary
	  added on top of the content. It is used to distinguish different
	  kinds of content: paragraphs, lists, tables, warnings (and so on).
	  This is also known as document <quote>markup</quote> and is typically
	  what people are referring to when they talk about SGML, XML and HTML.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	  The rules that
	  define the structure of a document are known as a Document Type
	  Definition (DTD). Depending on what kind of document you are writing,
	  you will use a different set of rules. The rules include the required
	  elements (tagset) and the order in which they must appear.
	  This document was written in
	  DocBook version 4.2 (although that version will likely change over
	  time).
	  For more information about marking up your document read: FIXME
		</para></listitem>

	  	<listitem><para>
      Finally the document is formatted for displayed. This is
	  controlled through the Document Style Semantics and Specification
	  Language (DSSSL).
      The DSSSL tells the program doing the rendering how to convert
      the SGML into something that a human can read.  It tells the
      renderer to convert a <sgmltag>title</sgmltag> tag into 14 point
      bold if it
      is going to RTF format, or to turn it into a &lt;h1&gt; tag if
      it is going to HTML.
	  For more information about transforming your document to other
	  document formats read: FIXME
	  	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      <para>
        The eXtensible Markup Language (XML) is a sub-set of SGML. Like
		SGML it is also a metalanguage and defines the rules of how a
		controlled vocabulary (DTD) can be used. Both SGML and XML
		documents must point to a DTD for the rules about a document's
		structure. DocBook is a DTD which is available in both SGML and XML
		formats. Although the element names do not change between the two
		there are slight differences between the two. The LDP has chosen
		to store its documents in XML format using the DocBook DTD. (Other
		markup languages are accepted--this is covered later in the
		document.)
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="whydocbook">
      <title>Why DocBook instead of HTML or other formats?</title>
      <para>DocBook provides for more than just formatting. You can
      automatically build indexes, tables of contents, and links within
      the document or to outside. The Jade and OpenJade packages also
      let you transform DocBook to LaTeX,
      info, text, HTML, and RTF. From these basic formats, you can
      then create other formats such as MS Word, PostScript, PDF and
      so on. Programs like LyX allow you to write in TeX format, then
      export it as DocBook SGML and transform from SGML to whatever you
      chose. In
      the end, DocBook is more concerned about the way elements work
      instead of the way they look.
      </para>

      <para>
      There are other DTDs which could be used for documentation other 
	  than DocBook, but there are a few reasons
      not to use them.  First, DocBook is the most popular DTD, being
      used by more than a dozen major open source projects from GNOME
      to Python to FreeBSD. Second, the tools for
      DocBook are far more developed than others.  DocBook support is
      included in most Linux distributions, allowing you to send raw
      files to be processed at the receiver's end.  And finally,
      while DocBook has an extensive set of tags (over 300 in all), a
      majority of them do not need to be used for simple
      documentation.  Starting with one of the available templates
      will allow you to quickly start writing DocBook with minimal
      experience. To get started using an LDP template read
      <xref linkend="templates"/></para>
    </section>

	  LINKS OF INTEREST:
	The Secret Life of Markup
	http://hotwired.lycos.com/webmonkey/02/42/index4a.html
	  
	XML Matters: Getting started with the DocBook XML dialect
	http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/xml/library/xml-matters3.html
	 
	FAQ for DocBook markup
	http://www.dpawson.co.uk/docbook/markup.html

	Where we are now. Part of "Progressive Enhancement and the Future of Web Design".
	http://hotwired.lycos.com/webmonkey/03/21/index3a_page2.html

	SGML
	http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/SGML/
  
  <section id="docbookxml">
    <title>Writing in DocBook XML</title>
    <para>
      While tools for writing XML are not as developed as those
      for SGML, there are a few reasons why you may want to start
      writing in XML: 
    </para> 

    <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Libraries for handling XML files are developing at
          a rapid pace.  These utilities may make it easier
          for new authoring tools to become available.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> 
          Many popular word processing programs are now creating
          XML output.  While it may not be DocBook XML, this does make
          it easier for application writers to either add DocBook XML
          support, or provide some method of translating between
          their format and DocBook XML.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Everyone else is doing it.  While this might not be a real
          reason, it allows the LDP to keep up-to-date with similar
          projects.  Tools, procedures, and issues can be worked out
          in a common framework.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      The real intent of this section is to get you familiar with the changes
      between writing in previous versions of DocBook SGML and DocBook XML.
      Since the LDP supports DocBook SGML 3.1 (which much of this Guide
      is written against) and up, and DocBook XML 4.1 and up, there will be
      a few differences.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the following sections, if you see DocBook followed by XML or SGML,
      it refers to the XML or SGML version of DocBook.  If DocBook is
      followed by a version number, it refers to both the XML and SGML
      versions of DocBook.
    </para>

    <section id="xmldifferences">
      <title>Differences between XML and SGML</title>
      <para>
        There are a few changes between writing XML and SGML.  Handling
        these differences should be relatively easy for most small documents,
        and many authors will not need to make any changes except
        for the XML declaration and DocBook declaration at the start
        of their document.
      </para>

      <para>
        For others, here is a list of what you should keep in mind
        when writing.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Most tags are case-dependent, or at least should have
            the same case.  That is, you do not want to have code
            like this:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;para&gt;This part will fail XML validation&lt;/PARA&gt;
</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The above being said, most XML-specific tags (like entity)
            have to be in all capital letters (ENTITY).
          </para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
          <para>
            All arguments to a tag have to be in quotes.  This can
            be either single (') or double (") quotes, but no
            reverse (`) or smart quotes are allowed.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Tags that have no close (like <sgmltag>xref</sgmltag>) have to have
            a trailing / as part of the tag. (&lt;xref/&gt;)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Processing instructions that get sent to the DSSSL (like
            &lt;?dbhtml&gt;) have to have a question mark at the
            end of the tag.  The new tag would look like this:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;?dbhtml filename="foo"?&gt;
</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you're converting to XML, be sure file names refer
            to .xml files instead of .sgml.  Some tools may get
            confused if a .sgml file contains XML.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Tag minimizations (<sgmltag class="endtag"></sgmltag>)
            are not supported.  Their use is discouraged in DocBook SGML.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="differences3040">
      <title>Differences between DocBook 3.x and DocBook 4.x</title>
      <para>
        The big changes between DocBook 3.x and 4.x involve deprecated
        tags, changed tags, and new ones.  Almost all authors will run
        into a changed or deprecated tag when going to DocBook 4.x.
        All tags that have been deprecated or changed for 4.x are listed
        in DocBook:  The definitive guide, published by O'Reilly and
        Associates.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <sgmltag>artheader</sgmltag> tag has been changed
            to <sgmltag>articleinfo</sgmltag>;.
            Most other header tags have been renamed to info.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <sgmltag>graphic</sgmltag> tag is being deprecated in
            DocBook 5.x.  To prepare for this, you can instead use the
            <sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag>
            tag.  You can find out using <sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag> at 
            <xref linkend="images"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            The file format for <sgmltag>imagedata</sgmltag> has to be in
            capital letters.  If you use lowercase or mixed-case spellings
            for your file formats, it will fail.
          </para>
          <para>
            Valid:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;imagedata format="EPS" fileref="foo.eps"&gt;
</screen>
          <para>
            Invalid:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;imagedata format="eps" fileref="foo.eps"&gt;
</screen>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>

