<!-- <!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.2//EN"> -->
<?dbhtml filename="glossary.html"?>
<glossary id="glossary">
  <title>Glossary</title>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Abiword</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Open Source word processor.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>aspell</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Spell check program.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>attribute</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An attribute makes available extra information regarding the 
          element on which it appears. The attributes always appear as a 
          name-value pair on the initialization pointers
			 (i.e. the <quote>start tag</quote>). Example of an
          attribute is <parameter
          class="option">id="identification"</parameter>, which gives the
          attribute <parameter class="option">id</parameter> the value
          <parameter class="option">identification</parameter>.</para>
    </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Cascading Style Sheet
    (<acronym>CSS</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Set of overlay rules that are read by your HTML browser, which uses these rules for doing the display, layout and formatting of the XML-generated HTML file(s).  <acronym>CSS</acronym> allows for fast changes in look and feel without having to plunge in the HTML file(s).
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Catalog</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Helper file for the display and transformation tools, which
		maps public identifiers and URLs to the local file system.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Concurrent Versions System
    (<acronym>CVS</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A common document management system used by the LDP.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>DocBook</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An SGML (and XML) application, describing a document format
		that allows easy management of documentation.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>docbook-utils</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Software package easing XML conversions.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Document Type Definition      
    (<acronym>DTD</acronym>)</glossterm> 
    <glossdef>
      <para>A group of statements that define element names and their attributes
          specifying the rules for combinations and sequences. It's the
          <acronym>DTD</acronym> that defines which elements can or cannot
          be inserted in the given context.   
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm><acronym>DSSSL</acronym></glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para><acronym>DSSSL</acronym> stands for Document Style Semantics and
          Specification Language. It's an <acronym>ISO</acronym> standard
          (ISO/IEC 10179:1996). The <acronym>DSSSL</acronym> standard is
          internationally used as a language for documents style sheets pages for
          <acronym>SGML</acronym>.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>element</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
		The elements describe the content's structure in a document.
		Most elements contain a start tag, content and a closing tag. For
		example a paragraph element includes all of the following <sgmltag
		class="starttag">para</sgmltag>This is the paragraph.<sgmltag
		class="endtag">para</sgmltag>. Some elements are <quote>empty</quote> and do not
		contain content and a closing tag. An example of this is a link to
		an external document where the URL is printed to the page. This
		element would include only the following <sgmltag
		class="emptytag">ulink url="http://google.com</sgmltag>. 
		</para>
      </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Emacs</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Popular text editor, especially on UNIX systems or alikes.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>entity</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An entity is a name designated for some part of data so that it
          can be referenced by a name.  The data could be anything from
          from simple characters to chapters to sets
          of statements in a <acronym>DTD</acronym>.
          Entity parameters can be generic, external, internal or
          <acronym>SGML</acronym> data.  An entity is similar to a variable
          in a programming language, or a macro.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>epcEdit</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Cross-platform XML editor.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>external entity</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An external entity points to an external document. External entities
          are used to include texts on certain locations of a
          <acronym>SGML</acronym> document. It could be used to include
          sample screens, legal notes, and chapters for example.</para> 
     </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>float</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
        <para>Objects such as side bars, pictures, tables, and charts are called          floats when they don't have a fixed placement on the text. For
          printed text, a chart can appear either at the top or at the
          bottom of the page. It can also be placed on the next page if it is
          too large.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Frequently Asked Questions
    (<acronym>FAQ</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>LDP hosts a number of documents that are a list in the form of 
	questions and answers.  These documents are called FAQs.  A FAQ is usually a single-page document.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>generic entities</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An entity referenced by a name, which starts with  
          <quote>&amp;</quote> and ends with semicolon is a generic    
          entity. Most of the time this type of entity is used in the 
          document and not on the <acronym>DTD</acronym>. There are two types
          of entities: external and internal.  They can refer to special
          characters or to text objects such as repeated sentences, names or
          chapters.</para> 
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>git</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Git is a widely-used source code management system for software development. It is a distributed revision control system with an emphasis on speed, data integrity, and support for distributed, non-linear workflows. (Source: <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Git_(software)">Wikipedia</ulink>)</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>GNU Free Documentation License
    (<acronym>GFDL</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Like the GNU Public License for free software, but with specifics for written text and documentation with software.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>GNU Public License
    (<acronym>GPL</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>License type for software that guarantees that the software remains freely distributable, that the source code is available, that you can make changes to it and redistribute those changes if you want, on the condition that you keep on using the same license for your derived works.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Guide</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>TLDP documents that are too long to be a HOWTO are usually stored 
	as guides.  These are more like entire books that treat a particular 
	subject in-dept.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>HOWTO</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Documents that discuss how to do something with a system or 
	application.  Most documents hosted at TLDP are HOWTOs,
	explaining how to install, configure or manage tens of applications 
	on a variety of systems.  HOWTOs are typically 10-25 pages.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>internal entity</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An internal entity refers to part of the text and is often used
          as a shortcut for frequently repeated text.</para>
           </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>ispell</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Spell check program.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Jade</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An application which applies the rules defined in a DSSSL
		style sheet to an SGML or XML document, transforming the document
		into the desired output.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Markup, markup language
    (<acronym>ML</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Code added to the content of a document, describing its structure.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Metadata</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Text in your document that is not important for understanding the subject, but that should be there anyway, such as version information, co-authors, credits to people etc.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>nedit</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Text editor oriented to programmers.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>nsgmls, onsgmls</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>SGML document parser and validator program.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>OpenOffice
    (<acronym>OOo</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Open Source office suite, compatible with Microsoft Office.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>parameter entity</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An entity type often used in the <acronym>DTD</acronym> or a
		document's internal subset. The entity's
          name starts with a percent sign (&#37;) and ends with a
          semicolon.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>PSGML</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Emacs <emphasis>major mode</emphasis> that customizes Emacs for editing SGML documents.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Organization for the Advancement of Structured Information Standards
    (<acronym>OASIS</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>OASIS is a non-profit, global consortium that drives the development, convergence and adoption of e-business standards.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Outline</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Draft of your document that conceptualizes the subject and scope.  Summary and To-Do list for the work to come.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Portable Document Format
    (<acronym>PDF</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Standard document type supported on a wide range of operating systems.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>processing instruction</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A processing instruction is a command passed to the document 
          formatting tool. It starts with <quote>&lt;?</quote>. This document
          uses processing instructions for naming files when it
          is rendered into
          <acronym>HTML</acronym>: <sgmltag class="starttag">?dbhtml
          filename="file.html"</sgmltag></para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>PostScript
    (<acronym>PS</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Document format designed for printable documents.  PS is the standard print format on UNIX(-alikes).
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Reviewer, review process</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>TLDP doesn't accept just anything.  Once you submit a document, it will be checked for consistency, grammar, spelling and style by a reviewer, a volunteer assigned by the review coordinator.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm><acronym>SGML</acronym></glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para><foreignphrase>Standard Generalized Markup
          Language</foreignphrase>.
          It is an international standard (<acronym>ISO</acronym>8879) that
          specifies rules for the creation of electronic documents in markup
          systems, regardless of the platform used.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Subject and scope</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Obviously, the subject is what your documentation is about.  The scope defines which areas of the subject you are going to discuss, and how much detail will be involved.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>tag</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An <acronym>SGML</acronym> element bounded by the marks
          <quote>&lt;</quote> and <quote>&gt;</quote>. Tags are used
          to mark the semantic or logical structure of a document. A sample
          is the tag <emphasis><sgmltag
          class="starttag">title</sgmltag></emphasis> to mark the beginning
          of a title.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>TeX</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Popular UNIX text formatting and typesetting tool.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Transformation</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The process of converting a document from its original DocBook XML form to another format, such as PDF, HTML or PostScript.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Validation</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The process of checking your XML code to ensure it complies
		with the XML DTD you declared at the top of your document.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>vi Improved
    (<acronym>vIm</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Popular text editor on UNIX and alike systems.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>WordPerfect
    (<acronym>WP</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Popular word processor, runs on many systems.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm><acronym>XML</acronym></glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>eXtensible Markup Language. A sub-product of <acronym>SGML</acronym>
          created specifically for Internet use.</para> 
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>xmllint</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Command line XML parser and validator.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>XMLmind XML Editor
    (<acronym>XXE</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Free but not Open XML editor.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>xmlto</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Command line XML transformation program.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm><acronym>XSL</acronym></glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para><acronym>XML</acronym> Style
          Language. XSL is to a <acronym>XML</acronym> document what a 
          <acronym>DSSSL</acronym> style is for a <acronym>SGML</acronym>
          document. The XSL is written in
          <acronym>XML</acronym>.</para>  
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Extensible Stylesheet Transformation 
    (<acronym>XSLT</acronym>)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Framework for managing documents, consisting of the XSLT transformation language, the XPath expression language and XSL formatting objects.
          </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

</glossary>
