
<chapter id="styleguide">
<title>LDP Style Guide</title>

  <sect1 id="sg-subject">
    <title>Deciding on a Subject</title>

      <para>
        Before you begin writing a HOWTO, it is essential that
        you determine what subject area you will cover. It is best if the
        subject area is:
      </para>
      
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Not too broad, and not too narrow.</title>
              <para>
                Try to cover too much information,
                and you may sacrifice depth. It is better to cover a
                small subject area fully than to cover a large subject
                area poorly.
                Linux tools are known for doing exactly one
                thing and doing that one thing <emphasis>well</emphasis>. 
                Similarly, your HOWTO should cover one subject and cover it
                <emphasis>well</emphasis>.
              </para>
          </formalpara>

          <para>
            If your subject matter is very small, it might be better
            included as part of another HOWTO. This makes it easier
            for readers to find the HOWTO they need. Search the LDP repository
            for HOWTOs on related topics, and see if you could place
            your information in an existing HOWTO.
          </para>
        
          <para>
            How much is too much?
            How little is too little? That depends on the subject
            you chose, your mastery of that subject, and many other
            factors. Just keep this admonition in mind, and use good judgment.
          </para>

        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>          
            <title>Clearly defined.</title>

            <para>
              Know before you begin exactly where the boundaries of your
              subject area lie. You should not cover the same ground as another
              HOWTO, and you should try not to leave gaps between your HOWTO
              and related HOWTOs, either.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Undocumented</title>
            
            <para>
              Before writing on a particular subject, check other HOWTOs at the LDP,
              and see if the topic is already documented. If it is, refer to the 
              other HOWTO instead of rewriting documentation that already exists.
              Don't reinvent the wheel.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
      
          <para>
            If the HOWTO already in place is insufficient, or needs updating, 
            contact the author and offer to help. LDP authors are usually nice folks.
            After all, they put in their own valuable time to help people they
            don't even know. And, they appreciate your help. But, please, don't
            duplicate work. It causes confusion for everyone.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Pre-approved by the LDP</title>
            
            <para>
              Before you proceed with your HOWTO, post to the ldp-discuss list
              and get some feedback from other LDP volunteers. Checking with the
              list <emphasis>before</emphasis> you begin can save you headaches
              <emphasis>later</emphasis>.
              The author speaks from experience.
            </para>
            
          </formalpara>

          <para>
            It is a really good idea to join the ldp-discuss list, and follow
            it regularly, even if you never post. It's a good way to stay current
            on the activities, needs, and policies of the LDP. Although the LDP
            volunteers are here to assist you, it is ultimately your 
            responsibility to learn these policies, and to follow them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
  
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="sg-outline">
    <title>Developing an Outline</title>
    
    <para>
      Before you actually begin writing, prepare an outline.
      An outline will help you get a clear picture of the subject matter,
      and allow you to concentrate on one small part of the HOWTO
      at a time.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Unless your HOWTO is exceptionally small, your outline will probably
      be multilevel.
      When developing a multilevel outline, the top level should contain general
      subject areas, and sub-headings should be more detailed and specific.
      Look at each level of your outline independently,
      and make sure it covers all key areas of the subject matter. Sub-headings
      should cover all key areas of the heading under which they fall.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Each item in your outline should logically follow the item before it,
      and lead into the item it precedes. For example, a HOWTO about a particular
      program shouldn't have a section on <emphasis>configuration</emphasis>
      before one on <emphasis>installation</emphasis>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      When you are comfortable with your outline, look over it once more,
      with a critical eye. Have you covered every relevant topic in
      sufficient detail? Have you wandered beyond the scope of the HOWTO?
      You might want to show it to someone else, and ask for feedback. 
      It's much easier to reorganize your
      HOWTO at the outline stage than it will be later. Consider submitting
      the outline to the ldp-discuss list for more feedback.
    </para>
    
    <note>
      <para>
        You might have noticed a theme developing here.
        Just like Free software, Free documentation is best when you
        <quote>release early, release often.</quote> The ldp-discuss list includes
        many experienced LDP authors, and you would be wise to seek their
        advice when making decisions about your HOWTO.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      Remember Linus' Law:
    </para>
    
    <blockquote><attribution>Eric S. Raymond</attribution>
      <para>
        <quote>Given enough eyeballs, all [typos] are shallow.</quote>
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    
    <para>
      (With apologies to Mr. Raymond.)
    </para>

    <para>
      FIXME: Need a reference to the "standard" HOWTO layout, for 
      topic areas such as Credits, License, Copyright, etc., etc.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="sg-writingstyle">
    <title>Writing the Text</title>
    
    <para>
      At this point, your HOWTO has been organized, and bits of raw information
      have been collected, documented, and inserted into the outline.
      Good news: You're past the
      midpoint; it's all downhill from here. 
    </para>
    
    <para>      
      Your next challenge is to
      massage all of the raw data you've collected into a readable,
      entertaining, and understandable whole.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      It has taken quite a bit of work to get to the point where you can
      actually start writing, hasn't it? Well, the hard work begins to pay
      off for you now. At this stage, you can begin to really use your
      imagination and creativity to communicate this heap of dry, 
      boring information in 
      your own unique way.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      It is beyond the scope of this document to provide a comprehensive
      guide to effective writing, so I won't try to go beyond the basics. 

      In the <quote><link linkend="sg-references" endterm="sg-references.title"></link></quote>
      section, you will find a list of resources that cover the subject
      better than this guide could hope to. Consult them, and follow their
      advice.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      For starters, here is some good advice from 
      <ulink url="http://www.resort.com/~prime8/Orwell/patee.html"><citetitle>Politics and the English Language</citetitle></ulink>:
    </para>
    
    <blockquote>
      <attribution>George Orwell</attribution>
    
      <para>
        A scrupulous writer, in every sentence that he writes, will ask himself
        at least four questions, thus:
      </para>
      
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What am I trying to say?
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            What words will express it?
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            What image or idiom will make it clearer?
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Is this image fresh enough to have an effect?
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
        And he will probably ask himself two more:
      </para>
      
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Could I put it more shortly?
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Have I said anything that is avoidably ugly?
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      
      <para>
        ...One can often be in doubt about the effect of a word or phrase, 
        and one needs rules that one can rely on when instinct fails.
        I think the following rules will cover most cases:
      </para>
      
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Never use a metaphor, simile, or other figure of speech which you are used to seeing in print.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Never use a long word where a short one will do.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            If it is possible to cut a word out, always cut it out.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Never use the passive where you can use the active.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Never use a foreign phrase, a scientific word, 
            or a jargon word if you can think
            of an everyday English equivalent.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Break any of these rules sooner than say anything outright barbarous.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      
    </blockquote>
    
    <para>
      And, from a purely stylistic point of view, I believe that 
      the first-person perspective of many HOWTOs adds to their charm,
      an attribute most documentation in other forms sorely lacks.
      Don't be afraid to speak for yourself, use the word <quote>I</quote>,
      or describe personal experiences and opinions.
    </para>
        
    <para>
      If it hasn't become painfully obvious yet, the underlying principle
      of all these suggestions is simplicity. 
      Your readers are already struggling with new concepts, so don't
      make them struggle to understand your language.
      Remember the <acronym>KISS</acronym> principle: Keep It Simple, Stupid!
    </para>

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="sg-editing">
    <title>Editing and Proofing the Text</title>
    
    <para>
      Once you've written the text of your HOWTO, it is time to polish      
      and refine it. Good editing can make the difference between a good
      HOWTO and a great one.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      One of the goals of editing is to remove extraneous material that
      has crept its way into your document.
      You should go through your HOWTO carefully, and ruthlessly
      delete anything that doesn't contribute to the reader's understanding
      of the subject matter. It is natural for writers to go off on tangents
      while in the process of writing. This is the time to correct that.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      When editing and proofing your work, you must check for obvious mistakes, 
      such as spelling errors and typos. 
      However, you should check for deeper, but
      less obvious errors as well, such as <quote>holes</quote> in the
      information. Make sure that the contents of every section match
      the title of that section precisely.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      When you are completely satisfied with the quality and accuracy of
      your work, forward it to someone else for third-party proofing.
      You will be too close to the work to see fundamental flaws.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      In a sense, editing is like code review in software development.
      Having a programmer review their own code doesn't make much sense,
      does it? Why should having a writer edit their own document make
      any more sense?
      So, recruit a friend, or write the
      ldp-discuss list to find a volunteer to proofread before submitting
      your HOWTO.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        If you are writing in a language in which you are not fluent,
        I strongly recommend that you seek an editor who is. Technical
        documentation, more than any other type of writing, must use
        extremely precise grammar and vocabulary. Misuse of the language,
        no matter how understandable and unintended, makes your HOWTO
        less valuable.
      </para>
    </note>

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="sg-maintaining">
    <title>Maintaining Your HOWTO</title>
    
    <para>
      Just because your HOWTO has now been published doesn't mean your
      job is done. HOWTOs need regular maintenance, to make sure they
      are up to date, and to improve them in response to readers' ideas
      and suggestions. A HOWTO is a living, growing body of knowledge,
      not just a publish-and-forget-it static document.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You put your email address in the HOWTO, and politely requested
      feedback from your readers, right? Once you are officially published,
      you will begin to receive notes with suggestions. Some will be
      very valuable; others will request personal assistance. You should
      feel free to decline personal assistance if you cannot spare the
      time. Writing a HOWTO for the LDP doesn't commit you to a lifetime
      of free support for anyone on the net. It is polite to refer
      questioners to another resource, if you can. And, if you see a
      pattern in the questions you receive, it might indicate a topic
      you should add to your HOWTO.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sg-references">
    <title id="sg-references.title">References</title>
    
    <para>
      There are many guides to writing style available online.
      Here is a brief list of some of the best:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="http://www.resort.com/~prime8/Orwell/patee.html"><citetitle>Politics and the English Language</citetitle></ulink>.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="http://bartleby.com/141"><citetitle>The Elements of Style</citetitle></ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          FIXME: Please send the URL of your favorite resource on technical writing.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    
  </sect1>
    
</chapter>
