<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
    <section id="theldp">
      <title>About The LDP</title>
      <para>The Linux Documentation Project (LDP) was started to
      provide new users a way of quickly getting information about a
      particular subject. It not only contains a series of books on
      administration, networking, and programming, but also has a large
      number of smaller works on individual subjects, written by those
      who have used it. If you want to find out about printing, you
      get the <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Printing-HOWTO.html">Printing
      HOWTO</ulink>. If you want to do find out if your Ethernet card
      works with Linux, grab the <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Ethernet-HOWTO.html">Ethernet
      HOWTO</ulink>, and so on.
	</para>
	<para>
		  The LDP provides documents to the world in a variety of
  convenient formats and also accepts submissions in a
  number of formats.  The current standard for storing
  the source documentation is a format known as DocBook, see <xref
  linkend="docbook-why" />.		
		</para> 
      
	  <blockquote>
        <attribution>LDP Manifesto located at <ulink
        url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html</ulink></attribution>
        <para>The Linux Documentation Project (LDP) is working on
        developing free, high-quality documentation for the GNU/Linux
        operating system. The overall goal of the LDP is to
        collaborate in all of the issues of Linux documentation. This
        includes the creation of <quote>HOWTOs</quote> and <quote>Guides</quote>. We hope to
        establish a system of documentation for Linux that will be
        easy to use and search. This includes the integration of the
        manual pages, info docs, HOWTOs, and other documents.</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>
        The human readable version goes more like this:  The LDP consists
        of a large group of volunteers who are working on documentation
        about Linux and the programs which run on the Linux kernel.
		  These documents exist primarily as shorter HOWTOs and longer
		  Guides. Both are available from <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/" />.
        This Guide focuses primarily on how to write your own HOWTOs for
        submission to the LDP.
       </para>
    </section>
