<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
    <section id="theldp">
      <title>About The LDP</title>
      <para>The Linux Documentation Project (LDP) was started to
      provide new users a way of quickly getting information about a
      particular subject. It not only contains a series of books on
      administration, networking, and programming, but also has a large
      number of smaller works on individual subjects, written by those
      who have used it. If you want to find out about printing, you
      get the <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Printing-HOWTO.html">Printing
      HOWTO</ulink>. If you want to do find out if your Ethernet card
      works with Linux, grab the <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Ethernet-HOWTO.html">Ethernet
      HOWTO</ulink>, and so on. At first, many of these works were in
      text or HTML. As time went on, there had to be a better way of
      managing these documents. One that would let you read it from a
      web page, a text file on a CD-ROM, or even your hand-held
      PDA. The answer, as it turns out, is DocBook.</para> 
      
	  <blockquote>
        <attribution>LDP Manifesto located at <ulink
        url="http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html">http://www.tldp.org/manifesto.html</ulink></attribution>
        <para>The Linux Documentation Project (LDP) is working on
        developing free, high-quality documentation for the GNU/Linux
        operating system. The overall goal of the LDP is to
        collaborate in all of the issues of Linux documentation. This
        includes the creation of "HOWTOs" and "Guides". We hope to
        establish a system of documentation for Linux that will be
        easy to use and search. This includes the integration of the
        manual pages, info docs, HOWTOs, and other documents.</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>
        The human readable version goes more like this:  The LDP consists
        of a large group of volunteers that are working on documentation
        for the Linux OS.  The most visible documentation are the HOWTOs
        located at <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">http://www.tldp.org/"</ulink>.
        This Guide focuses primarily on how to write your own HOWTOs for
        submission to the LDP.
       </para>
    </section>
