<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<section id="tools-word-processors">
<title>Word Processors</title>
<para>
	Even if you are not comfortable working DocBook's tagset
	in a text editor you can still produce valid DocBook
	documents using a word processor. Support at this point
	is very limited, but it does exist in the following
	programs. The up side, of course, is that things like
	spell check are built in to the program. In addition to
	this, support for DocBook (and XML) is constantly
	improving.
</para>

<!-- duplicated in x2docbook.xml -->
<note><title>Converting Microsoft Word documents</title><para>
	Even if you want to use MS Word to write your documents, you may
	find <ulink url="http://www.docsoft.com/w2xmlv2.htm">w2XML</ulink>
	useful. Note that this is not free software--the cost is around $130USD.
	There is, however, a trial version of the software.
</para></note>

<note><title>Work on the content!</title><para>
	Remember that all formatting changes you make to your
	document will be ignored when your document is released
	by the LDP. Instead of focusing on how your document
	<emphasis>looks</emphasis>, focus on the content.
</para></note>

<section id="abiword"> <title>AbiWord</title> <para>
	Through word of mouth I've heard that AbiWord can work (natively)
	with DocBook documents. This will need to be tested by someone
	(possibly me) and should definitely be included if it is
	the case.
</para> </section>

<!-- duplicated in x2docbook.xml -->
<section id="openoffice"> <title>OpenOffice.org</title> <para>
	<ulink url="http://openoffice.org">http://openoffice.org</ulink>
</para>

<para>
	As of OpenOffice.org (OOo) 1.1RC there has been support for
	exporting files to DocBook format.
</para>

<para>
	Although OOo uses the full DocBook document type declaration,
	it does not actually export the full list of DocBook elements. It
	uses a <quote>simplified</quote> DocBook tagset which is geared
	to on-the-fly rendering. (Although it is not the official
	Simplified DocBook which is described in <xref linkend="dtd" />.)
  The OpenOffice simplified (or <quote>special</quote> docbook) is available from
	<ulink url="http://www.chez.com/ebellot/ooo2sdbk/">
		http://www.chez.com/ebellot/ooo2sdbk/
	</ulink>.
</para>

<section id="ooo-1-0">
<title>Open Office 1.0.x</title>
<para>
	OOo has been tested by LDP volunteers with mostly positive
	results. Thanks to Charles Curley
		(<ulink
		url="http://www.charlescurley.com">charlescurley.com</ulink>)
	for the following notes on using OOo version 1.0.x:
</para>

<note><title>Check the version of your OpenOffice</title>
	<para>
		These notes may not apply to the version of OOo you
		are using.
	</para>
</note>

<itemizedlist> <listitem><para>
	To be able to export to DocBook, you must have a Java runtime
  environment (JRE) installed and registered with OOo--a minimum of
  version 4.2.x is recommended. The configuration instructions will
  depend on how you installed your JRE.  Visit the OOo web site for
  help with your setup.
</para>

<para>
  Contrary to the OOo documentation, the Linux OOo did not come with
  a JRE. I got one from Sun.
</para> </listitem> <!-- openoffice -->

<listitem><para>
	The exported file has lots of empty lines. My 54 line exported
	file
  had 5 lines of actual XML code.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
	There was no effort at pretty printing.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> The header is:
    <computeroutput>
	 &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
    &lt;!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC &quot;-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN&quot;
	 &quot;http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd&quot;&gt;
	</computeroutput>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> The pull-down menu in the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Save
As</guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog box for
file format
  indicates that the export format is <quote>DocBook (simplified).</quote> There is
  no explanation of what that <quote>simplified</quote> indicates. Does OOo export
  a subset of DocBook? If so, which elements are ignored? Is there any
  way to enter any of them manually?
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> There is NO documentation on the DocBook export filter
or whether
  OOo will import it again.
</para></listitem> </itemizedlist>

<para>
	Conclusions: OOo 1.1RC is worth looking at if you want a word
	processor for preparing DocBook documents.
</para>

<para>
	However, I hope they cure the lack of documentation.  For one
	thing, it would be nice to know which native OOo styles map to
	which DocBook elements. It would also be nice to know how to
	map one's own OOo styles to DocBook elements.
</para>
</section>

<section id="ooo-1-1">
<title>Open Office 1.1</title>
<para>
	<ulink url="http://www.merlinmonroe.com">Tabatha Marshall</ulink>
	offers the following additional information for OOo 1.1.
</para>

<blockquote>
	<para> The first problem was when I tried to do everything on version
	1.0.1.	That was
obviously a problem.  I have RH8, and it was installed via rpm packages,
so I ripped it out and did a full, new install of OpenOffice 1.1.
It took a while to find out 1.1 was a requirement for XML to work.
	</para>

	<para>
During the install process I believe I was offered the choice to install
the XML features.  I have a tendency to do full installs of my office
programs, so I selected everything.
	</para>

	<para>
I can't offer any advice to those trying to update their current
OO 1.1.  Their <quote>3 ways</quote> aren't documented very well at the site
(<ulink url="http://xml.openoffice.org">xml.openoffice.org</ulink>) and as of this writing, I can't even find THAT
on their site anymore.	I think more current documentation is needed
there to walk people through the process.  Most of this was unclear
and I had to pretty much experiment to get things working.
	</para>

	<para>
Well, after I installed everything I had some configuration to do.
I opened the application, and got started by opening a new file,
choosing templates, then selecting the DocBook template.  A nice menu
of <guisubmenu>Paragraph Styles</guisubmenu> popped up for me, which are the names for all those
tags, I noticed (you can see I don't use WYSIWYG often).
	</para>

	<para>
		With a blank doc before me (couldn't get to the <guisubmenu>XML Filter
		Settings</guisubmenu> menu unless some type of doc was opened), I went into
		<menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>XML
		Filter Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and edited the entry for DocBook file.
		I configured mine as follows:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			<guilabel>Doctype</guilabel>  
			<userinput>-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN</userinput>
		</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>
			<guilabel>DTD</guilabel>
			<userinput>http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd</userinput>
		</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>
			<guilabel>XSLT for export</guilabel>
			<userinput>/usr/local/OpenOffice.org1.1.0/share/xslt/docbook/ldp-html.xsl</userinput>
		</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>
			<guilabel>XSLT for import</guilabel>
			<userinput>/usr/local/OpenOffice.org1.1.0/share/xslt/docbook/docbooktosoffheadings.xsl</userinput>
			(this is the default)
		</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<para>
			<guilabel>Template for import</guilabel>
			<userinput>/home/tabatha/OpenOffice/user/template/DocBook
			File/DocBookTemplate.stw</userinput>
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
At first, if I opened an XML file that had even one parsing error, it
would just open the file anyway and display the markup in OO.  I have
many XML files that use &amp;copy; and other types of entities which show
up as parse errors (depending on the encoding) even though they can be
processed through.  But today I was unable to open any of those files.
I got input/output errors instead.  Still investigating that one.
	</para>

	<para>
However when you do successfully open a document (one parsing with no
errors), it puts it automatically into WYSIWYG based on the markup,
and you can then work from the paragraph styles menu like any other
such editor.
	</para>

	<para>
To validate the document, I used <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>XML
Filter Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, then
clicked the <guibutton>Test XSLTs</guibutton> button.  On my screen, I set up the XSLT
for export to be <filename>ldp-html.xsl</filename>.	If you test and there are errors,
a new window pops up with error messages at the bottom, and the lines
that need to be changed up at the top.	You can change them there and
progress through the errors until they're all gone, and keep testing
until they're gone.
	</para>

	<para>
If you want to open a file to see the source instead of the processed
results, go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>XML Filter
Settings</guimenuitem><guisubmenu>Test XSLTs</guisubmenu></menuchoice>, and then
under the <menuchoice><guimenu>Import</guimenu></menuchoice> section, check the
<guilabel>Display Source</guilabel> box.  My import XSLT
is currently <filename>docbooktosoffheadings.xsl</filename> (the default) and the template
for import is <filename>DocBookTemplate.stw</filename> (also default).
	</para>

	<para>
I think this might work for some people, but unfortunately not for me.
I've never used WYSIWYG to edit markup.  <application>Emacs with
PSGML</application> can tell me
what my next tag is no matter where I am, validate by moving through
the trouble spots, and I can parse and process from command line.
	</para>

	<para>
With OpenOffice, you have to visit <ulink
url="http://xml.openoffice.org/filters.html">http://xml.openoffice.org/filters.html</ulink>
to find conversion tools.
	</para> </blockquote>

</section> </section>

<section id="wordperfect"> <!-- I don't run Windows - can someone please
confirm this information is still true? --> <title>WordPerfect 9 (Corel
Office 2000)</title> <para>
	<ulink url="http://www.corel.com/">
		http://www.corel.com/</ulink>
</para>

<para>
	<!-- what about XML capabilities? Please replace if
	appropriate. --> WordPerfect 9 for the MS Windows platform has
	support for SGML and DocBook 3.0. WordPerfect 9 for Linux has
	no SGML capabilities.
</para>

<para>
	If you are using WordPerfect on the Linux operating system, please
	read: <ulink
	url="http://en.tldp.org/FAQ/WordPerfect-Linux-FAQ/">WordPerfect on
	Linux FAQ</ulink>
</para>

</section> <!-- wordperfect -->

<!-- xmlmind --> <section id="XMLmind">

<title>XMLmind's XML editor</title>
  <para>
    <ulink url="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/" />
  </para>

    <para>
	Although strictly speaking, it is not a word processor,
	XMLmind's <application>XML editor</application> allows authors to concentrate
	on the content, and not the markup. It has built in
	spelling and conversion utilities which allow you to transform your
	documents without having to install and configure an additional
	processing tool such as jade. There is a free <quote>standard
	edition</quote>, which is a simplified version of their
	<quote>professional edition.</quote>
  </para>

  </section> <!-- xmlmind -->

</section> <!-- tools-word-processors -->
