<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<section id="tools-word-processors">
<title>Word Processors</title>
<para>
	Even if you aren't comfortable working DocBook's tagset
	in a text editor you can still produce valid DocBook
	documents using a word processor. Support at this point
	is very limited, but it does exist in the following
	programs. The up side, of course, is that things like
	spell check are built in to the program. In addition to
	this, support for DocBook (and XML) is constantly
	improving.
</para>

<note><para>
	Even if you want to use MS Word to write your documents, you may
	find <ulink url="http://www.docsoft.com/w2xmlv2.htm">w2XML</ulink>
	useful. Note it is not free software--the cost is around $130USD.
	There is, however, a trial version of the software.
</para></note>

<note><para>
	Remember that all formatting changes you make to your
	document will be ignored when your document is released
	by the LDP. Instead of focusing on how your document
	<emphasis>looks</emphasis>, focus on the content.
</para></note>

<section id="abiword"> <title>AbiWord</title> <para>
	Through word of mouth I've heard that AbiWord can work (natively)
	with DocBook documents. This will need to be tested by someone
	(possibly me) and should definitely be included if it is
	the case.
</para> </section>

<section id="openoffice"> <title>OpenOffice.org</title> <para>
	<ulink url="http://openoffice.org">http://openoffice.org</ulink>
</para>

<para>
	As of OpenOffice.org (OOo) 1.1RC there has been support for
	exporting files to DocBook format.
</para>

<para>
	Although OOo uses the full DocBook document type declaration,
	it does not actually export the full list of DocBook elements. It
	uses a <quote>simplified</quote> DocBook tagset which is geared
	to on-the-fly rendering. (Although it is not the official
	Simplified DocBook which is described in <xref linkend="dtd" />.)
  The OpenOffice simplified (or "special" docbook) is available from
	<ulink url="http://www.chez.com/ebellot/ooo2sdbk/">
		http://www.chez.com/ebellot/ooo2sdbk/
	</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
	OOo has been tested by LDP volunteers with mostly positive
	results. Thanks to Charles Curley
		(<ulink
		url="http://www.charlescurley.com">charlescurley.com</ulink>)
	for the following notes on using OOo version 1.0.x:
</para>

<note>
	<para>
		These notes may not apply to the version of OOo you
		are using.
	</para>
</note>

<itemizedlist> <listitem><para>
	To be able to export to DocBook, you must have a Java runtime
  environment (JRE) installed and registered with OOo--a minimum of
  version 4.2.x is recommended. The configuration instructions will
  depend on how you installed your JRE.  Visit the OOo web site for
  help with your setup.
</para>

<para>
  Contrary to the OOo documentation, the Linux OOo did not come with
  a JRE. I got one from Sun.
</para> </listitem> <!-- openoffice -->

<listitem><para>
	The exported file has lots of empty lines. My 54 line exported
	file
  had 5 lines of actual XML code.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
	There was no effort at pretty printing.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> The header is:
    <computeroutput>
	 &lt;?xml version=3D"1.0" encoding=3D"UTF-8"?&gt;
    &lt;!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	 "http:/=/www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"&gt;
	</computeroutput>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> The pull-down menu in the "Save As" dialog box for
file format
  indicates that the export format is "DocBook (simplified)." There is
  no explanation of what that "simplified" indicates. Does OOo export
  a subset of DocBook? If so, which elements are ignored? Is there any
  way to enter any of them manually?
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> There is NO documentation on the DocBook export filter
or whether
  OOo will import it again.
</para></listitem> </itemizedlist>

<para>
	Conclusions: OOo 1.1RC is worth looking at if you want a word
	processor for preparing DocBook documents.
</para>

<para>
	However, I hope they cure the lack of documentation.  For one
	thing, it would be nice to know which native OOo styles map to
	which DocBook elements. It would also be nice to know how to
	map one's own OOo styles to DocBook elements.
</para> </section>

<section id="wordperfect"> <!-- I don't run Windows - can someone please
confirm this information is still true? --> <title>WordPerfect 9 (Corel
Office 2000)</title> <para>
	<ulink url="http://www.corel.com/">
		http://www.corel.com/</ulink>
</para>

<para>
	<!-- what about XML capabilities? Please replace if
	appropriate. --> WordPerfect 9 for the MS Windows platform has
	support for SGML and DocBook 3.0. WordPerfect 9 for Linux has
	no SGML capabilities.
</para> <para>
	This is the least expensive of the commercial
   applications which supports SGML.
</para> </section> <!-- wordperfect -->

<!-- xmlmind --> <section id="XMLmind">

<title>XMLmind's XML editor</title>
  <para>
    <ulink url="http://www.xmlmind.com/">
     http://www.xmlmind.com/</ulink>
  </para>

    <para>
	Although strictly speaking, it is not a word processor,
	XMLmind's XML editor allows authors to concentrate mainly
	on the content and less on the markup. It also has built in
	spelling and conversion utilities so that people don't have to
	go through the trouble of install and configuring jade should
	they not want to do so.
  </para>

  </section> <!-- xmlmind -->

</section> <!-- tools-word-processors -->
