<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<section id="transformations">
	<title>Transformations</title>
		<warning><title>TLDP can convert your document</title><para>
			This section is about how to transform documents
			from DocBook to other formats. If you do not want
			to transform documents on your own computer you may
			<emphasis>skip this section</emphasis>.
		</para>
	
		<para>
			If you would like to transform your documents for 
			proofreading purposes, please use the <ulink
			url="http://www.xml-dev.com/blog/xml2html.php">XML to HTML on-line
			converter</ulink>. You will need to upload your XML file(s)
			to a web site. Then simply drop the URL into the form and
			click the submit button. Your document will be magically
			transformed into a beautiful (and legible)
			HTML document. External files are supported. You may use 
			either absolute or relative URIs.
		</para>

		<para>
			Another fairly straight-forward package is
			<application>xmlto</application>. It is a front-end for
			<application>xsltproc</application>. It is available as a
			RedHat, Debian (etc) package or can be downloaded from <ulink
			url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/xmlto/" />. You can use it to convert
			documents with:
		</para>
		
<programlisting>
<prompt>bash$ </prompt><userinput>xmlto html <filename>mydoc.xml</filename></userinput>
<prompt>bash$ </prompt><userinput>xmlto txt <filename>mydoc.xml</filename></userinput>
</programlisting>

		<para>
			You do not ever need to transform documents
			before submitting to the LDP. The LDP
			volunteers have a system which transforms
			your DocBook file into HTML, PDF and plain
			text formats. There, you've been warned.
		</para></warning>

<para>
	Still here? Great! Transformations are
	a pretty basic requirement to get what
	you've written from a messy tag-soup into
	something that can be read.  This section
	will help you get your system set up and
	ready to transform your latest document
	into other formats. This is very useful
	is you want to <emphasis>see</emphasis>
	your document before you release it to
	the world.
</para>

<para>
	There are currently two ways to transform
	your document: Document Style Semantics and
	Specification Language (DSSSL); and XML
	Style sheets (XSLT). Although the LDP web site uses
	DSSSL to convert documents you may use XSLT
	if you want. You only need to choose <emphasis>one</emphasis> of these
	methods. For more information about DSSSL read: <xref linkend="dsssl"
	/>, for more information about XSLT read: <xref linkend="xsl" />.
</para>

<section id="dsssl">
<title>DSSSL</title>
<para>
	There are three basic requirements to transform a document using DSSSL:
</para> 
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
	The Document Style and Semantics Specification Language files
	(these are plain text files). <xref linkend="dsssl-files" />
	</para>
</listitem> 
<listitem><para>
	The Document Type Definition file
	which matches the DOCTYPE of your
	document (this is a plain text file).
	<xref linkend="dtd" />
</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>
	A processor to do the actual work. <xref linkend="dsssl-processors" />
	</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist> 

<section id="dsssl-files">
<title>The Style Sheets</title>
<para>There are two versions of the
		Document Style Semantics and Specification Language
		used by the LDP to transform documents from your
		raw DocBook files into other formats (which are then
		published on the Web). The LDP version of the style
		sheets requires the Norman Walsh version--which
		basically means if you're using DSSSL the Norman
		Walsh version can be considered a requirement for
		system setup.</para>

	<formalpara>
	<title>Norman Walsh DSSSL <ulink
	url="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/projects/dsssl/" /></title>
	<para>The
				<indexterm><primary>DSSSL</primary></indexterm>
	Document Style Semantics and Specification Language tells
	Jade (see <xref linkend="dsssl-processors"/>) how to render
		  a DocBook document into print or on-line
	form. The DSSSL is what converts a
		  <sgmltag>title</sgmltag> tag into an
	&lt;h1&gt; HTML tag, or to 14 point bold Times Roman for
	RTF, for example. Documentation for DSSSL is located at
	the same site. Note that modifying the DSSSL doesn't modify
	DocBook itself. It merely changes the way the rendered text
	looks. The LDP uses a modified DSSSL (see below).</para>
	</formalpara>

	<formalpara>
	<title>LDP DSSSL <ulink
	url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/tools/ldp.dsl">http://www.tldp.org/authors/tools/ldp.dsl</ulink></title>
	<para>The LDP DSSSL requires the Norman Walsh version (see
	above) but is a slightly modified DSSSL to provide things
	like a table of contents.</para>
	</formalpara>

	<example id="ex-dsssl">
	<title><quote>Installing</quote> DSSSL style sheets</title>
	<para>Create a base directory to store everything such as <filename moreinfo="none"
	      class="directory">/usr/share/sgml/</filename>. Copy the DSSSL
			style sheets into a sub-directory named 
			<filename class="directory">dsssl</filename>.
	</para>
	</example>
</section>

<section id="dsssl-processors"> 
<title>DSSSL Processors</title>
<para>
	<indexterm><primary>jade</primary></indexterm> 
		There are two versions of the <application>Jade</application> processor: the
		  original version by James Clark; and an open-source
		  version of approximately the same program, <application>OpenJade</application>.
		  You only need <emphasis>one</emphasis> of these programs. It should
		  be installed <emphasis>after</emphasis> the DTD
		  and DSSSL have been <quote>installed.</quote>
</para>

	<variablelist>
	<title>DSSSL Transformation Tools</title>
	<varlistentry>
	<term>Jade</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	<ulink url="ftp://ftp.jclark.com/pub/jade/" /></para>
	<para>Currently, the latest version of the package is <filename>jade-1.2.1.tar.gz</filename>.</para>
	<para>Jade is the front-end processor for SGML and
	XML. It uses the DSSSL and DocBook DTD to perform the
	verification and rendering from SGML and XML into the target
	format.</para> 
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term>OpenJade</term>
	<listitem>
	<para><ulink
	url="http://openjade.sourceforge.net/">http://openjade.sourceforge.net/</ulink></para>
	<para>An extension of Jade written by the DSSSL
	community. Some applications require jade, but are being
	updated to support either software package.</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>

<section id="dsssl-setup">
<title>System Setup for DSSSL Transformations</title>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
	Tell your system where to find the SGML_CATALOG_FILES (yes, even if you
	are using XML). You can find an example of how to do this in <xref
	linkend="ex-catalog-files" />.
<!--
export
SGML_CATALOG_FILES=$_toolroot/dtd/docbook.cat:\
$_toolroot/dsssl/docbook/catalog:$_toolroot/jade-1.2.1/dsssl/catalog</command>
-->
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
	Download the DSSSL and DTD files and copy them into your working
	directory. You can find an example of how to do this in <xref
	linkend="ex-dsssl" /> and <xref linkend="ex-dtd" />.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
	
<section id="usingjade">
<title>Transformations with DSSSL</title>
<para>
	Once your system is configured (see the previous section), you should
	be able to start using <application>jade</application> to transform
	your files from XML to XHTML.
</para>

<!--
     <para>To do this you must add the following lines to the file
	<filename>/etc/sgml/catalog</filename>, by bringing it up under
	your favorite text editor:</para>

      <informalexample>
        <screen format="linespecific">
PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DOCUMENT DocBook HTML Stylesheet//EN"
  /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/nwalsh-modular/html/docbook.dsl<co id="html"/>

PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DOCUMENT DocBook Print Stylesheet//EN"
 /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/nwalsh-modular/print/docbook.dsl<co
 id="print"/>

PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DOCUMENT DSSSL Library//EN"
  /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/nwalsh-modular/lib/dblib.dsl

PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DOCUMENT DSSSL Library V2//EN"
  /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/nwalsh-modular/lib/dblib.dsl
</screen>
      </informalexample>
-->

<para>
	To create individual HTML files, point <application>jade</application>
	at the correct DSL (style sheet). The following example uses the LDP
	style sheet.
</para> 
<screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$ </prompt><command>jade -t xml -i html \
	-d /usr/local/sgml/dsssl/docbook/html/ldp.dsl#html \
	<replaceable>HOWTO.xml</replaceable></command>
</screen>

	<para>
		If you would like to produce a single-file HTML page, add the
		<parameter>-V nochunks</parameter> parameter. You can specify the 
		name of the final HTML file by appending the command with <parameter>
		&gt; <replaceable>output.html</replaceable></parameter>.
	</para>

<screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$ </prompt><command>jade -t xml -i html -V nochunks \
	-d /usr/local/sgml/dsssl/stylesheets/ldp.dsl#html \
	<replaceable>HOWTO.sgml</replaceable> &gt; output.html</command>
</screen>

<note id="dcl-errors">
	<title><emphasis>Not a function name</emphasis> errors</title>
	<para>
		If you get an error about <quote>is not a function name</quote>, you
		will need to add a pointer to <filename>xml.dcl</filename>. It has
		to be listed immediately before the pointer to your XML
		document. Try one of the following locations:
		<filename>/usr/lib/sgml/declaration/xml.dcl</filename>, or
		<filename>/usr/share/sgml/declaration/xml.dcl</filename>. Use
		<application>locate</application> to find the file if it is not in
		either of those two places. The modified command would be as
		follows:
	</para> 
	<screen>
<prompt>bash$ </prompt><command>jade -t xml -i html \
	-d /usr/local/sgml/dsssl/docbook/html/ldp.dsl#html \
	/usr/lib/sgml/declaration/xml.dcl <replaceable>HOWTO.xml</replaceable></command>
	</screen>
</note>

<para>
	If you would like to create print-friendly files instead of HTML files,
	simply change the style sheet that you are using. In the file name
	above, note <quote>html/ldp.dsl</quote> at the end. Change this to
	<quote>print/docbook.dsl</quote>, or if you want XHTML output, instead
	of HTML, change the file name to <quote>xhtml/docbook.dsl</quote>.
</para>

<section id="dsssl-css">
<title>Changing CSS Files</title>
	<para>If you want your HTML files to use a specific 
	<acronym>CSS</acronym> stylesheet, you will need to edit 
	<filename>ldp.dsl</filename>. Immediately after
 	<literal>;; End of $verbatim-display$ redefinition</literal> 
	add the following lines:</para>

<screen format="linespecific">
(define %stylesheet-type%
  ;; The type of the stylesheet to use
  "text/css")

(define %stylesheet%
  ;; Name of the css stylesheet to use, use value #f if you don't want to
  ;; use css stylesheets
  "base.css")
</screen>

	<para>
		Replace <filename>base.css</filename> with the name of the
		<acronym>CSS</acronym> file you would like to use.
	</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<!--Emma: I found that all these thingies you were talking about were way too difficult, no wonder people are objecting.  I've never bothered setting any variable at all, for instance, using the docbook-utils.  I took the liberty of adding a section about them. -->
<section id="docbook-utils"><title>The docbook-utils Package</title>
<para>The <application>docbook-utils</application> provide commands like <command>db2html</command>, <command>db2pdf</command> and <command>db2ps</command>, based on the <command>jw</command> scripts, that is a front-end to <application>Jade</application>.  These tools ease the everyday management of documentation and add comfortable features.</para>
<para>The package, originally created by RedHat and available from <ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/docbook-tools/" /> can be installed on most systems.</para>

<example id="ex-htmloutput">
<title>Example creating HTML output</title>
<para>After validating your document, simply issue the command
<command>db2html <filename>mydoc.xml</filename></command> to create (a)
HTML file(s).  You can also use the
<application>docbook-utils</application> as validation tools.  Remember: when errors occur, always start by solving only the first problem. The rest of the problems may be fixed when you fix the first error.</para>
<para>
	If you get errors about a function name, please read <xref linkend="dcl-errors" />.
</para>
</example>

<section id="stylesheets"><title>Using CSS and DSL for pretty output</title>
<para>You can define your own additional DSL instructions, which can
include a pointer to a personalized CSS file. Sample DSL and CSS files are
provided in <xref linkend="templates" />.</para>

<para>The sample DSL file will create a table of contents, and have all
HTML files start with the prefix <filename>intro2linux-</filename> and end
with a suffix of <filename>.html</filename>.  The
<varname>%stylesheet%</varname> variable points to the CSS file which
should be called by your HTML file.</para>

<para>To use a specific DSL style sheet the following command should be
used:</para>
<cmdsynopsis><command>db2html <option>-d</option> <filename>mystyle.dsl</filename> <filename>mydoc.xml</filename></command></cmdsynopsis>
<para>You can compare the result here: <ulink url="http://tille.soti.org/training/unix/" /> is a book formatted with the standard tools; <ulink url="http://tille.soti.org/training/tldp/" /> is one using personalized DSL and CSS files.  Soft tones and special effects, for instance in buttons, were used to achieve maximum effect.</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="xsl"> 
<title>XSL</title> 
<para>
	There are alternatives to DSSSL and Jade/OpenJade.</para>

<para>When working with DocBook XML, the LDP offers a series of 
      XSL<footnote><para>In truth, "XSL" is actually comprised of three
      components: the <emphasis>XSLT</emphasis> transformation language,
      the <emphasis>XPath</emphasis> expression language (used by XSLT), 
      and XSL Formatting Objects (FO) that are used for describing a page.
      The style sheets are actually written in XSLT and generate either HTML
      or (for print output) FO. The FO file is then run through a FO processor
      to create the actual print (PDF or PostScript) output. See the
      <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/WhatIsXSL.html">W3C web 
      site</ulink> for more information.</para></footnote>
      style sheets to process documents into HTML.  These style 
sheets create
      output files using the XML tool set that are similar to those produced by
      the SGML tools using <link linkend="dsssl">ldp.dsl</link>.
      </para>

      <para>The major difference between using <filename>ldp.dsl</filename>
      and the XSL style sheets is the way that the generation of multiple
      files is handled, such as the creation of a separate file for each chapter,
      section and appendix.  With the SGML tools, such as
      <application>jade</application> or
		<application>openjade</application>, the tool
      itself was responsible for generating the separate files. Because of
      this, only a single file, <filename>ldp.dsl</filename> was necessary as
      a customization layer for the standard DocBook DSSSL style sheets.
      </para>
      <para>With the DocBook XSL style sheets, generation of multiple files is
      controlled <emphasis>by the style sheet</emphasis>. If you want to
      generate a single file, you call one style sheet. If you want to generate
      multiple files, you call a different style sheet.  For that reason the
      LDP XSL style sheet distribution is comprised of four files:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>tldp-html.xsl</filename> - style sheet called to generate
      a <emphasis>single</emphasis> file.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>tldp-html-chunk.xsl</filename><footnote><para>In XSL
      terminology, the process of generating multiple files is referred to
      as "chunking".</para></footnote> - style sheet called to generate
      multiple files based on chapter, section and appendix elements.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>tldp-html-common.xsl</filename> - style sheet containing
      the actual XSLT transformations. It is called by the other two HTML
      style sheets and is <emphasis>never</emphasis> directly called.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>tldp-print.xsl</filename> - style sheet for generation of
      XSL Formatting Objects for print output.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
		
      <para>
      You can find the latest copy of the files at <ulink
      url="http://my.core.com/~dhorton/docbook/tldp-xsl/">http://my.core.com/~dhorton/docbook/tldp-xsl/</ulink>.
		The package includes installation instructions which are duplicated
		at <ulink
		url="http://my.core.com/~dhorton/docbook/tldp-xsl/doc/tldp-xsl-howto.html"
		/>. The short version of the install instructions is as follows: 
		Download and unzip the latest package from the web site. Take the 
		files from the <filename class="directory">html</filename> 
		directory of TLDP-XSL and put them in the
		<filename class="directory">html</filename> directory of Norman Walsh's 
		stylesheets. Take the file from the TLDP-XSL <filename
		class="directory">fo</filename> directory and put it in the Norman Walsh
		<filename class="directory">fo</filename> directory.
		</para>
    
	 <para>
	 	Once you have installed these files you can use
		<application>xsltproc</application> to generate HTML files from your
		XML documents. To transform your XML file(s) into a single-page HTML
		document use the following command:
    </para>
		
      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command> xsltproc -o <replaceable>HOWTO.html</replaceable> /usr/local/sgml/stylesheets/tldp-html.xsl <replaceable>HOWTO.xml</replaceable></command>
</screen>

    <para>To generate a set of linked HTML pages, with a separate page for each 
	 <sgmltag>chapter</sgmltag>, <sgmltag>sect1</sgmltag> or
	 <sgmltag>appendix</sgmltag>,  use the following
    command:
    </para>

      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$ </prompt><command>xsltproc /usr/share/sgml/stylesheets/tldp-html-chunk.xsl <replaceable>HOWTO.xml</replaceable></command>
</screen>

    <para>Note that you never directly call the style sheet
    <filename>tldp-html-common.xsl</filename>. It is called by both of the
    other two style sheets.
    </para>

<section id="xsl-css">
<title>Changing CSS Files</title>
	<para>If you want your HTML files to use a specific 
	<acronym>CSS</acronym> stylesheet, you will need to edit 
	<filename>tldp-html-common.xsl</filename>. Look for a line that
	ressembles <literal>&lt;xsl:param name="html.stylesheet"
	select="'style.css'"/&gt;</literal>.</para>
	
	<para>
		Replace <filename>style.css</filename> with the name of the
		<acronym>CSS</acronym> file you would like to use.
	</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="dtd">
<!-- not sure if this is in the right place.... -->
<title>DocBook DTD</title> 
<para>
	<indexterm><primary>DocBook DTD</primary></indexterm>
	The DocBook DTD defines the structure of a DocBook
		  document. It contains rules about how the elements
		  may be used; and what the elements ought to be
		  describing. For example: it is the DocBook DTD
		  which states all <sgmltag>warning</sgmltag>s are to
		  <emphasis>warn</emphasis> the reader (this is the
		  definition of the element); and may not contain
		  plain text (this is the content model--and the
		  bit which forces you to wrap your warning text
		  in a <sgmltag>para</sgmltag> or perhaps a list).
      </para>

		<caution><title>Versions</title><para>
			It is important that you download the
			version(s) that match your document. You
			may want to configure your system now to
			deal with <quote>all</quote> DocBook DTDs
			if you are going to be editing older LDP
			documents. If you are a new author, you
			only need the first one listed: XML DTD
			for DocBook version 4.2.
		</para></caution>

      <para>The XML DTD is available from <ulink
		url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2">http://www.oasis-open.org/xml/4.2/</ulink>.
		The LDP prefers this version of the DocBook DTD.
      </para>

      <para>
			If you are going to be working with SGML
			versions of DocBook you will need one
			(or both) of:
		<ulink
      url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/sgml/4.1/docbk41.zip">http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/sgml/4.1/docbk41.zip</ulink>
      or <ulink
      url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/sgml/3.1/docbk31.zip">http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/sgml/3.1/docbk31.zip</ulink>
		</para>
	
	<example id="ex-dtd">
	<title><quote>Installing</quote> DocBook Document Type Definitions</title>
	<para>Create a base directory to store everything such as <filename moreinfo="none"
	      class="directory">/opt/local/sgml/</filename>. Copy the DTDs 
			into a sub-directory named <filename class="directory">dtd</filename>.
	</para>
	</example>

	<warning><title>Do not edit DTD files</title><para>
		 The DocBook standard is described in these
		 files.  If you change these files, you are no longer working
		 with DocBook.
	</para></warning>
   </section>

<section id="doc-components">
<title>Formatting Documents</title>
    <section id="toc-articles">
      <title>Inserting a summary on the initial articles page</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>tools</primary> <secondary>articles</secondary>
	<tertiary>summary</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>A feature that might be valuable in some cases is
      the insertion of the summary on the initial page of an
      article. DocBook articles do not include it as a standard
      feature.</para>

      <para>To enable this, it is necessary to modify the style
      sheet file.</para>

<example>
<title>Style sheet to insert summaries in articles</title>
<programlisting>
&dsl-example;
</programlisting>
</example>

</section>

    <section id="automatic-indexes">
      <title>Inserting indexes automatically</title>

      <indexterm>
	<primary>tools</primary> <secondary>indexes</secondary>
	<tertiary>automatic generation</tertiary> <seealso>edition,
	index</seealso>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
	Although DocBook has markups for the composition of
	them, indexes are not generated automatically. The
	<command>collateindex.pl</command> command allows indexes
	to be generated from the source DocBook for inclusion into the
	finished/transformed document.
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Process the document with
	  <application>jade</application> using the style to
	  <glossterm><acronym>HTML</acronym></glossterm> with
	  the option <option>-V html-index</option>.</para>
	  <informalexample>
<screen>
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command>jade</command> <option>-t sgml \
	-d html/docbook.dsl -V html-index document.sgml</option>
</screen>
</informalexample>
</listitem> 
<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Generate the <filename>index.sgml</filename> file with
	    <command>collateindex.pl</command>.
	  </para> <informalexample>
<screen>
<prompt>bash$ </prompt> <command>perl</command> <option>collateindex.pl \
	-o index.sgml HTML.index</option>
</screen>
</informalexample>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

      <para>For the above example to work, it is necessary to define
      an <glossterm>external entity</glossterm> by calling the
      file <filename>index.sgml</filename>.</para>

      <example id="ex-entity-external-index">
	<title>Configuring an external entity to include the
	index</title>
	 <programlisting>
<sgmltag class="starttag">!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD
DocBook V3.1//EN" [

&lt;!-- Insertion of the index --&gt; &lt;!entity index SYSTEM
"index.sgml"&gt; ]</sgmltag>
	</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>See also <xref linkend="encoding-index"/> for information
      on how to
	  insert necessary information on the text.</para>

      <note><title>Odd behavior generating indexes for print versions</title>
	<para>Remember that if you're trying to get Tables of
	Contents or Indexes on PS or PDF output you'll need to
	run <application moreinfo="none">jadetex</application>
	or <application moreinfo="none">pdfjadetex</application>
	at least three times. This is required by <application
	moreinfo="none">TeX</application> but not by DocBook or
	related applications.</para>
      </note>
</section>
</section>

