    <section id="usingldpxsl">
      <title>Using the LDP XSL stylesheets</title>
      <para>When working with DocBook XML, the LDP uses a series of 
      XSL<footnote><para>In truth, "XSL" is actually comprised of three
      components: the <emphasis>XSLT</emphasis> transformation language,
      the <emphasis>XPath</emphasis> expression language (used by XSLT), 
      and XSL Formatting Objects (FO) that are used for describing a page.
      The stylesheets are actually written in XSLT and generate either HTML
      or (for print output) FO. The FO file is then run through a FO processor
      to create the actual print (PDF or PostScript) output. See the
      <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/WhatIsXSL.html">W3C web 
      site</ulink> for more information.</para></footnote>
      stylesheets to process documents into HTML.  These stylesheets create
      output files using the XML toolset that are similar to those produced by
      the SGML tools using <link linkend="usingldpdsssl">ldp.dsl</link>.
      </para>
      <note>
      <para>At the current time, the LDP XSL stylesheets are still in 
      development and may not have all the functionality found in 
      <filename>ldp.dsl</filename>. Specifically, the XSL-FO stylesheet for 
      creating print documents has not yet been created.  If you need PDF
      or other print output, you will need to use the SGML toolset and
      ldp.dsl.</para>
      </note>
      <para>The major difference between using <filename>ldp.dsl</filename>
      and the XSL stylesheets is the way that the generation of multiple
      files is handled, i.e. the creation of a separate file for each chapter,
      section and appendix.  With the SGML tools, such as
      <emphasis>jade</emphasis> or <emphasis>openjade</emphasis>, the tool
      itself was responsible for generating the separate files. Because of
      this, only a single file, <filename>ldp.dsl</filename> was necessary as
      a customization layer for the standard DocBook DSSSL stylesheets.
      </para>
      <para>With the DocBook XSL stylesheets, generation of multiple files is
      controlled <emphasis>by the stylesheet</emphasis>. If you want to
      generate a single file, you call one stylesheet. If you want to generate
      multiple files, you call a different stylesheet.  For that reason the
      LDP XSL stylesheet distribution is comprised of four files:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>ldp-html.xsl</filename> - stylesheet called to generate
      a <emphasis>single</emphasis> file.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>ldp-html-chunk.xsl</filename><footnote><para>In XSL
      terminology, the process of generating multiple files is referred to
      as "chunking".</para></footnote> - stylesheet called to generate
      multiple files based on chapter, section and appendix elements.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>ldp-html-common.xsl</filename> - stylesheet containing
      the actual XSLT transformations. It is called by the other two HTML
      stylesheets and is <emphasis>never</emphasis> directly called.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para><filename>ldp-print.xsl</filename> - stylesheet for generation of
      XSL Formatting Objects for print output. <emphasis>(Currently this 
      file is a placeholder and has not been customized.)</emphasis>
      </para>
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
      You can find the latest copy of the files at <ulink
      url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/tools/ldp-xsl.zip">http://www.tldp.org/authors/tools/ldp-xsl.zip</ulink>.</para>
      <para>Once you have the file, you may need to do some editing of
      the first few lines based on the location of your DocBook XSL
      files.</para>
      <para>Unzip the files into a directory where you will call them.
      You will then need to modify the files for your local installtion
      of the DocBook XSL stylesheets from Norman Walsh.</para>
      
      <para>First open up <filename>ldp-html.xsl</filename> and look for the
      following line:
      </para>
      <informalexample>
        <screen format="linespecific">
<![CDATA[
<xsl:import href="/usr/share/sgml/docbook/docbook-xsl-1.44/html/docbook.xsl"/>
]]>
</screen>
      </informalexample>
      <para>Modify that path if necessary to point to where you have the
      <filename>docbook.xsl</filename> stylesheet installed.
      </para>
      <para>Next open up <filename>ldp-html-chunk.xsl</filename> and look for
      the line:
      </para>
      <informalexample>
        <screen format="linespecific">
<![CDATA[
<xsl:import href="/usr/share/sgml/docbook/docbook-xsl-1.44/html/chunk.xsl"/>
]]>
</screen>
      </informalexample>
      <para>Modify that path if necessary to point to where you have the
      <filename>chunk.xsl</filename> stylesheet installed.
      </para>
      <para>With that complete, you can now generate HTML files.  To generate
      a single HTML file from your DocBook XML file, use the command:</para>

      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command> xsltproc -o <replaceable>outputfilename.xml</replaceable> /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/ldp-html.xsl <replaceable>inputfilename.xml</replaceable></command>
</screen>

    <note><para>This example uses Daniel Veillard's <command>xsltproc</command>
    command available as part of <command>libxslt</command> from 
<ulink url="http://www.xmlsoft.org/XSLT/">http://www.xmlsoft.org/XSLT/</ulink>.
    If you are using other XML processors such as Xalan or Saxon, you will
    need to change the command line appropriately.
    </para></note>

    <para>To generate a set of linked HTML pages, with a separate page for each 
    <![CDATA[<chapter>, <sect1> or <appendix>]]> tag,  use the following
    command:
    </para>
      <screen format="linespecific">
<prompt>bash$</prompt> <command> xsltproc /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/ldp-html-chunk.xsl <replaceable>filename.xml</replaceable></command>
</screen>

    <para>Note that you never directly call the stylesheet
    <filename>ldp-html-common.xsl</filename>. It is called by both of the
    other two stylesheets.
    </para>
    <para>At the current time, the print stylesheet, <filename>ldp-print.xsl</filename>
    has not been developed and provides no additional functions or
    customizations to the standard DocBook XSL stylesheets.
    </para>
    </section>
