<!-- 
	<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN'>
-->
<appendix id="docbook">
	<title>Converting Documents to DocBook XML</title>
  
    <section id="xmldifferences">
      <title>Differences between XML and SGML</title>
      <para>
        There are a few changes between DocBook XML and SGML.  Handling
        these differences should be relatively easy for most small documents,
        and many authors will not need to make any changes
		to convert their documents other than the XML and DocBook 
		declarations at the start of their document.
      </para>

      <para>
        For others, here is a list of what you should keep in mind
        when converting your documents from SGML to XML.
      </para>

	  <note>
	  <para>
	  	An element typically has three parts: the start tag,
		the content (your words) and the end tag. Qualifiers
		are added in the start tag and are known as
		attributes. They will always have a name and a
		quoted value.</para>
	  <screen>
&lt;filename class="directory"&gt;/usr/local&lt;filename&gt;
	</screen>
	  <para>
	  The start tag contains one attribute (class)
	  with a value of directory. The end tag (also filename)
	  must not contain any attributes.
	  </para>
	  </note>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Element names (tags) and their attributes are 
			case-dependent--typically lowercase. 
			The following will not validate because the end tag
			&lt;PARA&gt; is uppercase:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;para&gt;This part will fail XML validation&lt;/PARA&gt;
</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Most XML-specific tags (like entity)
            have to be in all capital letters (ENTITY).
          </para>
        </listitem>


        <listitem>
          <para>
            All attributes in the start tag must be
			"quoted".  This can
            be either single (') or double (") quotes, but
			not
            reverse (`) or <quote>smart quotes</quote>. 
			The quote used to start a name="value"
			pair must be the same quote used at the end of
			the value. In other words: "this" would
			validate, but 'that" would not.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Tags that have a start tag, but no end tag are
			referred to as <quote>empty</quote> because they do
			not contain (wrap around) anything. These tags must still be
			closed with a trailing slash (/). For example: 
			<sgmltag>xref</sgmltag> must be written as 
			&lt;xref linkend="software"/&gt;. You may not 
			have any spaces between the / and &gt;.
			(Although you may have a space after the final
			attribute: &lt;xref linkend="foo" /&gt;.)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Processing instructions that get sent to the DSSSL
            must have a question mark at the
            end of the tag.  The XML version of this tag
			would look like this:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;?dbhtml filename="foo"?&gt;
</screen>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you're converting from SGML to XML, be sure 
			file names refer to .xml files instead of .sgml.  
			Some tools may get confused if a .sgml file contains XML.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Tag minimizations were used in SGML instead of
			writing out the element name in the end tag.
			e.g. <sgmltag>para</sgmltag>This is foo.<sgmltag
			class="endtag"></sgmltag> Tag minimizations are
			not supported in XML and their use is
			discouraged in DocBook.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="differences">
      <title>Changing DTDs</title>
      <para>
        The big changes between version changes in the DTD
		involve changed elements (tags). Elements may be:
		depricated (which means they will be removed in
		future versions); removed; modified; or added.
		Almoost all authors will run into a changed or 
		depricated tag when going to from a lower version 
		of DocBook to a higher version (e.g. 3.x to 4.x).
	</para>
	<para>
		The <citetitle>DocBook: The Definitive Guide</citetitle> does
		an excellent job of showing you how elements fit
		together. For each element it tells you what an
		element must contain (its content model) and what is
		may be contained in (who its parents are). For
		example: a <sgmltag>note</sgmltag> must contain a
		<sgmltag>para</sgmltag>. If you try to write
		&lt;note&gt;Content in a
		note&lt;/note&gt; your document will not validate.
		Learning how elements are assembled will make it a
		lot easier to understand any validation errors that
		are thrown at you. If you get trully stuck you can
		also email the LDP's docbook mailing list for extra
		hints. Information on subscribing is available from
		<xref linkend="mailinglists" />
	</para>
	<para>
        All tags that have been depricated or changed for 4.x are listed
        in <citetitle>DocBook: The definitive guide</citetitle>, 
		published by O'Reilly and Associates. This book is
		also available online from <ulink
		url="http://www.docbook.org">http://www.docbook.org</ulink>.
      </para>

	<section id="differences3040">
	<title>Differences between version 3.x and 4.x</title>
	<para>
		Here are a few elements that are of particular
		relevence to LDP authors:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag>artheader</sgmltag></title>
			<para>has been changed to
			<sgmltag>articleinfo</sgmltag>.
            Most other header elements have been renamed to info.
          </para>
			 </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag>graphic</sgmltag></title> 
			<para>has being depricated and will be removed as of DocBook 5.x.
			To prepare for this, start using 
			<sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag>. There is more
			information about <sgmltag>mediaobject</sgmltag>
			in <xref linkend="inserting-pictures"/>.
          </para>
			 </formalpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag>imagedata</sgmltag></title>
				<para>file formats
			must now be written in UPPERCASE letters. If you 
			use lowercase or mixed-case spellings
            for your file formats, it will fail.
          </para>
			 </formalpara>
          <para>
            Valid:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;imagedata format="EPS" fileref="foo.eps"&gt;
</screen>
          <para>
            Invalid:
          </para>
<screen>
&lt;imagedata format="eps" fileref="foo.eps"&gt;
</screen>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>
</appendix>  
