<appendix id="gfsfsim"><title>OpenGFS file system interface module</title>

<para>
The OpenGFS FSIM lets EVMS users create and manage OpenGFS 
file systems from within the EVMS interfaces.  
In order to use the OpenGFS FSIM, the OpenGFS utilities must be
installed on your system.  Go to 
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/opengfs">http://sourceforge.net/projects/opengfs</ulink> for the OpenGFS project.
</para>

<sect1 id="createopengfsfsim"><title>Creating OpenGFS file systems</title>
<para>
OpenGFS file systems can be created with <command>mkfs</command> on any EVMS
or compatibility volume that does not already
have a file system and that is produced from a shared cluster container.  
The following options are available for creating
OpenGFS file systems:</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>blocksize</term>
<listitem>
<para>Set the file system block size.
The block size is in bytes.
The block size must be a power of 2 between 512 and 65536, inclusive.
The default block size is 4096 bytes.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>journals</term>
<listitem>
<para>The names of the journal volumes, one for each node.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>protocol</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specify the name of the locking protocol to use.
The choices are "memexp" and "opendlm."
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>lockdev</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specify the shared volume to be used to contain the locking metadata.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>
The OpenGFS FSIM only takes care of file system operations.
It does not take care of OpenGFS cluster and node configuration.
Before the volumes can be mounted, you must configure the cluster and
node separately after you have made the file system and saved the changes.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="checkopengfsfsim"><title>Checking OpenGFS file systems</title>
<para>
The OpenGFS utility for checking the file system has no additional options.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="removeopengfsfsim"><title>Removing OpenGFS file systems</title>
<para>
An OpenGFS file system can be removed from its volume if the file system is
unmounted.  This operation involves erasing the superblock from the volume,
erasing the log headers for the journal volumes, and erasing the control
block on the cluster configuration volume associated with the file
system volume so that the file system will not be recognized in the future.
There are no options available for removing file systems.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="expandshrinkopengfsfsim"><title>Expanding and shrinking OpenGFS
file systems</title>

<para>
OpenGFS only allows a volume to be expanded.  
OpenGFS only allows a volume to expanded when the volume is mounted.
An OpenGFS file system is automatically expanded when its volume is
expanded.
</para>

</sect1>

</appendix>

