<appendix id="xfsfsim"><title>XFS file system interface module</title>

<para>
The XFS FSIM lets EVMS users create and manage XFS file systems from
within the EVMS interfaces.  In order to use the XFS FSIM, version 2.0.0 or
later of the XFS utilities must be installed on your system.  The latest
version of XFS can be found at 
<ulink url="http://oss.sgi.com/projects/xfs/">http://oss.sgi.com/projects/xfs/</ulink>.
</para>

<sect1 id="createxfsfsim"><title>Creating XFS file systems</title>
<para>
XFS file systems can be created with <command>mkfs</command> on any EVMS
or compatibility volume that does not already
have a file system.  The following options are available for creating
XFS file systems:</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>vollabel</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specify a volume label for the file system.  The default is none.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>journalvol</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specify the volume to use for an external journal. 
The default is none.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>logsize</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Specify the inline log size (in MB).  This option is only available if
the journalvol option is not set.  The default is 4 MB; the
allowed range is 2 to 256 MB.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="checkxfsfsim"><title>Checking XFS file systems</title>
<para>
The following options are available for checking XFS file systems with
<command>fsck</command>:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>readonly</term>
<listitem>
<para>Check the file system is in read-only mode.  Report but do not
fix errors.  The default is false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry><term>verbose</term>
<listitem>
<para>Display details and debugging information during the check.
The default is false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="removexfsfsim"><title>Removing XFS file systems</title>

<para>
An XFS file system can be removed from its volume if the file system is
unmounted.  This operation involves erasing the superblock from the volume
so the file system will not be recognized in the future.  There are no
options available for removing file systems.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="expandxfsfsim"><title>Expanding XFS file systems</title>

<para>
An XFS file system is automatically expanded when its volume is expanded.
However, XFS only allows the volume to be expanded if it is mounted,
because XFS performs all of its expansions online.  
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="shrinkxfsfsim"><title>Shrinking XFS file systems</title>

<para>
At this time, XFS does not support shrinking its file systems.
Hence, volumes with XFS file systems cannot be shrunk.
</para>

</sect1>

</appendix>

