<appendix id="appxcsm"><title>The CSM plug-in</title>

<para>The Cluster Segment Manager (CSM) is the EVMS plug-in that identifies and
manages cluster storage.  The CSM protects disk storage objects by writing metadata
at the start and end of the disk, which prevents other plug-ins from attempting to use the disk.
Other plug-ins can look at the disk, but they cannot see their own metadata signatures
and cannot consume the disk.  The protection that CSM provides allows the CSM to
discover cluster storage and present it in an appropriate fashion to the system. </para>
<para>All cluster storage disk objects must be placed in containers that have the
following attributes:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>cluster ID that identifies the cluster management software
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>node ID that identifies the owner of the disk objects
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>storage type: private, shared, or deported
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
The CSM plug-in reads metadata and constructs containers that consume
the disk object.  Each disk provides a usable area, mapped as an EVMS
data segment, but only if the disk is accessible to the node viewing
the storage.</para>

<para>The CSM plug-in performs these operations:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
examines disk objects
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
creates containers
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
uses the containers to consume disk objects
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
produces data segment objects if the disk is accessible to the node
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<sect1 id="csmassn"><title>Assigning the CSM plug-in</title>
<para>Assigning a segment manager to a disk means that you want the plug-in to
manage partitions on the disk.  In order to do this, the plug-in needs to create and
maintain appropriate metadata.  The CSM creates the follow three segments on the disk:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>primary metadata segment</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>usable area data segment</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>secondary metadata segment</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
<para>The CSM collects the information it needs to perform the assign operation with the
following options:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>NodeId</term>
<listitem><para>Choose only from a list of configured node IDs that have been
provided to the CSM by clustering software.  The default selection is the
node from which you are running the EVMS user interface.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Container Name</term>
<listitem><para>The name for the container.  You need to keep this name unique
across the cluster to prevent name-in-conflict errors should the container fail over to
another node that has a container with the same name.  
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Storage Type</term>
<listitem><para>Can be either: share, private, or deported. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Note that you would typically assign the CSM to a disk when you want to
add a disk to an existing CSM container.  If you are creating a new container, you
have a choice of using either:
<menuchoice>
<guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Container</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> or
<menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Add</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Segment Manager</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>

<para>If the container doesn't exist, it will be created for the disk.  If the container already
exists, the disk will be added to it.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="unassignCSM"><title>Unassigning the CSM plug-in</title>
<para>Unassigning a CSM plug-in results in the CSM removing its metadata from
the specified disk storage object.  The result is that the disk has no segments
mapped and appears as a raw disk object.  The disk is removed from the
container that consumed it and the data segment is removed as well.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1><title>Deleting a CSM container</title>

<para>An existing CSM container cannot be deleted if it is producing any data segments, 
because other EVMS plug-ins might be building higher-level objects on the CSM objects.
To delete a CSM container, first remove disk objects from the container.  When the last
disk is removed, the container is also removed.</para>
</sect1>
	      
</appendix>

