

<appendix id="reiserfsim"><title>ReiserFS file system interface module</title>

<para>
The ReiserFS FSIM lets EVMS users create and manage ReiserFS file systems from
within the EVMS interfaces.  In order to use the 
ReiserFS FSIM, version 3.x.0 or
later of the ReiserFS utilities must be installed on your system.  
In order to get full functionality from the ReiserFS FSIM, use version
3.x.1b or later. The latest
version of ReiserFS can be found at 
<ulink url="http://www.namesys.com/">http://www.namesys.com/</ulink>.
</para>

<sect1 id="createreiserfsim"><title>Creating ReiserFS file systems</title>
<para>
ReiserFS file systems can be created with <command>mkfs</command> on any EVMS
or compatibility volume that does not already
have a file system.  The following option is available for creating
ReiserFS file systems:</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>vollabel</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specify a volume label for the file system.  The default is none.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="checkreiserfsim"><title>Checking ReiserFS file systems</title>
<para>
The following option is available for checking XFS file systems with
<command>fsck</command>:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>mode</term>
<listitem>
<para>There are three possible modes for checking a ReiserFS file system:
Check Read-Only, Fix, and Rebuild Tree."</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="removexreiserfsim"><title>Removing ReiserFS file systems</title>

<para>
A ReiserFS file system can be removed from its volume if the file system is
unmounted.  This operation involves erasing the superblock from the volume
so the file system will not be recognized in the future.  There are no
options available for removing file systems.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="expandreiserFSfsim"><title>Expanding ReiserFS file systems</title>

<para>
A ReiserFS file system is automatically expanded when its volume is expanded.
ReiserFS file systems can be expanded if the volume is mounted or
unmounted.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="shrinkreiserfsim"><title>Shrinking ReiserFS file systems</title>

<para>
A ReiserFS file system is automatically shrunk if the volume is shrunk.
ReiserFS file systems can only be shrunk if the volume is unmounted.
</para>

</sect1>

</appendix>