
<appendix id="ext23fsim"><title>Ext-2/3 file system interface module</title>

<para>
The Ext-2/3 FSIM lets EVMS users create and manage Ext2 and
Ext3 file systems from
within the EVMS interfaces.  In order to use the Ext-2/3 FSIM, 
the e2fsprogs package 
must be installed on your system.  The e2fsprogs package
can be found at 
<ulink url="http://e2fsprogs.sourceforge.net/">http://e2fsprogs.sourceforge.net/</ulink>.
</para>

<sect1 id="createext23fsim"><title>Creating Ext-2/3 file systems</title>
<para>
Ext-2/3 file systems can be created with <command>mkfs</command> on any EVMS
or compatibility volume that does not already
have a file system.  The following options are available for creating
Ext-2/3 file systems:</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>badblocks</term>
<listitem>
<para>Perform a read-only check for bad blocks on the volume
before creating the file system.  The default is false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>badblocks_rw</term>
<listitem>
<para>Perform a read/write check for bad blocks on the volume before
creating the file system.  The default is false.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>vollabel</term>
<listitem>
<para>Specify a volume label for the file system.  The default is none.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>journal</term>
<listitem>
<para>Create a journal for use with the Ext2 file system.  The default
is true.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="checkext23fsim"><title>Checking Ext-2/3 file systems</title>
<para>
The following options are available for checking Ext-2/3 file systems with
<command>fsck</command>:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>force</term>
<listitem>
<para>Force a complete file system check, even if the file system is
already marked clean.  The default is false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>readonly</term>
<listitem>
<para>Check the file system is in read-only mode.  Report but do not
fix errors.  If the file system is mounted, this option is
automatically selected.  The default is false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry><term>badblocks</term>
<listitem>
<para>Check for bad blocks on the volume and mark them as busy.  The
default is false.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>badblocks_rw</term>
<listitem>
<para>Perform a read-write check for bad blocks on the volume and mark
them as busy. The default is false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="removeext23fsim"><title>Removing Ext-2/3 file systems</title>

<para>
An Ext-2/3 file system can be removed from its volume if the file system is
unmounted.  This operation involves erasing the superblock from the volume
so the file system will not be recognized in the future.  There are no
options available for removing file systems.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="expandshrinkext23fsim"><title>Expanding and shrinking Ext-2/3 
file systems</title>

<para>
An Ext-2/3 file system is automatically expanded or shrunk when its volume 
is expanded or shrunk.
However, Ext-2/3 only allows these operations if the volume is
unmounted, because online expansion and shrinkage is not yet supported.
</para>

</sect1>

</appendix>
