<chapter id="displaydetails"><title>Obtaining interface display details</title>

<para>The EVMS interfaces let you view more detailed information about an EVMS object than 
what is readily available from the main views of the EVMS user interfaces.  The type and extent
of additional information available is dependent on the interface you use.  For example, the
EVMS GUI provides more in-depth information than does the CLI.</para>

<para>The following sections show how to find detailed information on the region
<filename>lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region</filename>, which is part of
volume <filename>/dev/evms/Sample Volume</filename> (created in section 10.2).</para>

<sect1 id="displaygui"><title>Using the EVMS GUI</title>
<para>With the EVMS GUI, it is only possible to display additional details on an object through
the Context Sensitive Menus, as shown in the following steps:

<orderedlist><listitem><para>Looking at the <guibutton>volumes view</guibutton>, click the &quot;+&quot; next
to volume <filename>/dev/evms/Sample Volume</filename>.  Alternatively, look at the <guimenu>regions</guimenu> view.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Right click <filename>lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region</filename>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Point at <guibutton>Display Details...</guibutton> and click.  A new window opens
with additional information about the selected region.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Click <guimenu>More</guimenu> by the <guibutton>Logical Extents box</guibutton>.  Another window opens that displays the mappings of logical extents to physical extents.</para>
</listitem></orderedlist>


</para></sect1>

<sect1 id="displaydatancurses"><title>Using Ncurses</title>
<para>Follow these steps to display additional details on an object with Ncurses:

<orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>Press
	<keycap>Tab</keycap> to reach the Storage Regions view.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Scroll down using the <keycap>down</keycap> arrow until
	 <filename>lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region</filename> is highlighted.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>In the context menu, scroll down using the <keycap>down</keycap> arrow 
	to highlight &quot;Display Details...&quot;
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to activate the menu item.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>In the Detailed Information dialog, use the <keycap>down</keycap> arrow to
	highlight the &quot;Logical Extents&quot; item and then use <keycap>spacebar</keycap> to open
	another window that displays the mappings of logical extents to physical extents.
	</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>
</para></sect1>

<sect1><title>Using the CLI</title>
<para>Use the
	<command>query</command> command (abbreviated <command>q</command>) with filters to display details about EVMS objects.  There are two filters that are especially helpful for navigating
within the command line: <command>list options</command> (abbreviated <command>lo</command>) and <command>extended info</command> (abbreviated <command>ei</command>). </para>
<para>The <command>list options</command> command tells you what can currently be done and what options you
can specify.  To use this command, first build a traditional query command starting with the command name <command>query</command>, followed by a colon (<command>:</command>), and then the type of object you
want to query (for example, volumes, objects, plug-ins).  Then, you can use filters to narrow
the search to only the area you are interested in.  For example, to determine the acceptable
actions at the current time on <filename>lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region</filename>, enter the following command:</para>

<programlisting>query: regions, region=&quot;lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region&quot;, list options</programlisting>

<para>The <command>extended info</command> filter is the equivalent of Display Details in the EVMS GUI and Ncurses interfaces.  The command takes the following form: <command>query</command>, followed by a colon (<command>:</command>), the filter (<command>extended info</command>), a comma (<command>,</command>), and the object you want more information about.  The command returns a list containing the field names, titles, descriptions and values for each field defined for the object.  For example, to obtain details on <filename>lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region</filename>, enter the following command:</para>

<programlisting>query: extended info, &quot;lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region&quot;</programlisting>

<para>Many of  the field names that are returned by the <command>extended info</command> filter can be expanded
further by specifying the field name or names at the end of the command, separated
by commas.  For example, if you wanted additional information about logical extents, the query would look like the following:</para>

<programlisting>query: extended info, &quot;lvm/Sample Container/Sample Region&quot;, Extents</programlisting>

</sect1>
</chapter>

