
<chapter id="debuglevels"><title>The EVMS log file and error data collection</title>

<para>This chapter discusses the EVMS information and error log file and the various logging levels.  It also explains how to change the logging level.</para>


<sect1 id="FSIMsupp"><title>About the EVMS log file</title>
<para>The EVMS Engine creates a log file called <filename>/var/log/evmsEngine.log</filename> every time the Engine is opened.  The Engine also saves copies of up to nine previous Engine sessions in the files <filename>/var/log/evmsEngine.n.log</filename>, where <filename>n</filename> is the number of the session between 1 and 9.  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="loglevels"><title>Log file logging levels</title>
<para>There are several possible logging levels that you can choose to be collected in <filename>/var/log/evmsEngine.log</filename>.  The &quot;lowest&quot; logging level, <filename>critical</filename>, collects only messages about serious system problems, whereas the &quot;highest&quot; level, <filename>everything</filename>, collects all logging related messages.  When you specify a particular logging level, the Engine collects messages for that level and all the levels below it.  </para>

<para>The following table lists the allowable log levels and the information they provide:</para>	
<para><table><title>EVMS logging levels</title><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colnum="1" colname="C1"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="C2"/>
<thead><row><entry>Level name</entry>
<entry>Description</entry> </row></thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Critical</entry><entry>The health of the system or the Engine is in jeopardy; for example, an operation has failed because there is not enough memory.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Serious</entry><entry>An operation did not succeed.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Error</entry><entry>The user has caused an error.  The error messages are provided to help the user correct the problem.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Warning</entry><entry>An error has occurred that the system might or might not be able to work around.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Default</entry><entry>An error has occurred that the system has already worked around.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Details</entry><entry>Detailed information about the system.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Entry_Exit</entry><entry>Traces the entries and exits of functions.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Debug</entry><entry>Information that helps the user debug a problem.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Extra</entry><entry>More information that helps the user debug a problem than the &quot;Debug&quot; level provides.</entry></row>
<row><entry>Everything</entry><entry>Verbose output.</entry></row>
</tbody></tgroup></table></para>

		
</sect1>
<sect1 id="specifylevels"><title>Specifying the logging levels</title>
<para>By default, when any of the EVMS interfaces is opened, the Engine logs the <filename>Default</filename> level of messages into the <filename>/var/log/evmsEngine.log</filename> file.  However, if your system is having problems and you want to see more of what is happening, you can change the logging level to be higher; if you want fewer logging messages, you can change the logging level to be lower.  To change the logging level, specify the <command>-d</command> parameter and the log level on the interface open call.  The following examples show how to open the various interfaces with the highest logging level (<filename>everything</filename>):</para>
<programlisting>GUI:		evmsgui -d everything</programlisting>
<programlisting>Ncurses:	evmsn -d everything</programlisting>
<programlisting>CLI:		evms -d everything</programlisting>

<note><title>NOTE</title>
<para>If you use the EVMS mailing list for help with a problem, providing to us
the log file that is created when you open one of the interfaces (as shown 
in the previous commands) makes it easier for us to help you.
</para>
</note>

<para>The EVMS GUI lets you change the logging level during an Engine session.  To do so, follow these steps:

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Log Level</guimenuitem>
	<guimenuitem>Engine</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Click the <guibutton>Level</guibutton> you want.
	</para></listitem>
</orderedlist></para>

<para>The CLI command, <command>probe</command>, opens and closes the Engine, which causes a new log to start.  The log that existed before the <command>probe</command> command was issued is renamed <filename>/var/log/evmsEngine.1.log</filename> and the new log is named <filename>/var/log/evmsEngine.log</filename>.</para>

<para>
If you will be frequently using a different log level than the default,
you can specify the default logging level in 
<filename>/etc/evms.conf</filename> rather than
having to use the <command>-d</command> option when starting the user interface.
The "debug_level" option in the "engine" section sets the default
logging level for when the Engine is opened.  
Using the <command>-d</command> option
during the command invocation overrides the setting in
<filename>/etc/evms.conf</filename>.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
