<chapter id="evmsmigrate"><title>Viewing Compatibility Volumes after Migrating</title>
<para>Migrating to EVMS allows you to have the flexibility of EVMS without losing the integrity of your existing data. EVMS discovers existing volume management volumes as compatibility volumes. After you have installed EVMS, you can view your existing volumes with the interface of your choice. </para>

<sect1 id="guimigrate"><title>Using the EVMS GUI</title>
<para>If you are using the EVMS GUI as your preferred interface, you can view your migrated volumes by typing <command>evmsgui</command> at the command prompt. The following screen appears listing your migrated volumes. </para>

<figure><title>GUI Start-up Window</title>
<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="gui.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>GUI start-up window</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure></sect1>



<sect1 id="ncurmigrate"><title>Using Ncurses</title>

	<para>If you are using the Ncurses interface, you can view your migrated volumes by 
	typing <command>evmsn</command> at the command prompt. The following screen will 
	appear listing your migrated volumes. </para>

	<figure><title>Ncurses Start-up Window</title>
<mediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref="n.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
<textobject>
	<phrase>Ncurses Start-up Window</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="climigrate"><title>Using the CLI</title>
	<para>If you are using the Command Line Interpreter (CLI) interface, you can view 
	your migrated volumes by typing the following:</para>

	<orderedlist><listitem><para>Start the Command Line Interpreter by typing 
		<command>evms</command> at the command line.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Query the volumes by typing the following at the 
		<prompt>EVMS</prompt> prompt:</para>

		<programlisting>query:volumes</programlisting>
		<para>Your migrated volumes are displayed as results of the 
		query. </para></listitem></orderedlist>

		<figure><title>CLI Volume Query Results</title>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="cli.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
		<textobject><phrase>CLI Volume Query</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="lvmmigrate"><title>Using Linux LVM Emulation Tools</title>
	<para>If you are using the EVMS emulation of the Linux LVM command set, you can view 
	your Linux LVM migrated volumes by typing the following command:
	<programlisting>evms_lvscan</programlisting></para>

<para>The following screen appears listing your migrated volumes.</para>

<figure><title>EVMS Emulation of Linux LVM</title>

<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="lvm.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>EVMS Emulation of Linux LVM to view Linux LVM volumes.</phrase></textobject></mediaobject></figure></sect1></chapter>





