<chapter id="intro"><title>What is EVMS?</title>

<para>EVMS brings a new model of volume management to Linux&reg;. 
EVMS integrates all aspects of volume management, 
such as disk partitioning, Linux logical volume manager (LVM) and 
multi-disk (MD) management, and file system operations into a single 
cohesive package. 
With EVMS, various volume management technologies are accessible through 
one interface, and new technologies can be added as plug-ins as they are developed.</para>

<sect1 id="cando"><title>Why choose EVMS?</title>
	<para>EVMS lets you manage storage space in a way that is more 
intuitive and flexible than many other Linux volume management systems. 
Practical tasks, such as migrating disks or adding new disks to your 
Linux system, become more manageable with EVMS because EVMS can  
recognize and read from different volume types and file systems. 
EVMS provides additional safety controls by not allowing commands that are
unsafe.
These controls help maintain the integrity of the data stored on the system.</para>

<para>You can use EVMS  to create and manage data storage. 
With EVMS, you can use multiple volume management technologies under one 
framework while ensuring your system still interacts correctly with 
stored data. 
With EVMS, you are can use drive linking, shrink and expand volumes, 
create snapshots of your volumes, and set up RAID 
(redundant array of independent devices) features for your system. 
You can also use many types of file systems and manipulate these storage pieces 
in ways that best meet the needs of your particular work environment.</para>

<para>EVMS also provides the capability to manage data on storage that is
physically shared by nodes in a cluster.  This shared storage allows data to
be highly available from different nodes in the cluster.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="uis"><title>The EVMS user interfaces</title>

<para>There are currently three user interfaces available for EVMS: graphical (GUI), text mode (Ncurses), and the Command Line Interpreter (CLI). 
Additionally, you can use the EVMS Application Programming Interface to implement your own customized user interface. </para>
<para><xref linkend="userinterf"></xref> tells more about each of the EVMS user interfaces.

</para>
<table id="userinterf" frame="all"><title>EVMS user interfaces</title>
<tgroup cols="4"><colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1in"></colspec><colspec colnum="2" colwidth="1.5in"></colspec><colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1in"></colspec><colspec colnum="4" colwidth="2.5in"></colspec>
<thead><row><entry>User interface</entry>
<entry>Typical user</entry>
<entry>Types of use</entry>
<entry>Function</entry></row></thead>
<tbody><row><entry>GUI</entry>
<entry>All</entry>
<entry>All uses except automation</entry>
<entry>Allows you to choose from available options only, instead of having to sort through all the options, including ones that are not available at that point in the process. </entry></row>
<row><entry>Ncurses</entry>
<entry>Users who don't have GTK libraries or X Window Systems on their machines</entry>
<entry>All uses except automation</entry>
<entry>Allows you to choose from available options only, instead of having to sort through all the options, including ones that are not available at that point in the process. </entry></row>
<row><entry>Command Line</entry>
<entry>Expert</entry>
<entry>All uses</entry>
<entry>Allows easy automation of  tasks</entry></row>
</tbody></tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="terminology">
<title>EVMS terminology</title>
	<para>To avoid confusion with other terms that describe volume 
	management in general, EVMS uses a specific set of terms. 
	These terms are listed, from most fundamental to most comprehensive, 
	as follows:
	</para>

		<variablelist>

		<varlistentry><term>Logical disk</term>
		<listitem><para>Representation of anything EVMS can access as a physical disk. 
		In EVMS, physical disks are logical disks.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

                <varlistentry><term>Sector</term>
		<listitem><para>The lowest level of addressability on a block
		device. This definition is in keeping with the standard
		meaning found in other management systems.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Disk segment</term>
		<listitem><para>An ordered set of physically contiguous
		sectors residing on the same storage object. 
		The general analogy for a segment is to a traditional disk
		partition, such as DOS or OS/2 &reg;</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Storage region</term>
		<listitem><para>An ordered set of logically contiguous sectors
		that  are not necessarily physically contiguous. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Storage object</term>
		<listitem><para>Any persistent memory structure in EVMS that can be used to 
		build objects or create a volume. Storage object is a  generic term for disks, segments, regions, and feature objects.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Storage container</term>
		<listitem><para>A collection of storage objects. A storage
		container consumes one set of storage objects and produces new 
		storage objects. One common subset of storage containers is volume groups, 
		such as AIX&reg;  or LVM.</para>
		<para>Storage containers can be either of type private or cluster.</para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Cluster storage container</term>
	<listitem><para>Specialized storage containers that consume only disk objects 
	that are physically accessible from all nodes of a cluster.</para>

	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term>Private storage container</term>
	<listitem><para>A collection of disks that are physically accessible from all
	nodes of a cluster, managed as a single pool of storage, and owned and accessed
	by a single node of the cluster at any given time.</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	

	<varlistentry><term>Shared storage container</term>
	<listitem><para>A collection of disks that are physically accessible from all
	nodes of a cluster, managed as a single pool of storage, and owned and accessed
	by all nodes of the cluster simultaneously.</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry><term>Deported storage container</term>
	<listitem><para>A shared cluster container that is not owned by any node of the cluster.</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	</listitem></varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Feature object</term>
		<listitem><para>A storage object that contains an EVMS native feature. 
		</para>
		<para>An <glossterm>EVMS Native Feature</glossterm> is a  function of volume management designed 
		and implemented by 
		EVMS. These features are not intended to be backward compatible with other 
		volume management technologies. </para></listitem> 
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Logical volume</term>
		<listitem><para>A volume that consumes a storage object and exports 
		something mountable. There are two varieties of logical volumes: <glossterm>EVMS Volumes</glossterm> 
		and <glossterm>Compatibility volumes</glossterm>.</para>
		<para> <glossterm>EVMS  Volumes</glossterm> contain EVMS native metadata and can support all 
		EVMS features. <filename>/dev/evms/my_volume</filename> would be an example 
		of an EVMS Volume.</para>
		<para><glossterm>Compatibility volumes</glossterm> do not contain any EVMS native metadata. 
		Compatibility volumes are backward compatible to their particular scheme, but 
		they cannot support EVMS features. <filename>/dev/evms/md/md0</filename> would 
		be an example of a compatibility  volume. </para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
<sect1><title>What makes EVMS so flexible?</title>

<para>There are numerous drivers in the Linux kernel, such as Device
Mapper and MD (software RAID), that implement volume management schemes.  EVMS is built
on top of these drivers to provide one framework for combining and
accessing the capabilities.</para>

<para>The EVMS Engine handles the creation,
configuration, and management of volumes, segments, and disks.
The EVMS Engine is a programmatic interface to the EVMS system.
User interfaces and programs that use EVMS must go through the Engine.</para>

<para>EVMS provides the capacity for plug-in modules to the Engine that
allow EVMS to perform specialized tasks without altering the core code.
These plug-in modules allow EVMS to be more extensible and customizable than
other volume management systems.</para>
</sect1>
	      
		<sect1 id="LAYERDEF">
		<title>Plug-in layer definitions</title>
		<para>EVMS defines a layered architecture where plug-ins in each layer
		create abstractions of the layer or layers below. EVMS also allows most plug-ins
		to create abstractions of objects within the same layer. The following
		list defines these layers from the bottom up.</para>
			
		<variablelist termlength="15">
		<varlistentry><term>Device managers</term>
			<listitem><para>The first (bottom) layer consists
			of device managers.
			These plug-ins communicate with hardware device drivers to
			create the first EVMS objects. Currently, all devices are handled by a single plug-in.
			Future releases of EVMS might need additional device managers
			for network device management (for example, to manage
			disks on a storage area network (SAN)).</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>	
		<varlistentry><term>Segment managers</term>
			<listitem><para>The second layer consists of segment 
			managers. These plug-ins
			 handle the segmenting, or partitioning,
			of disk drives. The Engine components can replace partitioning
			programs, such as <command>fdisk</command> and
			<application>Disk Druid</application>, and EVMS
			uses Device Mapper to replace the in-kernel disk
			partitioning code. 
			Segment managers can also be "stacked," meaning that 
			one segment manager
			can take as input the output from another segment 
			manager.</para>

			<para> EVMS provides the following segment managers: 
			DOS, GPT, System/390&reg; (S/390), Cluster, BSD,
			Mac, and BBR. Other segment manager
			plug-ins can be added to support other 
			partitioning schemes.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>	
		<varlistentry><term>Region managers</term>
			<listitem><para>The third layer consists of region 
			managers. 
			This layer provides a place for plug-ins that ensure
			compatibility with existing volume management schemes 
			in Linux and other operating systems. 
			Region managers are intended to model systems that 
			provide a logical abstraction above disks
			or partitions.</para>

			<para>Like segment managers, region managers can 
			also be stacked. 
			Therefore, the input object(s) to a region manager can
			be disks, segments, or other regions.</para>

			<para>There are currently three region manager plug-ins in EVMS: 
			Linux LVM, LVM2, and Multi-Disk (MD).
			<variablelist><varlistentry><term>Linux LVM</term>
				<listitem><para>The Linux LVM plug-in provides compatibility with
				the Linux LVM and allows the creation of volume groups 
				(known in EVMS as containers) and logical volumes 
				(known in EVMS as regions). </para></listitem></varlistentry>

				<varlistentry><term>LVM2</term>
				<listitem><para>
				The LVM2 plug-in provides compatibility with the
new volume format introduced by the LVM2 tools from Red Hat.  This plug-in
is very similar in functionality to the LVM plug-in.  The primary difference
is the new, improved metadata format.	
				</para></listitem></varlistentry>
			
				<varlistentry><term>MD</term>
				<listitem><para>The Multi-Disk (MD) plug-in for RAID provides 
				RAID levels linear, 0, 1, 4, and 5 in 
				software. MD is one plug-in that displays as four region
				managers that you can choose from.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
			</variablelist></para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>	
		<varlistentry><term>EVMS features</term>
			<listitem><para>The next layer consists of EVMS 
			features. This layer is
			where new EVMS-native functionality is implemented. EVMS
			features can be built on any object in the system, including
			disks, segments, regions, or other feature objects. 
			All EVMS features share a common type of metadata, 
			which makes discovery of feature objects much more 
			efficient, and recovery
			of broken features objects much more reliable. There are three 
			features currently available in EVMS: drive linking, Bad 
			Block Relocation, and snapshotting. </para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Drive Linking</term>
<listitem><para>Drive linking allows any
			number of objects to be linearly concatenated together into a
			single object. A drive linked volume can be expanded by 
			adding another storage object to the end or shrunk by removing the last object.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Bad Block Relocation</term>
<listitem><para>Bad Block Relocation (BBR)
			monitors its I/O path and detects write failures (which can be
			caused by a damaged disk). In the event of such a failure, the
			data from that request is stored in a new location. BBR keeps
			track of this remapping. Additional I/Os to that
			location are redirected to the new location.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Snapshotting</term>
<listitem><para>The Snapshotting feature provides
			a mechanism for creating a "frozen" copy of a volume at a single
			instant in time, without having to take that volume off-line.
			This is useful for performing backups on a live system.
			Snapshots work with any volume (EVMS or compatibility), and can
			use any other available object as a backing store. After a
			snapshot is created and made into an EVMS volume, writes to the "original" volume cause the
			original contents of that location to be copied to the snapshot's
			storage object. Reads to the snapshot volume look like they
			come from the original at the time the snapshot was created.
</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
			

			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry><term>File System Interface Modules</term>
			<listitem><para>File System Interface Modules (FSIMs) 
			provide coordination with the
			file systems during certain volume management 
			operations. For
			instance, when expanding or shrinking a volume, 
			the file system
			must also be expanded or shrunk to the appropriate size.
			Ordering in this example is also important; 
			a file system cannot
			be expanded before the volume, and a volume cannot 
			be shrunk before the file system. 
			The FSIMs allow EVMS to ensure this
			coordination and ordering.</para>

			<para>FSIMs also perform file system
			operations from one of the EVMS user interfaces. For instance,
			a user can make new file systems and check existing file systems
			by interacting with the FSIM.</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry><term>Cluster Manager Interface Modules</term>
		<listitem><para>Cluster Manager Interface Modules, also
		known as the EVMS Clustered Engine (ECE), interface
		with the local cluster manager installed on the system.
		The ECE provides a standardized ECE API to the Engine
		while hiding cluster manager details from the Engine.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	    </sect1>

</chapter>

