<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN' "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="Accessibility-HOWTO">
   <articleinfo>
   <title>Linux Accessibility HOWTO</title>

   <author>
     <firstname>Michael</firstname>
      <surname>De La Rue</surname>
   </author>

   <author>
      <firstname>Sharon</firstname>
      <surname>Snider</surname>
      <authorblurb><para><ulink url="mailto:snidersd@us.ibm.com">snidersd@us.ibm.com</ulink></para></authorblurb>
   </author>

   <pubdate>v3.1, June 21, 2002</pubdate>

   <abstract><para>The Linux Accessibility HOWTO covers the use of adaptive technologies that are available for the Linux operating
   system, as well as the software applications and hardware devices that can be installed to make Linux accessible to users with  
   disabilities. The information provided targets specific groups of individuals with similar disabilities.</para></abstract>

<legalnotice>
<para>The Access-HOWTO is copyrighted (c) 1996 by Michael De La Rue</para>
<para>The following terms are trademarks and registered trademarks of International Business Machines Corporation in the United States and/or other countries: IBM and ViaVoice. A full list of trademarks may be found at <ulink url="http://www.ibm.com/legal/copytrade.shtml"></ulink>. Linux is a trademark of Linus Torvalds. Java and all Java-based trademarks are trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. in the United States, other countries, or both.</para>
</legalnotice>

   <revhistory>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>v3.1</revnumber>
         <date>2002-06-21</date>
         <authorinitials>sds</authorinitials>
         <revremark>
               Updated and converted to DocBook XML.
         </revremark>
      </revision>
	<revision>
         <revnumber>v3.0</revnumber>
         <date>2001-10-25</date>
         <authorinitials>sds</authorinitials>
         <revremark>
                Updated and converted to DocBook SGML.
         </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>v2.11</revnumber>
         <date>1997-03-28</date>
         <authorinitials>mdlr</authorinitials>
         <revremark>
                Last Linuxdoc revision.
         </revremark>
      </revision>
   </revhistory>

   </articleinfo>

<sect1 id="Introduction"> <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>The purpose of this HOWTO is to introduce the tools, applications, and configuration utilities that are available to 
      Linux users who are disabled. The information provided targets groups of individuals with the following disabilities:</para>
    
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><link linkend="visual"><emphasis role="strong">Visually Impaired</emphasis></link></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><link linkend="hearing"><emphasis role="strong">Hearing Impaired</emphasis></link></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><link linkend="physical"><emphasis role="strong">Physically Disabled</emphasis></link></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><link linkend="other"><emphasis role="strong">Cognitive, Language, and Other 
      Impairments</emphasis></link></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>Please send any comments, or contributions via e-mail to <ulink url="mailto:snidersd@us.ibm.com"> Sharon Snider. </ulink>
      This document will be updated regularly with new contributions and suggestions.</para>

   <sect2>
      <title>Distribution Policy</title>
      <para>The Access-HOWTO may be distributed, at your choice, under either the terms of the GNU Public License version 2 or later or
      the standard Linux Documentation Project (LDP) terms. These licenses should be available from the LDP Web site:
      <ulink url="http://www.linuxdoc.org/docs.html"></ulink>. Please note that since the LDP terms do not allow modification (other 
      than translation), modified versions can be assumed to be distributed under the GPL.</para>
      <para>ViaVoice&reg; is a registered trademark of International Business Machines Corporation.</para>
   </sect2>
</sect1>  

<sect1 id="LinuxOS">
      <title>The Linux Operating System</title>
      <para>The Linux operating system has many software applications and utilities that run in the non-graphical environment. The
      graphical user interface (GUI), which is often referred to as X Windows, is clearly separate from the underlying
      non-graphical, text-only environment. One major reason that a visually impaired individual can use Linux is that network
      connectivity is built in to the operating system and provides full access to the Internet from the non-graphical interface. 
      All visible text on the screen can be translated using a screen reader and speech synthesizer.</para>

      <para>Over the past few years many improvements have been made to the GUI, and many of the desktops now 
      provide features and enhancements designed for accessibility. In the following sections you will find information on the tools,
      utilities, and applications that are available to assist users in configuring their desktop environment.</para>

   <sect2>
      <title>Assistive Technologies Available for Linux</title>
      <para>Assistive technologies are computer hardware devices and software applications that provide individuals with impairments
      access to the information and applications on a computer. Although there are not many commercial applications available
      specifically for Linux accessibility, there are free software applications that can make the computer more accessible.   
      Detailed information on assistive technologies that are available has been listed in this document based on the type of 
      disability.</para> 
   </sect2>

   <sect2>
      <title>Usability</title>
      <para>Linux has the advantage over Windows that a large majority of Linux software has been developed for the console. Although
      many programs are now being developed for the GUI, programs continue to be written for the non-graphical, 
      text-based environment. Linux originated as a programmer's operating system and, for the physically disabled, this means that it 
      is easy to build and customize programs to suit an individual's needs.</para>
 
      <para>The windowing system used by Linux (X11) includes many programming tools that enable further modification and customization 
      of the GUI. KDE and GNOME have included many accessibility and usability features in their latest
      releases and are continuing to test, upgrade, and enhance the graphical environment. The following are links to KDE and GNOME's
      accessibility and usability projects:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>KDE Accessibility  Project - <ulink url="http://accessibility.kde.org/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GNOME Accessibility  Project - <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gap/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>KDE Usability  Project - <ulink url="http://usability.kde.org/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GNOME Usability  Project - <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gup/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
</sect1>  

<sect1 id="visual">
      <title>Visual Impairments</title>
      <para>There are two categories of visual impairments. Individuals who are partially sighted (for example, blurred vision, near
      and far-sightedness, color blindness) and those who are totally blind. Assistive technologies are available for the Linux
      operating system for visually impaired users, and many of the software packages are free.</para>

   <sect2>
      <title>Technologies for the Visually Impaired</title> 
      <para>The following is a list of assistive technologies for visually impaired users:</para>
      <sect3><title>Screen Readers</title>
      <para>Screen readers are software applications that are installed on the computer to provide translation of the information 
      on the computer screen to an audio output format. The translation is passed to the speech synthesizer and the words are spoken
      out loud. Currently, fully functional screen readers are only available for Linux in console mode. This section describes some of 
      the most common screen readers.</para>

      <itemizedlist>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Emacspeak </emphasis>is the complete Audio Desktop is an excellent non-graphical, text
      based interface for users who are visually
      impaired. This application can be used as a screen reader in conjunction with a hardware synthesizer or IBM ViaVoice&reg; 
      Run-time text-to-speech application. More information and software packages of are available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/home/raman/emacspeak/"></ulink>. The Emacspeak HOWTO 
      <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/docs/HOWTO/"></ulink> includes a tutorial and
      installation guide.   
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Jupiter Speech System </emphasis>is a screen reader for Linux in console mode. A user guide 
      and software packages are available at:
      <ulink url="http://www.eklhad.net/linux/jupiter/"></ulink>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Screader </emphasis>is a screen reader for Linux in console mode that works with the 
      Festival software speech synthesizer and the Accent hardware synthesizer. Information and downloads are available at:
      <ulink url="http://www.euronet.nl/~acj/eng-screader.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Speaker </emphasis>is a new plugin for the Konqueror file manager and Web browser. 
      Speaker provides Text to Speech using the Festival speech system or IBM ViaVoice. Downloads are available at: 
      <ulink url="http://dogma.freebsd-uk.eu.org/~grrussel/speaker.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Speakup </emphasis> is a screen review package for the Linux operating system. It requires 
      a hardware speech synthesizer, such as the DecTalk Express. An installation boot disk and packages are available at: <ulink url="http://www.linux-speakup.org/"></ulink> that allow a
      visually impaired user to install the Linux operating system. </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ZipSpeak </emphasis>is a talking mini-distribution of Linux.
      More information and software packages are available at:
      <ulink url="http://www.linux-speakup.org/zipspeak.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Speech Synthesizers</title>
      <para>Speech synthesizers can be a hardware device or a text to speech (TTS) software application that creates the sounds 
      necessary to provide speech output. Hardware synthesizers are available for the Linux operating system; however, they can 
      be very expensive and must be compatible with the screen reader application in order to function properly. The alternative is to 
      download and install a software synthesizer such as IBM's ViaVoice or Festival and configure the application to a compatible
      screen reader, such as Emacspeak.</para>

      <sect4><title>Hardware Speech Synthesizers</title>
      <para>A hardware speech synthesizer is a device that is connected to the computer's serial or parallel port and translates the
      text to a spoken output. Normally there are Braille labels on all controls to indicate the off and on position, and volume 
      control. Hardware synthesizers also have the ability to speak in different tones that can be setup to indicate various parts of a
      document or text. Some models will provide a connection for headphones. The following is a list of speech
      synthesizers that are supported on the Linux operating system and can be used with Emacspeak: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="strong">Accent SA and Apollo 2 </emphasis>(<ulink url="http://polio.dyndns.org/chip/vss.html"></ulink>)  
      </para> </listitem>  
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">DECTalk Express </emphasis>(<ulink url="http://www.4access.com/synthesizers.asp"></ulink>) </para> </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">DoubleTalk </emphasis>(<ulink url="http://www.rcsys.com"></ulink>) </para></listitem> 
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect4>

      <sect4><title>Software Speech Synthesizers</title>
      <para> A software speech synthesizer is an application that translates the text on the screen to speech output and provides  
      speech synthesis, so that the screen reader application can read information out loud to the user. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Festival </emphasis>is a general, multi-lingual speech synthesis system developed at the 
      Center for Speech Technology Research (CSTR). It offers a full TTS system with various application program interfaces, as well as 
      an environment for development and research of speech synthesis techniques. Mbrola or FestVox are needed to complete the Festival 
      installation. Software packages and installation instructions are available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.cstr.ed.ac.uk/projects/festival/"></ulink>. </para> </listitem>

      
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Mbrola </emphasis>is a speech synthesizer that can be used with a TTS application, such 
      as, Festival to provide speech output. More information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://tcts.fpms.ac.be/synthesis/mbrola.html"></ulink>. </para> </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Screen Magnifiers</title>
      <para>Screen magnifiers enable users that are partially sighted to view selected areas of the screen in a manner similar to using 
      a magnifying glass. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">GMag </emphasis>is a screen magnifier for X Windows. It provides continuous magnification 
      while you work, as well as the option to change the contrast of images at run-time. More information and downloads are available 
      at: 
      <ulink url="http://projects.prosa.it/gmag/"></ulink>. </para> </listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Puff </emphasis>is a screen magnifier for users who need a high magnification of text and 
      graphics 
      in X Windows. Puff follows the focus of the mouse or pointer and enlarges the portion of the screen under the cursor. In order 
      for Puff to run properly on Linux the source code needs to be modified. This application is not a good option for inexperienced 
      users. The software packages and source code modification instructions are available at:
      <ulink url="http://trace.wisc.edu/world/computer_access/unix/unixshare.html"></ulink>. </para> </listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">SVGATextmode </emphasis> enlarges or reduces the font size for users who perfer to work in 
      console 
      mode. The normal text screen that Linux provides is 80 characters across and 25 vertically. After SVGATextmode is installed, the 
      text can be displayed much larger. One example would be 50 characters across and 15 vertically. The program does not offer the 
      ablitity to zoom in and out, but the user can re-size when necessary. The most current download is available at:
      <ulink url="http://freshmeat.net/projects/svgatextmode/"></ulink>.  
      Do not run try to run SVGATextmode from an X Windows terminal. You must be in console mode for the display to
      function properly.</para> </listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">UnWindows </emphasis>is a collection of programs that includes Dynamag, a screen 
      magnification program that helps the user locate the mouse pointer. The source code is available for Dynamag as a stand alone    
      application, or the entire UnWindows package can be downloaded at:
      <ulink url="http://www.cs.rpi.edu/pub/unwindows/"></ulink>. The entire UnWindows package will not work with Linux without 
      programming modifications. However, the Dynamag
      application can be installed successfully without any additional code changes.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Xzoom </emphasis> is a screen magnifier similar to Xmag that allows the user to magnify
      rotate or mirror a portion of the screen. The most current download is available at:
      <ulink url="http://filewatcher.org/sec/xzoom.html"></ulink>. </para> </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Adjusting the Screen's Resolution</title>
	<para>The X Windows server can be setup with different screen resolutions. The ability to adjust the screen's resolution allows 	a partially sighted user to magnify the screen with a single key sequence. The steps to set up your system are as 		 	follows:</para>
	
	<orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Changed directories, <emphasis role="strong">type cd /etc</emphasis></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Using a text editor, open the <emphasis role="strong">XF86Config</emphasis> file</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Locate the line beginning with Modes and change it to <screen>Modes &quot;1280x1024&quot; &quot;1024x768&quot; &quot;800x600&quot; &quot;640x480&quot; &quot;320x240&quot;</screen>  Note: The settings may vary based your monitor's highest resolution mode.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Save the file and exit.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

<para>To enlarge  the text on the screen type <emphasis role="strong">Ctrl+Alt+keypad-plus</emphasis> and to make the text smaller type <emphasis role="strong">Ctrl+Alt+keypad-minus</emphasis></para>
	
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Braille Devices</title>
      <para>Braille terminals are normally used by individuals who are totally blind and may be hearing impaired as well. A
      Braille display uses a series of pins to form Braille symbols that are continuously updated as the users changes focus.
      A Braille embosser is a hardware device for printing a hard copy of a text document in Braille. Braille translation 
      software is required to translate the on-screen text to a Braille format.</para>

      <sect4><title>Braille Hardware Devices</title>
      <para> The following Braille devices have been listed on the hardware compatibility list of one or more of the following Braille 
      translation applications:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Braillex </emphasis>
      <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/mailing-lists/blinux-announce/msg00031.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Alva B.V.</emphasis>: ABT3xx, Delphi (serial and parallel ports), Satellite.
      <ulink url="http://www.alva-bv.nl/alvacorp/alva_corp_home.html">  
      </ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Baum</emphasis>: Vario/RBT 40/80 (emulation 1/2) 
      <ulink url="http://www.baum.de/English/homeeng1.htm"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Blazie Engineering</emphasis>: BrailleLite 18/40 
      <ulink url="http://www.freedomscientific.com/index.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Handialog</emphasis>: VisioBraille 2040 
      <ulink url="http://www.handialog.com/indexuk.htm"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Handy Tech Elektronik GmbH</emphasis>: BrailleWave, mod20, mod40, mod80 
      <ulink url="http://www.handytech.de/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">MDV</emphasis>: MB208/MB408L/MB408S (protocol 5) 
      <ulink url="http://www.cavazza.it/cnt/schede/scheda-mb408l-eng.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Pulse Data International</emphasis>: BrailleNote 18/32 
      <ulink url="http://www.pulsedata.co.nz/graphics.htm"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Telesensory Systems Inc.</emphasis>: Navigator 20/40/80 (latest firmware version only),
      PowerBraille 40/65/80 <ulink url="http://www.telesensory.com/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Tieman B.V.</emphasis>: CombiBraille 25/45/85, MiniBraille 20, MultiBraille 
      MB125CR/MB145CR/MB185CR 
      <ulink url="http://www.braillevoyager.nl/uk/index.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Tiflosoft</emphasis>: VideoBraille 40 
      <ulink url="http://www.tinlecco.it/tiflosoft/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect4>
    
      <sect4><title>Braille Translation Software</title>
      <para>The following Braille translation applications are available for download:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Brass </emphasis>is a new program that combines speech and Braille output. The current 
      version is still in testing and can be downloaded at: <ulink url="http://www.butenuth.onlinehome.de/blinux/"></ulink>. 
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">BrLTTY </emphasis>supports parallel port and USB Braille displays and provides access to the Linux 
      console. It drives the terminal and provides complete screen review capabilities. It is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://dave.mielke.cc/brltty/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">NFBTrans </emphasis>is a freeware Braille translator written by the National Federation for 
      the Blind (NFB). Software packages are available for download at: <ulink url="http://www.nfb.org/nfbtrans.htm"></ulink>. </para>
      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect4>
      </sect3>
 
      <sect3><title>Cursors for X Windows</title>
      <para>Changing the shape and size of the mouse cursor can help users who have a problem following or seeing the cursor. The 
      X Big Cursor mini HOWTO explains how to configure enlarged mouse cursors with the X Windows system. This HOWTO is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.icewalk.com/doclib/howtos/mini/X-Big-Cursor.html"></ulink>. </para>
      <para>There are also a large select of cursors that can be downloaded at:
      <ulink url="http://themes.tucows.com/cursors.html"></ulink>. </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Audio</title>
      <para>Audio can be very useful to users who are visually impaired. In most X Windows desktop environments audio
      alerts and sound events can be setup within the desktop control center by enabling sound and verifying that the option to show 
      sound is activated. You will need to check the desktop users manual for setup and configuration of sound events.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="strong">Locktones </emphasis>is an excellent application for providing toggle keys that sound an audio 
      alert to warn the user that a keystroke has created a locking state such as Cap Locks, or Num Locks. The application can be 
      downloaded at: 
      <ulink url="http://leb.net/pub/blinux/"></ulink>. </para>
      <para>Linux can also be configured to beep at the login prompt so the user knows when to type in the password. A configuration 
      utility can be downloaded and installed that can provide this function at: 
      <ulink url="http://leb.net/pub/blinux/bootmeup/"></ulink>. </para>
      </sect3>      

      <sect3><title>Additional Resources</title>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Access Mozilla </emphasis> has a goal to build an accessible Web suite: browser, e-mail,  
      news, composer and chat that conform to the W3C accessibility standards. More information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://access-mozilla.sourceforge.net/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Blind + Linux = BLINUX </emphasis>provides documentation, downloads and a mailing 
      list that focus on users who are blind. Information and software packages are available at:
      <ulink url="http://leb.net/blinux"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">LaTex/Tex </emphasis>is an extremely powerful document preparation system and it can be 
      used to produce large print documents. More information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.emerson.emory.edu/services/latex/latex_toc.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">National Federation for the Blind's (NFB) purpose is to help blind persons achieve 
      self-confidence and self-respect and to act as a vehicle for collective self expression by the blind. 
      Information for blind users, as well as software are available at: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="http://www.nfb.org/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Project Ocularis </emphasis>is run by volunteers, and the project's aim is to improve Linux 
      accessibility through the creation of new free software and the modification of pre-existing free software. More information is
      available at:
      <ulink url="http://ocularis.sourceforge.net"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Screen </emphasis>is a standard piece of software that allows many different applications 
      to run at the same time on a single terminal in console mode. Screen has been enhanced to support some Braille terminals 
      directly. It is available for download at:
      <ulink url="http://www.icewalk.com/softlib/app/app_01508.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">SuSE Linux </emphasis>is the first Linux distribution to support installation of the
      Linux operating system and applications that run on Linux in Braille. The Blinux screen reader runs in the background to enable
      visually impaired users to work in a Linux console environment. More information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.suse.de/us/products/susesoft/70news/new_in_70.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">xocr </emphasis>is an optical character recognition program that scans written text, 
      such as a book  
      and translates it to audio output, so the information is available to visually impaired users. More information is 
      available at:
      <ulink url="http://sal.unimedya.net.tr/Z/3/XOCR.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="hearing"><title>Hearing Impaired</title>
      <para>For users who have hearing impairments the audio output must be conveyed visually on the screen. Most desktops provide 
      visual audio alerts and warnings. In console mode the system can also be configured to provide visual bells. There is a 
      "Visual Bells mini-HOWTO" written by Alessandro Rubini that provides the configuration details available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/docs/HOWTO/mini/"></ulink>. </para>
      
   <sect2><title>Assistive Technologies for the Hearing Impaired</title>
      <para>The following is a list of assistive technologies for the hearing impaired:</para>

      <sect3><title>Telecommunications Devices for the Deaf (TDD)</title>
      <para>TDD allows for the user you to communicate over the telephone using the 
      computer as a text terminal.</para> 
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong"> Zapata </emphasis>is a computer-based, high-density telephony project. The current version 
      is available for download as source code on at:  
      <ulink url="http://www.zapatatelephony.org/project.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>Closed Captioning</title>
      <para>Closed captioning provides text translation of spoken words to video display. Closed captioning can be used for distance 
      learning, video-teleconferencing, audio from a CD-ROM, and other types of interactive technology.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Ccdecoder </emphasis>is a closed captioned, extended data services decoder for the bttv 
      and video4linux based tv video cards:
      <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ccdecoder/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="physical"><title>Physically Disabled</title>
      <para>There are a wide range of physical disabilities that can impair a user's mobility, and many of these impairments need to be 
      addressed on an individual basis. This section addresses impairments that apply to users who have difficulty using a mouse, 
      pointing device, or keyboard.</para>

   <sect2><title>Keyboard Navigation</title>
      <para>There are features that are built into the Linux operating system that allow for additional keyboard configuration. In some 
      of the X Windows desktops these settings can be changed from the control center. An application has also been developed for X 
      Windows called AccessX and it provides a graphical user interface for configuring all the AccessX keyboard 
      settings. These settings are:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">StickyKeys </emphasis>enable the user to lock modifier keys (for example,
      control and shift) allowing single finger operations in place of multiple key combinations.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">MouseKeys </emphasis>provide alternative keyboard sequences for cursor movement and mouse 
      button operations.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">SlowKeys </emphasis>requires the user to hold the key down for a specified period of time 
      before the keystroke is accepted. This prevents keystrokes that are pressed by accident from being sent.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ToggleKeys</emphasis> sound an audio alert that warns the user that a keystroke created a 
      locking state for keys, such as Caps Lock, and Num Lock. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">RepeatKeys </emphasis>allow a user with limited coordination additional time to release 
      keys before multiple key sequences are sent to the application.</para></listitem> 
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">BounceKeys </emphasis>or <emphasis role="strong">Delay Keys </emphasis>have a delay between 
      keystrokes. This function can help prevent the system from accepting unintentional keystrokes.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>

   <sect2><title>Assistive Technologies for the Physically Disabled</title>
      <para>The following is a list of assistive technologies for the physically disabled:</para>

      <sect3><title>On-Screen Keyboard</title>
      <para>On-screen keyboards enable a user to select keys using a pointing device, such as a mouse, trackball, or touch pad. 
      This application can be used in place of a standard keyboard.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">GTkeyboard </emphasis>is a on-screen, graphical keyboard and can be downloaded at:  
      <ulink url="http://opop.nols.com/gtkeyboard.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">GNOME Onscreen Keyboard (GOK)</emphasis>is a on-screen, graphical keyboard that enables users to control their computer without having to rely on a standard keyboard or mouse. MOre information is available at <ulink url="http://www.gok.ca"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>Speech Recognition</title>
      <para>Speech recognition utilities are used by people with mobility impairments, so they can operate the computer using
      voice control.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Open Mind Speech </emphasis>is a development project for 
      speech recognition tools and applications. Information for the project and a mailing list are available at:
      <ulink url="http://freespeech.sourceforge.net/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">ViaVoice Dictation for Linux </emphasis>allows you to write documents using your 
      voice rather than a keyboard. Information and downloads are available at:
      <ulink url="http://www-4.ibm.com/software/speech/dev/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>This site has information and links related to several different speech recognition utilities.
      <ulink url="http://www.trace.wisc.edu/world/computer_access/unix/unixshar.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>

   <sect2><title>Additional Resources</title>
      <para>The following is a list of additional Web sites that may be of interest to users with mobility  
      impairments:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>This site provides a kernel patch that can be downloaded to enable a one-handed keyboard. The download is
      available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.fourtytwo.de"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Configuration and information on Adapting the Linux Keyboard for a one handed user is available at:
      <ulink url="http://www.eklhad.net/linux/app/onehand.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Morseall </emphasis>allows the user to control a Linux shell by tapping Morse code on the 
      left mouse button: 
      <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/morseall"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The keyboard and console HOWTO provides additional keyboard configuration information. 
      <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/docs/HOWTO/Keyboard-and-Console-HOWTO"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>There is a <emphasis role="strong">Speech Recognition HOWTO</emphasis>, written by Stephen Cook that provides 
      complete details for anyone interested in learning more about speech recognition applications. 
      <ulink url="http://www.linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="other"><title>Cognitive, Language, and Other Impairments</title>
      <para>Cognitive and language impairments include dyslexia and problems with; memory, comprehension, problem solving,
      and written language. 
      For many individuals with cognitive and language disabilities, complex graphical displays and inconsistent use of words 
      can make using the computer more difficult. 
      A user with epilepsy can have a seizure from an application with blinking lights and animation. Most desktops now allow users to
      disable animation. Web browsers such as Mozilla and Netscape allow users to disable graphics. It is important to 
      check the documentation for preferences that are available in the desktop environment you are using, 
      as well as any applications that are 
      used. This section discusses the tools that are available to aid users with these impairments:          
      </para>

   <sect2><title>Assistive Technologies for Cognitive, Language and Other Impairments</title>
      <para>The following is a list of assistive technologies that can be helpful to users with cognitive, language, and other 
      impairments:</para>
      <sect3><title>Screen Readers and Speech Synthesis</title>
      <para>Screen readers with speech synthesis enable the system to read on-screen information and text out loud to the user. This 
      type of assistive technology can be particularly helpful to individuals who have dyslexia and other learning 
      disabilities. Although there are no screen readers available for the GNOME desktop, screen reader applications are available for 
      Linux in console mode that provide this functionality.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Emacspeak </emphasis>is a speech interface that will provide audio output for all text. The 
      program works in terminal and console mode and requires a software or hardware speech synthesizer. The downloads and users
      manuals are available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/home/raman/emacspeak/"></ulink>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para> The Trace Center provides information and downloads for various screen readers and speech synthesizers. More 
      information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.trace.wisc.edu/world/computer_access/unix/unixshar.html"></ulink>.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Keyboard filters and Word Processing</title>
      <para>Keyboard filters and word processing applications that have word prediction and spell checking utilities can be an
      excellent aid for users with learning and language impairments.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3><title>Speech Recognition</title>
      <para>Speech recognition applications enables you to control the computer with your voice rather than having to type or
      write out the information.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">CVoice Control </emphasis>is a speech recognition system that enables a user to connect 
      spoken commands to UNIX commands. More information is available at:
      <ulink url="http://www.kiecza.de/daniel/linux/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">IBM ViaVoice Dictation for Linux </emphasis>allows the user to write documents using their 
      voice rather then a keyboard and can read the information back to the user. More information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www-4.ibm.com/software/speech/dev/"></ulink>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Open Mind Speech </emphasis>is a development project for 
      speech recognition tools and applications. The developers have established a mailing list for asking questions and obtaining 
      information at: <ulink url="http://freespeech.sourceforge.net/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">XVoice </emphasis>enables continuous speech to text dictation for many applications. More 
      information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.compapp.dcu.ie/~tdoris/Xvoice/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Developing Accessible Applications</title>
      <para>It is important to consider accessibility when developing new applications for the Linux operating system.  
      The American Foundation for the Blind, the GNOME Accessibility Project, IBM, Sun, and W3C have written guidelines that are excellent 
      road maps for developing and testing new Linux software.
      The following Web sites provide the tools, checklists and testing information to help developers write accessible programs for
      impaired users.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">American Foundation for the Blind</emphasis> provides information on creating accessible 
      computer applications at:
      <ulink url="http://www.afb.org/info_document_view.asp?documentid=198"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">GNOME Accessibility Project </emphasis>has written a guide specifically for application 
      development for the GNOME 2.0 desktop. More information is available at: 
      <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gap/guide/gad/index.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">IBM Accessibility Center </emphasis>provides links to a software accessibility checklist, 
      testing information, and the Section 508 Rehabilitation Act. This site is located at: 
      <ulink url="http://www-3.ibm.com/able/guidelines.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Sun Accessibility </emphasis>provides information on designing applications for 
      accessibility at:
      <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/access/developers/software.guides.html"></ulink> and an Accessibility Quick Reference Guide is 
      available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/access/developers/access.quick.ref.html"></ulink>. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">W3C User Agent Accessibility Guidelines 1.0</emphasis> provides guidelines on accessible Web browser development including multimedia players and Web related software. <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/UAAGIO/"></ulink>.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </sect1>

<sect1><title>Other Helpful Information</title>
      <para>The following is a list of additional information that may be helpful, but is not necessarily targeting a specific 
      disability:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para> <emphasis role="strong">The CMU Sphinx Group Source </emphasis>has released a set of reasonably mature, speech 
      components that provide a basic level of technology to anyone interested in creating speech enabled applications. More 
      information is available at:
      <ulink url="http://fife.speech.cs.cmu.edu/sphinx/"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Access to Linux documentation is critical to learning and using Linux. The <emphasis role="strong">Linux 
      Documentation Project </emphasis>has links to many Linux HOWTOs, mini HOWTOs, and guides, as well as information on becoming 
      involved in authoring new HOWTOs. More information and downloads are available at:
      <ulink url="http://www.linuxdoc.org"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">RPMFind.net </emphasis>provides rpm downloads for Linux applications on most Linux 
      operating systems. The site is located at:<ulink url="http://www.rpmfind.net"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Sourceforge </emphasis>provides updated information, documentation, and software for Linux. 
      Some of the applications available are under development. More information and downloads are available at: 
      <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net"></ulink>. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">The Trace Center </emphasis>provides accessibility information and software for the Linux 
      operating system. More information is available at:
      <ulink url="http://trace.wisc.edu/worl/computer_access/"></ulink> and the Linux Accessibility Resource Site (LARS) <ulink url="http://trace.wisc.edu/linux/"></ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">W3C Web Accessibility initiative</emphasis> provides information and links on Web site accessibility. More information is available at: <ulink url="https://www.w3.org/WAI/">their website</ulink>.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <para>These are the orignal acknowledgments documented by Michael De La Rue. They have been included in their entirety to 
      ensure that each persons efforts to make Linux more accessibile are acknowledged.</para>

      <para>Much of this document was created from various information sources
      on the Internet, many found from Yahoo and DEC's Alta Vista Search
      engine.  Included in this was the documentation of most of the
      software packages mentioned in the text.  Some information was also
      gleaned from the Royal National Institute for the Blind's help sheets.</para>

      <para>T.V. Raman, the author of Emacspeak has reliably contributed comments,
      information and text as well as putting me in touch with other people
      who he knew on the Internet.</para>

     <para>Kenneth Albanowski <ulink url="mailto:kjahds@kjahds.com">kjahds@kjahds.com</ulink> provided the
     patch needed for the Brailloterm and information about it.</para>

      <para>Roland Dyroff of <ulink url="http://www.suse.de/">S.u.S.E. GmbH</ulink> 
      (Linux distributors and makers of S.u.S.E. Linux (English/German)) looked up
      KTS Stolper GmbH at my request and got some hardware details and
      information on the Brailloterm.</para>

      <para>The most major and careful checks over of this document were done by
      James Bowden, <ulink url="mailto:jrbowden@bcs.org.uk">jrbowden@bcs.org </ulink> 
      and Nikhil Nair <ulink url="mailto:nn201@cus.cam.ac.uk">nn201@cus.cam.ac.uk</ulink>, the
      BRLTTY authors who suggested a large number of corrections as well as extra information 
      for some topics.</para>

      <para>The contributors to the blinux and linux-access mailing lists have
      contributed to this document by providng information for me to read.</para>

      <para>Mark E. Novak of the Trace R and D centre <ulink url="http://trace.wisc.edu/"></ulink>
      pointed me in the direction of several packages of software and information which I had not seen before.  He
      also made some comments on the structure of the document which I have
      partially taken into account and should probably do more about.</para>

      <para>Other contributors include Nicolas Pitrie and Stephane Doyon.</para>

      <para>A number of other people have contributed comments and information.
      Specific contributions are acknowledged within the document.</para>

      <para>This version was specifically produced for <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/">
      RedHat</ulink>'s Dr. Linux book.  This is
      because they provided warning of it's impending release to myself and
      other LDP authors.  Their doing this is strongly appreciated since
      wrong or old information sits around much longer in a book than on the
      Internet.</para>

      <para>No doubt you made a contribution and I haven't mentioned it.  Don't
      worry, it was an accident.  I'm sorry.  Just tell me and I will add
      you to the next version.</para>
</sect1>
</article>























