<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY aacute	    "&#x00E1;"> <!-- LATIN SMALL LETTER A WITH ACUTE -->
<!ENTITY copy       "&#x2117;"> <!-- COPYRIGHT SIGN -->
]>
<article id="index">
  <!-- CVS revision info: $Id$ -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>The Indic Fonts HOWTO</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Maninder</firstname>
      <surname>Bali</surname>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>mb</authorinitials>

    <othercredit role="converter">
      <firstname>Dan</firstname>
      <surname>Scott</surname>
      <contrib>Conversion from HTML to DocBook v4.1.2 (XML)</contrib>
    </othercredit>

    <revhistory id="revhistory">
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
        <date>2002/01/07</date>
        <authorinitials>mb</authorinitials>
        <revremark>First rendition released by Maninder Bali.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This is a detailed guide on how to install and use Indic scripts (devanagri etc.) using UTF-8 encoding under GNU/Linux. This HOWTO is a work in progress. More sections regarding fonts and other related things shall be added to this HOWTO in due course of time. Special thanks to Dan Scott for conversion from HTML to DocBook v4.1.2(XML). Any feedback, sugestions, pointers, gifts, cds, BMWs will be gladly accepted. All flames will be redirected to <filename>/mnt/praises_for_thee/</filename> for future reference. Be afraid.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This HOWTO has been written to help you setup your Linux box to use UTF-8 encoding for using various Indic scripts. You will have to install the IndiX system developed by NCST, Mumbai on your machine in order for you to use various Indic scripts. I have tested the IndiX system on Exodus GNU/Linux, RedHat Linux, and Mandrake Linux. Anyone who has tested this system on a machine running Debian, please let me know and I will include that in this HOWTO.
      I want to thank Mr. Keyur Shroff from NCST, Mumbai for allowing me to modify and redistribute his Devanagri-HOWTO.
    </para>
    <para>
      Please note that Exodus GNU/Linux, developed by the good guys at Centurion Linux, India will ship with the IndiX system installed, thanks to the Transfer of Technology deal signed by NCST, Mumbai and Centurion Linux Pvt. Ltd.
    </para>
    <para>
      Almost all of the leading GNU/Linux distributions available today have been localized in various international languages like French, German, Spanish, Chinese, Arabic, etc. This HOWTO aims at documenting the steps involved in enabling you to localize your GNU/Linux distribution to Indic scripts of your choice. To begin with, you must be aware of the complexity involved in localizing any of the Indian languages. Any Indian language text input differs from that of English. Perhaps the most significant difference is that in English, each keystroke maps directly onto a letter where each letter has a unique code. On the other hand, a 'syllable' - the Indian language equivalent unit of writing letter is composed of one or more characters entered through the keyboard.
    </para>
    <para>
      The syllable is composed of vowels, consonants, modifiers and other special graphics signs. These are encoded, just as roman letters are. The user types in a sequence of vowels, consonants, modifiers and the graphics signs. The machine then composes these syllables at run time based on language dependent rules. Every syllable is thus represented in the machine as a unique sequence of vowels, consonants and modifiers. In a text sequence, these characters are stored in logical (phonetic) order.
    </para>
    <para>
      Indic characters can combine or change shape depending on their context. A character's appearance is affected by its ordering with respect to other characters, the font used to render the character, and the application or system environment. These variables can cause the appearance of Devanagari characters to be different from their nominal glyphs (used in the code charts).  Additionally, characters cause a change in the order of the displayed glyphs. This reordering is not commonly seen in non-Indic scripts and occurs independent of any bi-directional character reordering that might be required.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each syllable has a unique visual representation. However, there are too many syllables to design glyphs for each one individually. So a font normally contains certain component glyphs from which a syllable is composed at run time. The onscreen representation of a syllable is then a composition of glyphs from the Indian language font. There is no direct mapping of glyph codes to the consonant, vowel or modifier codes. However, for every syllable (a sequence of consonants, vowels and modifiers) there is a corresponding sequence of glyphs. This constitutes a many-to-many mapping from keystrokes to glyphs as opposed to a simplistic one-to-one mapping in roman scripts.
    </para>
    <para>
      Please read the <ulink url="http://www.linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/Unicode-HOWTO.html">Unicode-HOWTO</ulink> and visit <ulink url="http://www.unicode.org/">http://www.unicode.org/</ulink> for more information on the UTF-8 encoding.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Indix system developed by NCST, Mumbai enables most applications in X Windows (irrespective of the toolkit used), to render Indic characters according to the unicode standard specification. IndiX provides support for OpenType fonts and Unicode encoding at X Windows level. This enables most of the existing applications to handle Indic scripts without any modification or recompilation.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once you have installed the IndiX system, following all the steps mentioned in this HOWTO, you will be able to fly across seven seas and slap that annoying sailor who keeps goin' hic' hic'... Okay, on a more serious note, you will be able to enjoy your Linux experience in Devanagri and other Indic scripts of your choice.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="install">
    <title>Installing the IndiX system</title>
    <para>
      You can obtain the IndiX system from NCST, Mumbai site <ulink url="http://rohini.ncst.ernet.in/indix/">http://rohini.ncst.ernet.in/indix/</ulink>. The system is available in its source as well as binary form. This HOWTO covers the installation of the IndiX system using the binary files avaiable for download. At a later stage, I plan to cover the source installation of IndiX on your box, too. You need to download the following files in order to install IndiX sucessfully onto your machine:
    </para>
    <para>
      <simplelist>
        <member><filename>gtk.tar.gz</filename></member>
        <member><filename>indix.tar.gz</filename></member>
      </simplelist>
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Installing IndiX</title>
      <para>
        NCST has written Simpm ( Simple Package Manager ) that takes care of the entire installation process on your system. Simpm carries out the following steps for a binary distribution of the IndiX system:
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>It reads the names of the files within the distribution by essentially running the command <command>tar -tzpPf package.tgz &gt; .package.list</command></para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>It saves all these files and the file containing the list using the command <command>tar -czpPf .old.package.tgz .package.list `cat .package.list`</command></para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Simpm then extracts the files from the package and installs them using <command>tar -xzpPf package.tgz</command></para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        Should you wish to go back to the old system state for any reason, you can easily do so using <command>tar -xzpPf .old.package.tgz</command>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Running Simpm</title>
      <para>
        simpm with no arguments/parameters will display its usage.

      </para>
      <para>
        <programlisting>  # simpm -i package.tgz [-d savdir/]</programlisting>
        does all the above steps, 1 through 3. The 'i' flag indicates install. Successful installation will create <filename>savdir/.old.package.tgz</filename>. If it finds an existing <filename>.old.package.tgz</filename>, simpm will not proceed as it means that the IndiX system has already been installed earlier. However, you can force an IndiX install by renaming it to a newpackage. Alternatively, you can uninstall the package and install it again.
      </para>
      <para>
        <programlisting>  # simpm -u package.tgz [-d savdir/]</programlisting>
        uninstalls the package. Note, however, that this command will work only if it finds a readable <filename>.old.package.tgz</filename>. Having uninstalled the package, simpm will restore the original files that were overwritten by the package. The <filename>.old.package.tgz</filename> will be deleted after the uninstallation so that all instances of the previous installation are removed. Simpm maintains a log of all installs and uninstalls in the <filename>savdir/simpm.log</filename> file.
      </para>
      <para>
        To install the IndiX system, all you have to do is (pray and do your favourite tribal dance) type in the following commands:
      </para>
      <para>
        <programlisting>  # simpm -i /path/to/gtk.tar.gz
  # simpm -i /path/to/indix.tar.gz</programlisting>
        and all the necessary files will be backed up, and the IndiX system installed on your machine. Hurrah.
      </para>
      <para>
        Congratulations, o' most precious one, on having installed IndiX system on your machine. The remainder of this HOWTO will focus on setting up your Linux environment to support Indic fonts and scripts in X.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="iosetup">
    <title>Devanagri Input and Output setup</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Linux console</title>
      <para>
        Devanagari characters do not display properly in a Linux console. However, NCST has developed ncst-term (a terminal emulator program in X Window System) which has support for converting keystrokes to UTF-8 before sending them to the application running in the ncst-term, and for displaying Unicode characters that the application outputs as UTF-8 byte sequence.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="xwindows">
      <title>X Window System</title>
      <para>
        You need to make some changes in your <filename>XF86Config-4</filename> file (usually resides in <filename class="directory">/etc/X11/</filename> directory). A sample config file <filename>XF86Config-4.indix</filename> is installed along with IndiX system. This file can be found in <filename class="directory">/etc/X11/</filename> directory.
      </para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Devanagri Font</title>
        <para>
          OpenType is the most suitable font format to render any Indic script properly. The IndiX system ships with one OpenType font called "raghu" for Hindi. Anyone can use and distribute this font free-of-cost. You can find this font in <filename class="directory">/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/TrueType/</filename> directory.
        </para>
        <para>
          Installing the Indic Fonts:
        </para>
        <para>
          In order to install the Indic fonts, you must log in as root. The X Font Server (xfs) is known to have some problems with the IndiX system, so remove it from the FontPath of the X Server. This can be achieved by modifying your <filename>XF86Config-4</filename> file (usually in <filename class="directory">/etc/X11/</filename>) and commenting the line in the Files section and adding <filename class="directory">/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/TrueType/</filename> to the current FontPath.
        </para>
        <para>
          After that, the FontPath should look something similar to this:
          <programlisting>  FontPath   "unix/:7100"
  FontPath   "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/misc"
  FontPath   "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi"
  FontPath   "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi"
  FontPath   "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/TrueType"
  FontPath   "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/Type1"</programlisting>
          Next, in order to make use of the OpenType font you have, load the "freetype" module at startup. You can achieve this by adding the following line in the Module section of <filename>XF86Config-4</filename> file.
          <programlisting>  Load "freetype"</programlisting>
          Make sure you specify the modules search path in the Files section, too.
          <programlisting>  ModulePath "/usr/X11R6/lib/modules/fonts"
  ModulePath "/usr/X11R6/lib/modules/drivers"
  ModulePath "/usr/X11R6/lib/modules"
  ModulePath "/usr/X11R6/lib"
  ModulePath "/usr/lib"</programlisting>
          Any new Indic fonts you want to install should be placed in the <filename class="directory">/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/TrueType/</filename> directory. Now, change to this directory and run the following commands:
          <programlisting>  $ mkfontdir
  $ xset fp rehash</programlisting>
          In case you want to place your new Indic fonts in some other directory, you must use <command>xset</command> to add the new FontPath. Please see the <command>xset</command> man-page for further assistance.  You can check the new installed fonts by running the <command>xlsfonts</command> command. In case you don't see any Indic fonts using this command, you may need to restart X.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Devanagri Keyboard Layout</title>
        <para>
          The IndiX system comes with a keyboard map file for xmodmap. You can use the utility <command>xmodmap</command> to map a Devanagri keyboard. For most distributions, when you start X, the X-Server will look for a <filename>Xmodmap</filename> in <filename class="directory">/etc/X11/</filename> directory. If that file does not exist, the server will look for a <filename>.Xmodmap</filename> in your $HOME. Just putting the <filename>.Xmodmap</filename> in your $HOME will be okay. When you start the X server, it will load this file.  You can also load <filename>.Xmodmap</filename> from the command line:
          <programlisting>  $ xmodmap ~/.Xmodmap</programlisting>
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            If you are using XFree86 version 4.0 or later, you need to add the line XkbDisable in InputDevice section of <filename>XF86Config-4 file</filename>. You may config the keyboard section like the following sample.
            <programlisting>  Section "InputDevice"
  Identifier  "Keyboard0"
  Driver      "keyboard"
  Option      "XkbDisable"
  EndSection</programlisting>
          </para>
        </note>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="locale">
    <title>Locale Setup</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Files and the kernel</title>
      <para>
        You can now use any Unicode characters in file names. No kernel or file utilities need modifications. This is because file names in the kernel can be anything not containing a null byte, and '/' is used to delimit subdirectories. When encoded using UTF-8, non-ASCII characters will never be encoded using null bytes or slashes. All that happens is that file and directory names occupy more bytes than they contain characters. For example, a filename consisting of five greek characters will appear to the kernel as a 10-byte filename. The kernel does not know (and does not need to know) that these bytes are displayed as greek.
      </para>
      <para>
        This is the general theory, so long as your files reside on Linux. On filesystems which are used from other operating systems, you have mount options to control conversion of filenames to or from UTF-8:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The "vfat" filesystems has a mount option "utf8". See file <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/filesystems/vfat.txt</filename>. When you give an "iocharset" mount option different from the default (which is "iso8859-1"), the results with and without "utf8" are not consistent. Therefore, it is not I recommend to use the "iocharset" mount option.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The "msdos", "umsdos" filesystems have the same mount option, but appear to have no effect.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The "iso9660" filesystem has a mount option "utf8". See file <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/filesystems/isofs.txt</filename>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Since Linux 2.2.x kernels, the "ntfs" filesystem has a mount option "utf8". See file /usr/src/linux/Documentation/filesystems/ntfs.txt.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        The other filesystems (nfs, smbfs, ncpfs, hpfs, etc.) don't convert filenames; therefore they support Unicode file names in UTF-8 encoding only if the other operating system supports them. Please note that to enable a mount option for all future remounts, you add it to the fourth column of the corresponding <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> line.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Locale environment variables</title>
      <para>
        You should have the following environment variables set, containing locale names:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>LANGUAGE</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>override for LC_MESSAGES</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>LC_ALL</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>override for all other LC_* variables</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>LC_CTYPE, LC_MESSAGES, LC_COLLATE, LC_NUMERIC, LC_MONETARY, LC_TIME</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>individual variables for: character types and encoding, natural language messages, sorting rules, number formatting, money amount formatting, date and time display.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>LANG</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>default value for all LC_* variables. (See `man 7 locale' for a detailed description.)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>
        In order to tell your system and all applications that you are using UTF-8, you need to add a codeset suffix of UTF-8 to your locale names. For example, if you want to run an application in UTF-8 Hindi locale then with bash shell, you can specify which environment variable to be passed to the application.
        <programlisting>  $ LANG=hi_IN.UTF-8 xman</programlisting>
        In order to set locale the Hindi locale globally for a particular user, you can append the following line in <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> file.
        <programlisting>  export LANG=hi_IN.UTF-8</programlisting>
        After that you need not to set the LANG environment variable each time you run a specific application.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="apps">
    <title>Applications with Devanagri</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Browsers</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Netscape Navigator</title>
        <para>
          Netscape 6.01 or later can display HTML documents in UTF-8 encoding.  All a document needs is the following line between the &lt;head&gt; and &lt;/head&gt;  tags:
          <programlisting>  &lt;meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8"&gt;</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
          To setup Netscape so that it displays Hindi characters:
          <simplelist type="vert">
            <member>Goto, Edit -> Preferences </member>
            <member>Select category, Appearance -> Fonts</member>
            <member>Select Language encoding "Unicode"</member>
            <member>Set Variable-width and Fixed-width fonts to "raghu"</member>
            <member>Check button "Always use my font settings, overriding web page font"</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
        <para>
          Also, ensure that the character coding scheme is set to UTF-8
        </para>
        <para>
          <simplelist type="vert">
            <member>Goto, View -> Character Coding</member>
            <member>Select "Unicode (UTF-8)" from the list</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Konqueror</title>
        <para>
          Konqueror has good support for Unicode. To setup konqueror so that it displays Hindi characters:
          <simplelist type="vert">
            <member>Goto, Settings -> Configure Konqueror</member>
            <member>Select "Konqueror Bowser" from the left pan</member>
            <member>Goto "Appearance" tab on the right pan</member>
            <member>Select charset "iso106460-1"</member>
            <member>Set all fonts to "raghu" for this encoding and also set Default encoding to "utf8"</member>
          </simplelist>
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Editors</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>yudit</title>
        <para>
          <command>yudit</command> by G&aacute;sp&aacute;r Sinai (<ulink url="http://czyborra.com/yudit/">http://czyborra.com/yudit/</ulink>) is an excellent unicode text editor for the X Window System. It supports simultaneous processing of many languages, input methods, conversions for local character standards etc. It has facilities for entering text in all languages with only an English keyboard, using keyboard configuration maps. Customization is very easy. Typically you will first want to customize your font. From the font menu, choose "Unicode". Next, you should customize your input method. The input methods "Straight", "Unicode" and "SGML" are most remarkable. For details about the other built-in input methods, look in <filename class="directory">/usr/local/share/yudit/data/</filename>.  To make a change the default for the next session, edit your <filename>$HOME/.yuditrc</filename> file. The general editor functionality is limited to editing, cut and paste and search and replace. There is no provision for an undo. <command>yudit</command> can display text using a TrueType font. But it doesn't seem to support combining characters.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Vim</title>
        <para>
          Vim (as of version 6.0) has good support for UTF-8. When started in an UTF-8 locale, it assumes UTF-8 encoding for the console and the text files being edited. It supports double-wide (CJK) characters as well and combining characters and therefore fits perfectly into UTF-8 enabled ncst-term.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>gedit</title>
        <para>
          gedit is an editor developed using GtkText widget. gedit-0.9.0 does not support FontSet. This means that you can't edit both English and Hindi text simultaneously. But if you choose a proper font then you will be able to use any one language at a time.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>xedit</title>
        <para>
          With XFree86-4.0.1, <command>xedit</command> is capable of editing UTF-8 files if your locale is set appropriately. Add the line
          <programlisting>  "Xedit*international: true"</programlisting>
          to your <filename>$HOME/.Xdefaults</filename> file.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Mailers</title>
      <para>
        Mail clients released after January 1, 1999, should be capable of sending and displaying UTF-8 encoded mails, otherwise they are considered deficient. But these mails have to carry the MIME labels:
        <programlisting>  Content-Type: text/plain; charset=UTF-8
  Content-Transfer-Encoding: 8bit</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        Simply piping an UTF-8 file into "mail" without caring about the MIME labels will not work. Mail client implementors should take a look at <ulink url="http://www.imc.org/imc-intl/">http://www.imc.org/imc-intl/</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.imc.org/mail-i18n.html">http://www.imc.org/mail-i18n.html</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Now about some of the individual mail clients (or "mail user agents"):
      </para>
      <sect3>
        <title>kmail</title>
        <para>
          kmail (as of KDE 1.0) does not support UTF-8 mails at all.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Netscape Mail</title>
        <para>
          Netscape Mail can send and display mails in UTF-8 encoding, but it needs a little bit of manual user intervention. To send an UTF-8 encoded mail:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para>After opening the "Mail" window, but before starting to compose the message, select from the menu "View -> Character Coding -> Unicode (UTF-8)".</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Then compose the message and send it.</para></listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
          When you receive an UTF-8 encoded mail, Netscape does not display it in UTF-8 right away, and does not even give a visual clue that the mail was encoded in UTF-8. You have to manually select from the menu
          <guimenu>View</guimenu> -> <guisubmenu>Character Coding</guisubmenu> -> <guimenuitem>Unicode (UTF-8)</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para>
          For displaying UTF-8 mails, Netscape uses different fonts. You can adjust your font settings in the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> -> <guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu> -> <guimenuitem>Fonts</guimenuitem>
          dialog by selecting the "Unicode" font category.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>exmh</title>
        <para>
          exmh 2.1.2 with Tk 8.4a1 can recognize and correctly display UTF-8 mails if you add the following lines to your <filename>$HOME/.Xdefaults</filename> file.
          <programlisting>  !
  ! Exmh
  !
  exmh.mimeUCharsets: utf-8
  exmh.mime_utf-8_registry: iso10646
  exmh.mime_utf-8_encoding: 1
  exmh.mime_utf-8_plain_families: fixed
  exmh.mime_utf-8_fixed_families: fixed
  exmh.mime_utf-8_proportional_families: fixed
  exmh.mime_utf-8_title_families: fixed</programlisting>
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="references">
    <title>References and sites</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>IndiX links</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://rohini.ncst.ernet.in/indix/">IndiX Homepage</ulink></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://rohini.ncst.ernet.in/indix/download/">IndiX Download</ulink></para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Centurion Linux and Exodus GNU/Linux</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The good guys at Centurion Linux have finished work on <productname>Exodus GNU/Linux</productname>, a 100% Free Software distribution featuring full Hindi language support for GNOME and KDE. The much awaited <productname>Exodus GNU/Linux</productname> (code named BitterCoffee) is expected to be released in the Indian market shortly.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://centurionlinux.com/">Centurion Linux Homepage</ulink></para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><ulink url="http://cl-india.sourceforge.net/">The Official GNOME i18n Team - India (hindi)</ulink></para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unicode</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.unicode.org">The official Unicode website</ulink></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/unicode.html">UTF-8 and Unicode FAQ</ulink></para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="faq">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>
            I can't start the X windows system. It gives an error "Could not open default Indic font 'xyz'".
          </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            Please make sure that the font 'xyz' is correctly installed and is in the current FontPath. The Indic fonts usually reside in the <filename class="directory">/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/TrueType/</filename> directory. Your FontPath is defined in the <filename>/etc/X11/XFree86Config-4</filename> file. To learn more about howto specify your FontPath, read the section on X Window System (3.2) in this HOWTO.
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>
            Can I use any other font as the default system font instead of the raghu font shipped with the IndiX system?
          </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            You can load an Indic script font by giving command line server option while starting X Window System. e.g.
            <programlisting>  $ startx -- -devanagari "my_devanagari_font"</programlisting> 
            or 
            <programlisting>  $ startx -- -tamil "my_tamil_font"</programlisting>
            Here, "my_devanagari_font" and "my_tamil_font" should be replaced by the font name that you want to load. You can either specify alias name or full XLFD name for the font. However alias name must be there in <filename>fonts.alias</filename> file and XLFD name in <filename>fonts.dir</filename> file.
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>
            I have installed IndiX system but it doesn't show Hindi characters. Why?
          </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            This could possibly be due to the fact that your Hindi locale has not been setup correctly. To change/set the locale you should set LANG environment variable. Append the line
            <programlisting>  export LANG=hi_IN.UTF-8</programlisting>
            in your <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> and <filename>~/.bash_profile</filename> files. Restart your terminal emulator program and run the application. After this the application should display Hindi characters.
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>
            Why are some of the pixels in Hindi characters distorted?
          </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            This is probably because the X Font Server (xfs) is running and is still in the current FontPath. You can either shutdown the X Font Server or remove it from the current FontPath. To shutdown xfs issue the following command after becoming root:
            <programlisting>  # /etc/rc.d/init.d/xfs stop</programlisting>
            To remove xfs from the current FontPath, read the section <xref linkend="xwindows"/> in this HOWTO.
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>
            All Hindi characters are displayed, but why are they not rendered properly?
          </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            IndiX system uses an OpenType font to render Indic script characters, as it is the most suitable font format for Indic scripts. If you use some other kind of font, for example a TrueType font or a Bitmap font, then the font does not have enough information that is required to render Indic script text properly. So it is recommended to use only OpenType fonts for Indic scripts. Also, in case you are already using an OpenType font, please update your glibc.
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>
            Why can't I download <acronym>ISO</acronym> images of <productname>Exodus GNU/Linux</productname>, yet?
          </para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>
            The good guys at Centurion Linux are looking for sponsors who can take care of their hosting needs. If you are interested in helping Centurion Linux out, please contact me on <email>bali@centurionlinux.com</email>.
          </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="notices">
    <title>Acknowledgements and Copyright</title>
    <para>
      Parts of this HOWTO have been taken from <ulink url="http://www.linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/Unicode-HOWTO.html">The Unicode HOWTO</ulink> by Bruno Haible and The Devanagri HOWTO by Keyur Shroff.
    </para>
    <para>
      I would also like to take this opportunity to thank my papa, mummy and my brothers Manvinder and Kulvinder for their unconditional love and support, without whom I could never have achieved anything in life. Forever, I love you. Loshaca :)
    </para>
    <para>
      To Girija, my girlfriend: :) Thanks for everything.
    </para>
    <para>
      I am very grateful to Keyur Shroff for allowing me to modify and redistribute his Devanagri HOWTO. Special thanks go out to him for his guidance, help, and support.
    </para>
    <para>
      Thanks to Rohan D'Sa and Manvinder Bali of Centurion Linux for having helped me with various UTF-8 and Indic scripts issues. Also, thanks for representing Centurion Linux at the Business Technology meet organised by Ministry of Information Technology, New Delhi.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once again, special thanks to Dan Scott for converting the HOWTO to DocBook XML format. Thanks Dan :) 
    </para>
    <para>
      This HOWTO is copyrighted &copy; 2001-2002 by Maninder Bali, <email>bali@centurionlinux.com</email> and is distributed under the terms of the <link linkend="fdl">GNU Free Documentation License</link> (<acronym>GFDL</acronym>) stated below.
    </para>
  </sect1>
<!--  
     The GNU Free Documentation License 1.1 in DocBook
     Markup by Eric Baudais <baudais@okstate.edu>
     Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
     http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
     Version: 1.0.1
     Last Modified: Nov 16, 2000
-->
<appendix id="fdl">
  <appendixinfo>
    <releaseinfo>
      Version 1.1, March 2000
    </releaseinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year><holder>Free Software Foundation, Inc.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice id="fdl-legalnotice">
      <para>
	<address>Free Software Foundation, Inc. <street>59 Temple Place, 
        Suite 330</street>, <city>Boston</city>, <state>MA</state>  
        <postcode>02111-1307</postcode>  <country>USA</country></address> 
	Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this 
        license document, but changing it is not allowed.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </appendixinfo>
  <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

  <sect1 id="fdl-preamble">
    <title>0. PREAMBLE</title>
    <para>
      The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
      other written document <quote>free</quote> in the sense of
      freedom: to assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and
      redistribute it, with or without modifying it, either
      commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily, this License
      preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit for
      their work, while not being considered responsible for
      modifications made by others.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      This License is a kind of <quote>copyleft</quote>, which means
      that derivative works of the document must themselves be free in
      the same sense. It complements the GNU General Public License,
      which is a copyleft license designed for free software.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for

      free software, because free software needs free documentation: a
      free program should come with manuals providing the same
      freedoms that the software does. But this License is not limited
      to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
      regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
      printed book. We recommend this License principally for works
      whose purpose is instruction or reference.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="fdl-section1">
    <title>1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>
    <para id="fdl-document">
      This License applies to any manual or other work that contains a
      notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
      distributed under the terms of this License. The
      <quote>Document</quote>, below, refers to any such manual or
      work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is addressed
      as <quote>you</quote>.
    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-modified">
      A <quote>Modified Version</quote> of the Document means any work
      containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
      verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
      language.
    </para>
	
    <para id="fdl-secondary">
      A <quote>Secondary Section</quote> is a named appendix or a
      front-matter section of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> that deals exclusively
      with the relationship of the publishers or authors of the
      Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related
      matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within
      that overall subject. (For example, if the Document is in part a
      textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
      mathematics.)  The relationship could be a matter of historical
      connection with the subject or with related matters, or of
      legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position
      regarding them.
    </para>

    <para id="fdl-invariant">
      The <quote>Invariant Sections</quote> are certain <link
      linkend="fdl-secondary"> Secondary Sections</link> whose titles
      are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the
      notice that says that the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> is released under this
      License.
    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-cover-texts">
      The <quote>Cover Texts</quote> are certain short passages of
      text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts,
      in the notice that says that the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> is released under this
      License.
    </para>
	
    <para id="fdl-transparent">
      A <quote>Transparent</quote> copy of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document"> Document</link> means a machine-readable
      copy, represented in a format whose specification is available
      to the general public, whose contents can be viewed and edited
      directly and straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for
      images composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for
      drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is
      suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
      translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
      formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
      whose markup has been designed to thwart or discourage
      subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent.  A copy
      that is not <quote>Transparent</quote> is called
      <quote>Opaque</quote>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
      plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
      format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
      standard-conforming simple HTML designed for human
      modification. Opaque formats include PostScript, PDF,
      proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
      proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD
      and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the
      machine-generated HTML produced by some word processors for
      output purposes only.
    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-title-page">
      The <quote>Title Page</quote> means, for a printed book, the
      title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed to
      hold, legibly, the material this License requires to appear in
      the title page. For works in formats which do not have any title
      page as such, <quote>Title Page</quote> means the text near the
      most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the
      beginning of the body of the text.
    </para>
  </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section2">
    <title>2. VERBATIM COPYING</title>
    <para>
      You may copy and distribute the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> in any medium, either
      commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
      copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License
      applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that
      you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
      License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or
      control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
      distribute. However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
      copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
      must also follow the conditions in <link
      linkend="fdl-section3">section 3</link>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
      above, and you may publicly display copies.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section3">
    <title>3. COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>
    <para>
      If you publish printed copies of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> numbering more than 100,
      and the Document's license notice requires <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover Texts</link>, you must enclose
      the copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these
      Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and
      Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also
      clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these
      copies. The front cover must present the full title with all
      words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
      other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes
      limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the
      <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> and satisfy these
      conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
      respects.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
      legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
      reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
      adjacent pages.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If you publish or distribute <link
      linkend="fdl-transparent">Opaque</link> copies of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> numbering more than 100,
      you must either include a machine-readable <link
      linkend="fdl-transparent">Transparent</link> copy along with
      each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
      publicly-accessible computer-network location containing a
      complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added
      material, which the general network-using public has access to
      download anonymously at no charge using public-standard network
      protocols. If you use the latter option, you must take
      reasonably prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque
      copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent copy will
      remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
      year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly
      or through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the
      public.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors
      of the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> well before
      redistributing any large number of copies, to give them a chance
      to provide you with an updated version of the Document.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section4">
    <title>4. MODIFICATIONS</title>
    <para>
      You may copy and distribute a <link
      linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link> of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> under the conditions of
      sections <link linkend="fdl-section2">2</link> and <link
      linkend="fdl-section3">3</link> above, provided that you release
      the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the
      Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus
      licensing distribution and modification of the Modified Version
      to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do
      these things in the Modified Version:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>A</title>
	  <para>
	    Use in the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title
	    Page</link> (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct
	    from that of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>, and from those of
	    previous versions (which should, if there were any, be
	    listed in the History section of the Document). You may
	    use the same title as a previous version if the original
	    publisher of that version gives permission.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>B</title>
	  <para>
	    List on the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title
	    Page</link>, as authors, one or more persons or entities
	    responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
	    <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>,
	    together with at least five of the principal authors of
	    the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> (all of
	    its principal authors, if it has less than five).
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>C</title>
	  <para>
	    State on the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title
	    Page</link> the name of the publisher of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>, as the
	    publisher.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>D</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve all the copyright notices of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>E</title>
	  <para>
	    Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
	    adjacent to the other copyright notices.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>F</title>
	  <para>
	    Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a
	    license notice giving the public permission to use the
	    <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link> under
	    the terms of this License, in the form shown in the
	    Addendum below.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>G</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve in that license notice the full lists of <link
	    linkend="fdl-invariant"> Invariant Sections</link> and
	    required <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover
	    Texts</link> given in the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document's</link> license notice.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>H</title>
	  <para>
	    Include an unaltered copy of this License.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>I</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve the section entitled <quote>History</quote>, and
	    its title, and add to it an item stating at least the
	    title, year, new authors, and publisher of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version </link>as given on
	    the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title Page</link>.  If
	    there is no section entitled <quote>History</quote> in the
	    <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>, create one
	    stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the
	    Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item
	    describing the Modified Version as stated in the previous
	    sentence.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>J</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve the network location, if any, given in the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> for public access
	    to a <link linkend="fdl-transparent">Transparent</link>
	    copy of the Document, and likewise the network locations
	    given in the Document for previous versions it was based
	    on. These may be placed in the <quote>History</quote>
	    section.  You may omit a network location for a work that
	    was published at least four years before the Document
	    itself, or if the original publisher of the version it
	    refers to gives permission.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>K</title>
	  <para>
	    In any section entitled <quote>Acknowledgements</quote> or
	    <quote>Dedications</quote>, preserve the section's title,
	    and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of
	    each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
	    dedications given therein.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>L</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve all the <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
	    Sections</link> of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>, unaltered in their
	    text and in their titles.  Section numbers or the
	    equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>M</title>
	  <para>
	    Delete any section entitled
	    <quote>Endorsements</quote>. Such a section may not be
	    included in the <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified
	    Version</link>.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>N</title>
	  <para>
	    Do not retitle any existing section as
	    <quote>Endorsements</quote> or to conflict in title with
	    any <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
	    Section</link>.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
      If the <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>
      includes new front-matter sections or appendices that qualify as
      <link linkend="fdl-secondary">Secondary Sections</link> and
      contain no material copied from the Document, you may at your
      option designate some or all of these sections as invariant. To
      do this, add their titles to the list of <link
      linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant Sections</link> in the
      Modified Version's license notice.  These titles must be
      distinct from any other section titles.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may add a section entitled <quote>Endorsements</quote>,
      provided it contains nothing but endorsements of your <link
      linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link> by various
      parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text
      has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
      definition of a standard.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may add a passage of up to five words as a <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Front-Cover Text</link>, and a passage
      of up to 25 words as a <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Back-Cover Text</link>, to the end of
      the list of <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover Texts</link>
      in the <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>.
      Only one passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text
      may be added by (or through arrangements made by) any one
      entity. If the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>
      already includes a cover text for the same cover, previously
      added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are
      acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
      replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
      publisher that added the old one.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The author(s) and publisher(s) of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> do not by this License
      give permission to use their names for publicity for or to
      assert or imply endorsement of any <link
      linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version </link>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section5">
    <title>5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>
    <para>
      You may combine the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>
      with other documents released under this License, under the
      terms defined in <link linkend="fdl-section4">section 4</link>
      above for modified versions, provided that you include in the
      combination all of the <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
      Sections</link> of all of the original documents, unmodified,
      and list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in
      its license notice.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The combined work need only contain one copy of this License,
      and multiple identical <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
      Sections</link> may be replaced with a single copy. If there are
      multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different
      contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding
      at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original
      author or publisher of that section if known, or else a unique
      number. Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the
      list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined
      work.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled
      <quote>History</quote> in the various original documents,
      forming one section entitled <quote>History</quote>; likewise
      combine any sections entitled <quote>Acknowledgements</quote>,
      and any sections entitled <quote>Dedications</quote>.  You must
      delete all sections entitled <quote>Endorsements.</quote>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section6">
    <title>6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>
    <para>
      You may make a collection consisting of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> and other documents
      released under this License, and replace the individual copies
      of this License in the various documents with a single copy that
      is included in the collection, provided that you follow the
      rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of the
      documents in all other respects.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
      dispbibute it individually under this License, provided you
      insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
      follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
      copying of that document.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section7">
    <title>7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
    <para>
      A compilation of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> or its derivatives with
      other separate and independent documents or works, in or on a
      volume of a storage or distribution medium, does not as a whole
      count as a <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>
      of the Document, provided no compilation copyright is claimed
      for the compilation.  Such a compilation is called an
      <quote>aggregate</quote>, and this License does not apply to the
      other self-contained works thus compiled with the Document , on
      account of their being thus compiled, if they are not themselves
      derivative works of the Document.  If the <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover Text</link> requirement of <link
      linkend="fdl-section3">section 3</link> is applicable to these
      copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one
      quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may
      be placed on covers that surround only the Document within the
      aggregate. Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole
      aggregate.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section8">
    <title>8. TRANSLATION</title>
    <para>
      Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
      distribute translations of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> under the terms of <link
      linkend="fdl-section4">section 4</link>. Replacing <link
      linkend="fdl-invariant"> Invariant Sections</link> with
      translations requires special permission from their copyright
      holders, but you may include translations of some or all
      Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these
      Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this
      License provided that you also include the original English
      version of this License. In case of a disagreement between the
      translation and the original English version of this License,
      the original English version will prevail.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section9">
    <title>9. TERMINATION</title>
    <para>
      You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> except as expressly
      provided for under this License. Any other attempt to copy,
      modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
      automatically terminate your rights under this License. However,
      parties who have received copies, or rights, from you under this
      License will not have their licenses terminated so long as such
      parties remain in full compliance.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section10">
    <title>10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>
    <para>
      The <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnu.org/fsf/fsf.html">Free Software
      Foundation</ulink> may publish new, revised versions of the GNU
      Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
      will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ
      in detail to address new problems or concerns. See <ulink
      type="http"
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
      number. If the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>
      specifies that a particular numbered version of this License
      <quote>or any later version</quote> applies to it, you have the
      option of following the terms and conditions either of that
      specified version or of any later version that has been
      published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If
      the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
      you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by
      the Free Software Foundation.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="fdl-using">
    <title>Addendum</title>
    <para>
      To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy of
      the License in the document and put the following copyright and
      license notices just after the title page:
    </para>
    
    <blockquote>
      <para>
	Copyright &copy; YEAR YOUR NAME.
      </para>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
	document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
	License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the
	Free Software Foundation; with the <link
	linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant Sections</link> being LIST
	THEIR TITLES, with the <link
	linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Front-Cover Texts</link> being LIST,
	and with the <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Back-Cover
	Texts</link> being LIST.  A copy of the license is included in
	the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation
	License</quote>.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
      
    <para>
      If you have no <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
      Sections</link>, write <quote>with no Invariant Sections</quote>
      instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have no
      <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Front-Cover Texts</link>, write
      <quote>no Front-Cover Texts</quote> instead of
      <quote>Front-Cover Texts being LIST</quote>; likewise for <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Back-Cover Texts</link>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code,
      we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
      choice of free software license, such as the <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"> GNU General Public
      License</ulink>, to permit their use in free software.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>  
</article>




