<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Linux Installfest HOWTO</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Eric</firstname>
      <othername>(AKA Rick)</othername>
      <surname>Meyerhoff</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <address>
          <email>rick-at-eworld3-dot-net</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
         <editor>
             <firstname>Simon</firstname>
             <surname>Gibson</surname>
             <contrib>Language Review</contrib>
         </editor>
         <editor>
             <firstname>Emma Jane</firstname>
             <surname>Hogbin</surname>
             <contrib>Metadata/Markup Review</contrib>
         </editor>
         <editor>
             <firstname>Rick</firstname>
             <surname>Moen</surname>
             <contrib>Language Review</contrib>
         </editor>
    <pubdate>2004-06-01</pubdate>
    <abstract>
      <para>
      This document provides some guidelines that should help you
      run a successful installfest. 
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
        <date>2010-01-01</date>
        <authorinitials>EM</authorinitials>
        <revremark>
        Annual review and update. 
	Just changed the copyright date.
        </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
        <date>2006-12-31</date>
        <authorinitials>EM</authorinitials>
        <revremark>
        Annual review and update. 
	Just changed the copyright date and added AKA.
        </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
        <date>2006-04-12</date>
        <authorinitials>EM</authorinitials>
        <revremark>
        Added the Translations section, corrected the section number
        references in the license and removed the 
        reference to the defunct www.installfest.org.
        </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
        <date>2004-09-04</date>
        <authorinitials>EM</authorinitials>
        <revremark>
        Added obfuscated email address. 
        </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>2004-06-01</date>
        <authorinitials>EM</authorinitials>
        <revremark>
        Initial release. 
        Thanks to
        Tabatha "CTRL-I" Marshall for all her encouragement.
        </revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1
    id = "Introduction"
  >
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    This document provides some guidelines that should help you
    run a successful installfest. 
    For purposes of this document, an installfest is a gathering at
    which experienced Linux users assist less experienced users with the
    installation and configuration of Linux distributions,
    and where Linux users can
    bring Linux systems to receive assistance with system problem
    remediation.
    </para>
    <para>
    Please take from this document whatever you want. It is meant to be
    a guide, not a recipe that must be followed exactly 
    to have a successful installfest.
    Any installfest where most of the people leave happy is a 
    successful event.
    </para>
    <sect2
      id = "CopyrightAndLicense"
    >
      <title>Copyright and License</title>
      <para>
      Copyright (c) 2003 through 2010 Eric Meyerhoff.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and 
      no Back-Cover Texts.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled 
      "GNU Free Documentation License".
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2
      id = "Scope"
    >
      <title>Scope</title>
      <para>
      In order to limit the scope of this document, there
      are some issues that will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be covered:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            While other activities may occur at the same time and in
            roughly the same location as an installfest, they will not be
            considered part of the installfest for the purposes of
            this document. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            This document does not include any discussion of
            technical issues related to the
            installation of any Linux distribution. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            This document does not currently contain any discussion
            of installfest
            server or network configuration, although such a discussion may be
            added to this document in the future. It may be more appropriate
            for such information to be contained in a separate HOWTO.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            This document does not contain any discussion of new
            user education.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2
      id = "Version"
    >
      <title>Version</title>
      <para>
      The current version of this document can be found at 
      <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">
      The Linux Documentation Project (http://www.tldp.org)
      </ulink>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2
      id = "Translations"
    >
      <title>Translations</title>
      <para>
      You are welcome to translate this document into another language but
      please see the TRANSLATIONS section of the license for
      information regarding your responsibilities. 
      <para>
      Also, please work with the helpful and kind people at
      <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">
      The Linux Documentation Project (http://www.tldp.org)
      </ulink>
      so that you can contribute your translation to the project.
      </para>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2
      id = "Disclaimer"
    >
      <title>Disclaimer</title>
      <para>
      No liability for the contents of this document can be
      accepted. Use the concepts, examples and information at your own
      risk. There may be errors and inaccuracies, that could be
      damaging to your system. Proceed with caution, and although it
      is highly unlikely that accidents will happen because of
      following advice or procedures described in this document, the
      author(s) take no responsibility for damage claimed to be caused
      by doing so.
      </para>
      <para>
      All copyrights are held by their by their respective owners,
      unless specifically noted otherwise. Use of a term in this
      document should not be regarded as affecting the validity of any
      trademark or service mark. Naming of particular products or
      brands should not be seen as endorsements. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1
    id = "Roles"
  >
    <title>Roles</title>
    <para>
    People involved in an installfest will assume one or more of the
    following roles
    </para>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>coordinator</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            contact for all other participants
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>host</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            has the connection to the location
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>sponsor</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            represents an organization that provides the location, 
            equipment, network, materials, food, beverages, etc. to 
            the installfest
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>user</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            needs assistance installing a Linux distribution
            or solving a specific problem
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>receptionist</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                  greets people as they come in, gives them a name tag and
                  has them sign a waiver
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                  can direct people to the restrooms, 
                  the nearest computer store
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                  orders food and beverages
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>tier 1 support</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            people who are knowledgeable about Linux and
            are willing to share their knowledge and provide hands-on 
            assistance to users
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>tier 2 support</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            sets up and maintains network hardware and 
            services (DNS, DHCP), mirrors of Linux distributions
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1
    id = "BeforeDuringAndAfter"
  >
    <title>Before, During and After</title>
    <para>
    This HOWTO has three sections for things you should think about or do
    <emphasis>before</emphasis>, <emphasis>during</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>after</emphasis> 
    the day of the installfest. It is assumed
    that you will be having installfests periodically and hopefully regularly.
    </para>
    <sect2
      id = "Before"
    >
      <title>Before (preparation)</title>
      <sect3
        id = "DateTimeAndDuration"
      >
        <title>date, time and duration</title>
        <para>
        In order to reach the most people, fests should be held
        on both weekends and weekdays. The time of day is not
        as important as the duration of the fest, which should
        be 6 to 10 hours. Here is why:
        </para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
              some people will not be able to arrive when the fest starts 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
              it takes time to get systems moved in, connected,
              disconnected and moved out of the working area
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
              making sub-systems like sound, printers and other
              peripherals function
              properly sometimes takes as long as a Linux installation
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
              some people want to get some life out of older CPUs but
              OS installation takes longer on slower machines
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3
        id = "Location"
      >
        <title>location</title>
        <para>
        Make sure that the place where your installfest will be held has:
        </para>
        <para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>strong tables</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Each table may have to hold multiple monitors and computers.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>restrooms</term>
              <listitem>
                <para></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>chairs</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                People will want to sit down since they will be at 
                the fest for several hours.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Internet access</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Some people will want to know that they can access the
                Internet from their computer. Some people will need 
                to download drivers or other software. A lot of helpful
                information is available on the Net. There is a list of
                Web sites at the end of this document.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>an address that is easy to find</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                A map and simple directions will help.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>telephone connection</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                A normal line, not through a PBX, not digital, just POTS
                will be useful for testing modems.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>an easy way to get hardware in and out</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                How will people bring their hardware from their cars
                to the installation room? Are 
                carts and elevators available?
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>sufficient AC power</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Try to make sure that you have
                enough power for the number of computers that you 
                expect people to bring. You do not want people
                to suddenly lose power because one person too many
                turned on his or her computer.
                </para>
                <para>
                How much power does a computer need?
                Laptops need about 0.5 amps.
                For a desktop/tower/workstation type of computer
                the amount of power needed depends on the monitor, 
                number of disk drives, etc.
                Basically though, if everything is connected to one
                power strip, then they need at most 3 to 4 amps at the moment
                that the power is turned on and 1.5 to 2 amps while
                they are running.
                </para>
                <para>
                You should try to have access to the circuit breakers 
                either directly or 
                through readily available maintenance staff.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </para>
        <para>
        If you are lucky you will be able to make arrangements to
        regularly hold installfests at
        a few locations that meet your needs. If possible you should 
        hold your fests at a variety of locations such as 
        technical colleges, universities and businesses because 
        Linux is for everyone.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3
        id = "Administration"
      >
        <title>administration</title>
        <para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Linux distributions (distros)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Make sure that you will have several copies of the latest
                versions of the major Linux distributions available
                on CD. Some users will need small/minimal distributions
                on floppy disks so make sure that those are available.
                To learn which distributions to make available, please 
                do a little research on the Web sites listed in the 
                appendix of this document.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>installfest server</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                You may want to consider setting up a server for:
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>DNS</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>DHCP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>mirrors of distributions</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
                <para>
                You should provide multiple methods of 
                accessing the distributions on the server:
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>FTP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>rcp</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>HTTP</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>CD burning</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>NFS</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
                <para>
                In order to conserve disk space
                you can create a virtual CD-ROM jukebox. 
                See Randolph J. Tata's "CDServer-HOWTO"
                (<ulink url="http://talcon.com/cdserver-howto/">
                http://talcon.com/cdserver-howto/</ulink>) 
                and Jeremy Impson's article 
                "Build a Virtual CD-ROM Jukebox"
                (<ulink url="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article.php?sid=5639">
                http://www.linuxjournal.com/article.php?sid=5639
                </ulink>) for more information.
                </para>
                <para>
                Hopefully someone will create a new Linux distribution to make
                it easy to set up such a server. 
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>name tags</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Something similar to the classic "hello my name is:" stickers.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>misc. office supplies</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                You may want to make some of the following items available:
                scratch paper, ball-point pens,
                sharpies, scissors, stapler, duct tape, packing tape,
                blank FAT formatted floppy disks (used are fine),
                blank CD-R media.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>advertising</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                People will need to know:
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>when and where the installfest will be held</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>what to expect: waiver, soft drinks, pizza</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      that if they wish to install a Linux
                      distribution should bring every 
                      part of their computer system:
                      monitor, keyboard, mouse, speakers, USB devices, 
                      power strip. Support people will need all the components
                      to make sure everything is functioning properly.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      that they may want to bring blank CD-R media
                      to trade for copies of distributions on CD-R (they should
                      determine the number of disks needed for each 
                      distribution)
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
                <para>
                Here are some places to consider advertising:
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>local computer user Web sites</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>local news media</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>local computer retail stores</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>minimum system requirements</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Some people will want to install Linux on very old/slow 
                systems in an attempt to make them usable. This is OK,
                but there are limitations. Please look at the
                distributions area of 
                <ulink url="http://www.linux.org">
                www.linux.org</ulink> 
                for minimalist distributions. 

                You may want to include minimum system requirements 
                in your installfest advertisement so that people do
                not show up with an old machine, hoping to turn it
                into a power-house but leave disappointed.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>networking equipment</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                someone will need to bring network switches and cables
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>signage</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                You should have a few signs posted to help people
                find their way around the location and provide other 
                information. Some examples are:
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      main entrance:
                      So people know that they have found the right location.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      reception desk:
                      People will need to find the reception desk from the
                      main entrance.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      installation room:
                      People will need to know how to get to the installation
                      from the reception desk.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>rest rooms</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>networking information</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>food and beverages</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                Due to the duration of an installfest you should  
                consider the availability of food and drink.
                </para>
                <para>
                Pizza usually works out well.
                Tell people that you will be collecting a specific amount
                of money at the door for pizza. If they 
                <emphasis>do not</emphasis> want to
                share some pizza, then they 
                <emphasis>do not</emphasis> need to pay.
                In order to know who has paid, use an ink stamp to
                mark their hand. Do not forget paper plates and napkins.
                </para>
                <para>
                If there are no vending machines at the 
                location you may want to
                provide soft drinks, including water and possibly coffee
                during the fest. If you do provide drinks, you should
                consider selling them at cost. 
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2
      id = "During"
    >
      <title>During (on the day of the installfest)</title>
      <para>
          <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              before the starting time
              </para>
            <para>
              The people who run the fest need to be at the location at 
              least one hour before the fest is to begin. They will need
              time to set up the network, installfest server, 
              power system, signage, etc.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            at the door/reception
            </para>
            <para>
            Depending on how you have decided to operate your fest, 
            the receptionist will:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>ask users to sign a waiver</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>ask users to fill out a data sheet</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>ask all attendees to contribute money for 
                  food and/or drinks</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>give all attendees name tags</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            during
            </para>
            <para>
            Since you are using this HOWTO, everything will work out fine.
            People should understand that it is OK to ask around for help. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            after the fest is finished
            </para>
            <para>
            Make sure that all areas are cleaned up because 
            you may want to use the location again and you do not
            want to give the location owner a bad impression. 
            Look for: items people have forgotten, items that people
            brought as "give aways", drink cans and cups.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2
      id = "After"
    >
      <title>After (lessons learned)</title>
      <para>
      We would like to continually improve this document and 
      everyone's installfest experience, so please share with us:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>what went wrong?</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>what went well?</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>new ideas?</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>How this document helped or hindered you.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <appendix>
    <title>Sample Forms</title>
    <sect1
      id = "DataSheet"
    >
      <title>Data Sheet</title>
      <para>
      This data sheet is intended to be filled out by users when 
      they arrive at the reception area.
      </para>
      <para>
      <emphasis>Installfest Data Sheet</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
      This form is <emphasis>for your benefit</emphasis>!
      It will help you and anyone
      who works on your computer to make reasonable decisions.
      Please complete
      one form per computer. If you don't know the answer now, just wait
      until you do.
      </para>
      <para>
      Your name: ______________________________________________________
      </para>
      <para>
      CPU type: __________________________________
      speed: ________ megahertz / gigahertz
      </para>
      <para>
      RAM: _________ megabytes
      </para>
      <para>
      Hard drive 1: ______gigabytes  
      2: ______gigabytes  
      3: ______gigabytes  
      4: ______gigabytes  
      </para>
      <para>
      Video card: ____________________________
      </para>
      <para>
      Monitor:  ______________________________
      </para>
      <para>
      Sound card: __________________________________________
      </para>
      <para>
      Does this computer have (circle all that apply):
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>CD or CD-RW drive</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>DVD</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>floppy drive</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>network interface</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>modem / winmodem</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>printer</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>other: _________________________________________</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
      Which of these do you want to do:
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Install Linux:
            </para>
            <para>
            What distribution? ____________________________
            </para>
            <para>
            Do you need disks? Yes / No
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Fix one or more specific problems with an installation of Linux:
            </para>
            <para>
            What distribution is installed? __________________
            </para>
            <para>
            List the software tool(s) and/or hardware that you
            need help fixing: __________________________________________
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Other, please explain:____________________________
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
      Do you want to (circle one):
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Dual-boot Linux and an already-installed OS?
            </para>
            <para>
            What is the name of other O.S.? ______________________
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Install Linux as the only O.S.?
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Install multiple Linux distributions?
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
      What do you want to use the computer for? (circle all that apply) 
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Internet access and usage</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>learn Linux</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>firewall</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>server</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>writing documents</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>music/image storage</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>other (please explain):</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
      What is your skill level with (circle all that apply):
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Linux/Unix:
            </para>
            <para>first-timer</para>
				<para>rookie beginner </para> 
            <para>intermediate</para>
				<para>advanced</para>
				<para>guru</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            computer hardware:
            </para>
            <para>first-timer</para>
				<para>rookie beginner </para> 
            <para>intermediate</para>
				<para>advanced</para>
				<para>guru</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            ______________________ :
            </para>
            <para>first-timer</para>
				<para>rookie beginner </para> 
            <para>intermediate</para>
				<para>advanced</para>
				<para>guru</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id = "LegalProtection"
    >
      <title>Legal Protection</title>
      <para>
      You may want to consider having users sign some kind of agreement 
      before any work
      is performed on their systems. Such a document will make it clear to 
      users exactly what they can and cannot expect from the installfest.
      </para>
      <para>
      If you do decide to use one of these documents, please
      have it reviewed by a lawyer in your area. 
      </para>
      <para>
      If you do have an agreement approved by a lawyer, 
      please contribute to the Linux community by sending a copy
      to the lead author of this HOWTO so that it may be included in
      future versions.
      </para>
      <sect2
        id = "Release"
      >
        <title>Release</title>
        <para>
        The following is a significantly modified version of a form posted on 
        David Pitts's Web site.
        </para>
        <para>INSTALLFEST RELEASE FORM</para>
        <para>
        By signing this release agreement
        between you and the group holding the installfest (members of the
        __________________________ Linux User's Group, hereinafter 
        referred to as
        Installers), you give up certain legal rights. Therefore, you should
        read the agreement carefully. If you have any questions about the
        legal effect of this agreement, you should consult an attorney and
        not any of the Installers. Please be aware that you may not participate
        in the installfest event unless you have signed this agreement.
        By signing this release agreement, you
        acknowledge the following: 
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That your signing this agreement
            is partial consideration for the services provided by Installers. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That Installers do not promise
            that the work done on your computer equipment will be successful.
            An Installer will help you attempt to install, configure, or
            otherwise get the Linux operating system to work on your computer
            equipment. However, because of possible defects in computer
            software or computer hardware, including improperly configured
            computer hardware, not every attempt is successful. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That the attempt to install,
            configure, or otherwise get the Linux operating system to work on
            your computer equipment has inherent dangers that no amount of
            care, caution, instruction, or expertise can eliminate. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That any attempt to install,
            configure, or otherwise get the Linux operating system to work on
            your computer equipment, especially including any attempt to
            partition or re-partition your computer's hard drive, may result in
            the loss of some or all of the data stored on that hard drive. That
            you are hereby advised that you should back up all important data
            before the attempt to install, configure or otherwise get the Linux
            operating system to work on your computer equipment. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That an installfest is an inherently chaotic event at which
            many computer components, peripherals and systems are present;
            therefore, you are responsible for the security of your property.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That you are expressly assuming
            the risks of the dangers set forth above. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            That by signing this release agreement, you hereby forever
            release the Installers from any legal liability they might have
            arising from the attempt to install, configure, or otherwise get
            the Linux operating system to run on your computer equipment. That
            this release includes, but is not limited to, any losses caused by
            the negligence of any Installer who attempts to install, configure
            or otherwise get the Linux operating system to work on your
            computer. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
        By signing below, you agree that you understand the terms above: 
        </para>
        <para>
        Your:
        </para>
        <para>
        signature: __________________________________________________
        </para>
        <para>

        name: _______________________________________________________
        </para>
        <para>

        month: ____________ day: __________ year: ________
        </para>
        <para>
        
        Witness:
        signature: __________________________________________________
        </para>
        <para>

        name: _______________________________________________________
        </para>
        <para>

        month: ____________ day: __________ year: ________
        </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id = "Waiver"
      >
        <title>Waiver</title>
        <para>
        The following is Copyright 1998 Chris Halsall 
        and the <ulink url="http://www.vlug.org/">
        Victoria Linux Users Group</ulink>. 
        Reuse permitted for Open Source 
        Software promotion.
        </para>
        <para>Linux InstallFest Waiver</para>
        <para>
        I, _______________________________ acknowledge that I am participating
        in the "Linux Install Festival" entirely at my own risk. 
        I assume
        responsibility for the integrity of the data on my computer system,
        have backed up all important data, and I will hold the volunteer
        helpers blameless for any damage to my computer system, to my data, or
        any other damages or liability that may result through my
        participation in this event. I further agree to be responsible for any
        licensing fees, shareware registrations, or other licensing
        requirements that may apply to the software I will receive. The
        purpose of this event is to distribute software packages that are Open
        Source, legally distributable with no charge to the user.
        </para>
        <para>
        Every reasonable effort will be made to ensure that my system operates
        correctly before and after the installation, but I recognize that,
        because the software installed at this event is licensed free of
        charge, the copyright holder(s) and volunteer helpers and/or other
        parties provide this material "as is" without 
        warranty of any kind,
        either expressed or implied, including, but not limited to, the
        implied warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular
        purpose. The entire risk as to the quality and performance of this
        software, and the accuracy of its associated documentation, is with
        me. Should this software or its associated documentation prove
        defective, I assume the cost of all necessary servicing, repair, or
        correction.
        </para>
        <para>
        Signature: __________________________________ Date: ___________ 
        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </appendix>
  <appendix
    id = "gfdl"
  >
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
    <subtitle>Version 1.2, November 2002</subtitle>
    <blockquote
      id = "fsf-copyright"
    >
      <para>Copyright (C) 2000,2001,2002  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
    </blockquote>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-0"
    >
      <title>PREAMBLE</title>
      <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with
or without modifying it, either commercially or non-commercially.
Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way
to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible for
modifications made by others.</para>
      <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense.  It
complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
designed for free software.</para>
      <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
software does.  But this License is not limited to software manuals; it
can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or
whether it is published as a printed book.  We recommend this License
principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-1"
    >
      <title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-doc"
      >This License applies to any manual or other work, in
any medium, that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying
it can be distributed under the terms of this License.  Such a notice
grants a world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use
that work under the conditions stated herein.  The "Document", below,
refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the public is a
licensee, and is addressed as "you".  You accept the license if you
copy, modify or distribute the work in a way requiring permission under
copyright law.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-mod-ver"
      >A "Modified Version" of the Document means any
work containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim,
or with modifications and/or translated into another language.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-secnd-sect"
      >A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or
a front-matter section of the Document that deals exclusively with the
relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing
that could fall directly within that overall subject.  (Thus, if the
Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may
not explain any mathematics.)  The relationship could be a matter of
historical connection with the subject or with related matters, or of
legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position
regarding them.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-inv-sect"
      >The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary
Sections whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant
Sections, in the notice that says that the Document is released under
this License.  If a section does not fit the above definition of
Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as Invariant.  The
Document may contain zero Invariant Sections.  If the Document does not
identify any Invariant Sections then there are none.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-cov-text"
      >The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of
text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the
notice that says that the Document is released under this License.  A
Front-Cover Text may be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at
most 25 words.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-transparent"
      >A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a
machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification is
available to the general public, that is suitable for revising the
document straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images
composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely
available drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text
formatters or for automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable
for input to text formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent
file format whose mark-up, or absence of mark-up, has been arranged to
thwart or discourage subsequent modification by readers is not
Transparent.  An image format is not Transparent if used for any
substantial amount of text.  A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
"Opaque".</para>
      <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
ASCII without mark-up, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
PostScript or PDF designed for human modification.  Examples of
transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG.  Opaque formats
include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or
processing tools are not generally available, and the machine-generated
HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors for output
purposes only.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-title-page"
      >The "Title Page" means, for a printed book,
the title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold,
legibly, the material this License requires to appear in the title page.
For works in formats which do not have any title page as such, "Title
Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of the work's
title, preceding the beginning of the body of the text.</para>
      <para
        id = "gfdl-entitled"
      >A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit
of the Document whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in
parentheses following text that translates XYZ in another language.
(Here XYZ stands for a specific section name mentioned below, such as
"Acknowledgments", "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".)  To
"Preserve the Title" of such a section when you modify the Document
means that it remains a section "Entitled XYZ" according to this
definition.</para>
      <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
which states that this License applies to the Document.  These Warranty
Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
meaning of this License.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-2"
    >
      <title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>
      <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
commercially or non-commercially, provided that this License, the
copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to
the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
conditions whatsoever to those of this License.  You may not use
technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying
of the copies you make or distribute.  However, you may accept
compensation in exchange for copies.  If you distribute a large enough
number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 4.
</para>
      <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
and you may publicly display copies.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-3"
    >
      <title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>
      <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly
have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
cover.  Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
publisher of these copies.  The front cover must present the full title
with all words of the title equally prominent and visible.  You may add
other material on the covers in addition.  Copying with changes limited
to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and
satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
respects.</para>
      <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent
pages.</para>
      <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable
Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each
Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general
network-using public has access to download using public-standard
network protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of
added material.  If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably
prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity,
to ensure that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the
stated location until at least one year after the last time you
distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers)
of that edition to the public.</para>
      <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of
the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
Document.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-4"
    >
      <title>MODIFICATIONS</title>
      <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document
under the conditions of sections 3 and 4 above, provided that you
release the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the
Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing
distribution and modification of the Modified Version to whoever
possesses a copy of it.  In addition, you must do these things in the
Modified Version:</para>
      <orderedlist
        id           = "gfdl-modif-cond"
        numeration   = "upperalpha"
      >
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a
  title distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous
  versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History
  section of the Document).  You may use the same title as a previous
  version if the original publisher of that version gives permission.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more
  persons or entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in
  the Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal
  authors of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer
  than five), unless they release you from this requirement.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of
  the Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your
  modifications adjacent to the other copyright notices.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a
  license notice giving the public permission to use the Modified
  Version under the terms of this License, in the form shown in the
  <link linkend="gfdl-addendum">Addendum</link> below.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of
  Invariant Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's
  license notice.</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its
  Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new
  authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title
  Page.  If there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document,
  create one stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the
  Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the
  Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the
  Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and
  likewise the network locations given in the Document for previous
  versions it was based on.  These may be placed in the "History"
  section.  You may omit a network location for a work that was
  published at least four years before the Document itself, or if the
  original publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgments" or
  "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the
  section all the substance and tone of each of the contributor
  acknowledgments and/or dedications given therein.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
  unaltered in their text and in their titles.  Section numbers or the
  equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements".
  Such a section may not be included in the Modified Version.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Do not re-title any existing section to be Entitled
  "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.
</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all
of these sections as invariant.  To do this, add their titles to the
list of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice.
These titles must be distinct from any other section titles.</para>
      <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it
contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has
been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
standard.</para>
      <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text,
and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the
list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one passage of
Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through
arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the Document already includes
a cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by
arrangement made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may
not add another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission
from the previous publisher that added the old one.</para>
      <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to
assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-5"
    >
      <title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>
      <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
this License, under the terms defined in <link linkend="gfdl-4">section
4</link> above for modified versions, provided that you include in the
combination all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original
documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your
combined work in its license notice, and that you preserve all their
Warranty Disclaimers.</para>
      <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single
copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but
different contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding
at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or
publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number.  Make the
same adjustment to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections
in the license notice of the combined work.</para>
      <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
"History" in the various original documents, forming one section
Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled
"Acknowledgments", and any sections Entitled "Dedications".  You must
delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-6"
    >
      <title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>
      <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
respects.</para>
      <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a
copy of this License into the extracted document, and follow this
License in all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that
document.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-7"
    >
      <title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
      <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a
storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the
copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal
rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works
permit.  When the Document is included in an aggregate, this License does
not apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves
derivative works of the Document.</para>
      <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 4 is applicable to these
copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of
the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers
that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic
equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form.  Otherwise
they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole
aggregate.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-8"
    >
      <title>TRANSLATION</title>
      <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 5.
Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may include a
translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include
the original English version of this License and the original versions
of those notices and disclaimers.  In case of a disagreement between the
translation and the original version of this License or a notice or
disclaimer, the original version will prevail.</para>
      <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgments",
"Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 5) to Preserve its
Title (section 2) will typically require changing the actual
title.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-9"
    >
      <title>TERMINATION</title>
      <para>You may not copy, modify, sub-license, or distribute the Document
except as expressly provided for under this License.  Any other attempt
to copy, modify, sub-license or distribute the Document is void, and will
automatically terminate your rights under this License.  However,
parties who have received copies, or rights, from you under this License
will not have their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain
in full compliance.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-10"
    >
      <title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>
      <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.  Such new versions
will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in
detail to address new problems or concerns.  See
http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.</para>
      <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
number.  If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option
of following the terms and conditions either of that specified version
or of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the
Free Software Foundation.  If the Document does not specify a version
number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not
as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.</para>
    </section>
    <section
      id = "gfdl-addendum"
    >
      <title>ADDENDUM: How to use this License for
  your documents</title>
      <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy
of the License in the document and put the following copyright and
license notices just after the title page:</para>
      <blockquote
        id = "copyright-sample"
      >
        <para>
    Copyright (c)  YEAR  YOUR NAME.
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
    under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
    or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
    with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
    A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
    Free Documentation License".
</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with this:</para>
      <blockquote
        id = "inv-cover-sample"
      >
        <para>
    with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
    Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.
</para>
      </blockquote>
      <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
situation.</para>
      <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit
their use in free software.</para>
    </section>
  </appendix>
  <appendix>
    <title>Useful Web Sites</title>
    <para>
    These Web sites may be useful in planning and running an installfest:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">
            The Linux Documentation Project (www.tldp.org)
            </ulink>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <ulink url="http://www.linux.org">www.linux.org</ulink>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <ulink url="http://www.distrowatch.com">
            www.distrowatch.com</ulink>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </appendix>
</article>

