<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[]>
<article id="LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Linux Documentation Project Reviewer HOWTO</title>

	 <author><firstname>Emma Jane</firstname><surname>Hogbin</surname>
	 <affiliation>
	 <orgname><ulink url="http://www.xtrinsic.com">xtrinsic</ulink></orgname>
	 <address><email>emmajane@xtrinsic.com</email></address>
	 </affiliation>
	 </author>
    <author>
      <firstname>David</firstname>
      <surname>Merrill</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<address>david -AT- lupercalia.net</address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <firstname>Joy</firstname>
      <surname>Yokley</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <address><email>jyokley@us.ibm.com</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <pubdate>2004-04-19</pubdate>
    <abstract><para>This document will help you review LDP documentation.
      It includes procedures and techniques for the review process
		of all new, and existing, LDP documents.</para>
    </abstract>

    <revhistory id="revhistory">
	 <revision>
	 <revnumber>1.4.2</revnumber>
	 <date>2004-05-24</date>
	 <authorinitials>EJH</authorinitials>
	 <revremark>Corrected spelling mistakes.</revremark>
	 </revision>
	<revision>
	<revnumber>1.4.1</revnumber>
	<date>2004-04-19</date>
	<authorinitials>EJH</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Minor updates to the language and markup, emphasizing the
	reporting procedures for reviews. Also changed the order of the reviews
	to reflect actual procedure (technical, language and finally metadata).</revremark>
	</revision>
	 
	 <revision>
	 <revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
	 <date>2004-04-18</date>
	 <authorinitials>EJH</authorinitials>
	 <revremark>Updated the language review: clarified use of capitals, and
	 added a new requirement that Latin abbreviations always use their
	 English counterpart instead.
	 </revremark>
	 </revision>
	 <revision>
	 <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
	 <date>2004-01-31</date>
	 <authorinitials>EJH</authorinitials>
	 <revremark>Added the metadata and markup review information.</revremark>
	 </revision>
       <revision>
	 <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
	 <date>2003-11-09</date>
	 <authorinitials>TMM</authorinitials>
	 <revremark>Updated content, URLs, mailing lists, converted to XML.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
         <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
         <date>2001-05-12</date>
         <authorinitials>DCM</authorinitials>
         <revremark>Minor bugfixes.</revremark>
      </revision>
       <revision>
         <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
         <date>2001-05-01</date>
         <authorinitials>jy</authorinitials>
         <revremark>Initial release.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
    <para>The LDP Review Project is a <quote>working group</quote> of the
    <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org"><citetitle>Linux Documentation Project</citetitle></ulink>,
    whose goal is to improve the quality of the LDP's documentation. We are approaching that
    goal from two different angles: a review of newly submitted documentation, and a review of existing documentation.
    We are open to your suggestions for improvement. </para>

    <para>We have a mailing list established for editors; instructions to subscribe are at
    <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">
    <citetitle>http://www.tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
    
    <sect2 id="copyright"><title>Copyright and License</title>
      <para>This document is copyright 2001 by David C. Merrill, Ph.D.,
		and copyright 2004 by Emma Jane Hogbin.</para>

      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
	document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
	License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the
	Free Software Foundation; with no invariant sections, no front-cover
	texts and no back-cover texts. A copy of the license is included in
	the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation
	License</quote>.
      </para>
		
      <para>Send feedback to <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>. Please
		reference the title of this document in your email.
      </para>
    </sect2>
   
    <sect2 id="acknowledgements"><title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <para>The original version of this document was written in 2001 by
		Joy Yokley and David C. Merrill, Ph.D.. Tabatha Marshall updated the
		content and converted the document to DocBook XML in November 2003.
		Emma Jane Hogbin added the section on Metadata and Markup Reviews in
		January 2004 and is the current maintainer of the document.</para>
    </sect2>
   
  
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="newdocs"><title>Reviewing Newly Submitted Documentation</title>
  		<para>This review project will continue throughout the life of the LDP. The process will act as a front-end
		quality assurance review for new documentation which is submitted to the LDP. Ideally documents will be reviewed 
		within one week of their submission to the LDP. </para>
		
		<para>Coordinators of this effort will announce to the list or notify individual review members of new document submissions. 
		The coordinators will try to funnel documents to reviewers who have knowledge in the same technical area 
		as the documentation. If the reviewer is not a technical expert in that particular area and needs technical questions 
		answered, there will be a technical expert designated who will be able to address any 
		technical issues or questions. </para>
		
		<para>
		Once reviewers have agreed to work on a document, they will have one week to complete the review. If they are
		not able to complete the review within that time frame, they will need to let the coordinator know of their difficulties so
		that the author can be notified of the problem. Because these reviews need 
		to be conducted quickly, there will be times when reviewers will be more able to accept review work.</para> 
		
		<para>When reviewing newly submitted documents, refer to the <xref linkend="techreview" /> and 
		<xref linkend="languagereview" /> portions of this guide for the types of information to verify and correct. 
		As a reviewer, you will need to check the documents out of the CVS
	  <footnote id="ftn-ok-to-return-changes-to-coordinator">
	    <para>Alternatively, if you've obtained the file from the Review Coordinator, or are unfamiliar with CVS, you can return the changes to the coordinator for further handling.</para>
	  </footnote>

and make any necessary changes. If changes are
		extensive or if the document has glaringly and fundamentally fatal errors, contact a 
		coordinator and let them know what the problems are. Once changes are made, the reviewer will update the minor 
		version number, add a new entry to the revision history, and include
		their name as an <quote>editor</quote> of the document. These
		changes will then be submitted to the CVS, and an original copy will
		be sent to the author of the document if the author does not have
		CVS access.
		</para>
	</sect1>
		
  
  <sect1 id="existing"><title>Reviewing Existing Documentation</title>

    <para>This project will focus on reviewing documentation that already exists at the LDP. Our goal is to implement
	 a quality management program that makes sure we are supplying up-to-date, accurate, easily read documentation.
	 This process will be ongoing throughout the life of the LDP. Initially, we will try to review all documents currently
	 on the LDP. Once we have made our way through existing documents, we will schedule dates for follow-up reviews.
	 By continually reviewing the documents throughout their life at the LDP, we help make sure readers have
	 the best possible experience with Linux documentation.</para>
	 
	<para>In addition to the primary goal of improving the quality of the documentation itself,
    we will also be gathering data about the collection for storage in some sort of database to
    facilitate the ongoing management of the collection. However, this stage of the review is still being defined; details
	 about the specifics and  how this data will be measured will be added in the future. </para>	 
	 <para>Below are some general guidelines that you should follow before you begin reviewing existing documentation
     for the LDP. Please try to have document reviews completed within two weeks of the time you sign up to review a document.</para>
    
    <sect2 id="picking"><title>Choosing a Document</title>

      <para>There are many documents that need review. The most 
		important thing is that you coordinate your work with the other
      reviewers. To coordinate the effort, we have set up a mailing list for reviewers.</para>
    
      <para>Notify the editor list (instructions for subscribing are at
      <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">
      <citetitle>http://www.tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists</citetitle></ulink>)
      before you begin to review a document. We want to make sure your work is directed where
      it is most needed and where it will be most useful. Of course, you may have a particular
      area of expertise and that will dictate your choice to some extent.
      You can ask on the list for an assignment, or you can select one for yourself
      and just let the mailing list know what you're doing.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="licenseissues"><title>License Issues</title>
      <para>Make sure you have the legal right to work on the document. If it is licensed
      under a free license that specifically grants such rights, you are fine. If not, you
      need to contact the author and get permission.</para>

      <para>If you do not plan to actually change any of the content, but simply report on
      the document's status, then you don't need permission, regardless of license.
      Of course, it is still polite, and advisable, to write the author anyway.</para>

      <para>If a document is missing a copyright and/or license, it's recommended you advise the
      author to choose and apply one.  More information on licensing is
		available in <xref linkend="metadatareview" />
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="newversion"><title>Working With the Latest Version</title>
        
      <para>Make sure the copy you are reviewing is the most current.</para>

      <para>If your document includes a URL to an official homepage, visit that page and see if it
      displays the same version number. If you find the same version number, you are fine. If you 
      find a newer version number, write to the author and ask him or her to please submit the newer 
      version to you.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="pickatype"><title>Picking a Review to Conduct</title>

      <para>There are many different ways a document can be reviewed, and you may have the skills
      to do only one or two types of reviews. It is sometimes useful (and easier) to do each review as a
      separate pass through the document; Your Mileage May Vary.</para>
		
      <para>The following sections explain the various types of reviews we are conducting. Use these sections as a guide to help you choose 
		the type of review to conduct and to help you conduct the review itself. Again, when you post your review
		choice to the review list, please specify the type of review you would like to be responsible for.</para>
      
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="peerreview"><title>Peer Review</title>

    <para>When an author submits a new document to the LDP, someone monitoring the submission email list will advise the author to post his draft to the discussion list for an initial peer review, prior to publication.  Besides determining whether the document thoroughly covers the subject matter, peers may also point out similar work already in the document collection, in which case the new author might want to contact the maintainer of the existing work.</para>  

    <para>As a member of the review team, you will recognize a peer review document as one the author has submitted to the discussion list, specifically requesting feedback for inclusion of their HOWTO in the collection.  This review can be performed by anyone subscribed to the discussion list (<ulink url="www.tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists" />).</para>
  </sect1>

  
  <sect1 id="techreview"><title>Technical Accuracy Review</title>

    <para>Make sure the facts as stated in the document are correct, helpful, and on topic.</para>

    <para>To do a technical accuracy review, you really need to know your subject matter,
    probably as well or better than the original author. Use whatever other documentation is
    available for your subject, including man pages, program documentation, other printed
    books, etc. You might also use mailing lists on the topic, asking for third parties to
    verify certain facts of which you are in doubt.</para>
	 
	 <para>When doing this type of review, consider if the information is only valid for certain types
	 of hardware or software. If this is the case, make sure to note the limitations of the document within
	 the document, either within the abstract or as a note at the beginning of the document. For example, if the
	 solutions in the document only are relevant for one type or brand of hardware, make sure that the 
	 limitation is defined. This will keep readers from trying to apply a certain type of technology to an application or
	 situation where it will not work. </para>
    
	 <para>The same should apply for the prerequisite knowledge of the reader.  If prior knowledge of a subject is assumed or required, the author should say so somewhere at the beginning of the document, and it's helpful to ask that authors provide a Resource section for further reading, to bring readers that much closer to the required information.</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="languagereview"><title>Language Review</title>

    <para>Because writers come from all types of backgrounds, there may be problems
    within the documentation that need to be fixed. Writers may be very knowledgeable
    in their subject areas but not great writers, or they may be excellent writers but
    not completely fluent in the language of the document. The language review addresses
    these types of problems by focusing on language issues that make the document easier
    for the user to read and understand. Some of the problems that may occur within the
    document are poor sentence structure, grammar, organization, clarity, and spelling.
    </para>
    
    <para>If you are doing a language review, you should be fluent in the language and
    the structure of the language. You want to consider both the logic and grammar of the
    document. Your primary goal in a language review is to identify and correct areas that
    could lead to confusion for the reader/user of the document. To this end, you can most
    certainly use language and grammar references such as dictionaries and handbooks
    when in doubt.</para>

    <para>Although this review does address the structure and delivery of the language,
    you should not attempt to purge the document of individuality and personality in an
    attempt to make it "sound better" or more technical. Stilted, humorless language
    and structures are not the goals here. Again, your goal should be to make the document
    clear, unambiguous, and correct in spelling and grammar.</para>

    <para>Items to evaluate:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Spelling</title>
	 <para>  Spelling should conform to a standardized English spelling of terms. For words that are new
	 to the language and not yet standardized (for example technical Linux terminology that is generally accepted
	 in the community), follow the most common spelling for the term.</para>
	 </formalpara>

	 <note><title>Note</title><para>Because there are two generally accepted forms of English, this review should
	 not privilege American English spellings over British English spellings, or vice-versa. For example, if the
	 author is writes British English and uses the word
	 <quote>realise</quote> you should not change the spelling of
	 the word to <quote>realize</quote> just because you speak/write American English.</para></note>
	 </listitem>
    
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Grammar</title>
	 <para>  For the purposes of this review, grammar should address issues such as standards of subject/verb agreement, 
	 pronoun/antecedent agreement, etc. One of the common and confusing mistakes made in HOWTOs is unclear pronoun antecedents. </para>
	 </formalpara>

         <para>For example, to say, <quote>You will need to set several parameters in the config file to make it compile correctly.
	 The ones you choose to set make a big difference.</quote> In this example it sounds like the config file is what is compiling and
	 it takes a re-reading of the phrase for it to be clear that <quote>The ones</quote> refers to the parameters.</para>
	 
	 <para>Along these same lines, many authors writing for the LDP use smiley faces and exclamation points where they
	 would never be accepted in formal documentation or grammar handbooks. The general rule to follow 
	 at this time is to leave the smiley faces and gratuitous punctuation marks in place unless they interfere with 
	 the reader's understanding of the concepts being explained. The rationale behind this is to protect the more conversational
	 tone of the LDP documentation.</para>
	 </listitem>
    
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Use of capital letters</title>
	 <para>The word <quote>HOWTO</quote> should always be in full caps with no hyphen.
	 The document's title and section headings may follow one of two
	 conventions, but must be consistent throughout. Titles may either
	 capitalize only the first word, or may capitalize each word. In the
	 second case the only words not capitalized in a title are prepositions, articles,
	 and proper nouns which would not be capitalized otherwise (for
	 example: insmod).  Other capitalization should follow rules of standard English.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>
    
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Clarity</title>
		<para>  Judgements on clarity are sometimes difficult to make. One successful strategy in 
		evaluating clarity is asking the question <quote>If I did not already know this information, would
		the explanation be clear from this document.</quote> If it is confusing to you and you already generally
		understand what the author is trying to say, then there is a good chance that the explanation is
		really confusing for someone reading the document for the first time. If you run across this situation,
		and you don't really know how to correct the technical explanation, or you are afraid your changes might
		affect the meaning of the document, ask for help from a technical expert. If no technical expert is available
		or no one responds to your requests, note the needed changes in 
		the review and mark that these concerns need to be addressed in the technical review. </para>
		</formalpara></listitem>
    
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Organization</title>
		<para>  In some cases the document would really benefit from a different structure. You should address these
		issues when they interfere with the understanding of the information within the document. If a document gives
		background information after a procedure has been performed, this may well be too late for the reader to 
		fully consider the information he or she needs before performing the task. Look for document organization that might
		confuse or mislead the reader. These will be the types of issues you want to address. Once these are identified, it
		may be worthwhile to let the author know your rationale and discuss major changes with him or her.</para>
		</formalpara></listitem>
		
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Sentence Structure</title>
		<para>  To some extent, sentence structure issues are discussed in the grammar section; however, there are some additional issues
		that are not grammatically incorrect but do interfere with the readers comprehension of the material. One of the most noticeable of these 
		is stacked prepositional phrases. Stacked prepositional phrases become a problem when the document's readability suffers
		because it becomes less and less clear what the subject and action of the sentence are. In some cases more 
		precise descriptors are needed or sentences need to be changed from one long sentence that is hard to 
		comprehend, to two or three more easily read sentences. </para>
		</formalpara></listitem>
		
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Readability</title>
		<para>  This area is somewhat subjective. What passes for fairly readable material to one person might be confusing to someone
		else. Because this is a value judgement you should be cautious when marking up an author's work for readability.
		Realize when basing a judgement on readability that you might be dealing with preferences of style. At this point
		in time within the LDP, there is no set style or stylistic rules that authors need to follow. In evaluating readability
		you must consider whether or not the way the document is written truly interferes with the readers understanding
		of the information. If the answer you come up with is <quote>No, but it doesn't sound like I think it should.</quote>
		then you should probably not re-write the text to make it sound better to you. </para>
		</formalpara></listitem>
		
    
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Title</title>
    <para>The title should be in proper title case. The general principle for this is that all words are 
	 capitalized in a title except prepositions and articles (an article will be capitalized if it is the 
	 first word in the title). The word HOWTO should be
    in all capital letters. There should be no hyphens within the word HOWTO.
    The version should not be included in the title.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Date Formats</title>
    <para>Dates should be in standard ISO format, which is YYYY-MM-DD.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>
    
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Uniform Use of Terms</title>
	 <para>  Because the HOWTO you are reviewing is probably filled with new information for the reader, it is important
	 that the terms discussed throughout the document be uniform. For example, referring to a part or parameter in one section of the 
	 document by one name and then calling it by another name (or an abbreviation that has not be explained) in another 
	 part of the document is confusing for the reader. Making sure that terms are the same throughout the document
	 goes a long way in helping the reader understand the documentation. </para>
	 </formalpara></listitem>
	 
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Definitions of Acronyms or Slang</title>
	 <para> Terminology and language within the realm of computer technology changes rapidly. In reviewing documents
	 you may find that many of the terms that are being discussed are not valid words in any dictionary or technical
	 reference that you are familiar with. In this case you will need to search on terms and find if they are, in fact,
	 terminology that is accepted in the general Linux community. Terms that are less familiar should be defined immediately
	 following the first instance of the term. Slang should be replaced with more common terminology if the slang will
	 causes the reader to be confused by the connotation or denotation of the term. Remember that readers using
	 the document may not come to English as a primary language and, therefore, you should do your best to make sure
	 that the document is as easy to understand as possible. </para>
	 </formalpara></listitem>
	 
	 <listitem><formalpara><title>Latin abbreviations</title>
	 <para>Avoid using abbreviations. e.g. (for example), et al. (and
	 others), etc (and so on) and i.e. (that is) should
	 always use the English equivalent.</para>
	 </formalpara></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

	<sect1 id="metadatareview"><title>Metadata and Markup Review</title>
		<para>The LDP uses a series of scripts to transform documents into their published format. In order for these scripts to work, documents must use valid markup and include specific metadata. Metadata is information about the document and includes author information, copyright, license and a revision history of the document.</para>

		<para>At this time Metadata and Markup Reviews will be conducted by
		one of the Review Coordinators and will be the final of the three
		reviews for new documents. Upon successful completion of a Metadata
		and Markup Review, the Review Coordinator will update the document's
		version number to 1.0 and submit the document for publication in the
		collection.</para>
   
	<sect2 id="requiredmarkup"><title>Required Markup</title>
		<para>Documents submitted to TLDP document repository must validate as one of the following:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		DocBook XML version 4.2 (preferred), 4.1.2
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		DocBook SGML version 4.2, 4.1 or 3.x
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		LinuxDoc SGML
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<warning><title>Authors are not required to submit documents in DocBook</title>
		<para>Authors are not required to submit their initial
		document in one of the required markup languages. A volunteer will
		be assigned to convert any document which is not submitted in valid
		markup. Authors must maintain their documents in one of the required
		formats. Help, of course, is available to authors. The main goal of
		The Linux Documentation Project is to provide quality documents, not
		to force authors to learn markup languages.</para></warning>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="requiredmetadata"><title>Required Metadata</title>
		<para>The following elements are all required:</para>
		
	 	<itemizedlist>
	 	<listitem><formalpara><title><sgmltag>articleinfo</sgmltag> or <sgmltag>bookinfo</sgmltag></title>
			<para>If you are writing a shorter HOWTO (this will be most documents) you will need to use an <sgmltag>articleinfo</sgmltag>, if you are writing a longer guide you will need to use <sgmltag>bookinfo</sgmltag>.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><formalpara><title><sgmltag>title</sgmltag></title>
		<para>Every document must contain a short, descriptive title. It should be reasonably unique; check other documents in the collection to make sure your document's title is distinctive from all other documents. Although it is not required, most <quote>HOWTO</quote> documents contain the word <quote>HOWTO</quote> in the title.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><formalpara><title><sgmltag>abstract</sgmltag></title>
		<para>A short description of your document must be included in the <sgmltag>abstract</sgmltag>. This description is typically one or two sentences in length.
		</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>


		<listitem>
		<formalpara><title><sgmltag>author</sgmltag></title>
		<para>Every document must have an author. If there are multiple authors, you may use  <sgmltag>authorgroup</sgmltag>. If the document was prepared by an organization with no individual author, please use <sgmltag>authorcorp</sgmltag> instead.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
		<formalpara><title><sgmltag>editor</sgmltag></title>
		<para>Every new document must go through the review process and have
		a technical, language and metadata/markup review editor listed. In
		some cases two of the reviews may have been conducted by the same
		person. The name of the editor and the version their review was
		conducted on should be included. For more information about this markup, please read the notes in the <citetitle>Author Guide</citetitle>'s <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/metadata-markup.html">Markup for Metadata</ulink>.</para>
		</formalpara>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		<formalpara><title><sgmltag>pubdate</sgmltag></title>
		<para>The date of publication for the document. The date should be in the ISO standard of YYYY-MM-DD.</para></formalpara></listitem>
		
		<listitem><formalpara><title>copyright</title>
		<para>Authors will always retain the copyright to any documents they submit to the LDP. Although it is not required, a copyright notice may be included. A license, however, is always required.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem><formalpara><title>Revision history (<sgmltag>revhistory</sgmltag>)</title>
		<para>A summary of revisions should be included in the document. For more information about their markup, please read the notes in the <citetitle>Author Guide</citetitle>'s <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/metadata-markup.html">Markup for Metadata</ulink>.</para></formalpara>
 
    <para>The initial release of a document should be marked up as Version 1.0. Subsequent updates should increment the version number appropriately. The preferred format is Major.Minor.Bugfix, where each section is an integer.
    Some authors use Alan Cox style versions (for example 1.4pre-3) and some include
    additional information (for example 1.3beta). This is acceptable but not encouraged.
    The most important thing is that we <emphasis>have</emphasis> a version
    number so we know which version we are dealing with! Once a document goes through review it should
	 advance in minor or bugfix version number, depending on the amount of change introduced.</para>
    </listitem>
		
		<listitem><formalpara><title>License and Legal Notice</title>
		<para>A license is required. The LDP currently accepts documents which are licensed under the GFDL, Creative Commons License and the LDP License. If you are using a license that is not listed it will need to be reviewed by our volunteers before the document is accepted. The full text of the license is required. A link is not sufficient. You may wish to include a disclaimer as part of the legal notice. A standard disclaimer is available from the <citetitle>Author Guide</citetitle>.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<formalpara><title>email</title>
		<para>The LDP must be able to reach any author of any document via email. Email addresses should be included in the <sgmltag>author</sgmltag> tag, but may be included in the DocBook source as a comment. Documents without email address will not be accepted into the collection. If the LDP is unable to reach an author, the document may be removed from the collection.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><formalpara><title>Acknowledgements and Other Credits</title>
		<para>Very few, if any, documents are written only by one person. It is good form to thank those who helped you with either the writing, research, testing or reviewing of your document. If someone added markup, or translated your document to another language they should also be given credit.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>

  <sect1 id="reporting"><title>Reporting Your Results</title>

    <para>Once you have completed your review of a document, you should send the updated file and your 
    results back to the Review Coordinator
<footnote>
    <para>The LDP is currently filtering documents back through the Review Coordinator until a
        document management system is implemented, allowing for review notes to be stored with the file
        in a database record.</para>
</footnote>
    , and advise the working group you've completed the review. A summary
	 of your findings should be included in the body of the email. If the
	 reviewer has access to the CVS, and permission of the author to submit
	 the changes directly, the reviewer may email the Review Coordinator
	 with only a summary of findings and a note that the document was
	 updated in the CVS.
     </para>

    <para>If you have made any modifications to the document, also send your updates to the
    author or maintainer, as well as the LDP <emphasis>submission
	 list</emphasis>, which is at
    <ulink
	 url="mailto:submit@en.tldp.org"><citetitle>submit@en.tldp.org</citetitle></ulink>.
	 The subject line should be the title of the document.
	 In the body of your email, please include a note which says something
	 to the effect of, <quote>I am a reviewer for the LDP and am submitting an
	 updated copy of this document on behalf of the author.</quote>
    </para>

	 <note><para>
		Updates should not be sent to the discuss list. 
	 </para></note>
    
  </sect1>

<!--  
     The GNU Free Documentation License 1.1 in DocBook
     Markup by Eric Baudais <baudais@okstate.edu>
     Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
     http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
     Version: 1.0.1
     Last Modified: Nov 16, 2000
-->

<appendix id="fdl">
  <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

  <sect1 id="fdl-preamble">
    <title>0. PREAMBLE</title>
    <para>
      The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
      other written document <quote>free</quote> in the sense of
      freedom: to assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and
      redistribute it, with or without modifying it, either
      commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily, this License
      preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit for
      their work, while not being considered responsible for
      modifications made by others.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      This License is a kind of <quote>copyleft</quote>, which means
      that derivative works of the document must themselves be free in
      the same sense. It complements the GNU General Public License,
      which is a copyleft license designed for free software.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
      free software, because free software needs free documentation: a
      free program should come with manuals providing the same
      freedoms that the software does. But this License is not limited
      to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
      regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
      printed book. We recommend this License principally for works
      whose purpose is instruction or reference.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="fdl-section1">
    <title>1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>
    <para id="fdl-document">
      This License applies to any manual or other work that contains a
      notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
      distributed under the terms of this License. The
      <quote>Document</quote>, below, refers to any such manual or
      work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is addressed
      as <quote>you</quote>.
    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-modified">
      A <quote>Modified Version</quote> of the Document means any work
      containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
      verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
      language.
    </para>
	
    <para id="fdl-secondary">
      A <quote>Secondary Section</quote> is a named appendix or a
      front-matter section of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> that deals exclusively
      with the relationship of the publishers or authors of the
      Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related
      matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within
      that overall subject. (For example, if the Document is in part a
      textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
      mathematics.)  The relationship could be a matter of historical
      connection with the subject or with related matters, or of
      legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position
      regarding them.
    </para>

    <para id="fdl-invariant">
      The <quote>Invariant Sections</quote> are certain <link
      linkend="fdl-secondary"> Secondary Sections</link> whose titles
      are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the
      notice that says that the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> is released under this
      License.
    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-cover-texts">
      The <quote>Cover Texts</quote> are certain short passages of
      text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts,
      in the notice that says that the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> is released under this
      License.
    </para>
	
    <para id="fdl-transparent">
      A <quote>Transparent</quote> copy of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document"> Document</link> means a machine-readable
      copy, represented in a format whose specification is available
      to the general public, whose contents can be viewed and edited
      directly and straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for
      images composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for
      drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is
      suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
      translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
      formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
      whose markup has been designed to thwart or discourage
      subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent.  A copy
      that is not <quote>Transparent</quote> is called
      <quote>Opaque</quote>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
      plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
      format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
      standard-conforming simple HTML designed for human
      modification. Opaque formats include PostScript, PDF,
      proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
      proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD
      and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the
      machine-generated HTML produced by some word processors for
      output purposes only.
    </para>
    
    <para id="fdl-title-page">
      The <quote>Title Page</quote> means, for a printed book, the
      title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed to
      hold, legibly, the material this License requires to appear in
      the title page. For works in formats which do not have any title
      page as such, <quote>Title Page</quote> means the text near the
      most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the
      beginning of the body of the text.
    </para>
  </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section2">
    <title>2. VERBATIM COPYING</title>
    <para>
      You may copy and distribute the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> in any medium, either
      commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
      copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License
      applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that
      you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
      License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or
      control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
      distribute. However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
      copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
      must also follow the conditions in <link
      linkend="fdl-section3">section 3</link>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
      above, and you may publicly display copies.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section3">
    <title>3. COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>
    <para>
      If you publish printed copies of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> numbering more than 100,
      and the Document's license notice requires <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover Texts</link>, you must enclose
      the copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these
      Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and
      Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also
      clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these
      copies. The front cover must present the full title with all
      words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
      other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes
      limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the
      <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> and satisfy these
      conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
      respects.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
      legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
      reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
      adjacent pages.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If you publish or distribute <link
      linkend="fdl-transparent">Opaque</link> copies of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> numbering more than 100,
      you must either include a machine-readable <link
      linkend="fdl-transparent">Transparent</link> copy along with
      each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
      publicly-accessible computer-network location containing a
      complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added
      material, which the general network-using public has access to
      download anonymously at no charge using public-standard network
      protocols. If you use the latter option, you must take
      reasonably prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque
      copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent copy will
      remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
      year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly
      or through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the
      public.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors
      of the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> well before
      redistributing any large number of copies, to give them a chance
      to provide you with an updated version of the Document.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section4">
    <title>4. MODIFICATIONS</title>
    <para>
      You may copy and distribute a <link
      linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link> of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> under the conditions of
      sections <link linkend="fdl-section2">2</link> and <link
      linkend="fdl-section3">3</link> above, provided that you release
      the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the
      Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus
      licensing distribution and modification of the Modified Version
      to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do
      these things in the Modified Version:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>A</title>
	  <para>
	    Use in the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title
	    Page</link> (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct
	    from that of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>, and from those of
	    previous versions (which should, if there were any, be
	    listed in the History section of the Document). You may
	    use the same title as a previous version if the original
	    publisher of that version gives permission.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>B</title>
	  <para>
	    List on the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title
	    Page</link>, as authors, one or more persons or entities
	    responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
	    <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>,
	    together with at least five of the principal authors of
	    the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> (all of
	    its principal authors, if it has less than five).
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>C</title>
	  <para>
	    State on the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title
	    Page</link> the name of the publisher of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>, as the
	    publisher.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>D</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve all the copyright notices of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>E</title>
	  <para>
	    Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
	    adjacent to the other copyright notices.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>F</title>
	  <para>
	    Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a
	    license notice giving the public permission to use the
	    <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link> under
	    the terms of this License, in the form shown in the
	    Addendum below.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>G</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve in that license notice the full lists of <link
	    linkend="fdl-invariant"> Invariant Sections</link> and
	    required <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover
	    Texts</link> given in the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document's</link> license notice.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>H</title>
	  <para>
	    Include an unaltered copy of this License.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>I</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve the section entitled <quote>History</quote>, and
	    its title, and add to it an item stating at least the
	    title, year, new authors, and publisher of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version </link>as given on
	    the <link linkend="fdl-title-page">Title Page</link>.  If
	    there is no section entitled <quote>History</quote> in the
	    <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>, create one
	    stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the
	    Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item
	    describing the Modified Version as stated in the previous
	    sentence.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>J</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve the network location, if any, given in the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> for public access
	    to a <link linkend="fdl-transparent">Transparent</link>
	    copy of the Document, and likewise the network locations
	    given in the Document for previous versions it was based
	    on. These may be placed in the <quote>History</quote>
	    section.  You may omit a network location for a work that
	    was published at least four years before the Document
	    itself, or if the original publisher of the version it
	    refers to gives permission.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>K</title>
	  <para>
	    In any section entitled <quote>Acknowledgements</quote> or
	    <quote>Dedications</quote>, preserve the section's title,
	    and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of
	    each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
	    dedications given therein.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>L</title>
	  <para>
	    Preserve all the <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
	    Sections</link> of the <link
	    linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>, unaltered in their
	    text and in their titles.  Section numbers or the
	    equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>M</title>
	  <para>
	    Delete any section entitled
	    <quote>Endorsements</quote>. Such a section may not be
	    included in the <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified
	    Version</link>.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
	  <title>N</title>
	  <para>
	    Do not retitle any existing section as
	    <quote>Endorsements</quote> or to conflict in title with
	    any <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
	    Section</link>.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
      If the <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>
      includes new front-matter sections or appendices that qualify as
      <link linkend="fdl-secondary">Secondary Sections</link> and
      contain no material copied from the Document, you may at your
      option designate some or all of these sections as invariant. To
      do this, add their titles to the list of <link
      linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant Sections</link> in the
      Modified Version's license notice.  These titles must be
      distinct from any other section titles.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may add a section entitled <quote>Endorsements</quote>,
      provided it contains nothing but endorsements of your <link
      linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link> by various
      parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text
      has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
      definition of a standard.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may add a passage of up to five words as a <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Front-Cover Text</link>, and a passage
      of up to 25 words as a <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Back-Cover Text</link>, to the end of
      the list of <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover Texts</link>
      in the <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>.
      Only one passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text
      may be added by (or through arrangements made by) any one
      entity. If the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>
      already includes a cover text for the same cover, previously
      added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are
      acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
      replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
      publisher that added the old one.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The author(s) and publisher(s) of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> do not by this License
      give permission to use their names for publicity for or to
      assert or imply endorsement of any <link
      linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version </link>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section5">
    <title>5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>
    <para>
      You may combine the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>
      with other documents released under this License, under the
      terms defined in <link linkend="fdl-section4">section 4</link>
      above for modified versions, provided that you include in the
      combination all of the <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
      Sections</link> of all of the original documents, unmodified,
      and list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in
      its license notice.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The combined work need only contain one copy of this License,
      and multiple identical <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
      Sections</link> may be replaced with a single copy. If there are
      multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different
      contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding
      at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original
      author or publisher of that section if known, or else a unique
      number. Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the
      list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined
      work.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled
      <quote>History</quote> in the various original documents,
      forming one section entitled <quote>History</quote>; likewise
      combine any sections entitled <quote>Acknowledgements</quote>,
      and any sections entitled <quote>Dedications</quote>.  You must
      delete all sections entitled <quote>Endorsements.</quote>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section6">
    <title>6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>
    <para>
      You may make a collection consisting of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> and other documents
      released under this License, and replace the individual copies
      of this License in the various documents with a single copy that
      is included in the collection, provided that you follow the
      rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of the
      documents in all other respects.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
      dispbibute it individually under this License, provided you
      insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
      follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
      copying of that document.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section7">
    <title>7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
    <para>
      A compilation of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> or its derivatives with
      other separate and independent documents or works, in or on a
      volume of a storage or distribution medium, does not as a whole
      count as a <link linkend="fdl-modified">Modified Version</link>
      of the Document, provided no compilation copyright is claimed
      for the compilation.  Such a compilation is called an
      <quote>aggregate</quote>, and this License does not apply to the
      other self-contained works thus compiled with the Document , on
      account of their being thus compiled, if they are not themselves
      derivative works of the Document.  If the <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Cover Text</link> requirement of <link
      linkend="fdl-section3">section 3</link> is applicable to these
      copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one
      quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may
      be placed on covers that surround only the Document within the
      aggregate. Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole
      aggregate.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section8">
    <title>8. TRANSLATION</title>
    <para>
      Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
      distribute translations of the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> under the terms of <link
      linkend="fdl-section4">section 4</link>. Replacing <link
      linkend="fdl-invariant"> Invariant Sections</link> with
      translations requires special permission from their copyright
      holders, but you may include translations of some or all
      Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these
      Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this
      License provided that you also include the original English
      version of this License. In case of a disagreement between the
      translation and the original English version of this License,
      the original English version will prevail.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section9">
    <title>9. TERMINATION</title>
    <para>
      You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the <link
      linkend="fdl-document">Document</link> except as expressly
      provided for under this License. Any other attempt to copy,
      modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
      automatically terminate your rights under this License. However,
      parties who have received copies, or rights, from you under this
      License will not have their licenses terminated so long as such
      parties remain in full compliance.
    </para>
    </sect1>
    
  <sect1 id="fdl-section10">
    <title>10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>
    <para>
      The <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnu.org/fsf/fsf.html">Free Software
      Foundation</ulink> may publish new, revised versions of the GNU
      Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
      will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ
      in detail to address new problems or concerns. See <ulink
      type="http"
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
      number. If the <link linkend="fdl-document">Document</link>
      specifies that a particular numbered version of this License
      <quote>or any later version</quote> applies to it, you have the
      option of following the terms and conditions either of that
      specified version or of any later version that has been
      published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If
      the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
      you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by
      the Free Software Foundation.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="fdl-using">
    <title>Addendum</title>
    <para>
      To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy of
      the License in the document and put the following copyright and
      license notices just after the title page:
    </para>
    
    <blockquote>
      <para>
	Copyright &copy; YEAR YOUR NAME.
      </para>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
	document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
	License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the
	Free Software Foundation; with the <link
	linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant Sections</link> being LIST
	THEIR TITLES, with the <link
	linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Front-Cover Texts</link> being LIST,
	and with the <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Back-Cover
	Texts</link> being LIST.  A copy of the license is included in
	the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation
	License</quote>.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
      
    <para>
      If you have no <link linkend="fdl-invariant">Invariant
      Sections</link>, write <quote>with no Invariant Sections</quote>
      instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have no
      <link linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Front-Cover Texts</link>, write
      <quote>no Front-Cover Texts</quote> instead of
      <quote>Front-Cover Texts being LIST</quote>; likewise for <link
      linkend="fdl-cover-texts">Back-Cover Texts</link>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code,
      we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
      choice of free software license, such as the <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"> GNU General Public
      License</ulink>, to permit their use in free software.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>  

</article>
