<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1' ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<article id="Lotus-DominoR5">
<articleinfo>
	<title>
		Lotus Domino R5 for Linux mini-HOWTO
	</title>

	<author>
		<firstname>Mykola</firstname>
		<surname>Buryak</surname>
                <affiliation>
	          <address>
<email>1upus@gmx.ch</email>
                  </address>
                </affiliation>
	</author>

	<othercredit>
		<firstname>Mary</firstname>
		<surname>Gardiner</surname>
		<contrib>Editing for style and consitency, conversion from text to
			DocBook v4.1.2 (XML)</contrib>
	</othercredit>

	<othercredit>
		<firstname>Dan</firstname>
		<surname>Scott</surname>
		<contrib>The document structure from DB2 Version
		        7.1 for Linux HOWTO</contrib>
	</othercredit>

        <pubdate>January 2003</pubdate>

	<revhistory id="revhistory">
                <revision>
	                <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	                <date>2003-01-18</date>
	                <revremark>
                                Initial Release, reviewed by LDP (Tab)
                        </revremark>
                </revision>
		<revision>
			<revnumber>0.1.2</revnumber>
	                <date>2003-01-13</date>
			<revremark>
				Corrected some factual and grammatical mistakes. Submitted document to LDP.
			</revremark>
		</revision>
                <revision>
			<revnumber>0.1.1</revnumber>
			<date>2003-01-01</date>
			<revremark>
				Mary Gardiner converts mini-HOWTO into Docbook XML 4.1.2.
			</revremark>
		</revision>
                <revision>
	        	<revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
			<date>2002-09-20</date>
			<revremark>
				My first mini-HOWTO, wrote install instructions Lotus
				Domino 5.08 &amp; 5.09a for Mandrake Linux 8.1 and SuSE 7.3
				Professional.
			</revremark>
		</revision>
      
               

	</revhistory>

</articleinfo>



	<para>
	This mini-HOWTO gives you explicit instructions on installing Lotus Domino
	R5 for Linux on the Intel x86-based distributions of Mandrake
	Linux 8.1 and SuSE 7.3 Professional. After installing Domino R5, you can
	connect to your Domino server from a remote Notes machine, and administer
	it locally (on the same Linux machine) using the Web Administrator.
	</para>


<sect1 id="intro">
	<title>
	Introduction
	</title>

	<sect2 id="whyr5">

	<title>
	Why a Domino R5 installation mini-HOWTO?
	</title>

	<para>

	I faced Domino for Linux in February 2002. It happened because of unstable
	Domino R5 functioning on an Windows NT Server with powerful hardware
	resources. I read the <quote>Understanding Domino for Linux</quote> white paper and I
	decided to move our Domino server to Linux. My first Linux distribution was
	Mandrake 8.1. I know this French distribution is one of the easiest and
	friendly for a newbie. Now it has worked pretty well for more than 10 months
	without any interference. Cool :) A few months ago the chairmen decided to
	implement one more Domino server at our high school; we had no money to
	purchase a powerful server and I made up my mind to deploy it on Linux
	again with existing hardware. Now we have a very stable second one on SuSE
	7.3 (I have studied this distribution already) with poor hardware (CPU:
	Celeron 400, RAM: 192MB, HDD: 20GB IDE).

	</para>

        <para>

	As time permits, I hope to provide hints and tips for improving
	performance of Domino on Linux, and for configuring the environment on
	various Linux distributions.

        </para>
      
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="whoshouldread">

	<title>
	Who should read this mini-HOWTO?
	</title>
	
	<para>

	If you plan to save your employer's money and get amazing stability (and
	save your time) you should think about Domino on Linux. This mini-HOWTO
	helps you to install and configure Domino on the Linux distributions
	supported by IBM Lotus Software (SuSE) and others (Mandrake). I describe
	specific prerequisites and quirks for each distribution. I do not want
	anyone to repeat my sleepless nights and all-day-long red eyes.
	
	</para>
	
	</sect2>


	<sect2 id="aboutauthor">
	<title>
	About the author
	</title>
	<para>
	Mykola Buryak is the originator and current maintainer of this mini-HOWTO.
	Please send all suggestions for improvement, criticisms, or more-or-less
	related questions to me at <email>m.b.@gmx.co.uk</email> or
	<email>1upus@gmx.ch</email>. Please do not send me spam or hate mail.
	</para>

	
	<para>
	Mykola Buryak has been employed by National Mining University, Ukraine, as
	Lotus System Administrator since September 2000. Before that time he was
	working as Computer/Network Technician there. He has 3 year experience
	with Web Development, 2 year in Lotus Domino/Notes Administration, 1 year
	in Linux and IBM DB2 UDB. In his spare time he teaches RUP and Python at
	the Geoinformatics Department, National Mining University.
	He holds an Hon. Masters Degree in Information Control Systems and Technologies 
        and the following certifications for the present:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Certified Lotus Specialist - Domino R5 System Administrator
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				IBM Certified Specialist - DB2 UDB V6.1/V7.1 User
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="acknowledgements">
	
	<title>
	Acknowledgements
	</title>

	<para>
	Mary Gardiner did an awesome job of editing the original version for
	style and consistency.
	</para>

	<para>
	Additional thanks to Dan Scott and his DB2 Version 7.1 for Linux HOWTO
	which I got the document structure from.
	</para>

	</sect2>
        
        <sect2 id="copyright">

        <title>
        License &amp; Copyright
        </title>

                <para>

		Copyright (c) 2002, 2003 Mykola Buryak

		</para>

		<para>
		
		Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
		document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
		Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software
		Foundation; with no invariant sections, with no Front-Cover Texts,
		with no Back-Cover Text.  A copy of the license is included in <xref
		linkend="gnufdl" />.

		</para>

		<para>

		This document is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
		WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
		MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See 
		<xref linkend="gnufdl" /> for more details.

		</para>

	</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="prerequisites">

	<title>
	Prerequisites
	</title>

	<para>
	What are prerequisites? Prerequisites are what you, your machine, and your
	distribution require before you will be able to successfully install or
	use Lotus Domino R5. The required prerequisites come straight from <citetitle>Notes,
	Domino and Domino Designer RELEASE NOTES</citetitle>, Chapter 2. The suggested
	prerequisites come from experience. For your convenience, I've divided
	them into hardware and software requirements.
	</para>
    
	<sect2>
	<title id="hardware">
	Hardware
	</title>

	<variablelist>	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		CPU
		</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		x86 compatible (for example, Intel, AMD, or Cyrix). I've successfully
		installed Domino Application Server 5.08 on an AMD Duron 800, Intel
		Celeron 400 and Enterprise Server 5.09a on an AMD Athlon 1000. Your
		experiences with other x86 processors would be appreciated.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		RAM
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		I've found 128 MB of RAM is enough to run a single Domino Application
		Server and test out your applications. In my case, I was working with a
		AMD Duron 800 processor and 128 MB of RAM. However, more memory is
		recommended if you're putting your application into production or
		running multiple services.  Swap file should be 3 times the physical
		RAM or greater.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		HDD
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		For a typical non-partioned installation of the Lotus Domino R5
		Application Server, you will need about 300 MB of free disk space.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	</variablelist>

	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="software">
	<title>
	Software
	</title>

	<para>
	You must have selected the following packages during Linux install or
	setup:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		C Development;
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		Development Libraries;
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		C++ Development.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		Also you need the libjitc.so file from the IBM Developer Kit for Java
		1.1.6.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="prepdistro">
	<title>
	Preparing your distribution for Domino R5
	</title>

	<sect2>
	<title id="mandrake81">
	Mandrake Linux 8.1
	</title>

	<para>
	Domino for Linux will need to be able to find a certain file with filename
	<filename>libjitc.so</filename>. This required file is absent from Mandrake Linux 8.1. 
        You will be unable to work correctly with the Agent Manager and Statistic Agent if
	you ignore this section of mini-HOWTO.
	</para>
      
	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	To find out if the file is absent, you can use the <command>locate</command> command.
	</para>
	  
	<para>
	First, issue the following command at the command prompt (login as <quote>root</quote>):
	</para>
	
	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>updatedb</userinput>
	</screen>
	
	<para>
	This command searches the hard drive and updates a database for the locate
	command in use. It can take a few minutes to run, but probably it will
	take only 20-30 seconds or so. Afterwards, issue the command:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>locate libjitc.so</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	If <filename>libjitc.so</filename> is on your hard drive somewhere, locate will find it and
	list where it is. If not, locate will list nothing. If libjitc.so is
	already there, it is probably already in your search path, until you get
	an error trying to work with Agent Manager and Statistic Agent indicating
	otherwise, just assume it is. If you do not have <filename>libjitc.so</filename>, you will 
        need to get it separately; it is not included as a part of the Domino for Linux
	package.
	</para>
	  
	<para>
	The file <filename>libjitc.so</filename> is included as a part of the IBM Developer Kit for
	Linux, which is IBM's port of Sun's JDK (Java Development Kit) 1.1.8
	to Linux/x86. <filename>libjitc.so</filename> is the Java <quote>Just-In-Time</quote> 
        compiler. The reason that this file is absent from SuSE 7.3 is that this Linux
	distribution comes with a different Java package named Kaffe Virtual
	Machine.
	</para>
	  
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	You can download the IBM Developer Kit for Linux from <ulink url="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/java/jdk/118/linux/?dwzone=java">http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/java/jdk/118/linux/?dwzone=java</ulink>.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Prepare a directory to download JDK into. Change to the <filename class="directory">/root</filename> directory:
	</para>
	  
	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>cd /</userinput>
	bash# <userinput>cd /root</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	and make a new directory named <filename class="directory">jdk118</filename>:
	</para>
	  
	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>mkdir jdk118</userinput>
	</screen>

	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Download the JDK into <filename class="directory">/root/jdk118</filename>. Install the IBM
	Developer Kit for Java by issuing the following command as root:
	</para>
	  
	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>rpm -ivh IBMJava118-SDK-1.1.8-5.0-i386.rpm</userinput>
	</screen>

	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	After successful installation of the IBM Developer Kit you need to copy
	<filename>libjitc.so</filename> to the <filename class="directory">/lib</filename> directory:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>cp /usr/jdk118/lib/linux/native_threads/libjitc.so /lib</userinput>
	</screen>

	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	You can uninstall the IBM Developer Kit with Software or Package
	Manager to clean things up, but consider keeping the rpm file
	IBMJava118-SDK-1.1.8-5.0-i386.rpm. You may decide later that JDK 1.1.8 is
	something you want to install (for example, it's necessary for using the IBM DB2 UDB
	V7.x Linux Control Center).
	</para>
	</listitem>

	</orderedlist>

	</sect2>


	<sect2>
	<title id="suse73pro">
	SuSE 7.3 Professional
	</title>
	
	<para>
	Domino for Linux will need to be able to find a certain file with filename
	<filename>libjitc.so</filename>. This required file is absent from SuSE 7.3 Professional. You
	will be unable to work correctly with the Agent Manager and Statistic Agent if
	you ignore this section of mini-HOWTO.
	</para>
      
	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	To find out if it is absent, you can use the <command>locate</command> command.
	First, issue the following command at the command prompt (log in as <quote>root</quote>):
	</para>
	  
	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>updatedb</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	This command searches the hard drive and updates a database for the locate
	command in use. It can take a few minutes to run, but probably it will
	take only 20-30 seconds or so. Then issue the command:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>locate libjitc.so</userinput>
	</screen>
	  
	<para>
	If <filename>libjitc.so</filename> is on your hard drive somewhere, 
        <command>locate</command> will find it and list where it is. If not, 
        <command>locate</command> will list nothing. If <filename>libjitc.so</filename> is
	already there, it is probably already in your search path, until you get
	an error trying to work with Agent Manager and Statistic Agent indicating
	otherwise, just assume it is. If you do not have <filename>libjitc.so</filename>, you will need
	to get it separately; it is not included as a part of the Domino for Linux
	package.
	</para>
	  
	<para>
	The file <filename>libjitc.so</filename> is included as a part of the IBM Developer Kit for
	Linux, which is IBM's port of Sun's JDK (Java Development Kit) 1.3 to
	Linux/x86. libjitc.so is the Java <quote>Just-In-Time</quote> compiler.
	The reason that this file is absent from SuSE 7.3 is that this Linux
	distribution comes with a different Java package named Java 2 SDK,
	Standard Edition.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Install IBM Developer Kit version 1.3 with YaST2 control center.
	IBM Developer Kit is located on one of the seven SuSE 7.3 Professional
	installation CD-ROMs.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	After successful installation of the IBM Developer Kit, you need to copy
	<filename>libjitc.so</filename> to <filename class="directory">/lib</filename>:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>cp /usr/lib/jdk1.3/jre/bin/libjitc.so /lib</userinput>
	</screen>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="installingr5">
	<title>
	Installing Domino R5
	</title>

	<sect2 id="r5instmandrake81">
	<title>
	Mandrake Linux 8.1
	</title>
	
	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Log in as <quote>root</quote>. Open a terminal session. Add a user and group to
	your system called <varname>notes</varname>:
	</para>
	
	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>adduser notes</userinput>
	</screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Give this new user a password by entering:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>passwd notes</userinput>
	</screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Mount the CD-ROM, and enter the following command to install the
	Lotus Domino R5 package:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>/mnt/cdrom/dom509ux/linux/install</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	The install program displays a series of screens about the IBM Lotus
	license agreement. Use the <keycap>TAB</keycap> key to accept a setting and advance to the
	next screen, the <keycap>ESC</keycap> key to back up to the previous screen, the space bar
	to toggle through possible choices other than the default, and <keycap>ENTER</keycap> to
	edit a text field.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select a setup type. Choose Domino Mail Server, Domino
	Application Server, or Domino Enterprise Server and press <keycap>TAB</keycap>.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select the program file location. The default is 
        <filename class="directory">/opt/lotus</filename>. 
        Make sure you have enough space. The installed files in the program directory
	are approximately 70 MB. If you select a program directory other than
	<filename class="directory">/opt/lotus</filename>, then a soft link will be created from 
        your program directory to <filename class="directory">/opt/lotus</filename> so that 
        commands may be executed from that path.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Indicate if you plan a number of Domino servers on the current
	physical machine. The default is <option>No</option>.
	</para>
	  
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select the data file location. The default is 
        <filename class="directory">/local/notesdata</filename>. If you do
	not have a large root partition it will not work. If so, change the
	directory to <filename class="directory">/usr/local/notesdata</filename>. 
        If you ignore this during installation process, later you will get an error like this one:
	</para>

	<screen>
	Error validation settings:
	There is not enough disk space for the data directory at /local/notesdata
	125889K is required, and only 95370K would be available.
	Make sure you have enough space. 
	</screen>

        <para>
	The installed files in the data directory are approximately 160 MB. 
	</para>

	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select the user and group for this server. Choose the default
	that you set up earlier (<varname>notes</varname> in the example).
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	The install program displays the settings you selected. Use the
	<keycap>TAB</keycap> key to accept these settings and begin the installation, or press the
	<keycap>ESC</keycap> key to back up to change any settings. The install program will then
	begin installing the files.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	During installation process you may see the warning:
	</para>

	<screen>
	The following system commands were not located: rsh.
	</screen>

	<para>
	It does not influence the local server installation.
	</para>

	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	After successful installation, this message will be displayed among
	others:
	</para>

	<screen>
	The installation completed successfully.
	</screen>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title id="r5instsuse73pro">
	SuSE 7.3 Professional
	</title>

	<orderedlist>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Log in as <quote>root.</quote> Open a terminal session. Add a user and group to
	your system called <varname>notes</varname>:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>groupadd notes</userinput>
	bash# <userinput>useradd notes -g notes</userinput>
	</screen>

	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Give this new user a password by entering:
	</para>
	
	<screen>
	bash# passwd notes
	</screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Mount the CD-ROM, and enter the following command to install the
	Lotus Domino R5 package:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>/mnt/cdrom/dom509ux/linux/install</userinput>
	</screen>
	
	<para>
	The install program displays a series of screens about the IBM Lotus
	license agreement. Use the <keycap>TAB</keycap> key to accept a setting and advance to the
	next screen, the <keycap>ESC</keycap> key to back up to the previous screen, the space bar
	to toggle through possible choices other than the default, and <keycap>ENTER</keycap> to
	edit a text field.
	</para>

	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select a setup type. Choose Domino Mail Server, Domino
	Application Server, or Domino Enterprise Server and press <keycap>TAB</keycap>.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select the program file location. The default is 
        <filename class="directory">/opt/lotus</filename>. Make
	sure you have enough space. The installed files in the program directory
	are approximately 70 MB. If you select a program directory other than
	<filename class="directory">/opt/lotus</filename>, then a soft link will be created 
        from your program directory to <filename class="directory">/opt/lotus</filename> so 
        that commands may be executed from that path.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Indicate if you plan a number of Domino servers on the current
	physical machine. The default is <option>No</option>.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select the data file location. The default is 
        <filename class="directory">/local/notesdata</filename>.
	It works perfectly. Make sure your have enough space. The installed files
	in the data directory are approximately 160 MB.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Select the user and group for this server. Choose the default
	that you set up earlier (<varname>notes</varname> in the example).
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	The install program displays the settings you selected. Use the
	<keycap>TAB</keycap> key to accept these settings and begin the installation, or press the
	<keycap>ESC</keycap> key to back up to change any settings. The install program will then
	begin installing the files.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>
	After successful installation, this message will be displayed among
	others:
	</para>

	<screen>
	The installation completed successfully.
	</screen>
	</listitem>

	</orderedlist>
	
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title id="foralldistros">
	For all Linux distributions
	</title>

	<sect3 id="rundssetup">
	<title>
	Run the Domino Server Setup program
	</title>

	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Log on to Linux as the user you established earlier (<varname>notes</varname> in
	the example).
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Change to the directory <filename class="directory">/usr/local/notesdata</filename> 
        (<filename class="directory">/local/notesdata</filename> for SuSE) by entering:
	</para>
	    
	<screen>
	bash# cd /
	bash# cd /usr/local/notesdata
	and then enter the following:
	bash# /opt/lotus/bin/http httpsetup
	</screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	A series of messages indicate the start of the Domino server. For
	example:
	</para>

	<screen>
	05/09/2002 8:39:09 PM Created new log file as
	/usr/local/notesdata/log.nsf
	05/09/2002 8:39:09 PM
	***************************************
	* Lotus Domino Server Setup           *
	* To setup this server, please connect*
	* your web browser to port 8081       *
	* Example: http://example.com:8081    *
	***************************************
	05/09/2002 8:39:09 AM JVM: Java Virtual Machine initialized.
	05/09/2002 8:39:10 AM HTTP Web Server started
	</screen>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	</sect3>

	<sect3 id="setupconfcont">
	<title>
	Continuing setup and configuration
	</title>

	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	You begin the configuration process by connecting to your Linux
	server with a Web browser, either from an external machine, or the Linux
	machine.
	</para>

	<para>
	To perform setup from another machine, enter:
	</para>

	<screen>
	<userinput>http://example.com:8081</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	To perform setup from the Linux machine, enter:
	</para>

	<para>
	<screen><userinput>http://localhost:8081</userinput></screen> or
	<screen><userinput>http://linux:8081</userinput></screen> for SuSE 7.3 Professional.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	where <varname>example.com</varname> is either the IP address or DNS name of your
	Linux server. At this point, the standard Domino configuration screens are
	displayed in your browser. Follow the instructions on these screens and
	click the <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> button on the final screen to complete the initial
	configuration. Online help is available on each of these screens.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	The HTTP Setup program will have created <filename>SERVER.ID</filename> and 
        <filename>CERT.ID</filename> files in 
        <filename class="directory">/usr/local/notesdata</filename>. The <filename>USER.ID</filename> 
        file is attached to a person document in <filename>NAMES.NSF</filename>.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	</sect3>

	<sect3 id="startdsserver">

	<title>
	Starting the Domino Server
	</title>

	<para>
	Before starting your Domino server, make sure no other Web server is
	running because it will block the Domino HTTP task from operating
	correctly, and you will be unable to use a Web browser to administer your
	server after the initial setup.
	</para>

	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Log on to Linux as the user you established earlier (<varname>notes</varname> in
	the example).
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	From the <filename class="directory">/usr/local/notesdata</filename> directory 
        (<filename class="directory">/local/notesdata</filename> for SuSE), enter:
	</para>

	<screen>
	bash# <userinput>/opt/lotus/bin/server</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	The server starts and the usual server console messages appear.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	</orderedlist>

	</sect3>

	<sect3 id="extractadminid">
	<title>
	Extracting your administrator ID file
	</title>

	<para>
	Before you can perform any more administration on your Domino for Linux
	server, you will need to extract the administrator ID file and move it to the
	machine you plan to use for administration.
	</para>

	<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	After the HTTP Web Server task has started, switch to your
	administration machine and use a Web browser to connect to your new
	server:
	</para>

	<screen>
	<userinput>http://example.com</userinput>
	</screen>

	<para>
	where <varname>example.com</varname> is either the IP address or DNS name of your
	Linux server. The default Lotus Domino navigator screen displays.
	</para>

	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Now open the address book by entering:
	</para>

	<screen>
	<userinput>http://example.com/names.nsf</userinput>
	</screen>

	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Click to the People view and open the Person document for the
	administrator you created earlier and download the <filename>USER.ID</filename> file to your
	administration machine. If you are using a Netscape browser, you may have
	to rename the id file to <filename>USER.ID</filename>.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	</orderedlist>
	</sect3>
	</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="resources">
	<title>
	Resources
	</title>

	<variablelist>

	<varlistentry>
	
		<term>
		<ulink url="http://domino.lotus.com/ldd/notesua.nsf/">Lotus Developer
		Domain: The Documentation Library</ulink>
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		This web site contains white papers, redbooks, FAQs etc., published by
		IBM about Lotus Domino/Notes.
		</para>
		</listitem>

	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		<ulink url="http://domino.lotus.com/ldd/down.nsf?OpenDatabase">Lotus
		Developer Domain: Downloads</ulink>
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		You can download a 90-day trial version of Domino/Notes and other Lotus
		products here.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		<ulink url="http://www-10.lotus.com/ldd/r5linuxforum.nsf">Lotus
		Developer Domain: Domino for Linux Feedback Forum</ulink>
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		Very useful, but archived Lotus Domino for Linux Feedback Forum.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		<ulink
		url="http://www.caldera-ee.com/howto/domino.openlinux.howto.html">HOWTO
		Install Lotus Domino Server 5.0.9 on Caldera OpenLinux '99
		 Server Release 3.1.1</ulink>
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		This HOWTO explains how to install Domino Server on the Caldera OpenLinux
		Server3.1.1.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		<ulink url="http://advisor.com">Advisor Magazine</ulink>
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		<citetitle pubwork="journal">Advisor</citetitle> presents the unmatched 
                advice of top experts in a full range
		of media, including magazines, journals, e-mail newsletters,
		conferences, seminars, workshops, CDs, on-site training, and dozens of
		Web sites. The expertise presented by <citetitle pubwork="journal">Advisor</citetitle>
                comes from hard-won hands-on involvement with the leading technology products 
                (as Lotus Domino/Notes) and services, and technical and business practices.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      
	<varlistentry>
		<term>
		<ulink url="http://searchdomino.techtarget.com/">SearchDomino.com: The
		Domino Specific Search Engine</ulink>
		</term>

		<listitem>
		<para>
		It's a Domino Specific Search Engine. Recommended for all Lotus
		Domino/Notes newbies.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		
	</variablelist>
</sect1>
  
<sect1 id="gnufdl">
<!-- - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) -->
<!-- LINK REV="made" HREF="mailto:webmasters@gnu.org" -->

    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

    <para>Version 1.1, March 2000</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Copyright (C) 2000  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
    </blockquote>

  <sect2 label="0">
    <title>PREAMBLE</title>

    <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook,
    or other written document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
    assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
    with or without modifying it, either commercially or
    noncommercially.  Secondarily, this License preserves for the
    author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not
    being considered responsible for modifications made by
    others.</para>

    <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that
    derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the
    same sense.  It complements the GNU General Public License, which
    is a copyleft license designed for free software.</para>

    <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals
    for free software, because free software needs free documentation:
    a free program should come with manuals providing the same
    freedoms that the software does.  But this License is not limited
    to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
    regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
    printed book.  We recommend this License principally for works
    whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="1">
    <title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

    <para>This License applies to any manual or other work that
    contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License.  The "Document",
    below, refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the
    public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you".</para>

    <para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work
    containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
    verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
    language.</para>

    <para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter
    section of the Document that deals exclusively with the
    relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
    Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains
    nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject.
    (For example, if the Document is in part a textbook of
    mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.)
    The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with
    the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
    philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
    them.</para>

    <para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections
    whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections,
    in the notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

    <para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that
    are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the
    notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

    <para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a
    machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification
    is available to the general public, whose contents can be viewed
    and edited directly and straightforwardly with generic text
    editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs
    or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
    translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
    formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
    whose markup has been designed to thwart or discourage subsequent
    modification by readers is not Transparent.  A copy that is not
    "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>

    <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
    plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
    format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
    standard-conforming simple HTML designed for human modification.
    Opaque formats include PostScript, PDF, proprietary formats that
    can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML
    or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML produced by some word
    processors for output purposes only.</para>

    <para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page
    itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly,
    the material this License requires to appear in the title page.
    For works in formats which do not have any title page as such,
    "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of
    the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
    text.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="2">
    <title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

    <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium,
    either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this
    License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this
    License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and
    that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
    License.  You may not use technical measures to obstruct or
    control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
    distribute.  However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
    copies.  If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

    <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
    above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="3">
    <title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

    <para>If you publish printed copies of the Document numbering more
    than 100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts,
    you must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and
    legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front
    cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover.  Both covers must
    also clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these
    copies.  The front cover must present the full title with all
    words of the title equally prominent and visible.  You may add
    other material on the covers in addition.  Copying with changes
    limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the
    Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim
    copying in other respects.</para>

    <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to
    fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
    reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
    adjacent pages.</para>

    <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
    numbering more than 100, you must either include a
    machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or
    state in or with each Opaque copy a publicly-accessible
    computer-network location containing a complete Transparent copy
    of the Document, free of added material, which the general
    network-using public has access to download anonymously at no
    charge using public-standard network protocols.  If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you
    begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that
    this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
    location until at least one year after the last time you
    distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or
    retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

    <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the
    authors of the Document well before redistributing any large
    number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an
    updated version of the Document.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="4">
    <title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

    <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the
    Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided
    that you release the Modified Version under precisely this
    License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the
    Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
    Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it.  In addition,
    you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
      <listitem><para>Use in the Title Page
      (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from that of the
      Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if
      there were any, be listed in the History section of the
      Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version if
      the original publisher of that version gives permission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>List on the Title Page,
      as authors, one or more persons or entities responsible for
      authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version,
      together with at least five of the principal authors of the
      Document (all of its principal authors, if it has less than
      five).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>State on the Title page
      the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, as the
      publisher.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve all the
      copyright notices of the Document.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Add an appropriate
      copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the other
      copyright notices.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Include, immediately
      after the copyright notices, a license notice giving the public
      permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this
      License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve in that license
      notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and required Cover
      Texts given in the Document's license notice.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Include an unaltered
      copy of this License.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve the section
      entitled "History", and its title, and add to it an item stating
      at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the
      Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If there is no
      section entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating
      the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given
      on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
      Version as stated in the previous sentence.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve the network
      location, if any, given in the Document for public access to a
      Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network
      locations given in the Document for previous versions it was
      based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.  You
      may omit a network location for a work that was published at
      least four years before the Document itself, or if the original
      publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>In any section entitled
      "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", preserve the section's
      title, and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of
      each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications
      given therein.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve all the
      Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their text and
      in their titles.  Section numbers or the equivalent are not
      considered part of the section titles.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Delete any section
      entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section may not be included in
      the Modified Version.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Do not retitle any
      existing section as "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with
      any Invariant Section.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections
    or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no
    material copied from the Document, you may at your option
    designate some or all of these sections as invariant.  To do this,
    add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified
    Version's license notice.  These titles must be distinct from any
    other section titles.</para>

    <para>You may add a section entitled "Endorsements", provided it
    contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by
    various parties--for example, statements of peer review or that
    the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
    definition of a standard.</para>

    <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover
    Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the
    end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one
    passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be
    added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the
    Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
    previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity
    you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
    publisher that added the old one.</para>

    <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by
    this License give permission to use their names for publicity for
    or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="5">
    <title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

    <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released
    under this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for
    modified versions, provided that you include in the combination
    all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original documents,
    unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your
    combined work in its license notice.</para>

    <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this
    License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced
    with a single copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with
    the same name but different contents, make the title of each such
    section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the
    name of the original author or publisher of that section if known,
    or else a unique number.  Make the same adjustment to the section
    titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of
    the combined work.</para>

    <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled
    "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
    entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections entitled
    "Acknowledgements", and any sections entitled "Dedications".  You
    must delete all sections entitled "Endorsements."</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="6">
    <title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

    <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and
    other documents released under this License, and replace the
    individual copies of this License in the various documents with a
    single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you
    follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of
    the documents in all other respects.</para>

    <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection,
    and distribute it individually under this License, provided you
    insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
    follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
    copying of that document.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="7">
    <title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
    
    <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
    separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of
    a storage or distribution medium, does not as a whole count as a
    Modified Version of the Document, provided no compilation
    copyright is claimed for the compilation.  Such a compilation is
    called an "aggregate", and this License does not apply to the
    other self-contained works thus compiled with the Document, on
    account of their being thus compiled, if they are not themselves
    derivative works of the Document.</para>

    <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to
    these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than
    one quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts
    may be placed on covers that surround only the Document within the
    aggregate.  Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole
    aggregate.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="8">
    <title>TRANSLATION</title>

    <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section
    4.  Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires
    special permission from their copyright holders, but you may
    include translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition
    to the original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may
    include a translation of this License provided that you also
    include the original English version of this License.  In case of
    a disagreement between the translation and the original English
    version of this License, the original English version will
    prevail.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="9">
    <title>TERMINATION</title>
    
    <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the
    Document except as expressly provided for under this License.  Any
    other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the
    Document is void, and will automatically terminate your rights
    under this License.  However, parties who have received copies, or
    rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
    terminated so long as such parties remain in full
    compliance.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="10">
    <title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

    <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised
    versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.
    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present
    version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or
    concerns.  See <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing
    version number.  If the Document specifies that a particular
    numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to
    it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
    either of that specified version or of any later version that has
    been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
    If the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
    you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the
    Free Software Foundation.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 label="">
    <title>How to use this License for your documents</title>

    <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include
    a copy of the License in the document and put the following
    copyright and license notices just after the title page:</para>

<blockquote><para>
      Copyright (c)  YEAR  YOUR NAME.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
      Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".
</para></blockquote>

    <para>If you have no Invariant Sections, write "with no Invariant
    Sections" instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have
    no Front-Cover Texts, write "no Front-Cover Texts" instead of
    "Front-Cover Texts being LIST"; likewise for Back-Cover
    Texts.</para>

    <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program
    code, we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
    choice of free software license, such as the GNU General Public
    License, to permit their use in free software.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

</article>


