<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-15"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY email   "jean DASH philippe DOT guerard AT tigreraye DOT org">
<!ENTITY tldpurl "http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Online-Troubleshooting-HOWTO/">
]>

<!-- $Id$ -->

<article lang="en">

<articleinfo>

<title>Online Troubleshooting Resources: HOWTO</title>

<author>
   <firstname>Jean-Philippe</firstname>
   <surname>Guérard</surname>
   <email>&email;</email>
</author>

<pubdate>2006-05-25</pubdate>
<releaseinfo>Version 1.7</releaseinfo>

<revhistory>
   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.7</revnumber>
      <date>2006-05-25</date>
      <authorinitials>JPG</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
       
         Two updates following suggestions of Oguz Yarimtepe (the Basic 
         Unix Tutorial of Idaho State University is not available 
         anymore, update of the link to the Why use Google page). Added 
         a section listing translations of this document.

       </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.6</revnumber>
      <date>2005-08-06</date>
      <authorinitials>JPG</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         Added FOLDOC (thanks to Howard Mann for suggesting this). 
         General document update and cleanup. Added the text of the Open 
         Publication Licence at the end of the document.
       </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.5</revnumber>
      <date>2002-10-20</date>
      <authorinitials>JPG</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         More dead links removal &amp; URL updates.
         Author and copyright updated as per Horward Mann request.
      </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
      <date>2002-03-04</date>
      <authorinitials>JPG</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         Dead links removal. Outdated links update. Revision of the 
         HOWTOs and FAQs sections.
      </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
      <date>2000-07-24</date>
      <authorinitials>HM</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         Update.
      </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
      <date>1999-11-20</date>
      <authorinitials>HM</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         Added "Introduction to Unix" to Unix section.
      </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
      <date>1999-11-08</date>
      <authorinitials>HM</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         Added Geocrawler.com to Mailing List Section. Convert to 
         DocBook.
      </revremark>
   </revision>

   <revision>
      <revnumber>0.5</revnumber>
      <date>1999-09-18</date>
      <authorinitials>HM</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
         Initial release. 
      </revremark>
   </revision>

</revhistory>

<abstract><para>

Troubleshooting a Linux-related issue is often perceived as a difficult 
task. But, often, the solution is just a few clicks away on the 
internet. This document will direct Linux users to resources available 
on the Internet that provide access to a vast amount of Linux-related 
information useful in the troubleshooting problems.

</para></abstract>

</articleinfo>

<section id="intro">

<title>Introduction</title>

<para>

The traditional means of troubleshooting computer-related problems 
involves consulting user's manuals, books, friends - probably enticed 
with goodies - and, when all the former do not yield a solution, calling 
the technical support service of the vendor of the product in question. 
And, we all know pleasant and reliably efficacious the latter stratagem 
is. Unfortunately, this is the norm in the sphere of commercial 
proprietary products.

</para>

<para>

In contradistinction, Linux, and related distributions, utilities and 
applications software, have largely been developed according to the 
<ulink url="http://www.opensource.org" >Open Source</ulink> model, 
wherein developers have used electronic communication over the Internet 
- typically in the form of publicly-accessible Mailing Lists - to 
collaborate with their peers in the refinement of the associated source 
code. Such collaboration has also traditionally involved the online 
publication of user's manuals, lists of Frequently-Asked-Questions 
(FAQ's), knowledge bases, release notes, formal guides such as this 
document (HOWTO's) and tutorials. In addition, users often assist others 
through the forum of Usenet and other newsgroups and the posted messages 
are readily accessible in the form of searchable archives. These 
Linux-related newsgroups are renowned for their high level of user 
participation. In significant measure, Linux may be considered a product 
of the Internet.

</para>

<para>

Considered together, these resources enable access to a large, 
ever-expanding factual database, and my intent is to encourage and 
direct the reader to utilize these repositories when faced with an issue 
not addressed in the documentation that is included with each 
distribution of Linux. Linux veterans who assist newcomers through the 
forum of Usenet soon become aware of the frequency with which certain 
technical questions are repeatedly posted - questions the answers to 
which are readily available in one or more of the existent online 
repositories. So, to diminish the likelihood of being "flamed" in 
response to your posted question on Usenet or irc, read further!

</para>

<para>

Armed with a browser, Linux users may rapidly become adept at 
troubleshooting their systems. The key is knowing how and where to look. 
My objective is to guide the user - particularly the Linux newbie - in 
this quest.

</para>

<section id="updates">

<title>Document Updates</title>

<para>
  
The <ulink url="&tldpurl;">latest version</ulink> of this document will 
always be available at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">Linux 
Documentation Project</ulink>. The document will also be available in 
SGML, PS, PDF, and other formats at that website.
  
</para>

</section>

<section id="copyright">

<title>Copyright and License</title>

<para>

Copyright &copy; 1999-2005, by Jean-Philippe Guérard. This material may 
be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the 
Open Publication Licence, v1.0 or later (see <xref linkend="openpub"/>).

</para>

</section>

<section id="feedback">

<title>

Feedback and Corrections

</title>

<para>

I always welcome feedback and constructive criticism. You can reach me 
at <email>&email;</email>. In particular, I wish to be notified about 
any errors in this document and resources you believe deserving of 
inclusion, but not presently covered herein. Because the assessment of 
the value of a particular resource is inherently subjective, I do not 
guarantee that I will include it, but I will certainly give any 
suggestion thoughtful consideration. In anticipation, Thanks.

</para>

</section>

<section id="translations">

<title>

Translations

</title>

<para>

This document has already been translated in several languages. If you 
have made a translation of this document, please e-mail me and I will 
add your translation to this list.

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>

A <ulink 
url="http://www.traduc.org/docs/howto/lecture/Online-Troubleshooting-HOWTO.html">French 
translation</ulink> has been made by Benoît Sibaud, of the <ulink 
url="http://www.traduc.org">Traduc.org</ulink> project.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

A <ulink 
url="http://docs.comu.edu.tr/howto/online-troubleshooting-howto-intro.html"> 
Turkish</ulink> translation has been made by Oguz Yarimtepe, of the 
<ulink url="http://docs.comu.edu.tr">docs.comu.edu.tr</ulink> project.

</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</para>

</section>

<section id="history">

<title>

Document history

</title>

<para>

Howard Mann conceived and formulated the first version of this HOWTO. He 
kept managing and updating it until version 1.3. Maintainership was then 
taken over by Jean-Philippe Guérard, who is now in charge of this 
document.

</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="faqs">

<title>Frequently-Asked-Questions (FAQs)</title>

<para>

Users of Internet Newsgroups and Mailing lists soon discovered that some 
basic questions were being asked over and over again. To provide an 
answer to these questions, and to avoid them being repeated continually, 
FAQs were developed, listing the most classical questions and their 
agreed answers.

</para>

<para>

A list of FAQs is also a traditional accompaniment to Linux-related 
software. The FAQ is the first document to peruse when troubleshooting a 
particular application. It provides answers to typical questions, and is 
a good place to start troubleshooting a specific problem. In addition, 
FAQs exist for Linux distributions, window managers, and the so-called 
desktop environments (KDE and Gnome).

</para>

<para>

A FAQ is typically provided online by the developers of the product in 
question, and enterprising users sometimes host an 
<quote>unofficial</quote> FAQ as well. Search for the latter with an 
Internet search engine.

</para>

<para>

For Linux newbies, I provide links to two FAQs that collectively
address <emphasis>many</emphasis> of the questions posted to the Usenet
newsgroups:

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>

<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/FAQ/Linux-FAQ/">The Linux FAQ</ulink>

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

<ulink url="http://www.tux.org/lkml/">The Linux Kernel mailing list 
FAQ</ulink>

</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id="onlinesupport">

<title>Online Support Sections</title>

<para>

These sections are typically found at the websites of Linux 
distributions, and often contain a variety of helpful documents with 
information not easily encompassed within a FAQ. This is the second 
place to go when troubleshooting a problem. Look for sections with one 
or more of the following titles:

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Installation Support
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Knowledge or Solutions Databases
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Tips and Tricks
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Errata, Fixes and Updates
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Security Information
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Bug Tracking System
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Bug Database
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Hardware Guide or Compatibility List
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Technical Guides
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
White Papers
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>

Some websites provide a site search engine that will facilitate your 
quest for a solution.

</para>

<para>

If you have a problem with a newly installed distribution, look here 
first as bugs and their fixes are typically posted here. You may find a 
detailed guide that will help you accomplish a task such as upgrading 
your kernel or the version of the X Window System you are using.

</para>

<para>

I have often been able to solve problems with my Linux distribution by 
looking into the bug report database, and finding that another user 
already has offered a solution to this issue.

</para>

<para>

I recommend you spend some time at the website of the distribution you 
are using, familiarizing yourself with what is available.

</para>

</section>

<section id="searchengines">

<title>Internet Search Engines</title>

<para>

I frequently use a Search Engine to retrieve helpful or necessary 
information from the 'net. These engines catalogue pages from 
commercial, personal and academic websites, as well as Mailing Lists and 
the like.

</para>

<para>

There are several good search engine. It is worthwhile becoming very 
familiar with the operational details of at least one non-directory 
engine to maximize the efficiency and efficacy of your search efforts. 
You probably already have a favorite - I like 
<emphasis>Google.com</emphasis>, and will discuss it in a little more 
detail.

</para>

<para>

The key to a successful search is to use a good set of keywords. If 
you're getting a specific error message, you might search for its text. 
Otherwise, you need to find a few relevant words describing your 
problem. Then, by trial and error, you should be able to find some 
pertinent information.

</para>

<section id="google">

<title>Google.com</title>

<para>

This <ulink url="http://www.google.com">engine</ulink> has several novel 
features that are described in its <ulink 
url="http://www.google.com/technology/">Google Technology page</ulink>. 
In particular, the engine often returns the most useful pages first; in 
fact, I have often found that the first listed page contains the 
information I need. Because it caches web pages, it is relatively fast 
at displaying requested items. It has a so-called 
<trademark>GoogleScout</trademark> feature, activated by clicking on the 
"similar pages" links, that provides additional relevant links with each 
item returned.

</para>

</section>

</section>

<section id="usenet">

<title>Usenet Newsgroup Archives</title>

<para>

The ability to search for and retrieve information from archived posts 
to the Linux-related (Usenet) newsgroups represents a powerful means of 
troubleshooting in Linux.

</para>

<para>

Search engines permit one to search the archives by stipulating the 
forum, keywords, authors, dates, language and combinations thereof. 
Because the number of Linux-related newsgroups is large, the likelihood 
of finding useful information is high.

</para>

<para>

The main web site that currently provides access to Usenet archives 
using a search engine is <ulink url="http://groups.google.com"/>. The 
most effective way to do a search is to use its <ulink 
url="http://groups.google.com/advanced_group_search">Advanced Groups 
Search page</ulink>.

</para>

<para>

I would like to relate a brief anecdote to demonstrate the efficacy of 
this approach. The first time I attempted to build a kernel, I was 
presented with this error message when I invoked a <quote>make</quote> 
command:

</para>

<screen>
make[1]: as86: Command not found
make[1]: *** [bootsect.o] Error 127
make[1]: Leaving directory `/usr/src/linux/arch/i386/boot'
make: *** [zImage]
Error 2
</screen>

<para>

I had no idea what <literal>as86</literal> was, but I entered it as the 
keyword in the <emphasis>Subject</emphasis> field of the Advanced Groups 
Search page at groups.google.com, and was presented with a large number 
of posts from folks who had encountered the same problem. Respondents 
had provided the reason and solution: I did not have an assembler/linker 
necessary to create machine code, and the <medialabel>bin86</medialabel> 
package provided it. I downloaded and installed a RPM package of the 
latter and was on my way. This entire process took about 10 minutes!

</para>

</section>

<section id="mailinglists">

<title>Mailing List Archives</title>

<para>

As you might expect, there are a very large number of Linux-related 
Mailing Lists that enable developers and users to communicate and 
collaborate on projects. These Lists cover every conceivable aspect of 
Linux, from the technical arcana of kernel development to the relatively 
unfocused discussion of issues at the newbie level. Subscribers to a 
particular Mailing List are generally very knowledgeable in the List's 
topic, and detailed and useful information is often retrievable. The 
communications are publicly accessible through Internet search engines 
and in the form of online Mailing List Archives. You will typically see 
archived pages when you conduct a search using an Internet search 
engine.

</para>

<para>

Usually, you will not need to look directly in a Mailing List Archive. 
<link linkend="searchengines">Search engines</link> like Google.com 
include these archives in their databases. If you can't find anything 
with a search engine, it might be worthwhile to browse or search in an 
appropriate Mailing List.

</para>

<para>

Also, not all Mailing Lists are associated with an online archive, but 
this is increasingly the case. Similarly, not all archives have an 
associated search engine.

</para>

<para>

Initially, try locate the Mailing List Archive you are interested in by 
typing keywords and "mailing list archive" in an Internet search engine.

</para>

<para>

You may also find Mailing List archives at the following locations:

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>

The website of the distribution of Linux you use.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

The website of the Window Manager or Desktop Environment you use.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

The website dedicated to the application or project in question.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

<ulink url="http://www.mail-archive.com/lists.html">The Mail 
Archive</ulink>

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

<ulink url="http://www.uwsg.indiana.edu/hypermail/">Mailing List 
Archives</ulink>

</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>

This is not a complete listing of archives and you may find additional 
sites with an Internet search engine. But, this should certainly get you 
going.

</para>

</section>

<section id="howtos">

<title>HOWTOs</title>

<para>

HOWTOs are detailed reference documents on a specific subject, usually 
following a step-by-step approach. A HOWTO is a good document to help 
you discover a task or a topic you don't know. It will provide you with 
the basic steps and the major references.

</para>

<para>

These documents are particularly useful when you decide to provide or 
access a new service with your Linux system, or when you embark on a 
technically complex project. For example, you may have the option of 
accessing the 'net with a DSL or Cable Modem service - excellent guides 
are available in the form of HOWTOs.

</para>

<para>

Authors of these documents often include references and links to sites 
that they have found useful. You may find the information you need at 
one of these hyperlinked sites rather than in the HOWTO itself.

</para>

<!-- It would be nice to find a new relevant example to put here. -->

<para>

To find HOWTOs, the first place to go is the <ulink 
url="http://www.tldp.org">Linux Documentation Project (LDP)</ulink>. The 
LDP includes a <ulink 
url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/HOWTO-INDEX/howtos.html">HOWTO Index 
Page</ulink> that I suggest you bookmark in your browser.

</para>

<para>

These HOWTOs are written by Linux users and are periodically updated by 
the authors. Many authors provide the latest version at a personal 
website and a hyperlink to the latter is typically provided in the 
document. This version may be newer than the one available at the LDP 
website.

</para>

<para>

Note also that other HOWTOs are available, the authors of which have not 
submitted them to the LDP. It is definitely worthwhile trying to find 
these with an <link linkend="searchengines">Internet search 
engine</link>, using the "howto" keyword.

</para>

</section>

<section id="usersmanuals">

<title>Online User's Manuals</title>

<para>

Some of the major Linux distributions, Window Managers and Desktop 
Environments publish their user's manual online. If the entire manual is 
not online, installation and configuration guides are typically found at 
the relevant website. This also applies to major applications like the 
<emphasis>Gimp</emphasis> (GNU Image Manipulation Program) or 
<emphasis>Apache</emphasis>.

</para>

<para>

So, for those users who do not have the printed manual, a wealth of 
installation and configuration guidance is generally available online.

</para>

</section>

<section id="unixrefs">

<title>

Online Unix References and Tutorials

</title>

<para>

As Linux is a Unix-like operating system, a general familiarity with 
fundamental Unix concepts such as the Unix directory hierarchy and file 
permissions is essential. Fortunately, there are many Unix tutorials 
online that collectively cover everything a user might need to know to 
use Linux. I suggest you bookmark the following as an online reference 
library:

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>

The Wikipedia <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix">Unix 
article</ulink> is a good place to start. It includes an Unix history, 
explains some Unix concepts and includes an explanation of basic 
commands and some relevant links.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

Eric S. Raymond's <ulink 
url="http://en.tldp.org/HOWTO/Unix-and-Internet-Fundamentals-HOWTO/">The 
Unix and Internet Fundamentals HOWTO</ulink> is a good document to learn 
about the Unix concepts.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

The <ulink url="http://www.ee.surrey.ac.uk/Teaching/Unix/">UNIX Tutorial 
for Beginners </ulink> of the University of Surrey is a good step by 
step tutorial for beginners.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

<ulink 
url="http://www.tru64unix.compaq.com/docs/base_doc/DOCUMENTATION/V40D_HTML/APS2HDTE/TITLETXT.HTM">The 
Command and Shell User's guide</ulink> from Digital Equipment 
Corporation is an excellent guide to the Unix Operating System. Bookmark 
the <emphasis>Index Page</emphasis> linked there as an online reference.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

<ulink url="http://star.pst.qub.ac.uk/help/unixhelp/">UNIXhelp</ulink> 
is mirrored on many servers around the world. It is a useful resource 
for newbies.

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

<ulink 
url="http://wks.uts.ohio-state.edu/unix_course/intro-1.html">Introduction 
to Unix</ulink> also contains a useful <ulink 
url="http://wks.uts.ohio-state.edu/unix_course/intro-137.html#HEADING137-0">Unix 
Command Summary</ulink> page with brief, but useful, explanations of 
commonly used Unix commands.

</para></listitem> 

<listitem><para>

<ulink url="http://unix.t-a-y-l-o-r.com/">Unix is a Four Letter 
Word...</ulink> is another resource suitable for newbies.

</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id="miscresources">

<title>Miscellaneous Resources</title>

<para>

In this section, I provide a number of links to websites that I have 
found useful while learning to use Linux. This is an eclectic 
collection, but keep these handy.

</para>

<section id="Xwindow">

<title>

Release Notes and Available Documentation related to the X Window Server

</title>

<para>

Depending on the X Window Server your distribution is using, you will 
need to look at either the <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/">XFree86 
website</ulink> or the <ulink url="http://xorg.freedesktop.org">X.Org 
Foundation website</ulink>. Whenever you have trouble with your X 
environment, peruse the notes applicable to your videocard and chipset. 
These typically provide details about the configuration of the X Window 
System relative to your card, and will enumerate any "options" you have 
to include in the <filename>XF86Config</filename> file that governs X.

</para>

</section>

<section id="gnumanuals">

<title>GNU Software and Manuals</title>

<para>

Many important programs that are frequently utilized by the Linux user 
are GNU utilities - for example, the <application>tar</application> 
(archive) and <application>gzip</application> (compression) programs. 
Descriptions of these programs are located at the <ulink 
url="http://directory.fsf.org/">FSF Free Software Directory</ulink> 
where many <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/manual/manual.html">Online 
Manuals</ulink> may also be found.

</para>

<para>

These manuals typically provide a lot more information than is found in 
the corresponding <application>man</application> page on your system. 
For example , compare the <application>man</application> page and online 
manual for the <application>tar</application> utility.

</para>

</section>

<section id="FOLDOC">
<title>The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</title>

<para>

The <ulink url="http://www.foldoc.org/">Free On-line Dictionary of 
Computing (FOLDOC)</ulink> is a huge encyclopedia of computing terms and 
concepts, maintained by Denis Howe. It has very detailed articles, with 
a lot of cross references. It's a very good reference to understand 
anything related to computing.

</para>

</section>

<section id="webopedia">

<title>An online dictionary of computer and technology terms</title>

<para>

The <ulink url="http://www.pcwebopedia.com/">PC Webopedia</ulink> 
consists of a large online dictionary of computer-related terms and a 
search engine that provides links to documents that discuss each item in 
more detail. For example, I used this site to learn the differences 
between <emphasis>ISA</emphasis> and <emphasis>PCI</emphasis> buses.

</para>

</section>

</section>

<section id="conclusions">

<title>

Concluding Comments

</title>

<para>

If you are a Linux newbie, you may want to create a 
<emphasis>Troubleshooting</emphasis> folder in your browser's bookmark 
list, into which you put the hyperlinks I have included in this 
document, as well as those pertinent to the distribution of Linux and 
the Window Manager or Desktop Environment you use.

</para>

<para>

As you use these links, you will quickly become adept at troubleshooting 
online.

</para>

<para>Cheers and happy searching!</para>

</section>

<appendix id="openpub">

<title>Open Publication License</title>

<subtitle>v1.0, 8 June 1999</subtitle>

<section id="opl-requirements">

<title>

Requirements on both unmodified and modified versions

</title>

<para>

The Open Publication works may be reproduced and distributed in whole or
in part, in any medium physical or electronic, provided that the terms
of this license are adhered to, and that this license or an
incorporation of it by reference (with any options elected by the
author(s) and/or publisher) is displayed in the reproduction.

</para>

<para>

Proper form for an incorporation by reference is as follows:

</para>

<blockquote><para>

Copyright (c) &lt;year&gt; by &lt;author's name or designee&gt;. This
material may be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set
forth in the Open Publication License, vX.Y or later (the latest version
is presently available at <ulink
url="http://www.opencontent.org/openpub/"></ulink>).

</para></blockquote>

<para>

The reference must be immediately followed with any options elected by
the author(s) and/or publisher of the document (see section VI).

</para>

<para>

Commercial redistribution of Open Publication-licensed material is 
permitted.

</para>

<para>

Any publication in standard (paper) book form shall require the citation
of the original publisher and author. The publisher and author's names
shall appear on all outer surfaces of the book. On all outer surfaces of
the book the original publisher's name shall be as large as the title of
the work and cited as possessive with respect to the title.

</para>

</section>

<section id="opl-copyright">

<title>

Copyright

</title>

<para>

The copyright to each Open Publication is owned by its author(s) or
designee.

</para>

</section>

<section id="opl-scope">

<title>

Scope of license

</title>

<para>

The following license terms apply to all Open Publication works, unless
otherwise explicitly stated in the document.

</para>

<para>

Mere aggregation of Open Publication works or a portion of an Open
Publication work with other works or programs on the same media shall
not cause this license to apply to those other works. The aggregate work
shall contain a notice specifying the inclusion of the Open Publication
material and appropriate copyright notice.

</para>

<para>

SEVERABILITY. If any part of this license is found to be unenforceable
in any jurisdiction, the remaining portions of the license remain in
force.

</para>

<para>

NO WARRANTY. Open Publication works are licensed and provided "as is"
without warranty of any kind, express or implied, including, but not
limited to, the implied warranties of merchantability and fitness for a
particular purpose or a warranty of non-infringement.

</para>

</section>

<section id="opl-modified-works">

<title>

Requirements on modified works

</title>

<para>

All modified versions of documents covered by this license, including
translations, anthologies, compilations and partial documents, must meet
the following requirements:

</para>

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>

The modified version must be labeled as such.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

The person making the modifications must be identified and the
modifications dated.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Acknowledgement of the original author and publisher if applicable must
be retained according to normal academic citation practices.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

The location of the original unmodified document must be identified.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

The original author's (or authors') name(s) may not be used to assert or
imply endorsement of the resulting document without the original
author's (or authors') permission.

</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</section>

<section id="opl-good-practice">

<title>

Good-practice recommendations

</title>

<para>

In addition to the requirements of this license, it is requested from
and strongly recommended of redistributors that:

</para>

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>

If you are distributing Open Publication works on hardcopy or CD-ROM,
you provide email notification to the authors of your intent to
redistribute at least thirty days before your manuscript or media
freeze, to give the authors time to provide updated documents. This
notification should describe modifications, if any, made to the
document.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

All substantive modifications (including deletions) be either clearly
marked up in the document or else described in an attachment to the
document.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Finally, while it is not mandatory under this license, it is considered
good form to offer a free copy of any hardcopy and CD-ROM expression of
an Open Publication-licensed work to its author(s).

</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</section>

<section id="opl-options">

<title>

License options

</title>

<para>

The author(s) and/or publisher of an Open Publication-licensed document
may elect certain options by appending language to the reference to or
copy of the license. These options are considered part of the license
instance and must be included with the license (or its incorporation by
reference) in derived works.

</para>

<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">

<listitem><para>

To prohibit distribution of substantively modified versions without the
explicit permission of the author(s). "Substantive modification" is
defined as a change to the semantic content of the document, and
excludes mere changes in format or typographical corrections.

</para>
<para>

To accomplish this, add the phrase `Distribution of substantively
modified versions of this document is prohibited without the explicit
permission of the copyright holder.' to the license reference or copy.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

To prohibit any publication of this work or derivative works in whole or
in part in standard (paper) book form for commercial purposes is
prohibited unless prior permission is obtained from the copyright
holder.

</para>
<para>

To accomplish this, add the phrase 'Distribution of the work or
derivative of the work in any standard (paper) book form is prohibited
unless prior permission is obtained from the copyright holder.' to the
license reference or copy.

</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</section>

</appendix>

</article>
