<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" 
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article id="Secure-CVS-Pserver">

<articleinfo>
 <title>Secure CVS Pserver Mini-HOWTO</title>

 <author>
  <firstname>Morgon</firstname>
  <surname>Kanter</surname>
  <affiliation>
   <address>
    <email>morgon AT surgo DOT net</email>
   </address>
  </affiliation>
 </author>

 <copyright>
  <year>2003</year>
  <holder>Morgon Kanter</holder>
 </copyright>

 <legalnotice>
  <para>
   Permission is granted to copy, distribute, and/or modify this document 
   under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 
   or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; 
   with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
   A copy of the license is included in <xref linkend="gfdl" />, entitled "GNU 
   Free Documentation License".
  </para>
 </legalnotice>

 <pubdate>February 2003</pubdate>

 <revhistory id="revhistory">
  <revision>
   <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
   <date>2003-03-21</date>
   <authorinitials>mk</authorinitials>
   <revremark>Fixed a missing link and added a section on CVSGrab</revremark>
  </revision>
  
  <revision>
   <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
   <date>2003-02-01</date>
   <authorinitials>mk</authorinitials>
   <revremark>Initial Release, reviewed by LDP.</revremark>
  </revision>
 </revhistory>

 <abstract><para>
  This document will help you set up a more secure CVS 
  Pserver for anonymous CVS access.
 </para></abstract>

</articleinfo>
  
<sect1 id="intro">
 <title>Introduction</title>
 <para>
  CVS Pserver is, by definition, an insecure protocol. Among 
  other things, passwords are transmitted in plain text, making it 
  undesirable for much use. However, CVS Pserver is very good for 
  providing anonymous CVS access to a repository.
 </para>
 <para>
  In this document we will introduce you to setting up a CVS 
  repository (although not intruding on the CVS HOWTO's space), 
  and how to set up a chroot jail for the Pserver. 
  We will also talk about using SSH for developer access to a repository.
 </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gettools">
 <title>Getting the tools</title>
 
 <sect2>
  <title>What you need</title>
  <para>
   You'll need the following things in order to set up a secure Pserver:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>CVS</term>
    <listitem><para>
     Of course, you will need to have CVS in order to be running it. 
     You can get it <ulink url="http://www.cvshome.org">here</ulink>.
    </para></listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>cvsd</term>
    <listitem><para>
     <command>cvsd</command> is a program that will run the CVS Pserver 
     in a chroot jail. You can get it <ulink url="http://tiefighter.et.tudelft.nl/~arthur/cvsd/">here</ulink>.
    </para></listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>SSHd</term>
    <listitem><para>
     If you want your developers to have secure access to the repository, 
     you'll have to be running an SSH server. However, setting up that 
     access is beyond the scope of this Mini-HOWTO.  More information can be found at 
     <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/CVS-RCS-HOWTO.html">the CVS-RCS howto</ulink>.
    </para></listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>
    
 <sect2 id="compiletools">
  <title>Compiling the tools</title>
  <para>
   If you are compiling from the sources, follow these instructions. 
   If you downloaded binaries, skip ahead to <xref linkend="compilecvsd" />.
  </para>
      
  <sect3 id="compilecvs">
   <title>Compiling CVS</title>
   <para>
    After you have downloaded the CVS sources, unpack them into a 
    directory and <command>cd</command> into it. The default prefix is 
    <filename class="directory">/usr/local</filename>; we've changed it 
    to <filename class="directory">/usr</filename> for this example. 
    You might want to change <varname>mandir</varname> to wherever 
    your man pages reside (the default is 
    <filename class="directory">PREFIX/man</filename>).
   </para>
   <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> ./configure --prefix=/usr
<prompt>$</prompt> make
<prompt>#</prompt> make install
   </programlisting></informalexample>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="compilecvsd">
   <title>Compiling cvsd</title>
   <para>
    There are a few configure switches you should be aware of here. 
    The default prefix is <filename class="directory">/usr/local</filename>, 
    which in this document we are changing to <filename class="directory">/usr</filename>. 
    You should also change <varname>sysconfdir</varname> to 
    <filename class="directory">/etc</filename>, where the system 
    config files usually reside. You might want to change 
    <varname>mandir</varname> to wherever your manual pages reside as 
    well.
   </para>
   <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> ./configure --prefix=/usr --sysconfdir=/etc
<prompt>$</prompt> make
<prompt>#</prompt> make install
   </programlisting></informalexample>
   <para>
    Now lets go on to setting up these wonderful tools.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="setuptools">
 <title>Setting up the tools</title>
 <para>
  Now that CVS and cvsd are built, let's set them up.
 </para>

 <sect2 id="createrepository">
  <title>Creating the CVS Repository</title>
  <para>
   Before we begin, I strongly recommend you read the CVS manual that 
   was installed with the rest of CVS. If the stand-alone info browser 
   or the texinfo package is installed on your system, you can see 
   this manual by typing the command <command>info cvs</command> at your shell.
  </para>
  <para>
   First, plan out where you want your repository. Debian defaults to 
   <filename class="directory">/var/lib/cvs</filename>. My repository 
   is under the directory <filename class="directory">/cvs/root</filename>, 
   and is on its own small partition. What you do depends on your needs 
   and can vary widely.
   <important>
	  <para>
    Make sure that the repository is a subdirectory of an empty directory! For example, if you are installing it into <filename class="directory">/var/lib/cvs</filename>, put the repository in <filename class="directory">/var/lib/cvs/root</filename> (or whatever you want for the last directory). This is because we create a chroot jail for the Pserver!
          </para>
   </important>
  </para>
  <para>
   After you have planned where you want to put your repository, 
   made the necessary partitions, if desired, and run the following command 
   (we assume that it will be at <filename class="directory">/cvs/root</filename>):
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> cvs -d /cvs/root init
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   That will initialize your repository and set up the necessary 
   <envar>CVSROOT</envar> files.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="setupjail">
  <title>Setting up the jail</title>
  <para>
   Now that we have the <envar>CVSROOT</envar> set up, we need to copy the 
   appropriate libraries and files for cvsd, which runs the 
   Pserver in the chroot jail.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="copyfiles">
   <title>Transferring the necessary files</title>
    <para>
     <note>
      <para>If you installed cvsd from a package management system like 
      RPM, this may already be done for you. If that is the case, 
      skip ahead to the next step.</para>
     </note>
     Change your directory to <filename class="directory">/cvs</filename> (or whatever the directory before your root is) and enter the following commands:
   </para>
   <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> cvsd-buildroot /cvs
<prompt>$</prompt> mkdir -p var/lock
<prompt>$</prompt> adduser cvsd
<prompt>$</prompt> addgroup cvsd
   </programlisting></informalexample>
   <para>
    Thankfully, cvsd comes with the script <command>cvsd-buildroot</command>, so we don't have to do all the necessary copying by hand. However, you should edit the <filename>/cvs/etc/passwd</filename> file, and remove the entry for <quote>root,</quote> as it's unneeded.
   </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="configcvsd">
   <title>Configuring cvsd</title>
   <para>
    The defaults in <filename>/etc/cvsd/cvsd.conf</filename> are okay, but can be less than desirable. Make sure that <envar>RootJail</envar> is set to wherever the chroot jail you built is, and the repository is the directory where the repository is <emphasis role="bold">relative to the chroot jail</emphasis>. Set <varname>maxconnections</varname> to whatever you desire, and make sure that Uid and Gid are set to cvsd. If you are lacking an already-built <filename>cvsd.conf</filename> file, here is mine:
   </para>
   <example>
    <title>My <filename>cvsd.conf</filename></title>
    <programlisting>
Uid cvsd
Gid cvsd
PidFile /var/run/cvsd.pid
RootJail /cvs
MaxConnections 10
Nice 1
Listen * 2401
Repos /root
Limit coredumpsize 0
    </programlisting>
   </example>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="addanonaccess">
  <title>Adding anonymous access</title>
  <para>
   It's back to configuring CVS, but don't worry, we are almost 
   there! We have to edit a couple of necessary files to allow for 
   anonymous access. First, making sure you aren't in the CVS directory, 
   check out the CVSROOT module:
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> cvs -d /cvs/root checkout CVSROOT
<prompt>#</prompt> cd CVSROOT
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   Now edit the file <filename>READERS</filename>. Create it if it isn't there, and add a line that reads <quote>anonymous</quote>.
   <important>
    <para>You NEED to have an extra line at the end of the file!</para>
   </important>
   The file <filename>READERS</filename> is a list of users who have 
   read-only access to the CVS repository. People with write access 
   are listed in the file <filename>WRITERS</filename>. Read the cvs 
   manual <footnote id="ftn-try-info-cvs"><para>info cvs, if you have the stand-alone 
   <command>info</command> viewer installed on your system</para></footnote> 
   for more information on these files.
  </para>
  <para>
   Now commit the repository with the command below. We assume 
   that your current working directory is <envar>CVSROOT</envar>. If it 
   isn't, forget the <command>cd</command> step.
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> cd ../
<prompt>#</prompt> cvs -d /cvs/root commit
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   You should now get a message that says something like <computeroutput>Re-building administrative files</computeroutput>, which means that it was successful.
  </para>
  <para>
   One last step and we're all done! Run the following command, 
   and when prompted for a password, just press <keycap>ENTER</keycap>:
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> cvsd-passwd /cvs/root anonymous
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   Congratulations! You now have secure, anonymous CVS Pserver access 
   to the repository!
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="lockfilelocation">
  <title>Not quite done yet! Changing lock file locations</title>
  <para>
   There is one small feature here that is really beyond the scope 
   of this Mini-HOWTO but is worth noting nonetheless. It is the 
   ability to change the directory where the Pserver will place lock files. 
  </para>
  <para>
   Normally the Pserver will place lock files in the same directory 
   as the files that you are trying to check out, but this can cause 
   permissions mayhem. Step back to when we built the chroot 
   jail for cvsd; we also created the directory <filename class="directory">var/lock</filename>. This is where we will place the lockfiles instead.
  </para>
  <para>
   So use the following example, replacing <filename class="directory">/cvs</filename> with wherever your <envar>chroot</envar> environment is, and <filename class="directory">var</filename> with wherever the locks are going to be placed. Mine are placed in <filename class="directory">var/lock</filename>, and there is nothing else under <filename class="directory">var</filename>, so a <command>chown -R</command> is safe. Also, replace the cvsd user and group ids with the user and group ids that cvsd runs as.
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> cd /cvs
<prompt>#</prompt> chown -R cvsd:cvsd var
<prompt>#</prompt> chmod -R 775 var
<prompt>#</prompt> cd
<prompt>#</prompt> cvs -d /cvs/root checkout CVSROOT
<prompt>#</prompt> cd CVSROOT
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   Now we want to edit the file <filename>config</filename>. Change 
   lock dir to the directory you want the locks to be placed, in our 
   case <filename class="directory">/var/lock</filename>.
   <important>
    <para>Note that this applies to the Pserver <emphasis role="bold">
    AS WELL AS THE NON-CHROOT SSH LOGIN METHOD!</emphasis>
    Ensure that this directory is not only in existence, but that you can  
    write to it as well, relative to your root directory. This is why I have 
    chosen <filename class="directory">/var/lock</filename>, because it satisfies those conditions.</para>
   </important>
   Now commit the changes:
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> cd ../
<prompt>#</prompt> cvs -d /cvs/root commit
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   And that's it!
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="pserveralternatives">
 <title>Alternatives to the Pserver</title>

 <sect2 id="developeraccess">
  <title>Access for developers</title>
  <para>
   Pserver is not a very good method to implement for your fellow developers 
   to access the repository. You can use CVS's SSH and ext method. 
   Simply add the user to the server's list of users, add the user 
   to the file WRITERS, and then they can do the following:
  </para>
  <informalexample><programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> export CVS_RSH='/usr/bin/ssh'
<prompt>$</prompt> cvs -d :ext:username@server.hostname:/cvs/root login
  </programlisting></informalexample>
  <para>
   This is a much more secure way for developers to access the 
   repository.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="anonhttpaccess">
  <title>Anonymous CVS access by http</title>
  <para>
   There is another way to allow anonymous access to CVS. If there 
   is an http server and Python installed on the server, you can use 
   a set of Python CGI scripts called <ulink url="http://viewcvs.sourceforge.net">
   viewcvs</ulink>, which allow people to view the CVS repository over 
   the web, and can generate tarballs for users to download.
  </para>
  <para>
   There is also a set of Perl CGI scripts that do the same thing 
   called <ulink url="http://stud.fh-heilbronn.de/~zeller/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/">
   cvsweb</ulink>, but Viewcvs is more mature and is preferred (at 
   least by me).
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="cvsgrab">
  <title>CVSGrab</title>
  <para>
   <ulink url="http://cvsgrab.sourceforge.net">CVSGrab</ulink> is an 
   end-user tool for downloading the CVS repository by a ViewCVS 
   interface. It is very useful when you are behind a corporate 
   firewall that blocks the Pserver, as you can just grab the repository 
   over standard HTTP. The only problem is if it doesn't have a 
   ViewCVS interface, but most free software 
   repositories are now on the web, and the few that still use 
   cvsweb seem to be switching over to ViewCVS.
  </para><para>
   CVSGrab is written in Java, which may at first be a turn-off to 
   some people (it is to me), but it seems completely compilable 
   using <application>GCJ</application>, the Java front-end to GCC.
  </para><para>
   CVSGrab is a tool that goes hand-in-hand with 
   ViewCVS. It is an end-user tool, not one that you as a system 
   administrator or repository administrator would set up and configure.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="acknowledgements">
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <para>
  This Mini-HOWTO was written by Morgon Kanter, who is reachable 
  at <email>morgon AT surgo DOT net</email>, public key available from 
  <ulink url="http://www.surgo.net/pubkey.asc">http://www.surgo.net/pubkey.asc</ulink>.
  Email all problems with this document to him, and they will be fixed 
  ASAP.
 </para><para>
  My thanks goes out to all the people who contributed to CVS over the 
  years, as well as the creators of Viewcvs, and in turn the creators 
  of cvsweb who inspired it.
 </para><para>
  I would also like to thank Tabatha Persad for reviewing and helping me edit 
  this monster, as well as putting up with me. Thanks!
 </para><para>
  Also thanks to the various email contributors who pointed out missing 
  stuff. Thank you Y Giridhar Appaji Nag and Pasi Hirvonen!
 </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl">
 <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
 <screen>
GNU Free Documentation License
Version 1.2, November 2002


Copyright (C) 2000,2001,2002  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.


0. PREAMBLE

The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
with or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially.
Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way
to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible
for modifications made by others.

This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense.  It
complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft
license designed for free software.

We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for free
software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
software does.  But this License is not limited to software manuals;
it can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or
whether it is published as a printed book.  We recommend this License
principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.


1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS

This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that
contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
distributed under the terms of this License.  Such a notice grants a
world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that
work under the conditions stated herein.  The "Document", below,
refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the public is a
licensee, and is addressed as "you".  You accept the license if you
copy, modify or distribute the work in a way requiring permission
under copyright law.

A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the
Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with
modifications and/or translated into another language.

A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of
the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the
publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject
(or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly
within that overall subject.  (Thus, if the Document is in part a
textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
mathematics.)  The relationship could be a matter of historical
connection with the subject or with related matters, or of legal,
commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
them.

The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles
are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice
that says that the Document is released under this License.  If a
section does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not
allowed to be designated as Invariant.  The Document may contain zero
Invariant Sections.  If the Document does not identify any Invariant
Sections then there are none.

The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed,
as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that
the Document is released under this License.  A Front-Cover Text may
be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.

A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
represented in a format whose specification is available to the
general public, that is suitable for revising the document
straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of
pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available
drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or
for automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input
to text formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file
format whose markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart
or discourage subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent.
An image format is not Transparent if used for any substantial amount
of text.  A copy that is not "Transparent" is called "Opaque".

Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML
or XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple
HTML, PostScript or PDF designed for human modification.  Examples of
transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG.  Opaque formats
include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or
processing tools are not generally available, and the
machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word
processors for output purposes only.

The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself,
plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material
this License requires to appear in the title page.  For works in
formats which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means
the text near the most prominent appearance of the work's title,
preceding the beginning of the body of the text.

A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose
title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following
text that translates XYZ in another language.  (Here XYZ stands for a
specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements",
"Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".)  To "Preserve the Title"
of such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.

The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which
states that this License applies to the Document.  These Warranty
Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this
License, but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other
implication that these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has
no effect on the meaning of this License.


2. VERBATIM COPYING

You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies
to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
conditions whatsoever to those of this License.  You may not use
technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further
copying of the copies you make or distribute.  However, you may accept
compensation in exchange for copies.  If you distribute a large enough
number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 3.

You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and
you may publicly display copies.


3. COPYING IN QUANTITY

If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have
printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover
Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on
the back cover.  Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify
you as the publisher of these copies.  The front cover must present
the full title with all words of the title equally prominent and
visible.  You may add other material on the covers in addition.
Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve
the title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated
as verbatim copying in other respects.

If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent
pages.

If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering
more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent
copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy
a computer-network location from which the general network-using
public has access to download using public-standard network protocols
a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material.
If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps,
when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure
that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
location until at least one year after the last time you distribute an
Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers) of that
edition to the public.

It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the
Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give
them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the Document.


4. MODIFICATIONS

You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under
the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release
the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified
Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution
and modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy
of it.  In addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:

A. Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct
 from that of the Document, and from those of previous versions
(which should, if there were any, be listed in the History section
 of the Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version
if the original publisher of that version gives permission.
B. List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities
 responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified
Version, together with at least five of the principal authors of the
 Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five),
unless they release you from this requirement.
C. State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
 Modified Version, as the publisher.
 D. Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
 E. Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
adjacent to the other copyright notices.
F. Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice
 giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under the
terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.
G. Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections
 and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.
 H. Include an unaltered copy of this License.
 I. Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add
to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and
 publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If
there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one
 stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as
given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
 Version as stated in the previous sentence.
 J. Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for
public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise
 the network locations given in the Document for previous versions
it was based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.
 You may omit a network location for a work that was published at
least four years before the Document itself, or if the original
 publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.
 K. For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications",
Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all
 the substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements
and/or dedications given therein.
L. Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
 unaltered in their text and in their titles.  Section numbers
or the equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.
M. Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section
 may not be included in the Modified Version.
 N. Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements"
or to conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
O. Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.

If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all
of these sections as invariant.  To do this, add their titles to the
list of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice.
These titles must be distinct from any other section titles.

You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains
nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has
been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
standard.

You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a
passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list
of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one passage of
Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or
through arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the Document already
includes a cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or
by arrangement made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of,
you may not add another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit
permission from the previous publisher that added the old one.

The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License
give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or
imply endorsement of any Modified Version.


5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS

You may combine the Document with other documents released under this
License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and
list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its
license notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.

The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single
copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but
different contents, make the title of each such section unique by
adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original
author or publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number.
Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the list of
Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined work.

In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History"
in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled
"History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements",
and any sections Entitled "Dedications".  You must delete all sections
Entitled "Endorsements".


6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS

You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents
released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this
License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in
the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for
verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other respects.

You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute
it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this
License into the extracted document, and follow this License in all
other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.


7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS

A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate
and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright
resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights
of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit.
When the Document is included an aggregate, this License does not
apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves
derivative works of the Document.

If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of
the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on
covers that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the
electronic equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form.
Otherwise they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole
aggregate.


8. TRANSLATION

Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may include a
translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
Document, and any Warrany Disclaimers, provided that you also include
the original English version of this License and the original versions
of those notices and disclaimers.  In case of a disagreement between
the translation and the original version of this License or a notice
or disclaimer, the original version will prevail.

If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
"Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve
its Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
title.


9. TERMINATION

You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except
as expressly provided for under this License.  Any other attempt to
copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
automatically terminate your rights under this License.  However,
parties who have received copies, or rights, from you under this
License will not have their licenses terminated so long as such
parties remain in full compliance.


10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE

The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions
of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.  Such new
versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may
differ in detail to address new problems or concerns.  See
http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.

Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number.
If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this
License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of
following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or
of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the
Free Software Foundation.  If the Document does not specify a version
number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not
as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.


ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents

To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy of
the License in the document and put the following copyright and
license notices just after the title page:

Copyright (c)  YEAR  YOUR NAME.
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
Free Documentation License".

If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover Texts,
replace the "with...Texts." line with this:

with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.

If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
situation.

If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of
free software license, such as the GNU General Public License,
to permit their use in free software.
 </screen>
</sect1>

</article>
