<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<article id="Tamil-Linux-HOWTO">
<!-- Headings {{{1 -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Tamil Linux HOWTO</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>V.</firstname>
      <surname>Venkataramanan</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <address>
<email>venkat@tamillinux.org</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
        
    <pubdate>
	Jan 2003
    </pubdate> 
    <copyright>
      <year>2002, 2003</year>
      <holder>V. Venkataramanan</holder>
    </copyright>

    <revhistory id="revhistory">
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2003-02-14</date>
	<authorinitials>venkat</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial release, reviewed by LDP</revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.9</revnumber>
        <date>2003-1-21</date>
        <authorinitials>venkat</authorinitials>
        <revremark>Changes made to comply to TDLP specs.</revremark>
     </revision>

     <revision>
        <revnumber>0.8</revnumber>
        <date>2002-10-24</date>
        <authorinitials>venkat</authorinitials>
        <revremark>First draft</revremark>
     </revision>
    </revhistory>
  
   <othercredit role='converter'>
   <firstname>D</firstname>
   <surname>Sivaraj</surname>
   <contrib>Initial conversion from LaTeX to Docbook XML</contrib>
   </othercredit>
  
    <abstract>
      <para>
       This document will help set up a working Tamil Linux environment.  This describes setting up fonts, keyboard drivers, editing and printing Tamil/bilingual documents, and working with the X Window system. The information is kept as generic as possible. When it pertains to a specific distribution (say RedHat or Debian), it is explicitly noted. 
      </para>
   </abstract>

  </articleinfo>

<!-- Preamble {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>About this HOWTO</title>

    <sect2><title>Purpose/Scope of this HOWTO</title>
   <para>
    This document will help set up a working Tamil Linux environment. 
   Step-by-step instructions are provided for setting up fonts, editors, 
   etc. This document also describes the essential instructions need to 
   use web browsers, edit documents and print them. 
   </para>

    <para>The base URL of this document is:
    <ulink url="http://www.tamillinux.org/doc/">
    </ulink>
    </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Feedback</title>
    <para>
    Comments and suggestions about this document may be directed to the author
    (<email>venkat@tamillinux.org</email>)
    </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Copyright and License</title>
    <para>&copy; 2002, 2003 V.Venkataramanan.</para>
    <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or
    modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free 
    Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version
    published by the Free Software Foundation; with no invariant
    Front-Cover text, no Back-Cover text and no invarient sections.
    </para>
    <para>
    A verbatim copy of the license can be obtained from the Free Software 
    Foundation Website at 
    <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html"></ulink>    
    </para>    
    </sect2>

    <sect2><title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <para>Several postings by the following people were useful in
    writing this document. The following people are thanked for all
    their help:</para>

    <para><emphasis>Thuraiappah Vaseeharan, D. Sivaraj, Sivakumar
    Shanmugasundaram, Dinesh Nadarajah, Anbumani Subramanian,
    Ganesan Rajagopal, M.K. Saravanan,...</emphasis></para>
   </sect2>

 

  </sect1>

<!-- Introduction {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Tamil is a member of the Dravidian languages.  Its
    origin is in southern India and the language is written with non-Roman
    alphabets. So there is a need for special fonts, encoding,
    keyboard layout and drivers, besides localization, including
    currency, date format, etc. This document will give a complete
    overview of setting up and working in the Tamil Linux
    environment. There are several pieces of information and tools
    available for Linux in Tamil; this how-to will serve as a
    meta-index to all the scattered resources.</para>

    <para>A word before you enter - most of the fonts, tools, RPMs
    and documents are being gathered under one site. So try the
    resources at 
    <ulink url="http://tamil.homelinux.org"></ulink>
    before you embark on treasure-hunting.</para>
  </sect1>

<!-- Fonts {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Fonts</title>

    <para>It can seem like anarchy. There are an unknown number of fonts, each
    encoded with their own tables, driven by arbitrary keyboard
    layouts and outputs. In my opinion, Tamil can seriously compete
    with any other language for maximum number of font tables.
    Added to this commotion are the dynamic fonts for the web
    pages, that enable anyone to get away with a non-standard font
    as long as his pages are viewable.</para>

    <para>Adding to all these is the official Indian Standard Code
    for Information Interchange (ISCII), the Government of India
    sponsored <quote>unifying</quote> 
    scheme to bring all Indian fonts under the Devanagari umbrella.
    Anyone familiar with the way the characters are written in
    Tamil and in Devanagari script will understand the lack of any
    rationale in this approach.</para>

    <para>Needless to say, this is serving to only add to the
    confusion. A good analysis of this and the unicode for Tamil is
    once again written by Sivaraj and can be found at 
    <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/people/sivaraj/tamil_unicode.html">
    </ulink>. For those not familiar with the Tamil script, a good
    introduction written by Sivaraj is at 
    <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/people/sivaraj/write-tamil.html">
    </ulink>.</para>
    
    <para>Let us ignore the anarchy for a moment and get a picture
    of the frequently used font encodings. There are two main
    contenders and luckily they will converge soon. The first and
    most popular one is the Tamil Standard Code for Information
    Interchange (TSCII), developed by volunteers throughout the world,
    and the other, TAmil Monolingual (TAM), and TAmil Bilingual
    (TAB) encodings, were proposed by the Tamil Nadu Government. Once
    again, TAM is of limited use in an OS environment and we can
    safely ignore that. Almost all Linux efforts are in TSCII
    (Console, KDE, GNOME localizations).</para>

<!-- TSCII {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>TSCII</title>

      <para>TSCII is a glyph-based, 8-bit bilingual encoding. It
      uses a unique set of glyphs; the usual lower ASCII set.
      Roman letters with standard punctuation marks occupy the
      first 128 slots and the Tamil glyphs occupy the 
      <emphasis>upper ASCII</emphasis> 
      segment (slots 128-256). A good overview of the early font
      encoding schemes and a the rationale behind the TSCII
      approach can be found at
      <ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/Athens/5180/tscii.html"></ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>The home URL for TSCII volunteers is
      <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/tscii"></ulink>. 
      This site discusses the TSCII
      encoding and provides tools including fonts, keyboard
      drivers, editors and inter-conversion tools for various
      platforms. The font encoding table according to TSCII-1.6 can be
      found at <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/tscii/charset16.gif"></ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>The current version of TSCII is 1.6, and a revision is
      expected anytime now that will fix some anomalies in using
      various slots for encoding. This version 1.7 will be fully
      backward compatible with 1.6 and is expected to gain
      popularity. The <ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/tscii">
      TSCII discussion group</ulink> currently brainstorms on
      modifications to TSCII-1.6. You may be able to participate in
      the discussions by becoming a member. You may also be
      able to download various beta tools from there. The font encoding
      table according to TSCII-1.7 (draft) can be found at
      <ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/tscii/files/charset17_a.gif">
      </ulink>.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- TAB {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>TAB</title>

      <para>TAB is a character based bilingual standard proposed by
      the government of Tamil Nadu. The TAB bilingual encoding table can be
      found at <ulink url="http://www.tamilnet99.org/annex4.htm"></ulink>. 
      Tools for TAB encoding (mostly restricted to the Windows 
      platform) can also be downloaded in the vicinity of this page.
      </para>
    </sect2>

<!-- Misc Fonts {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Miscellaneous fonts and encodings</title>
<para> 
There are too many types, and unfortunately they are not documented well. 
It is beyond the scope of this document to discuss them.       
</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!-- Console Tamil {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Console Tamil</title>
    
    <para>This so far has been a one man effort - once again by
    Sivaraj. He has written a set of console tools for Tamil that
    include a monospace font, keyboard driver and locale setup. In
    his words:</para> 
    <blockquote>
	<attribution>Sivaraj</attribution>
	<para>You can use it with Lynx to read any TSCII-based
    web sites or Pico to email in TSCII. Some characters may be disoriented,
    since I try to fit all the characters in an
    8x16 cell. But it is still readable. 
    </para></blockquote>

    <para>The tools can be downloaded <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/people/sivaraj/">here</ulink>. Follow the instructions in the REAME file to install and use.</para>
  </sect1>
  
<!-- X Window {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>X Window</title>

    <para>Welcome! This is where you will find the most useful
    tools for Tamil. Even for basic users, it is now possible to
    have close to a total Tamil-localized office suite. 
    Tamil GUI is achieved in KDE or GNOME environment with localization 
    settings (more about this later in this document), and Tamil character 
    input is achieved using keymanager programs. But first you need to get 
    some fonts to do all this.</para>

<!-- Installing fonts {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Installing fonts</title>

      <para>Linux, by default, uses <quote>pcf</quote> fonts and one can also 
      use <quote>bsd</quote> fonts; these are bitmapped fonts that display 
      under X and can be printed. But, as is common with all bitmapped
      fonts, these are not always <acronym>WYSIWYG</acronym> in print. For 
      high-quality printing you need <quote>Type-I</quote> fonts (Adobe), with
      Ghostscript you need PS fonts and for <quote>afm</quote> fonts (American
      Font metrics) are used. But most of the Tamil fonts
      that are freely available are TrueType (ttf). We will see next 
      how to get all these fonts working.</para>
    </sect2>
    
<!-- Bitmapped fonts {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Bitmapped fonts</title>

      <para>A bitmapped font is a matrix of dots; because of this,
      these fonts are device-independent. A 75 dpi font, which is
      good enough for displaying, is still a 75 dpi font in your
      1200 dpi printer. So usually bitmapped fonts are created for
      a specific purpose, such as for displaying on a monitor or for
      printing. Linux usually uses <varname>bdf</varname> or 
      <varname>pcf</varname> font for console or X
      display. Fonts like those created by <application>dvips</application> 
      or <application>dvi</application> are
      printer-related bitmapped fonts. These fonts occupy large sizes, but
      programs circumvent this by dynamically creating them as
      and when they are needed, and at a specific resolution.</para>
      
      <para>You can get bitmapped Tamil fonts for various
      applications from: 
      <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/tscii/tsciitools/tsciifonts.tar.Z">
      </ulink></para>

      <para>When an application makes a font request to the X Server,
      XFree86 looks for fonts in specific directories. This means
      that when you add fonts to your system and you want them to
      be recognized by X Server, you need to tell X about the
      location of these fonts. Simply add a directory to
      your font path with the commands:</para>

      <para><screen>
      mkfontdir
      xset fp+ &lt;directory&gt;
      </screen></para>

      <para>where the family directory is the name of the directory
      where you have fonts. Once you have done this you have to ask
      the server to get this registered for the session, with the
      command</para>

      <para><command>xset fp rehash</command></para>

      <para> Since you will want these commands to run automatically, you should put them in your <filename>.xinitrc </filename> file ( or possibly your <filename>.Xclients</filename>  or <filename>.xsession</filename> file -- this depends on how you start X. Another way to have the commands set automatically is edit <filename>XF86Config</filename>. For example, to add <command> /usr/share/fonts/myfonts </command> to the font path when X is started, edit <filename>XF86Config</filename> like this:</para>

<para> <screen>
	...
	Section "Files"
	...
	FontPath /usr/share/fonts/myfonts
	...
	EndSection
		...
</screen></para>

<para>The advantage of editing <filename> XF86Config </filename> is that the resulting changes are system wide.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- Truetype fonts {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>TrueType fonts</title>

      <para>You may get TrueType fonts for TSCII, TAB and
      TSCII1.7 encoding from the download section of 
      <ulink url="http://tamil.homelinux.org/"></ulink>. 
      Alternate sources for these fonts are</para>

      <para>TSCII - <ulink url="http://www.tamil.net/tscii/"></ulink>
      </para>

      <para>TAB - <ulink url="http://www.tamilnet99.org/"></ulink> and
      <ulink url="http://www.thinnai.com"></ulink></para>

      <para>TSCII-1.7 (experimental) - 
      <ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/tscii/files/"></ulink>
      </para>

      <para>Installing these fonts are either too easy or too
      difficult. Too easy if you have one of the latest
      distributions, like RedHat7.x or Mandrake7.x. This is because
      RedHat (and Mandrake, maybe SuSE) come with 
      <application>xfs</application> pre-packaged. It is also easy to find 
      <application>xfs</application> for Debian, but as far as I know, 
      Debian does not come with <application>xfs</application>
      packaged.</para>
      
      <para>Debian users are now redirected to this mini-howto on
      TrueType fonts in Debian -
      <ulink url="http://www.linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/mini/TT-Debian-3.html"></ulink>
      </para>
      
      <para>There is also another utility, <application>xfstt</application>, 
      which is easier to install and use, but <application>xfs</application> 
      is becoming popular as it can handle Adobe Type1 in addition to 
      TrueType fonts.
      </para>
      
      <para>If you do not have either of these, consider getting
      either <application>xfs</application> (not to be confused with 
      Silicon Graphics (SGI) sponsored XFS journaling file system) from
      <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org"></ulink>.</para>

      <para>or <application>xfstt</application> from
      <ulink url="http://www.dcs.ed.ac.uk/home/jec/programs/xfsft/"></ulink>. 
      You may also get <application>xfstt</application> binaries from 
      <ulink url="http://independence.seul.org/"></ulink>,
      or reading an article about <application>xfstt</application> in the 
      Linux Gazette at 
      <ulink url="http://www.linuxgazette.com/issue28/ayers1.html">
      </ulink></para>
      
      <sect3>
        <title>Installing TrueType Fonts</title>

        <para>You need to run these commands as root. If you are currently
        logged in as a normal user, you can use <command>su</command> to
        do this now.</para>
	
        <para>You should now have <application>xfs</application> availability, 
        otherwise use the steps in the previous section to obtain it.</para>

        <para>In some distributions like Mandrake, installing
        TrueType fonts is a cakewalk. Just go to <emphasis>DrakConf</emphasis>
        and use the font install utility - follow a few easy steps there and 
        you'll have them all.</para>

        <para>Put your TrueType fonts in whatever directory you want. For 
        example, <filename class="directory">/usr/share/tamiltt</filename>.
	</para>
	
        <para>From within the directory containing your
        new fonts, type:</para>

        <para><command>ttmkfdir -m 50 -o fonts.scale</command></para>

        <para>This makes a file that will contain the necessary
        information about the fonts for the xfs server. The option
        <option>-m 50</option> specifies the magnification for the fonts; 
        I have seen some Tamil fonts working well only with 
        <option>-m 100</option>.</para>
	
        <para>Then type:</para>

        <para><command>mkfontdir</command></para>

        <para>Now you can add the new directory to your 
        <application>xfs</application> search
        path. Red Hat (and Red Hat-like) distributions come with a
        neat utility to do this called <command>chkfontpath</command>. 
	Run chkfontpath like this:</para>

        <para><command>chkfontpath --add /usr/share/tamiltt</command></para>

        <para>This will add the new font directory to your font
        path.</para>

        <para>(Other users, who have an <application>xfs</application> font 
        server, without <varname>ttf</varname> support, can do this by 
        editing their <application>xfs</application> configuration
        file.</para>
	
        <para>If <application>xfs</application> is already installed on 
        your system, you should see which port it is running on. You can 
        do this with the following command:</para>
	
        <para><command>ps ax grep xfs</command></para>

        <para>Then check your XFree86 font path with this
        command:</para>

        <para><command>xset -q</command></para>

        <para>If your font path includes something like <quote>unix:/port
        number,</quote> where port number is the port on which the server
        is running, then you already have <application>xfs</application> 
        set up properly. Otherwise, you should add it to your XFree86 
        font path with these commands:</para>

        <para><command>xset fp+ &lt;unix/:port number&gt;</command></para>

        <para><command>xset fp rehash</command></para>

        <note>
	  <para>The port number is a numerical value, something like
        7100.</para>
	</note>
	
        <para>You can add the fontpath permanently by editing your
        <filename>.xinitrc</filename>. To add it system-wide, 
        edit your XF86Config file (either under 
        <filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config</filename>, 
        <filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config-4</filename>,
        <filename>/etc/XF86Config</filename>, or 
        <filename>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/XF86Config</filename>), by
        adding the following line to the <varname>Files</varname> section:
        </para>
	
        <para><command>FontPath &quot;unix/:port number&quot;
	</command></para>

        <para>Here is an example of how it should look:</para>

	<screen>
        ...
        Section Files
        ...
        
        FontPath &quot;unix/:-1&quot;
        ...
        EndSection
        ...
	</screen>      

        <para>If <application>xfs</application> is already properly installed, 
        then you can restart it like this as root:</para>

        <para><command>service xfs restart</command></para>

        <para>After restarting <application>xfs</application>, it is a good 
        idea to restart your X session.</para>

        <para>As most of the users in Tamil will be doing this, let
        me summarize the essential steps.</para>

       <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
        <para>Become root.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>Download and copy some <varname>ttf</varname> fonts into a 
        directory (say <filename class="directory">/usr/share/fonts/tamiltt
        </filename>).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>Go to that directory and do a 
        <command>ttmkfdir -m 50 -o fonts.scale</command> (use the 
        <option>-m 100</option> option if your fonts do not budge).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>Do a <command>mkfontdir .</command>  
	 (Notice that you need to specify the
        directory either absolutely or with a dot).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>Do a <command>chkfontpath --add /usr/share/fonts/tamiltt
	</command>.
        (Remember this command is available only in Red Hat-like
        distributions. If you can run this successfully, skip the
        remaining steps and restart the X server).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>Do <command>ps ax | grep xfs</command> and get 
	the <application>xfs</application> port known.</para>
	</listitem>
	  
	<listitem>
        <para>Check your font path: <command>xset -q</command></para>

        <para>If your font path includes something like <quote>unix:/port
        number</quote>, (something like <quote>unix: 7100</quote>), add this 
        to your xfont path:</para>

        <para><command>xset fp+ unix: port number</command></para>

        <para><command>xset fp rehash</command></para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>It is a good idea to restart the X Server.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>If everything works fine, update your 
	<filename>.xinitrc</filename> file, wherever it is.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
        <para>Have fun!</para>
	</listitem>
       </orderedlist>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>

<!-- Other font servers {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Other Font Servers</title>

      <para>There is another project, X-TrueType Server, worth
      looking into, at <ulink url="http://www.io.com/~kazushi/xtt/"></ulink>.</para>

      <para>Another interesting project with broader scope is
      FreeType; check <ulink url="http://www.freetype.org"></ulink>.</para>

      <para>I personally feel <application>xfs</application> is a great 
      utility; it can handle Type1 fonts (very useful if you use programs 
      like GIMP).  Besides, a stand alone <application>xfs</application> 
      server is not attached to X server.
      This means that you can deliver these fonts for remote X
      displays. I use this feature extensively with VNC Server
      running in my host and VNC Viewer running locally in Windows. 
      It's something of a luxury having a Tamil Linux desktop
      while working for my employer.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!-- Keyboard Drivers {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Keyboard Drivers</title>

    <para>Once again, lack of standards shows up here. There are
    quite a few Tamil keyboard layouts, the traditional typewriter
    keyboard; then with the surge of internet arrived the romanized
    transliteration keyboards; later the TAmil-Nadu government played
    its part by prescribing a tamilnet99 keyboard. These are only a
    few to talk about; we have a few others which do not fall into any
    of these <quote>standards.</quote></para>

    <para>There are two Tamil keyboard drivers for the X Window System, 
    both of them set to tamilnet99 standards (see 
    <ulink url="http://www.tamilnet99.org">tamilnet99 website</ulink> 
    for the details on the keymap). You will be able to download
    both the keydrivers from the
    <ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/tamilinix/files">
      Yahoo! tamilinix group files section
    </ulink>.</para>

<!-- tamil_kmap {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>tamil_kmap</title>

      <para>The first driver is <emphasis>tamil_kmap</emphasis>,
      created by Vasee. It is based on the original version of
      Siva. It is operable under both TSCII 1.6 and TAB encodings.
      The detailed installation instructions are given in the
      <filename>README</filename> file in the package. It is very 
      simple to install. First, untar the package into a temporary directory. 
      Then type:</para>

      <para>
        <command>cp ta /usr/X11R6/lib/X11/xkb/symbols/</command>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        then: <command>cp Compose /usr/X11R6/lib/X11/locale/iso8859-1</command>
      </para>

      <para>and put the shell script <filename>setkb</filename> 
      into a directory on your system <envar>PATH</envar> . 
      You may need to become <command>root</command> 
      to copy these files into these directories.</para>

      <para>To use the Tamil keyboard, type 
      <command>setkb tscii</command> or <command>setkb tab</command>. 
      From inside the keyboard driver you will be able to switch
      between the two standards, and also between Roman and Tamil
      fonts.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- tamilvp {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>tamilvp</title>

      <para>The other keyboard driver, <emphasis>tamilvp</emphasis>
      (vp for Visaip Palakai) is written and maintained by
      Dinesh. As indicated above, you may download that from the
      <citetitle>Yahoo! tamilinix group</citetitle> file section. 
      It is available as rpm (I have not tried it out yet). Just install 
      the rpm and files will be in appropriate locations. To run the 
      program type <command>tamilvp</command> and you will get the GUI 
      cell to choose between Tamil (TSCII 1.6 or TAB) and English.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!-- KDE {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>KDE</title>

    <para>Historically, the K Desktop Environment (KDE) was the first
    full Tamil user interface. Though far from complete, KDE was
    there for Tamil, and Tamil among the Indic languages, for the first time. 
    Under KDE, with your localization properly set to Tamil, you may be 
    able to do almost everything (from editing files, to browsing the web 
    and e-mail, to administrative tasks such as user management and task
    scheduling) with a Tamil user interface.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Getting Localization Files</title>

      <para>For the newbie, it is very easy to search the web for
      Tamil KDE localizations RPMs. They are usually labelled
      something like <filename>kde-i18n-Tamil-2.0-1mdk.i586.rpm</filename>.
      <varname>i18n</varname> is just that: i(nternationalizatio)n, 
      18(18letters).  <varname>Tamil</varname> is the
      localization setting corresponding to the Tamil language.
      <varname>mdk</varname> signifies the package for Mandrake distribution. 
      Then comes the most important part; <varname>2.0-1</varname>, 
      the KDE version number. Your base KDE version and this should be 
      the same, so when downloading, make sure that you get the proper 
      localized menus for the proper KDE version. <varname>i586</varname> 
      signifies the precompiled binaries for the intel 586 platforms. Make sure
      that you get the proper binary (there are usually source rpms
      and rpms for other platforms such as alpha). If you are a
      newbie you are better off using GUI based rpm installer such
      as GNORPM or KPackage. First do a test install and check if
      your system has all the needed packages. If not go to the
      same source from where you downloaded the Tamil localization
      and get them. After making sure that you installed all
      dependencies, install the kde-i18n-tamil package as
      well.</para>

      <para>If you are not a newbie, you know it. Get KDE Tamil
      i18n files, and if you have time, get the sources and compile
      them!</para>

      <para>KDE localization uses TSCII 1.6 encoding. This means
      that you will need at least one TSCII font. Read the section
      on fonts as to how to get it.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- Choosing a Tamil locale {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Choosing a Tamil locale</title>

      <para>This section assumes that have installed at least one
      TSCII font (preferably several, to jazz up your GUI) and the KDE
      Tamil localization package.</para>

      <para>From <guibutton>Start</guibutton>, go to 
      <guimenu>configuration</guimenu> &gt;
      <guisubmenu>KDE</guisubmenu> &gt; 
      <guimenuitem>Personalization</guimenuitem> and choose 
      <guibutton>default</guibutton> (c) location. 

      <note>
	  <para>Tamil/India is yet to be made available under 
          countries/languages.</para>
      </note>

      <guimenu>Choose language</guimenu> &gt;<guisubmenu>other</guisubmenu>
      &gt;<guimenuitem>Tamil</guimenuitem>. Accept this. All
      changes will be activated, and will work on all windows opened
      subsequently.</para>

      <para>Your user interface is now set in Tamil. If you see
      some garbage on the window header etc., pat yourself on the back. You
      are ready to see Tamil; move on!</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- Choosing Tamil fonts for GUI {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Choosing Tamil fonts for GUI</title>

      <para>Again, from <guibutton>Start</guibutton> go to 
      <guimenu>configuration</guimenu> &gt;<guisubmenu>KDE</guisubmenu> 
      &gt;<guimenuitem>LooknFeel</guimenuitem>. You will see a set of 
      fonts for most (these are the ones used in display). Choose a Tamil 
      font instead for all these. Accept.</para>

      <para>Well done, you now see Tamil everywhere on your
      desktop. You are ready, with a fully operational Tamil
      system.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- KDE-Miscellaneous {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>KDE Miscellaneous</title>

      <para>As with every other project, KDE-Tamil also needs a lot of
      volunteers. Contact either Sivakumar or Vaseeharan (both of
      them can be reached through the egroup</para>

      <para> Visit <ulink url="http://groups.yahoogroups.com/groups/tamilinix">
      </ulink> before you try KDE Tamil. If you want to convince yourself (and 
      be bowled over), view the screenshots from tamillinux.org site.</para>
      
      <para>KDE's i18n process is unicode-based. As a work around,
      Trolltech's QTsciiCodec class provides conversion to and from
      the Tamil TSCII encoding. This codec uses the mapping table
      found at <ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/Athens/5180/tsciiset.html">
      </ulink>. Unfortunately Tamil uses composed Unicode. As such, Unicode
      fonts cannot be used under KDE-TSCII; you need to have TSCII
      fonts. The TSCII codec was contributed to Qt by Hans Petter
      Bieker <email>bieker@kde.org</email>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
<!-- GNOME {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>GNOME</title>

    <para>GNOME Tamil localization works have just begun. There are
    few applications for which Tamil menus are translated, and are
    available. But it is yet to become the official member of GNOME
    i18n distribution.</para> 

    <para>In order to use them, download the currently available files 
    from:</para>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.tamillinux.org/gnome/gnome.html"></ulink>
    </para>

    <para>and put them into the directory 
    <filename class="directory">/usr/share/locale/ta/LCMESSAGES/</filename>.
    </para>
    
    <para>Under GNOME Control Panel you have set the fonts (both in
    Themes and the Window Manger applet) to a TSCII font.</para>

    <para>You need to create binary messages from the <varname>po</varname> 
    files.  This is done as follows:</para>

    <para>
    <command>msgfmt xxx.po -o /usr/share/locale/ta/LCMESSAGES/xxx.mo</command>.
    </para>

    <para>Note that the binary messages files contain an extension <filename>.mo</filename>
as opposed to <filename>.po</filename> for the text file.</para>

    <para>In order for you see Tamil, you have to set the locale to
    Tamil.</para>

    <para>If you are using bash as your shell, then enter the
    following line in your home directory.</para>

    <para><screen>
    export LANG=ta
    export LANGUAGE=ta
    export LC ALL=ta
    </screen></para>

    <para>Restart the X server. You should see Tamil menus and
    dialogs in many of the GNOME enabled applications. Once again,
    please consider contributing to the Tamil GNOME Project; we need a
    lot of volunteers. Contact Dinesh <email>(n_dinesh@yahoo.com)</email> or through tamilinix yahoogroups.</para>

    <para>
    </para>
  </sect1>

<!-- Printing {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Printing</title>

    <para>This section is all about getting high-quality Tamil
    output in printing. While it is one issue to load a binary font
    and start using Tamil in Linux, if your work is
    to destroy the forests, you need high-quality printing too!</para>

<!-- LATEX {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>L<superscript>A</superscript>T<subscript>E</subscript>X</title>

      <para>L<superscript>A</superscript>T<subscript>E</subscript>X 
      is perhaps the mother of all typographic systems. It frees the
      author from the trivia of typesetting and concentrate on
      the content. It does not use the <acronym>WYSWYG</acronym> input, 
      but the end result is great. Recent developments are centered
      toward internationalization. Unfortunately lack of unicode
      standard does not permit Tamil to be tried under the more
      ambitious Omega Project. Once again, workaround is the only
      way. A first step in Tamil has been attempted by Thuraiappah
      Vaseeharan. You may get the the package from the tamillinux.org
      site. The tar ball contains a great <filename>readme</filename> file that
      describes the installation and usage. The tamiltex package
      does a short work by keeping all related stuff under one
      directory (which means that you need to keep your work under
      the same directory to compile your source files). But the great
      thing about this package is that it is compatible with both
      TSCII and TAB encodings and the results are just what you
      would expect from a 
      L<superscript>A</superscript>T<subscript>E</subscript>X 
      package - great!</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- Postscript {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>Postscript</title>

      <para>Many Linux applications use Ghostscript to print, which
      means that you must have Ghostscript configured if you want
      to use Tamil in printed documents. If 
      L<superscript>A</superscript>T<subscript>E</subscript>X
      is there, can PostScript be far away? Not thanks to Vasee. 
      Set the environment variable <envar>GS_FONTPATH</envar> to point 
      to your TrueType font directory. For example, I have:</para>
      
      <para><screen>
      GS_FONTPATH=/usr/local/share/fonts/tamiltt
      export GS FONTPATH
      </screen></para>

      <para>You should be able to view Tamil PostScript files.</para>
    </sect2>

<!-- PDF {{{2 -->
    <sect2>
      <title>PDF</title>

      <para>As of now, the only source to create PDF files is the
      PDF package. If you are able to successfully compile your
      source with the tamiltex package, use</para>
 
      <para><command>pdflatex source.tex </command></para>

      <para>to generate the PDF file. You should be able to view it, using
      <application>xdvi</application> or Adobe's Acroread for Linux.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
<!-- Word Processors, Office Packages {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Word Processors, Office Packages</title>

    <para>Once TrueType fonts are installed properly, there is no
    problem using them in Abiword, GNumeric or KOffice. However,
    StarOffice needs Type 1 fonts. (I hear the latest StarOffice
    supports TrueType fonts?). You can expect Type 1 Tamil fonts to
    be available shortly:-).</para>

    <para>For receiving and sending email, KMail works well with
    TrueType fonts. You should also be able to use PINE with
    Sivaraj's console fonts and utils.</para>
  </sect1>

<!-- Viewing Web pages {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Viewing Web pages</title>

    <para>Konquerer supports Tamil fonts neatly, once made at the
    proper scale under your font directory and served to X. Widely
    used Netscape, however, is a problem. Netscape uses only 75 dpi
    fonts for display. You might have noticed this even while
    viewing Roman fonts, and got annoyed seeing small fonts. That
    being the case with Roman, Tamil is impossible to comprehend
    under 75 dpi. This can, however, be fixed by specifying the
    appropriate resources in your <filename>.Xdefaults</filename> file:</para>

    <para><screen>
    Netscape*documentFonts.sizeIncrement: 20
    Netscape*documentFonts.xResolution*iso-8859-1: 150
    Netscape*documentFonts.yResolution.iso-8859-1: 150
    </screen></para>

    <para>Remember that TSCII fonts are used as ISO-8859-1 fonts.
    The parameter <parameter>150</parameter> is arbitrary; I have seen 
    some fonts scaling neatly under <parameter>100</parameter> itself 
    (TSCparanar, for one) which is good enough for viewing. If you are 
    still not satisfied with what you see, try using anti-aliasing under 
    X.</para>
  </sect1>

<!-- Pango {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Pango</title>

    <para>
    <ulink url="http://www.pango.org">Pango</ulink>
    provides an open-source framework for the layout and rendering
    of internationalized text and uses Unicode for all of its
    encoding. It aims to eventually support output in all the major
    languages. When GNOME 2.0 comes out, the text rendering is
    expected to be by Pango. Pango is expected to be the panacea
    for complex font schemes like kanji, arabic/hebrew
    (bidirectional), so Tamil is no problem. Tamil is one of the
    early languages in Pango - right there in the first public
    version. Sivaraj provided TSCII support, which was later
    extended to TAB by Vikram.</para>
  </sect1>

<!-- Miscellaneous {{{1 -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>

    <para>For the latest news, views and tools in Tamil Linux:</para>
    <para><ulink url="http://tamil.homelinux.org/"></ulink></para>
    
    <para>Issues related to Tamil localization are mostly discussed
    at:</para>

    <para><ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/tamilinix/"></ulink>
    </para> 
    
    <para>Under the files section there you may get some tools, few HOWTOs 
    (most of those issues are unified in this document already) and some
    tutorials.</para>

    <para>If you want to read about Open Source (Free Software) history in 
    Tamil, see:</para>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.tamillinux.org/venkat/cover.html"></ulink>
    </para>

    <para>Ganesan Rajagopal is checking in CVS for Tamil locales
    under the Sourceforge project on Tamil Linux, you may be get
    them from:</para>

    <para>
    <ulink url="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/tamillinux/locale-ta/"></ulink>
    </para>

    <para>There is a simple guide to setting up a working Tamil
    Linux environment, addressed to newbies, available at:</para>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.tamillinux.org/venkat/tamil_inst.html"></ulink></para>
  </sect1>

<!-- Appendix: Font Encoding {{{1 -->
  <appendix>
    <title>Appendix of Tamil Font Encodings</title>

    <para>There are several non-standard font encoding schemes for
    Tamil. Then there are a whole lot of fonts (used mostly by
    publishing houses in Tamil Nadu, such as Vikatan, Kumutham,
    thinamaNi, etc.) which do not comply with any of these. The
    three major font encoding schemes are;</para>

    <para>TSCII (Tamil Standard Code of Information Interchange -
    currently running in beta version 1.7); the first efforts by
    volunteers throughout world.</para>

    <para>TAB (TAmil Bilingual); proposed and approved by the Tamil
    Nadu government</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced">

TSCII 1.6 Encoding Table 

vowels: a, aa/A, i, ii/I, u, uu/U, e, ee/E, ai, o, oo/O, au, aq

consonants: k, ng, c, ny, t, N, th, n^, p, m, y, r, l, v, zh, L, R, n

---------------------------------------------------------
Position |  character name        | TSCII glyph
---------|------------------------|----------------------
Characters 0-127 are as in the  standard lower ASCII set
---------|------------------------|----------------------
128  80  | c128                   |  tamil numeral 0
129  81  | c129                   |  tamil numeral 1                
130  82  | baseline single quote  |  tamil numeral 2      
131  83  | florin                 |  tamil numeral 3  
132  84  | baseline double quote  |  tamil numeral 4   
133  85  | ellipsis               |  tamil numeral 5   
134  86  | dagger (single)        |  tamil numeral 6   
135  87  | dagger (double)        |  tamil numeral 7   
136  88  | circumflex             |  tamil numeral 8   
137  89  | per mil (thousand)     |  tamil numeral 9   
138  8A  | S caron                |  modifier for aa/A   
139  8B  | left single guillemet  |  modifier for I   
140  8C  | OE ligature            |  modifier for Ii/I    
141  8D  | c141                   |  modifier for u    
142  8E  | c142                   |  modifier for uu/U     
143  8F  | c143                   |  modifier for e    
144  90  | c144                   |  modifier for ee/E        
145  91  | open single quote      |  (left single guillemet)
146  92  | close single quote     |  (right single guillemet )
147  93  | open double quote      |  (left double guillemet)
148  94  | close double quote     |  (right double guillemet )
149  95  | bullet (large)         |  tamil numeral 10  
150  96  | en dash                |  tamil numeral 100   
151  97  | em dash                |  tamil numeral 1000   
152  98  | tilde                  |  modifier for ai  
153  99  | unregistered trademark |  tamil vowel a   
154  9A  | s caron                |  tamil vowel aa/A   
155  9B  | right single guillemet |  tamil vowel i
156  9C  |  oe ligature           |  tamil vowel ii/Ai   
157  9D  |  c157                  |  tamil vowel u  
158  9E  |  c158                  |  tamil vowel uu/U  
159  9F  |  Y diaeresis           |  tamil vowel e  
160  A0  |  non-breaking space    |  (vacant) 
161  A1  |  Spanish inverted !    |  tamil vowel ee/E  
162  A2  |  cents                 |  tamil vowel ai  
163  A3  |  pounds                |  tamil vowel o  
164  A4  |  intl. monetary symbol |  tamil vowel oo/O  
165  A5  |  yen                   |  tamil vowel au  
166  A6  |  broken bar            |  tamil vowel aq  
167  A7  |  section symbol        |  tamil uyirmei ka 
168  A8  |  diaeresis             |  tamil uyirmei nga  
169  A9  |  copyright             |    copyright
170  AA  |  feminine ordinal      |  tamil uyirmei ca 
171  AB  |  left double guillemet |  tamil uyirmei nya 
172  AC  |  logicalnot            |  tamil uyirmei ta 
173  AD  |  soft hyphen (minus)   |  tamil uyirmei Na 
174  AE  |  registered trademark  |  registered trademark
175  AF  |  macron                |  tamil uyirmei tha  
176  B0  |  ring (also degrees)   |  tamil uyirmei n^a 
177  B1  |  plus/minus            |  tamil uyirmei pa 
178  B2  |  superscript 2         |  tamil uyirmei ma 
179  B3  |  superscript 3         |  tamil uyirmei ya 
180  B4  |  acute                 |  tamil uyirmei ra
181  B5  |  micro symbol (or mu)  |  tamil uyirmei la 
182  B6  |  pilcrow (paragraph)   |  tamil uyirmei va
183  B7  |  bullet (small)        |  bullet (small)  
184  B8  |  cedilla               |  tamil uyirmei zha 
185  B9  |  superscript 1         |  tamil uyirmei La  
186  BA  |  masculine ordinal     |  tamil uyirmei Ra  
187  BB  | right double guillemet |  tamil uyirmei na  
188  BC  |  one-fourth            |  grantha letter ja 
189  BD  |  one-half              |  grantha letter sha 
190  BE  |  three-fourths         |  grantha letter sa 
191  BF  |  Spanish inverted ?    |  grantha letter ha
192  C0  |  A grave               |  grantha letter ksha
193  C1  |  A acute|              |  grantha letter sri 
194  C2  |  A circumflex          |  tamil uyirmei ti/di 
195  C3  |  A tilde               |  tamil uyirmei tii/dii  
196  C4  |  A diaeresis           |  tamil uyirmei ku 
197  C5  |  A ring                |  tamil uyirmei ngu 
198  C6  |  AE ligature           |  tamil uyirmei cu 
199  C7  |  C cedilla             |  tamil uyirmei nyu 
200  C8  |  E grave               |  tamil uyirmei tu
201  C9  |  E acute               |  tamil uyirmei Nu
202  CA  |  E circumflex          |  tamil uyirmei thu
203  CB  |  E diaeresis           |  tamil uyirmei n^u
204  CC  |  I grave               |  tamil uyirmei pu
205  CD  |  I acute               |  tamil uyirmei mu
206  CE  |  I circumflex          |  tamil uyirmei yu
207  CF  |  I diaeresis           |  tamil uyirmei ru
208  D0  |  Icelandic Eth         |  tamil uyirmei lu
209  D1  |  N tilde               |  tamil uyirmei vu  
210  D2  |  O grave               |  tamil uyirmei zhu 
211  D3  |  O acute               |  tamil uyirmei Lu 
212  D4  |  O circumflex          |  tamil uyirmei Ru 
213  D5  |  O tilde               |  tamil uyirmei nu  
214  D6  |  O diaeresis           |  tamil uyirmei kU  
215  D7  |  multiply symbol       |  tamil uyirmei ngU  
216  D8  |  O with oblique stroke |  tamil uyirmei cU    
217  D9  |  U grave               |  tamil uyirmei nyU  
218  DA  |  U acute               |  tamil uyirmei tU  
219  DB  |  U circumflex          |  tamil uyirmei NU  
220  DC  |  U diaeresis           |  tamil uyirmei thU  
221  DD  |  Y acute               |  tamil uyirmei n^U 
222  DE  |  Icelandic Thorn       |  tamil uyirmei pU 
223  DF  |  German sharp s        |  tamil uyirmei mU  
224  E0  |  a grave               |  tamil uyirmei yU 
225  E1  |  a acute               |  tamil uyirmei rU 
226  E2  |  a circumflex          |  tamil uyirmei lU   
227  E3  |  a tilde               |  tamil uyirmei vU 
228  E4  |  a diaeresis           |  tamil uyirmei zhU 
229  E5  |  a ring                |  tamil uyirmei LU 
230  E6  |  ae ligature           |  tamil uyirmei RU 
231  E7  |  c cedilla             |  tamil uyirmei nU 
232  E8  |  e grave               |  tamil vowel  k (ik) 
233  E9  |  e acute               |  tamil vowel  ng (ing)
234  EA  |  e circumflex          |  tamil vowel  c (ikc)
235  EB  |  e diaeresis           |  tamil vowel  ny (iny)
236  EC  |  i grave               |  tamil vowel  t (it)
237  ED  |  i acute               |  tamil vowel  N (iN)
238  EE  |  i circumflex          |  tamil vowel  th (ith)
239  EF  |  i diaeresis           |  tamil vowel  n (in^)
240  F0  |  Icelandic eth         |  tamil vowel  p (ip)
241  F1  |  n tilde               |  tamil vowel  m (im)     
242  F2  |  o grave               |  tamil vowel  y (i&lt;)     
243  F3  |  o acute               |  tamil vowel  r (ir) 
244  F4  |  o circumflex          |  tamil vowel  l (il)    
245  F5  |  o tilde               |  tamil vowel  v (iv)  
246  F6  |  o diaeresis           |  tamil vowel  zh (izh)     
247  F7  |  divide symbol         |  tamil vowel  L (iL)     
248  F8  |  o with oblique stroke |  tamil vowel  R (iR)       
249  F9  |  u grave               |  tamil vowel  n (in)   
250  FA  |  u acute               |  grantha vowel  j (ij)  
251  FB  |  u circumflex          |  grantha vowel  sh (ish)    
252  FC  |  u diaeresis           |  grantha vowel  s (is)     
253  FD  |  y acute               |  grantha vowel  h (ih)     
254  FE  |  Icelandic thorn       |  grantha vowel  ksh (iksh)       
255  FF  |  y diaeresis           |  (vacant)   
---------|------------------------|------------------------
    </literallayout>
    

  </appendix>
 </article>
