<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "docbook/docbookxx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY ldpsite       "http://www.tldp.org/">
<!ENTITY howto         "&ldpsite;HOWTO/">
<!ENTITY mini-howto    "&ldpsite;HOWTO/mini/">
<!ENTITY home          "http://www.catb.org/~esr/">
]>

<article id="index">
 <articleinfo>
  <title>The Unix Hardware Buyer HOWTO</title>

  <author>
     <firstname>Eric</firstname>
     <surname>Raymond</surname>
     <affiliation>
        <address>
           <email>esr@thyrsus.com</email>
        </address>
     </affiliation>
  </author>

  <abstract>
    <para>
This is your one-stop resource for information about how to buy and
configure generic PC hardware for cheap, powerful Unix systems.
    </para>
  </abstract>

   <revhistory id="revhistory">
      <revision>
         <revnumber>4.2</revnumber>
         <date>2010-04-11</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    DVD region-locking firmware is no longer an issue, 
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>4.1</revnumber>
         <date>2009-07-01</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    DTX failed.  Finally deprecate SCSI. 32-bit is dead.
	    Avoiding the printer-consumables trap.  Invasion of the netbooks.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>4.0</revnumber>
         <date>2007-11-02</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Major revisions by Jonathan Marsden on SATA, bus standards,
            DVDs and other topics, followed by a cleanup pass from me.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>3.3</revnumber>
         <date>2007-18-13</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Updated for 2007 conditions.  CRTs are dead. BTX is
	    dead. CD-ROMs are competely generic now. USB modems are
	    recommended.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>3.2</revnumber>
         <date>2004-10-28</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Fix and remove bad links.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>3.1</revnumber>
         <date>2004-08-03</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Sound cards don't matter any more.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>3.0</revnumber>
         <date>2004-02-21</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
            Power-protection stuff moved to UPS HOWTO.  DIMM memory is
	    gone.  Tape drives don't make sense any more.  Lots of the
	    theory from my "Ultimate Linux Box"
	    articles now lives here.
          </revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
         <revnumber>2.4</revnumber>
         <date>2003-02-22</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
            URL fixes.
          </revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
         <revnumber>2.3</revnumber>
         <date>2002-08-06</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Buying at the low end isn't a lose anymore.  I recommend
	    Athlons.  Nuked the section on video standards, EDID takes 
	    care of all that now.  Also removed the section on older
	    memory types.  And keyboards, as the "ergonomic" ones all
	    vanished along with the 1990s carpal-tunnel scare.
          </revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
         <revnumber>2.2</revnumber>
         <date>2002-08-05</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    New section on DVD drives.
          </revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
         <revnumber>2.1</revnumber>
         <date>2002-07-08</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Corrected Kingston URL.  Various small updates for the last
	    year.  This HOWTO is much more stable than it used to be.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
         <revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
         <date>2001-08-09</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
	    Major update. Revisions based on Ultimate Linux Box experience.
	    Caches are on-chip now.  DDS4 tape drives are here.
	    486 machines, CD caddies, and most non-DDS backup
	    technologies are gone.
          </revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
         <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
         <date>2001-06-13</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
            Mid-2001 update.
          </revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
         <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
         <date>2001-02-06</date>
         <authorinitials>esr</authorinitials>
          <revremark>
            Initial revision; but see the history in the introduction.
          </revremark>
      </revision>
   </revhistory>

<!--
This is the revision history for the old PC-Clone Unix Hardware Buyer's Guide:

 Nov 9  1994: We resume publication after a long hiatus.
 Dec 1  1994: More about Pentiums, laptops, and dual-bus boards.
 Dec 13 1994: Pre-Christmas roundup.
 Jun 29 1995: More about E-IDE and SCSI disks.
 Jul 22 1995: More about printers for Unix.
 Jan 20 1996: Major update, with new material on Trends in Disk Capacity,
                  Modems, CD-ROMs, and many other topics.
 Mar 7  1996: Major update: Buying a Large Monitor.  Also, new material
                  on backup hardware, modems, printers.
 Jun 26 1996: More on caches and SCSI vs. IDE.  Also a handy glossary
                  of RAM-packaging terms.
 Oct 16 1996: Major Fall '96 update.  New stuff on the bus wars, modems,
                  benchmarks, lots of other topics.
 Dec 2  1996: New material on tape drives.
 Dec 10 1996: Reorganized and rewrote the `How To Buy' section. 
 Dec 16 1996: Added material on GDI printers and a new `Links' section.
                  Also more on RAM, ATX boards, video, and sound
		  cards, 33.6 modems.
 Jan  8 1997: Minor update on ATX, printers, keyboards.
 Mar 12 1997: Minor update on multimedia.
 Apr 5  1997: Minor update on SCSI cables, Exabyte, keyboards.
 Aug 7  1997: Minor upgrade of power section.
 Aug 12 1997: Major update: new stuff on the processor market,
                  memory, disk drives.
 Sep 12 1997: More good links.
 Sep 18 1997: Minor update on modems, keyboards, overall system prices.
 Dec 14 1997: Minor update on SCSI drives, and more resource links.
 Apr 21 1998: General update.  Modem section still needs work.
 Jun 7  1998: More on modems: V.90, ADSL, K2, 56Flex.
 Jul 24 1998: More on DAT drives.  Retired the 486 section and QIC
                  material. Updated section on processors and motherboards.
 Aug 24 1998: New section on tuning your I/O subsystem.
 Aug 28 1998: More stuff on modems thanks to Frederic Joly.
 Sep 9  1998: Yet more on modems and I/O tuning.  Fax section
                  removed, apparently it was obsolete and incorrect. 
 Dec 20 1998: Christmas update, various small fixes.
 Jun 11 1999: V90 modems have taken over.
 Jun 18 1999: Major Summer 1999 update.  We're actually current now.
 Jun 23 1999: Minor update based on suggestions from Andrew Comech.
 Jun 26 1999: Minor update on How To Buy.
 Jul  9 1999: Added link to http://www.pc-disk.de/pcdisk.htm
                  humongous disk database.
 Nov  6 1999: Minor updates on power protection and video cards.
 Apr 12 2000: Added link to the Linux Hardware Database.
 Jul 27 2000: Major update.  AGP rules graphics now.  Lots of
                  stale stuff about older processors removed; those
		  machines are just boat anchors now...
-->

 </articleinfo>

<sect1 id="intro"><title>Introduction</title>

<sect2 id="purpose"><title>Purpose of this document</title>

<para>The purpose of this document is to give you the background
information you need to be a savvy buyer of Intel hardware for running
Unix.  It is aimed especially at hackers and others with the technical
skills and confidence to go to the Internet/mail-order channel, but
contains plenty of useful advice for people buying store-front
retail.</para>

<para>This document is maintained and periodically updated as a service to
the net by Eric S. Raymond, who began it for the very best self-interested
reason that he was in the market and didn't believe in plonking down
several grand without doing his homework first (no, I don't get paid for
this, though I have had a bunch of free software and hardware dumped on me
as a result of it!).  Corrections, updates, and all pertinent information
are welcomed at <ulink
url="mailto:esr@snark.thyrsus.com">esr@snark.thyrsus.com</ulink>.  The
editorial &laquo;we&rsquo; reflects the generous contributions of many
savvy Internetters.</para>

<para>If you email me questions that address gaps in the FAQ material,
you will probably get a reply that says <quote>Sorry, everything I know
about this topic is in the HOWTO</quote>.  If you find out the
<emphasis>answer</emphasis> to such a question, please share it with
me for the HOWTO, so everyone can benefit.</para>

<para>If you end up buying something based on information from this HOWTO,
please do yourself and the net a favor; make a point of telling the vendor
<quote>The HOWTO sent me</quote> or some equivalent.  If we can show
vendors that this HOWTO influences a lot of purchasing decisions, we get
leverage to change some things that need changing.</para>

<para>Note that in December 1996 I published an introductory article on
building and tuning Linux systems summarizing much of the material in this
HOWTO.  It's <ulink url="&home;writings/lj-howtobuild.html">available
here</ulink>.  In 2001 I published an article on building the <ulink
url="&home;/writings/ultimate-linux-box/">Ultimate Linux
Box</ulink>.</para>

<para>This Buyer's Guide actually dates back to 1992, when it was known as
the <quote>PC-Clone Unix Hardware Buyer's Guide</quote>; this was before Linux
took over my world :-).  Before that, portions of it were part of 
a Unix Buyer's Guide that I maintained back in the 1980s on USENET.</para>

<para>It may be a matter of historical interest that the page count of this
guide peaked in mid-2001 and has been declining since.  Video, sound, and
other functions are migrating onto motherboards.  Several bus types have
disappeared, as have all the old-school backup technologies that couldn't
scale up to match disk capacities, Spec sheets are getting
simpler. Accordingly, there are parts that used to have whole sections to
hemselves that I barely even write about anymore &mdash; mice, floppy disks,
CD-ROM drives, and keyboards, for example, are utterly generic now,</para>

<para>Another consequence of the technology stabilizing is also that I'm 
updating this guide less often than I used to.  Years can now go by without
the PC market changing in any fundamental way. </para>

<para>In retrospect, the success of the ATX standard for motherboards in
1998-1999 was probably the turning point. The PC industry has become
sufficiently commoditized that your choices are now getting simpler rather
than more complicated.  This is a Good Thing.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="newversions"><title>New versions of this document</title>

<para>New versions of the Unix Hardware Buyer HOWTO will be periodically be
uploaded to various Linux WWW and FTP sites, including the LDP home
page.</para>

<para>You can view the latest version of this on the World Wide Web via the
URL <ulink
url="&howto;Unix-Hardware-Buyer-HOWTO/">&howto;Unix-Hardware-Buyer-HOWTO/</ulink>.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="feedback"><title>Feedback and corrections</title>

<para>If you have questions or comments about this document, please
feel free to mail Eric S. Raymond, at <ulink
url="mailto:esr@thyrsus.com"> esr@thyrsus.com</ulink>. I welcome any
suggestions or criticisms.  If you find a mistake with this document,
please let me know so I can correct it in the next
version. Thanks.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="resources"><title>Related resources</title>

<para>You may also want to look at the read the <ulink
url="&howto;Hardware-HOWTO.html">Hardware-HOWTO</ulink>.  It lists hardware
known to be compatible with Linux, and hardware known to be
incompatible. I've also done a series of articles on <ulink
url="&home;/writings/ultimate-linux-box/">The Ultimate Linux
Box</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="overview"><title>Overview of the Market</title>

<para>The central fact about PC hardware is that de-facto hardware
standards have created a commodity market with low entry barriers, lots of
competitive pressure, and volume high enough to amortize a
<emphasis>lot</emphasis> of development on the cheap.</para>

<para>The result is that this hardware gives you lots of
bang-per-buck, and it's getting both cheaper and better all the time.
Furthermore, margins are thin enough that vendors have to be lean,
hungry, and <emphasis>very</emphasis> responsive to the market to
survive.</para>

<para>One good general piece of advice is that you should avoid 
the highest-end new-technology systems (those not yet shipping in
volume). The problem with the high end is that it usually
carries a hefty <quote>prestige</quote> price premium, and may be a bit less
reliable on average because the technology hasn't been through a lot
of test/improve cycles.</para>

<para>There used to be a real issue with low-end PCs as well,
because there used to be a lot of dodgy crap PC components out
there going into boxes made by vendors trying to save a few cents.
That's not really a problem anymore.  Market pressure has been 
very effective at raising reliability standards for even low-end 
components as the market has matured.  It's actually hard to go
wrong even buying at the bottom end of the market these days.</para>

<para>I put together the first version of this guide around 1992;
Unix-capable systems are now ten to twenty times cheaper than they were
then.  At today's prices, building your own system from parts no
longer makes much sense at all &mdash;so this HOWTO is now more oriented
towards helping you configure a whole system from a single vendor.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="basics"><title>Buying the Basics</title>

<para>In this section, we cover things to look out for that are more or less
independent of price-performance tradeoffs, part of your minimum system
for running Unix.</para>

<para>Issues like your choice of disk, processor, and I/O bus (where there is
a significant tradeoff between price and capability) are covered in the section
on <link linkend="optimize">What To Optimize</link>.</para>

<sect2><title>Things to Not Care About</title>

<para>An effect of PC commoditization is that there aren lots of things
you used to have to worry about that don't matter any more, because 
the market has completely flattened out.  We list these here to get them
out of the way.</para>

<sect3 id="buswars"><title>Bus Wars</title>

<para>The system bus is what ties all the parts of your machine together.
This is an area in which progress has simplified your choices a lot.  There
used to be no fewer than <emphasis>four</emphasis> competing bus standards
out there (ISA, EISA, VESA/VLB, PCI, and PCMCIA).  Now there are
effectively just <emphasis>two</emphasis> &mdash;PCI-X on servers, and PCIe
for desktop/tower machines. Even PCI is now legacy technology, and the
PCMCIA bus that seemed so important a few years back has been reduced to
near-irrelevance by Ethernet, USB, and WiFi hardware built onto
motherboards.  The newcomer is PCIe, which is (in late 2007) a
&lsquo;video-card-mostly&rsquo; bus, though it seems to be gaining in
popularity for other uses too on mainstream desktop motherboards, whereas
PCI-X is only found on higher end &lsquo;server&rsquo; motherboards.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="memory"><title>Memory</title>

<para>Judging the memory-controller and cache design used to be one of the
trickiest parts of evaluating a motherboard, but that stuff is all baked
into the processor itself now. This removed a large source of latency and
design variations.  It also killed off the plethora of different RAM
types that used to be out there.</para>

<para>Today's advice is very simple. Make sure the memory is rated for your
machine's bus speed, then buy as much as you can afford to stuff in your
machine.</para>

<note><para>DDR3 RAM is beginning to appear.  Right now its extra expense
over DDR2 is not worth paying, for all but extremely specialized needs.  It
is almost always <emphasis>far</emphasis> more useful to have 4GB of
reasonably fast RAM, than 2GB of very fast RAM, in your
machine.</para></note>

<para>For more technical stuff on memory architectures, see <ulink
url="http://www.kingston.com/tools/umg/default.asp">The Ultimate Memory
Guide</ulink> maintained by Kingston Technologies.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="mice"><title>Keyboards and Mice</title>

<para>Keyboards are mostly generic nowadays.  One useful piece of advice is
to not buy any desktop machine with <quote>Internet</quote> buttons on it;
this is a sure sign of a PC that's an overpriced glitzy toy. Nowadays
keyboards with a USB connector are the norm, rather than the older
dedicated connectors; modern open-source Unixes handle these
just fine.</para>

<para>Mice and trackballs used to be simple; then, thanks to Microsoft,
they got complicated. Now they're simple again. Again, USB mice have
replaced the older PS/2-style dedicated connector.  XFree86 autodetects
your mouse when it starts up, so configuration is not a big deal any
more.</para>

<para>Some PC vendors, being Windows-oriented, still bundle two-button
mice.  Thus, you may have to buy your own three-button (or two button and a
scroll wheel) mouse.  Ignore the adspeak about dpi and pick a mouse or
trackball that feels good to your hand.</para>

<para>Your humble editor really, really likes the Logitech TrackMarble, an
optical trackball that eliminates the chronic roller-fouling problems of
the older TrackMan.  They're well-supported by X, so any Linux or BSD will
accept them.</para>

</sect3>
<sect3 id="floppies"><title>Floppy Drives</title>

<para>There's no longer much to be said about floppy drives.  They're
cheap, they're generic, and the rise of CD-ROM and DVD-ROM drives as a
cheap distribution medium has made them much less important than formerly.
You only ever see the 3.5-inch &lsquo;hard-shell&rsquo; floppies with
1.44MB capacity anymore.</para>

<para>Bootable CD-ROMs killed off the last use of floppies, which was OS
installation.  So go ahead and settle for cheap Mitsumi and Teac floppy
drives.  There are no &lsquo;premium&rsquo; floppy drives anymore.  Nobody
bothers.</para>

<para>It's possible your system won't even include one. No loss.</para>

</sect3>
<sect3 id="cdrom"><title>CD-ROM Drives</title>

<para>Standard CD-ROMs hold about 650 megabytes of read-only data in a
format called ISO-9660 (formerly <quote>High Sierra</quote>).  All current
Unixes support these devices.  Unix and Linux software is now distributed
on ISO-9660 CD-ROM, a cheaper and better method than the QIC tapes we used
to use.</para>

<para>CD-ROM speed used to be a big deal; vendors advertised 2X, 4X, all
the way up to 52X.  Vendors don't bother any more; the drives are all about
equivalently fast now.</para>

<para>There are one or two minor features to watch for. Most CD-ROMS will
include a headphone jack so you can play audio CDs on them.  Better-quality
ones will also include two RCA jacks for use with speakers.  Another
feature to look for is a drive door or seal that protects the drive head
from dust.</para>

<para>Increasingly, DVD-ROM drives (and burners) are replacing CD-ROM drives
as the default optical drive in PC systems.  They have significantly larger
capacity, and will read (and burn) CD media too.  The cost difference now
is so small that it is usually preferable to buy a DVD burner instead of
a CD-ROM drive.</para>

</sect3>
<sect3 id="backup"><title>Backup devices</title>

<para>It's good to be able to make backups that you can separate from your
system and store off-site in case of disaster. Until about 2001, tape
drives still seemed like a good idea for personal systems, but I found I
seldom used mine.  Today, tape drives with high enough capacity to image
today's huge hard disks are too expensive to make sense any more.</para>

<para>For the money you'd spend on a high-capacity tape drive (over $1000)
it makes more sense to buy a laptop and a pile of CD-R or DVD-R or DVD+R
media. Sit the laptop on your house Ethernet when you're not traveling, and
back up the main machine to it every day, or oftener.  Between the
efficiency of rsync and the speed of 100-megabit Ethernet, this will be a
lot faster than making a tape.  Every once in a while, burn a set of backup
CD-ROMs or DVDROMs.</para>

<para>But CD-ROMs aren't reusable; the cost piles up over time.  An
interesting alternative is a small external USB hard drive, especially if
you can salvage an old laptop drive and put it in a USB enclosure.  These
enclosures are available for about $30; Google for "USB HD Enclosure". This
is faster than a tape, cheaper and lighter than a full laptop.  For faster
transfer speeds, an enclosure that accepts eSATA connections as well as USB
helps a lot (assuming your PC or notebook has an eSATA connector).</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="processor"><title>How To Pick Your Processor</title>

<para>Right now (early 2010), the chips to consider for running Unix are
the 64-bit AMD Opteron or its Intel equivalents, especially the Core 2
Duo.  We're long past the point at which 32-bit chips are interesting for
new desktop systems, presuming you could even find one. AMD and Intel built
up a buffer before switching their fabs fully to 64-bit chips in 2006, and
the 32-bit chips you can still find are coming out of warehouses rather
than off production lines.</para>

<para>Brands don't matter much, so don't feel you need to pay Intel's
premiums if you see an attractive Cyrix, AMD or other chip-clone
system offered.  In the last few years I've been a big fan of 
the AMD line. They used to be faster, cheaper, and better-designed than
Intel processors; today Intel has clawed back the speed advantage, but 
AMD chips still deliver more performance than you're likely to be able
to use and do it with lower power dissipation (thus, less noise and 
heat).</para>

<para>On the other hand, Intel-chip motherboards now have the advantage
that the on-board graphics chip will give you 3D acceleration with fully
open-source drivers. This will avoid the problems you would otherwise face
trying to select a supported graphics card from ATI or Nvidia.</para>

<para>Many CPUs now are multi-core &mdash; that is, they have multiple CPUs
on a single chip.  This is very useful for doing something compute
intensive (re-encoding video, compressing large archives, etc.) in the
background and still having a responsive system for other work at the same
time.  At current prices, a dual-core CPU makes good sense for most desktop
systems.  If you are building a server or have specialized computing needs
you expect to be very CPU-intensive quad-core is worth considering, but on
a desktop system all the two extra cores will usually do is emit heat.  Only
at the very low end (sub US$50 CPUs) do single-core CPUs still make sense
on desktop machines.</para>

<para>Mainstream desktop CPUs now use one of two sockets: LGA 775 (Intel)
and AM2 (AMD).  Buying a system that uses one of these stands more chance
of allowing a useful CPU upgrade to extend its useful life than systems
using other less common sockets.</para>

<para>Current CPUs are <emphasis>much</emphasis> faster than those of just
a few years ago.  As a result, unless your needs are highly specialized,
spending more than about US$200 on a desktop CPU is hard to justify.  For
most users, putting extra budget into more RAM or a faster disk subsystem
will most likely result in greater benefit.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id='twospindles'><title> One Disk or Two?</title>

<para>I usually build with two disks &mdash; one <quote>system</quote> disk
and one <quote>home</quote> disk.  There are two good reasons to do this
that have nothing to do with the extra capacity.  One of them is the
performance advantage of being able to interleave commands to different
physical spindles that we'll explain a bit later in the section on disks.
The other is that I am quite a bit less likely to lose two disks at once
than I am to trash a single one.</para>

<para>Let's suppose you have a fatal disk crash.  If you have only one
disk, goodbye Charlie.  If you have two, maybe the crashed one was your
system disk, in which case you can buy another and mess around with a new
Linux installation knowing your personal files are safe.  Or maybe it was
your home disk; in that case, you can still run and do recovery stuff and
basic Net communications until you can buy another home disk and restore it
from backups (you <emphasis>did</emphasis> keep backups, right?).</para>

<para>Given today's high capacity drives, another way to use two disks well
is to set them up as a RAID1 (mirrored) array.  This can be done in
software or with a hardware RAID controller.  This way if either of the two
drives fail, the system will continue to function, no data is lost, and
upon replacing the failed drive, the array can be rebuilt from the
remaining working drive.  Hard drives are consumable media, they
<emphasis>do</emphasis> fail, so this approach (as well as good backups) is
well worth considering.</para>

<para>Buy SATA. The older IDE and EIDE buses are now obsolete, and SCSI no
longer has enough of a cost advantage to justify the premium. In fact, SCSI
has effectively nerged into SCSI; SATA is SCSI commands being shipped over
a single-wire data line.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="cases"><title>Getting Down to Cases</title>

<para>I used to say that cases are just bent metal, and that it doesn't
much matter who makes those.  Unfortunately, this isn't true any more.
Processors run so hot these days that fans and airflow are a serious
concern. They need to be well designed for proper airflow
throughout. </para>

<para>Look for the following quality features:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Aluminum rather than steel.  It's lighter and conducts
heat better.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Unobstructed air intake with at least one fan each
(in addition to the power supply and processor fans)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>No sharp metal edges. You don't want to shred
your hands when you're tinkering with things.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>There shouldn't be any hot spots (poor air flow).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sturdy card clips.  Some poorly-designed cases allow cards 
to wiggle out of their slots under normal vibration.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Effective and easy to use mechanisms for attaching hard
drives, CD-ROM, CD-R/W, DVDs, etc.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>If you're fussy about RFI (Radio-Frequency Interference), it's worth
finding out whether the plastic parts of the case have conductive coating
on the inside; that will cut down emissions significantly, but a few cheap
cases omit it.</para>

<para>Should you buy a desktop or tower case?  Our advice is go with tower
unless you're building a no-expansions personal system and expect to be
using the floppies a lot.  Many vendors charge nothing extra for a tower
case, and the cost difference will be trivial even if they do.  What you
get for that is less desktop clutter, more and bigger bays for expansion,
and often (perhaps most importantly) a beefed-up power-supply and fan.
Putting the box and its fan under a table is good for maybe 5db off the
effective noise level, too.  Airflow is also an issue; if the peripheral
bays are less cramped, you get better cooling.  Be prepared to buy
extension cables for your keyboard and monitor, though; vendors almost
never include enough flex.</para>

<para>The airflow thing is a good argument for a full- or mid-tower rather
than the &lsquo;baby tower&rsquo; cases some vendors offer.  However, smaller
towers are getting more attractive as boards and devices shrink and
more functions migrate onto the motherboard.  A state of the art
system, with all 3&quot; disks, 300W power supply, half-size motherboard,
on-board SATA and 4GB of RAM sockets, and half-sized expansion cards,
will fit into a baby or midsized tower with ample room for expansion;
and the whole thing will fit under a desk and make less noise than a
classic tower.</para>

<para>For users with really heavy expandability requirements,
rackmount PC cases do exist (ask prospective vendors).  Typically a
rackmount case will have pretty much the same functionality as an
ordinary PC case.  But, you can then buy drive racks (complete with
power supply), etc. to expand into.  Also, you can buy passive
backplanes with up to 20 or so slots. You can either put a CPU card in
one of the slots, or connect it to an ordinary motherboard through one
of the slots.</para>

<para>Since USB has taken over most forms of detachable peripheral, a good
feature to look for in a case is USB ports mounted at the top forward edge
where it's easy to plug in digital cameras and the like.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="power"><title>Power Supplies and Fans</title>

<para>A lot of people treat power supplies as a commodity, so many
interchangeable silver bricks.  We know better &mdash; cheap power supplies
go bad, and when they go bad they have a nasty habit of taking out the
delicate electronics they're feeding.  Also, the power supply tends to be
the noisiest component in your system.</para>

<para>Give preference to supplies with a Underwriter's Laboratories rating.
There's some controversy over optimum wattage level.  On the one hand, you
want enough wattage for expansion.  On the other, big supplies are noisier,
and if you draw too little current for the rating the delivered voltage can
become unstable.  And the expected wattage load from peripherals is
dropping steadily.  On the other hand, processors and their cooling fans
eat a lot more power than they used to.</para>

<para>The choice is generally between 200W and 300W.  After some years of
deprecating 300W-and-up supplies as overkill, I'm now persuaded it's time
to go back to them; a modern processor can consume 50-75W by itself, and
for the newer dual-processor board the power supply needs to be rated 450W
or up.</para>

<para>Processors on modern motherboards run hot enough that all vendors
have gone to embedded temperature sensors and variable-speed
thermostat-controlled fans, out sheer self-defense (this used to be
a high-end only feature).</para>

<para>To cut noise, look for 120mm fans rather than the old-style 80mm
muffin fans.  These can move the same amount of air per minute rotating at a
lower tip speed, which means less vortex formation and less noise.  These
are now becoming standard even on cheap white-box hardware.</para>

<para>In garden-variety tower cases there often isn't enough airflow to
cool all components effectively with a single fan, even going at full
speed.  And the single fan in the power supply was basically designed to
cool the power supply, not the components in the case.  This is why
processors and some graphics cards have their own fans now.</para>

<para>A few years ago PCs often had two or more case fans in addition to
the power-supply fan.  This made sense in the era of 80mm fans and lots of
expansion cards obstructing the airflow, but it was noisy.  Nowadays, with
sound and graphics and Ethernet integrated onto motherboards, expansion
cards are much less common (and processors carry their own mini-fans).
Thus, today's standard is to mount one 120mm fan, usually low and forward
just beneath the disk-drive stack.  This is much quieter, like by a factor
of three or four.</para>

<para>The noise produced by a fan is not just a function of the speed with
which it turns.  It also depends on the nature of the airflow produced by
the fan blades and the bearings of the rotor. If the blades cause lots of
turbulent airflow, the fan produces lots of noise. One brand of fans that
is much more silent than most others even if going at full throttle is
<ulink url="http://www.papstplc.com/">Papst</ulink>.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="motherboards"><title>Motherboards</title>

<para>Provided you exercise a little prudence and stay out of the price
basement, motherboards and BIOS chips don't vary much in quality.  There
are only six or so major brands of motherboard inside all those cases and
they're pretty much interchangeable; brand premiums are low to nonexistent
and cost is strictly tied to maximum speed and bus type.  There are only
four major brands of BIOS chip (AMI, Phoenix, Mylex, Award) and not much to
choose between 'em but the look of the self-test screens (even the
<quote>name</quote> vendors use lightly customized versions of these).  One
advantage Unix buyers have is that Unixes are built not to rely on the BIOS
code (because it can't be used in protected mode without more pain than
than it's worth).  If your BIOS will boot properly, you're usually going to
be OK.</para>

<para>Some good features to look for in a motherboard include:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Gold-plated contacts in the expansion slots and RAM
sockets.  Base-metal contacts tend to grow an oxidation layer which
can cause intermittent connection faults that look like bad RAM chips
or boards.  (This is why, if your hardware starts flaking out, one of
the first things to do is jiggle or remove the boards and reseat them,
and press down on the RAM chips to reseat them as well &mdash;this may
break up the oxidation layer.  If this doesn't work, rubbing what
contacts you can reach with a soft eraser is a good fast way to remove
the oxidation film. Beware, some hard erasers, including many pencil
erasers, can strip off the plating, too!)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The board should be speed-rated as high as your
processor, of course.  It's good if it's rated higher, so upgrade to a
faster processor is just a matter of dropping in the chip and a new
crystal.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>(I used to have "Voltage, temperature and fan speed monitoring
hardware." on this list.  But processors run so hot nowadays that all
current motherboards have it.)</para>

<para>The dominant form factor is still ATX.  Intel tried to replace it
with a new standard called BTX in late 2004-2005, but failed; the proposal
was effectively withdrawn in 2006.  In January 2007 AMD announced a <ulink
url="http://www.dtxpc.org/">DTX</ulink> specification for small-form-factor
PCs; it seems also to have sunk without trace.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2><title>Monitor and Video</title>

<para>The largest user-visible change since the last major update of this
guide is that the CRT (cathode-ray tube) is dead.  The manufacturers shut
down their production lines in late 2004; the remaining CRTs out there are
old stock that's been sitting in warehouses.  The only reason to buy one
since then has been to get high-end resolution at a price lower than the
insanely expensive high-end flatscreens; with 1920x1440 flatscreens having
become generally available at reasonable prices even that
reason is gone.  It's all flatscreens now, baby.</para>

<para>On flatscreens, only two statistics matter; pixel size and response
time.  The biggest functional drawback of flatscreens relative to CRTs is
that they refresh more slowly, because cheical reactions in a flatscreen
pixel take longer than remodulating a flying electron beam.  You'll never
notice this during ordinary desktop use, but it can cause streakiness and
artifacts when you're playing games or viewing movies.  If you're going to
do that a lot, the price premium for a flatscreen with better response time
may be worth it.</para>

<para>Next, buy your card (if you have to; see next paragraph). This used
to be complicated, with issues like matching the video bandwidths of the
card and the CRT, and the amount of display memory.  Now (unless you are a
gamer or have similarly extreme 3D acceleration requirements) it's simple;
all cards have enough display memory for every resolution in use, and the
issues are software (does it have an open-source driver, and do you
care?)</para>

<para>It's actually fairly likely you'll never buy a video card again.
Very capable graphics chips are routinely integrated onto motherboards now;
unless you're a gamer or somebody else who absolutely must have the latest
wheeze in 3D acceleration, they'll be good enough.  Even this is not
a stable situation, as 3D acceleration is commoditizing too.</para>

<para>I used to carry a lot of material on different video standards,
interlacing, and flicker.  That stuff is all obsolete now.</para>

<para>Here's what to look for on the monitor spec sheet:</para>

<itemizedlist> <listitem><para>Screen size and format.  Usually measured in
diagonal inches.  Most displays are now in a <quote>widescreen</quote>
format (16:10 ratio of width:height) rather than the older 5:4 or 4:3
ratios common for CRTs and older flat panel screens.  A <quote>19
inch</quote> widescreen monitor generally has considerably fewer pixels
than a <quote>19 inch</quote> 5:4 ratio one. Unfortunately, this chane is
bad for pogrammers, as it tends to lose us the vertical pixel resolution we
want for editor windows.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Screen resolution.  1280x1024 is now low end on the
desktop.  Seventeen inch 1280x1024 screens are the bargain basement now,
many manufacturers have already switched production to 19 inch widescreen
1440x900 screens instead.  The cost difference between such screens and 20
inch 1680x1050 screens is very small, making the 20 inch screens a better
choice unless funds (or desktop space!) are very tight.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>5ms or lower response time.  3ms is better.  There is some
marketing-speak going on in the way the response time is specified (grey to
gray rather than black to white) but since most manufacturers do it this
way these times are usually comparable between different manufacturers
screens.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Does it have a tilt-and-swivel base?  Adequate
controls, including both horizontal and vertical size and horizontal
and vertical centering?  A color-temperature control is a plus; the last is
particularly important if you compose graphics on screen for hardcopy
from a printer.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>If you can, buy your monitor from someplace that will let you
see the same monitor (the very unit you will walk out the door with,
not a different or `demo' unit of the same model) that will be on your
system.  There's significant quality variation (even in "premium" monitor
brands) even among monitors of the same make and model.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="dvd"><title>DVD Drives</title>

<para>DVD drives have two main uses in computer systems: playback of video
DVDs, and use for data storage (either installation media or backups, or
even as a primary drive in a few specialized systems).</para>

<para>DVD video playback used to be problematic on Unix due to various
stupid copy-protection schemes in firmware, but they have long since
been cracked. These days, any SATA DVD will do fine.</para>

<para>DVD burners (drives that can read and write CDROM media as well as
several kinds of DVD media) are now low cost and useful. The SATA interface
has taken over here, too.  Linux and most current PC Unix-like systems will
work fine with either interface, which is good as most PCs now ship with
one.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="sound"><title>Sound Cards and Speakers</title>

<para>You can't buy a really bad sound card any more. Even low-end
sound cards or the sound chips embedded in a lot of PC motherboards 
these days support all these features:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>16-bit sampling (for 65536 dynamic levels rather
	than 256).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mono and stereo support.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Full-duplex mode.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sampling rate of 44.1KHz (CD-quality).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>MIDI interface via a standard 15-pin D-shell 
	connector.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RCA output jacks for headphones or speakers.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>A microphone jack for sound input.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>If you are interested in multi-track digital recording, two
particularly good choices are the M-Audio Delta, or RME Hammerfall series
of cards.  Decent (and lower cost!) two-channel cards for more normal use
are those using the ICE1712 (Envy24) and ICE1724 (Envy24HT) audio chips.
For normal users, though, the on-motherboard chips will work fine.</para>

<para>A rather comprehensive list of sound cards and chips supported by the
ALSA project, which is the main way sound cards are supported under Linux,
can be found at <ulink
url="http://www.alsa-project.org/main/index.php/Matrix:Main">ALSA Sound
Card Matrix</ulink>.</para>

<para>In speakers, look for a magnetically-shielded enclosure with volume,
bass and treble controls.  Some speakers run off the card's 4-watt signal;
others are <quote>self-powered</quote>, using batteries or a separate power
supply.  Your major buying choice is which one of these options to pursue.
Usually you'll want separately-powered speakers.  If appropriate for your
listening habits, a pair of decent headphones will get you better quality
sound for the money compared to speakers.</para>

<para>One final, important tip: that audio cable from your CD-ROM back to
the sound card is used only when you play audio CD-ROMs through your
speakers.  Software-generated sound goes through the system bus, so you can
play games with sound even if your sound board or motherboard won't accept
the audio cable connector.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="modems"><title>Modems</title>

<para>Demand for (dialup telephone) modems is dropping as more and more
people get broadband Internet through DSL and cable.  This section still
has as much detail as it does only because (a) there are people out beyond
the exurbs who can't get broadband, and (b) there are one or two remaining
traps for the unwary.</para>

<para>The modem market has stabilized and standardized. If you can spend
$59, get a U.S. Robotics V.92 USB external.  You can then know that you've
got the best and skip the rest of this section.  If you really must
economize, spend $39 for the internal-card version (but you'll probably
regret the $20 first time you have to do diagnostics).</para>

<note><para>If you live somewhere with <emphasis>really</emphasis> bad
telephone lines, the U.S. Robotics V.92 Business Modem may be truly "the
best" for your needs, though it is about four times the price of the
U.S. Robotics V.92 USB external, which is marketed for home use.  See the
<ulink url="http://www.usrobotics.com">U.S. Robotics</ulink> web site for
current product numbers and more detailed specifications.</para></note>

<para>The modem market is like consumer electronics (and unlike the
computer market as a whole) in that price is a very poor predictor of
performance.  For ordinary file transfers, some $50 modems are better than
some $150 modems.  Paying top dollar mainly buys you better tolerance of
poor connections and better performance at heavy-duty bi-directional
transfers (such as you would generate, for exmaple, using SLIP or PPP over
a leased line to an Internet provider).</para>

<para>In today's market all modems do a nominal 56kbps &mdash;V.90 and V.92
plus V.29 or V.17 fax transmission and reception (over plain old phone
lines you won't get more than 53K of that).  You don't see much in the way
of slow/cheap to fast/expensive product ranges within a single brand,
because competition is fierce and for many modem board designs (those
featuring DSP (Digital Signal Processor) chips run by a program in ROM)
adding a new protocol is basically a software change.</para>

<sect3 id="modem_format"><title>Internal vs. External</title>

<para>Most modems come in two packagings: internal, designed to fit in a PC
card slot, and external, with its own case, power supply, and front-panel
lights.  Typically you'll pay $20 to $30 more for an external modem than
you will for the internal equivalent.  You'll also need a serial or USB
port to connect your external modem to.</para>

<para>Pay that premium &mdash; being able to see the blinkenlights on
the external ones will help you understand and recover from
pathological situations.  For example, if your Unix system is prone to
<quote>screaming-tty</quote> syndrome, you'll quickly learn to recognize the
pattern of flickers that goes with it.  Punch the hangup/reset button
on an external modem and you're done &mdash; whereas with an internal
modem, you have to go root and flounder around killing processes and
maybe cold-boot the machine just to reset the card.</para>

<para>See <ulink url="http://linuxmafia.com/~rick/faq/">Rick's
Rants</ulink> for extended discussion of this point.</para>

</sect3>
<sect3 id="modem_pitfalls"><title>Pitfalls to Avoid</title>

<para>Don't buy a serial (RS232C) modem.  This used to be the only kind
there was, but they were always a bitch to configure and troubleshoot.
Go USB instead; the sanity you save may be your own.</para>

<para>If the abbreviation <quote>RPI</quote> occurs anywhere on the box,
don't even consider buying the modem.  RPI (Rockwell Protocol Interface) is
a proprietary <quote>standard</quote> that allows modem makers to save a
few bucks at your expense by using a cheap-jack Rockwell chipset that
doesn't do error correction.  Instead, it hands the job off to a modem
driver which (on a Unix machine) you will not have.</para>

<para>Also avoid anything called a <quote>Windows Modem</quote> or
<quote>WinModem</quote>, <quote>HCF</quote>, or <quote>HSP</quote>; these
lobotomized pieces of crap require a Windows DLL to run. They will eat up
to 25% of your processor clocks during transfers, and hog high-priority
interrupts (causing your machine to stall under Windows even if your
processor still has spare cycles). </para>

<para>A good way to avoid falling into the WinModem trap is to look for
the designation "OEM modem".  This is apparently the new industry-speak
for a modem with an on-board harware DSP. Occasionally you'll see these
called "gaming modems".</para>

</sect3>
<sect3><title>Fax Modems</title>

<para>Many modems come with bundled Windows fax software that is at best
useless under Unix, and at worst a software kluge to cover inadequate
hardware.  Avoid these bundles and buy a bare modem &mdash; it's cheaper,
and lowers the likelihood that something vital to your communications needs
has been left out of the hardware.</para>

<para>Avoid <quote>Class 1</quote> and <quote>Class 2</quote> modems.  Look
for <quote>Class 2.0</quote> for the full EIA-standard command set.</para>

<para>Fax capability is included with effectively all modems these days; it's
cheap for manufacturers, being basically a pure software add-on.  The
CCITT also sets fax protocol standards.  Terms to know:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term> V.29</term>
<listitem><para> CCITT standard for Group III fax encoding at 9600bps</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term> V.17</term>
<listitem><para> CCITT standard for Group III fax encoding at
14400bps</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>There's a separate series of standards for software control of fax
modems over the serial (or USB) line maintained by the Electronics Industry
Association and friends. These are:</para>

<para><firstterm>Class 1</firstterm> &mdash; base EIA standard for fax
control as extensions to the Hayes AT command set.</para>

<para><firstterm>Class 2.0</firstterm> &mdash; enhanced EIA standard
including compression, error correction, station ID and other
features.</para>

<para><firstterm>Class 2</firstterm> &mdash; marketroidian for anything
between Class 1 and Class 2.0.  Different <quote>Class 2</quote> modems
implement different draft subsets of the 2.0 standard, so <quote>Class
2</quote> fax software won't necessarily drive any given <quote>Class
2</quote> modem.</para>

<para>There's also a proprietary Intel "standard" called CAS, Communicating
Applications Specification.  Ignore it; only Intel products support it.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="printers"><title>Printers</title>

<para>The most important thing to optimize nowadays is cost of consumables.
Printer manufacturers, especially at the low end, have adopted a model
under which they sell printers with near-zero or even negative margin, then
gouge you horribly on the cost of cartridges and ink.  Common tactics
include (a) shipping half-filled "starter" cartridges with your printer, so
you have to replace much sooner than you'd think, (b) toner-empty
sensors deliberately miscalibrated to blink the error light on your printer
when they're still a quarter to a third full, and (c) electronic
countermeasures to lock out cheap third-party refills - in one notorious
case, a printer manufacturer used the DMCA to sue refill vebdoers who
circumvented these!</para>

<para>Better dealers (the Staples chain, for example) will show you
a chart covering price and consumable-cost-per-page for all the models
they carry.  If you don't see this, leave.  When you do, estimate your
monthly print volume and trade off up-front against consumables price.
appropriately.  Hint: The vendors count on you underestimating your volume 
and consumables cost, and you usually will.  Payiing a few extra bucks
up front to lower that cost is smart.</para>

<para>Other than that, there really isn't all that much to be said about
printers; the market is thoroughly commoditized and printer capabilities
pretty much independent of the rest of your hardware.  The PC-clone
magazines will tell you what you need to know about print quality, speed,
features, etc.  The business users they feed on are obsessed with all these
things.</para>

<para>(There used to be a problem with <quote>GDI printers</quote> and
<quote>WinPrinters</quote> that only worked with Windows &mdash;they
required special drivers that took over your CPU to do image processing,
These were such a bad idea that they have basically disappeared off the
market.)</para>

<para>Most popular printers are supported by GhostScript, and so it's easy
to make them do PostScript.  If you're buying any letter-quality
printer (laser or ink-jet), check to see if it's on GhostScript's
supported device list &mdash; otherwise you'll have to pay a premium for
Postscript capability!  Postscript is still high-end in the Windows
market, but it's ubiquitous in the Unix world.</para>

<para>Warning, however: if you're using ghostscript on a non-Postscript
printer, printspeed will be slow, especially with a serial printer.  A
bitmapped 600 dpi page has a <emphasis>lot</emphasis> of pixels on it.  At
today's prices, paying the small premium for Postscript capability makes
sense.</para>

<para>If you're buying a printer for home, an inkjet is a good choice
because it doesn't use gobs of power and you won't have the
toner/ozone/noise/etc mess that you do with a laser.  If all
you want is plain-ASCII, dot-matrix is cheaper to buy and run &mdash; if
you can find one.  Inexpensive ink-jets and lasers have almost driven 
them off the market.</para>

<para>Inkjets are great in that they're cheap, many of them do color, and
there are many kinds which aren't PCL but are understood by
Ghostscript anyway.  If you print very infrequently (less than weekly,
say), you should be careful to buy a printer whose print head gets
replaced with every ink cartrige: infrequent use can lead to the
drying of the ink, both in the ink cartrige and in the print head.
The print heads you don't replace with the cartrige tend to cost
nearly as much as the printer (~$200 for an Epson Stylus 800) once the
warranty runs out (the third such repair, just after the warranty
expired, totalled one informant's Stylus 800).  Be careful, check
print head replacement costs ahead of time, and run at least a
cleaning cycle if you don't actually print anything in a given week.
(Conversely, toner starts out dry, and ribbon ink won't evaporate for
years...if you truly print only rarely, but neither a dot matrix nor a
laser makes sense, consider buying no printer and taking your
PostScript files to a copy shop...)</para>

<para>Nowadays, a lot of printers are moving away from parallel-port
interfaces to USB.  This is a good idea, because USB devices announce
themselves to the host computer and can be automatically configured.
Parallel ports (and serial ports for that matter) are becoming obsolete.
Many new PC motherboards no longer include them.</para> 

<para>Many printers (even some sub-$100 models) now come with a network
(10/100 Ethernet) interface.  This make sharing them trivial, and also
avoids having to leave a desktop PC powered on so others (using notebooks
perhaps) can print to your printer.  Therefore, such printers are worth
considering in many networked environments, including home networks.</para>

<para>In the near future, new motherboards may stop including parallel and 
serial ports altogether.  That's another good reason to go with a USB-
or Ethernet-capable printer.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="power_protection"><title>Power Protection</title>

<para>I strongly recommend that you buy a UPS to protect your hardware and
data.  MOV-filtered power bars make nice fuses (they're cheap to replace),
but they're not enough. I have written a <ulink url="&howto;UPS-HOWTO">UPS
HOWTO</ulink> that provides more complete coverage of what used to be in
this section.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="rfi"><title>Radio Frequency Interference</title>

<para>(Thanks to Robert Corbett &lt;Robert.Corbett@Eng.Sun.COM&gt; for
contributing much of this section)</para>

<para>Radio Frequency Interference (RFI) is a growing problem with PC-class
machines.  Today's processor speeds are such that the electromagnetic noise
generated by a PC's circuitry in normal operation can degrade or jam radio
and TV reception in the neighborhood.  Such noise is called Radio Frequency
Interference (RFI).  Computers, as transmitting devices, are regulated by
the Federal Communications Commission (FCC).</para>

<para>FCC regulations recognize two classes of computer:</para>

<para>If a PC is to be used in a home or apartment, it must be
certified to be FCC class B.  If it is not, neighbors have a legal
right to prevent its use.  FCC class A equipment is allowed in
industrial environments.</para>

<para>Many systems are not FCC class B.  Some manufacturers build
boxes that are class B and then ship them with class A monitors or
external disk drives.  Even the cables can be a source of RFI.</para>

<para>It pays to be cautious.  For example, the Mag MX17F is FCC class B.
There are less expensive versions of the MX17 that are not.  The Mag MX17
is a great monitor.  It would be painful to own one and not be allowed to
use it.</para>

<para>An upgradeable system poses special problems.  A system that is
FCC class B with a 33 MHz CPU might not be when the CPU is upgraded to
a 50 or 66 MHz CPU.  Some upgrades require knockouts in the case to be
removed.  If a knockout is larger than whatever replaces it, RFI can
leak out through the gap.  Grounded metal shims can eliminate the
leaks.</para>

<para>Even Class B systems don't mix well with wireless phonesets (not cellular
phones, but the kind with a base station and antennaed headset).  You'll often 
find a wireless phone hard to use withing 20 feet of a Class B machine.</para>

<para>To cut down on RFI, get a good metal case with tight joints, or at
least make sure any plastic one you buy has a conductive lining.  You
can also strip the painted metal-to-metal contacting parts of paint so
that there's good conductive metal contact.  Paint's a poor conductor
in most cases, so you can get some benefit from this.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id='optimize'><title>What To Optimize</title>

<sect2><title>First, add more memory</title>

<para>Max out your memory.  Having lots of free memory will improve your
virtual-memory performance (and Unix takes advantage of extra memory more
effectively than Windows does).  Fortunately, with RAM as cheap as it is
now, a gigabyte or three is unlikely to bust your budget even if you're
economizing.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2><title>Bus and Disk speeds</title>

<para>Most people think of the processor as the most important choice in
specifying any kind of personal-computer system.  But for typical job loads
under Linux, the processor type is nearly a red herring &mdash; it's far
more important to specify a capable system bus and disk I/O subsystem. If
you don't believe this, you may find it enlightening to keep
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>top</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
running for a while as you use your machine.  Notice how seldom the CPU
idle percentage drops below 90%!</para>

<para>It's true that after people upgrade their motherboards they often do
report a throughput increase.  But this is often more due to other changes
that go with the processor upgrade, such as improved cache memory or an
increase in the clocking speed of the system's front-side bus (enabling
data to get in and out of the processor faster).</para>

<para>If you're buying for Linux on a fixed budget, it makes sense to trade
away some excess processor clocks to get a faster bus and disk subsystem.
If you're building a monster hot-rod, go ahead and buy that fastest
available processor &mdash; but once you've gotten past that gearhead
desire for big numbers, pay careful attention to bus speeds and your disk
subsystem, because that's where you'll get the serious performance wins.
The gap between processor speed and I/O subsystem throughput has only
widened in the last five years.</para>

<para>How does it translate into a recipe in 2010?  Like this; if
you're building a hot rod,</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Do</emphasis> buy a machine with the fastest
available "front-side" (e.g. processor-to-memory) bus.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis>Do</emphasis> get the fastest SATA disks you can
get your hands on.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="diskwars"><title>Optimizing your disk subsystem</title>

<para>For the fastest disks you can find, pay close attention to
average seek and latency time.  The former is an average time
required to seek to any track; the latter is the maximum time 
required for any sector on a track to come under the heads, and is
a function of the disk's rotation speed.</para>

<para>Of these, average seek time is <emphasis>much</emphasis> more
important.  When you're running Linux or any other virtual-memory operating
system, a one millisecond faster seek time can make a really substantial
difference in system throughput.  Back when PC processors were slow enough
for the comparison to be possible (and I was running System V Unix), it was
easily worth as much as a 30MHz increment in processor speed.  Today the
corresponding figure would probably be as much as 300MHz!</para>

<para>The manufacturers themselves avoid running up seek time on the
larger-capacity drives by stacking platters vertically rather than
increasing the platter size.  Thus, seek time (which is proportional
to the platter radius and head-motion speed) tends to be constant across
different capacities in the same product line.  This is good because it
means you don't have to worry about a capacity-vs.-speed tradeoff.</para>

<para>Average drive latency is inversely proportional to the disk's
rotational speed.  For years, most disks spun at 3600 rpm; most disks now
spin at 7,200 or 10,000rpm, and high-end disks at 15,000 rpm. These
fast-spin disks run extremely hot; cooling is becoming a critical
constraint in drive design.</para>

<para>For years, your basic decision was SATA vs. SCSI (the older IDE and
EIDE buses are long obsolete). Not in 2009; SATA 3 devices and controllers
are good enough that the performance advantage of SCSI is marginal unless
you are designing a super-high-end server box - slightly faster transfer
speeds (320MB/s vs. 300MB/s) and slightly better susrained throughput.</para>

<para>The SCSI price premium entailed in an extra controller and more
expensive disks are no longer worth it for the home builder, even from the
point of view of grizzled old SCSI partisans like me. Accordingly, I've
dropped most of the detailed SCSI information I used to carry here.</para>

<para>Final note: Solid-state drives loom on the horizon as replacements
for SATA disks, but the price per megabyte is still high enough that as
yet they're only being deployed in small capacities on netbooks.  Watch
this space.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="iotune"><title>Tuning Your I/O Subsystem</title>

<para><emphasis>(This section comes to us courtesy of Perry The Cynic,
&lt;perry@sutr.cynic.org&gt;; it was written in 1998.  My own experience
agrees pretty completely with his. I have revised the numbers in it since
to reflect more recent developments.)</emphasis></para>

<para>Building a good I/O subsystem boils down to two major points:
<emphasis>pick matched components</emphasis> so you don't over-build any
piece without benefit, and <emphasis>construct the whole pipe such that
it can feed what your OS/application combo needs</emphasis>.</para>

<para>It's important to recognize that <quote>balance</quote> is with
respect to not only a particular processor/memory subsystem, but also to a
particular OS and application mix. A Unix server machine running the whole
TCP/IP server suite has radically different I/O requirements than a
video-editing workstation. For the <quote>big boys</quote> a good
consultant will sample the I/O mix (by reading existing system performance
logs or taking new measurements) and figure out how big the I/O system
needs to be to satisfy that app mix. This is not something your typical
Linux buyer will want to do; for one, the application mix is not static and
will change over time. So what you'll do instead is design an I/O subsystem
that is internally matched and provides maximum potential I/O performance
for the money you're willing to spend. Then you look at the price points
and compare them with those for the memory subsystem. That's the most
important trade-off inside the box.</para>

<para>So the job now is to design and buy an I/O subsystem that is well
matched to provide the best bang for your buck. The two major performance
numbers for disk I/O are latency and bandwidth. Latency is how long a
program has to wait to get a little piece of random data it asked for.
Bandwidth is how much contiguous data can be sent to/from the disk once
you've done the first piece. Latency is measured in milliseconds (ms);
bandwidth in megabytes per second (MB/s). Obviously, a third number of
interest is how big all of your disks are together (how much storage you've
got), in Gigabytes (GB).</para>

<para>Within a rather big envelope, minimizing latency is the cat's meow.
Every millisecond you shave off effective latency will make your system
feel significantly faster. Bandwidth, on the other hand, only helps you
if you suck a big chunk of contiguous data off the disk, which happens
rarely to most programs. You have to keep bandwidth in mind to avoid
mis-matching pieces, because (obviously) the lowest usable bandwidth in
a pipe constrains everything else.</para>

<para>I'm going to ignore IDE. IDE is no good for multi-processing systems,
period. You may use an IDE CD-ROM if you don't care about its
performance, but if you care about your I/O performance, go SCSI.
(Beware that if you mix an IDE CD-ROM with SCSI drives under Linux,
you'll have to run a SCSI emulation layer that is a bit flaky.)</para>

<para>Let's look at the disks first. Whenever you seriously look at a
disk, <emphasis>get its data sheet</emphasis>. Every reputable
manufacturer has them on their website; just read off the product code
and follow the bouncing lights.  Beware of numbers (`&lt;12ms fast!')
you may see in ads; these folks often look for the lowest/highest
numbers on the data sheet and stick them into the ad copy. Not
dishonest (usually), but ignorant.</para>

<para>What you need to find out for a disk is:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>What kind of SCSI interface does it have? Look for
    "fast", "ultra", and "wide". Ignore disks that say "fiber"
    (this is a specialty physical layer not appropriate for the insides
    of small computers). Note that you'll often find the same disk with
    different interfaces.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>What is the "typical seek" time (ms)? Make sure
    you get "typical", not "track-to-track" or "maximum" or some other
    measure (these don't relate in obvious ways, due to things like
    head-settling time).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>What is the rotational speed? This is typically
    4500, 5400, 7200, 10000, or 15000 rpm (rotations per minute). Also look
    for "rotational latency" (in ms). (In a pinch, average rotational
    latency is approx. 30000/rpm in milliseconds.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>What is the &lsquo;media transfer rate&rsquo; or speed (in
    MB/s)? Many disks will have a range of numbers (say,
    7.2-10.8MB/s). Don't confuse this with the "interface transfer rate"
    which is always a round number (10 or 20 or 40MB/s) and is the speed of
    the SCSI bus itself.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>These numbers will let you do apple-with-apples comparisons of disks.
Beware that they will differ on different-size models of the same disk;
typically, bigger disks have slower seek times.</para>

<para>Now what does it all mean? Bandwidth first: the `media transfer rate'
is how much data you can, under ideal conditions, get off the disk per
second. This is a function mostly of rotation speed; the faster the
disk rotates, the more data passes under the heads per time unit. This
constrains the sustained bandwidth of <emphasis>this disk</emphasis>.</para>

<para>More interestingly, your effective latency is the sum of typical seek
time and rotational latency. So for a disk with 8.5ms seek time and 4ms
rotational latency, you can expect to spend about 12.5ms between the
moment the disk `wants' to read your data and the moment when it
actually starts reading it. This is the one number you are trying to
make small. Thus, you're looking for a disk with low seek times and
high rotation (RPM) rates.</para>

<para>For comparison purposes, the first hard drive I ever bought was a
20MB drive with 65ms seek time and about 3000RPM rotation. A floppy drive
has about 100-200ms seek time. A CD-ROM drive can be anywhere between 120ms
(fast) and 400ms (slow). The best IDE harddrives have about 10-12ms and
5400 rpm. The best SCSI harddrive I know (the Fujitsu MAM) runs
3.9ms/15000rpm.</para>

<para>Fast, big drives are expensive. Really big drives are very
expensive. Really fast drives are pretty expensive. On the other end,
really slow, small drives are cheap but not cost effective, because it
doesn't cost any less to make the cases, ship the drives, and sell
them.</para>

<para>In between is a &lsquo;sweet spot&rsquo; where moving in either
direction (cheaper or more expensive) will cost you more than you get out
of it. The sweet spot moves (towards better value) with time. If you
can make the effort, go to your local computer superstore and write down a
dozen or so drives they sell &lsquo;naked&rsquo;. (If they don't sell at
least a dozen hard drives naked, find yourself a better store. Use the Web,
Luke!)  Plot cost against size, seek and rotational speed, and it will
usually become pretty obvious which ones to get for your budget.</para>

<para>Do look for specials in stores; many superstores buy overstock from
manufacturers. If this is near the sweet spot, it's often
surprisingly cheaper than comparable drives. Just make sure you
understand the warranty procedures.</para>

<para>Note that if you need a lot of capacity, you may be better off with
two (or more) drives than a single, bigger one. Not only can it be cheaper
but you end up with two separate head assemblies that move independently,
which can cut down on latency quite a bit (see below).</para>

<para>If you find yourself at the high end of the bandwidth game, be aware
that the theoretical maximum of the PCI bus itself is 132MB/s. That
means that a dual ultra/wide SCSI controller (2x40MB/s) can fill more
than half of the PCI bus's bandwidth, and it is not advised to add
another fast controller to that mix. As it is, your device driver
better be well written, or your entire system will melt down (figuratively
speaking).</para>

<para>Incidentally, all of the numbers I used are &lsquo;optimal&rsquo;
bandwidth numbers. The real scoop is usually somewhere between 50-70% of
nominal, but things tend to cancel out &mdash; the drives don't quite
transfer as fast as they might, but the SCSI bus has overhead too, as does
the controller card.</para>

<para>Whether you have a single disk or multiple ones, on one or several
SCSI buses, you should give careful thought to their partition layout.
Given a set of disks and controllers, this is the most crucial
performance decision you'll make.</para>

<para>A partition is a contiguous group of sectors on the disk. Partitioning
typically starts at the outside and proceeds inwards. All partitions
on one disk share a single head assembly. That means that if you try
to overlap I/O on the first and last partition of a disk, the heads
must move full stroke back and forth over the disk, which can
radically increase seek time delays. A partition that is in the
middle of a partition stack is likely to have best seek performance,
since at worst the heads only have to move half-way to get there (and
they're likely to be around the area anyway).</para>

<para>Whenever possible, split partitions that compete onto different
disks. For example, /usr and the swap should be on different disks if
at all possible (unless you have outrageous amounts of RAM).</para>

<para>Another wrinkle is that most modern disks use `zone sectoring'. The
upshot is that outside partitions will have higher bandwidth than inner
ones (there is more data under the heads per revolution). So if you
need a work area for data streaming (say, a CD-R pre-image to record),
it should go on an outside (early numbered) partition of a
fast-rotating disk. Conversely, it's a good convention to put
rarely-used, performance-uncritical partitions on the inside (last).</para>

<para>Ah yes, caches. There are three major points where you could cache
I/O buffers: the OS, the controller card or chip in your machine, and the
on-disk controller.  Intelligent OS caching is by far the biggest win, for
many reasons. RAM caches on controller cards are pretty pointless these
days; you shouldn't pay extra for them, and experiment with disabling them
if you're into tinkering.</para>

<para>RAM caches on the drives themselves are a mixed bag. At moderate size
(1-2MB), they are a potential big win for Windows 95/98, because
Windows has stupid VM and I/O drivers. If you run a true multi-tasking
OS like Linux, having unified RAM caches on the disk is a significant
loss, since the overlapping I/O threads kick each other out of the
cache, and the disk ends up performing work for nothing.</para>

<para>Most high-performance disks can be reconfigured (using mode page
parameters, see above) to have `segmented' caches (sort of like a
set-associative memory cache). With that configured properly, the RAM
caches can be a moderate win, not because caching is so great on the
disk (it's much better in the OS), but because it allows the disk
controller more flexibility to reschedule its I/O request queue. You
won't really notice it unless you routinely have &gt;2 I/O requests
pending at the SCSI level. The conventional wisdom (try it both ways)
applies.</para>

<para>And finally I <emphasis>do</emphasis> have to make a
disclaimer. Much of the stuff above is shameless simplification. In
reality, high-performance disks are very complicated
beasties. They run little mini-operating systems that are most
comfortable if they have 10-20 I/O requests pending <emphasis>at the
same time</emphasis>. Under those circumstances, the amortized global
latencies are much reduced, though any single request may experience
<emphasis>longer</emphasis> latencies than if it were the only one
pending. The only really valid analysis are stochastic-process models,
which we <emphasis>really</emphasis> don't want to get into
here. :-)</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id='economizing'><title>But What If I'm Economizing?</title>

<para>If you are economizing, here's a simple rule:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Do</emphasis> buy a CPU/motherboard one or two
levels lower than commercial state of the art.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>For best value, look in the <emphasis>middle</emphasis> of the
current range of available processors.  On the desktop, in late 2007, that
means a CPU costing perhaps $75 to $200, not the latest and greatest quad
core marvels selling for several times that!</para>

<para>Why?  Because of the way manufacturers' price-performance curves are
shaped.  The top-of-line system is generally boob bait for corporate
executives and other people with more money than sense.  Chances are the
system design is new and untried &mdash; if you're at the wrong point in the
technology cycle, the chip may even be a pre-production sample, or an early
production stepping with undiscovered bugs like the infamous FDIV problem
in early Pentiums.  You don't need such troubles.  Better to go with a
chip/motherboard combination that's been out for a while and is known good.
It's not like you really need the extra speed, after all.</para>

<para>Besides, if you buy one of these gold-plated systems, you're only
going to kick yourself three months later when the price plunges by
30%.  Further down the product line there's been more real competition
and the manufacturer's margins are already squeezed.  There's less
room for prices to fall, so you won't watch your new toy lose street
value so fast.  Its price will still drop, but it won't plummet 
sickeningly.</para>

<para>Again, bear in mind that the cheapest processor you can buy new today
is plenty fast enough for Linux.  So if dropping back a speed level or 
two brings you in under budget, you can do it with no regrets.</para>

<para>Consider one drive rather than two.  This <emphasis>will</emphasis>
reduce overall system performance somewhat, but the cost saving as a
fraction of total system cost is often substantial.</para>

<para>Another easy economy measure is looking for repaired or reconditioned
parts with a warranty.  These are often as good as new, and much
cheaper.</para>

<para>Your display is one of the areas where pinching pennies is
<emphasis>not</emphasis> a good idea.  You're going to be looking at that
display for hours on end.  You are going to be using the screen real estate
constantly.  Buy the best quality, largest screen you possibly can &mdash; it
will be worth it.</para>

<para>Similarly, do not reduce the amount of RAM in your system too far.  A
minimum of 4GB of RAM is helpful in desktop systems today.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id='noise'><title>Noise Control and Heat Dissipation</title>

<para>An increasingly critical aspect of machine design is handling the
waste heat and acoustic noise of operation.  This may seem like a boring
subject, but cooling is a centrally important one if you want your machine
to last &mdash; because thermal stress from the electronics' own waste heat
is almost certainly what will kill it.  You want that fatal moment to
happen later rather than sooner.  On the other hand, cooling makes acoustic
noise, which human beings don't tolerate well.</para>

<para>This tradeoff bites harder than you think; it's the fundamental
reason that, despite my money-is-no-object premise in the Ultimate Linux
Box artcles, I didn't go to relatively exotic technologies like
liquid-cooled overclocking or RAID disk arrays for a performance boost.
Sure, they may initially look attractive &mdash; but overclocked chips and
banks of disk drives require massive cooling with lots of moving parts, and
it's not good to be trying to do creative work like programming with
anything that sounds quite so much like an idling jet engine sitting beside
one's desk.</para>

<para>In 2001 we had already reached the point at which the thermal load
vs. cooling-noise tradeoff is the effective limiting factor in the
performance of personal machines.  Ten years ago, even low-end and medium
"server" machines differed from personal-PC designs in fairly important
ways (different processor and bus types, different speed ranges, etc.)
Nowadays specialized server architectures are in retreat at the high end of
the market and everything else looks like a PC.  And the difference between
a "PC" and a "server" is mainly that servers live in server rooms, and are
allowed to have monster cases with lots of noisy fans.</para>

<para>So how do we manage this tradeoff for a personal, desktop or
desk-side machine?  Careful choice of components and being willing to pay
some price premium for cool-running and low-noise characteristics can help
a lot.  Even exceptionally clueful system integrators can't generally
afford to do this, because they're under constant competitive pressure to
cut price and costs by using generic components.</para>

<para>Reducing expected noise and heat in a design call for different
strategies.  It's relatively easy to find decibel figures for the
noisemaking parts in a PC design.  And, once you know a little basic
audiometry and a few basic rules of thumb, it's not hard to form a fair
estimate of your design's noisiness.  Estimating a design's heat
dissipation is harder, partly because the waste-heat emission of a PC's
subsystems tends to vary in a more complex way than the acoustic emissions
of the mechanical parts.  This means that you can and should try to design
ahead for low noise, but on the other hand expect to have to monitor for
heat-dissipation problems in your prototype and solve them by building
in more cooling.</para>

<para>Here's the basic audiometry you need to know to control your
design's noise emissions:</para>

<para>Sound is measured in <firstterm>decibels</firstterm>, abbreviated dB,
relative to the threshold of audibility, "A".  (Thus, sound levels above
that threshold are written "dBA".)  The scale is logarithmic, with every
3dB increment roughly doubling sound intensity.</para>

<para>For sounds that are not phase-related, decibel levels add as a 
logarithmic sum.  Thus if X and Y are uncorrelated sound sources,</para>

<literallayout>
dBA(X + Y) = 10 * log(10 ^ (dBA(X)/10) + 10 ^ (dBA(Y)/10))
</literallayout>

<para>A consequence of the above formula is that dBA(X + Y) cannot be
more than 3dB above the greater of dBA(X) and dBA(Y) for uncorrelated
sources (6dB for perfectly correlated ones).</para>

<para>Sound from a point source decays by an inverse-square law,
roughly 6dB for each doubling of distance.</para>

<para>Important thresholds on the decibel scale:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>0   dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Threshold of hearing</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>20  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Rustling leaves, quiet living room</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>30  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Quiet office</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>40  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Quiet conversation</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>45  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Threshold of distraction, according to EPA</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>50  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Quiet street, average office noise</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>60  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Normal conversation (1 foot distance)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>70  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Inside car</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>75  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Loud singing (3 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>80  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Typical home-stereo listening level</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<!--
<varlistentry>
<term>85  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Pushing a lawnmower over grass</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>88  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Motorcycle (30 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>90  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Food Blender (3 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>94  dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Subway (inside)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>100 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Diesel truck (30 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>107 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Power mower (3 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>115 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Pneumatic riveter (3 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>117 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Chainsaw (3 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>120 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Amplified Rock and Roll (6 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>130 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Jet plane (100 feet)</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>140 dBA</term>
<listitem><para>Gunshot, firecracker</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
-->
</variablelist>

<para>The acoustic noise emitted by PCs is normally a combination of white
noise produced by airflow, high-frequency noise produced by bearing
friction in drive spindles and fans, and the constant frequency "blade
passing" noise that all propellers emit (the latter is often more intense
than white noise and bearing whine).</para>

<para>The best low-noise ball-bearing case fans emit around 20dBA.
Typical sleeve-bearing fans emit 30-50dBA.</para>

<para>According to the indispensable <ulink
url="http://tomshardware.com/">Tom's Hardware site</ulink>, you can expect
to cut at least 5dB off the interior noise level of the computer with a
good choice of case.  We'll improve on that by adding sound-absorbing 
material to the interior.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="laptops"><title>Special Considerations When Buying Laptops and Netbboks</title>

<para>First, don't be misled by the term "netbook".  A netbook is just a
small, low-priced, low-power laptop with relatively small solid-state
drives. Because the display and drive capacity are small, netbooks are
basically just good for email and surfing.  If you're going to do coding
or even much word processing you'll need something more like a traditional
laptop or desktop.</para>

<para>Up until about 1999 the laptop market was completely crazy.  The
technology was in a state of violent flux, with <quote>standards</quote>
phasing in and out and prices dropping like rocks.  Things are beginning to
settle out a bit more now.</para>

<para>One sign of this change is that there are now a couple of laptop lines
that are clear best-of-breeds for reasons having as much to do with 
good industrial design and ergonomics as the technical details of the
processor and display.</para>

<para>In lightweight machines, I was a big fan of the Sony VAIO line.
I owned one from early 1999 until it physically disintegrated under
the rigors of travel in late 2000, and could hardly imagine
switching.  They weigh 3.5 pounds, give you an honest 3 hours of life
per detachable battery pack, have a very nice 1024x768 display, and
are just plain <emphasis>pretty</emphasis>. Their only serious
drawback is that they're not rugged, and often fall apart after
a year or so of use.</para>

<para>If you want a full-power laptop that can compete with or replace your
desktop machine, the Lenovo (formerly IBM) ThinkPad line is the bomb.
Capable, rugged, and nicely designed.  I now use a ThinkPad X61, the
lightest and smallest machine in the line, and like it a lot.</para>

<para>These machines are not cheap, though.  If you're trying to save
money by buying a no-name laptop, here are things to look for:</para>

<para>First: despite what you may believe, the most important aspect
of any laptop is <emphasis>not</emphasis> the CPU, or the disk, or the
memory, or the screen, or the battery capacity.  It's the keyboard
feel, since unlike in a PC, you cannot throw the keyboard away and
replace it with another one unless you replace the whole computer.
<emphasis>Never buy any laptop that you have not typed on for a couple
hours</emphasis>.  Trying a keyboard for a few minutes is not enough.
Keyboards have very subtle properties that can still affect whether
they mess up your wrists.</para>

<para>A standard desktop keyboard has keycaps 19mm across with 7.55mm
between them.  If you plot frequency of typing errors against keycap size,
it turns out there's a sharp knee in the curve at 17.8 millimeters.  Beware
of <quote>kneetop</quote> and <quote>palmtop</quote> machines, which
squeeze the keycaps a lot tighter and typically don't have enough oomph for
Unix anyway; you're best off with the "notebook" class machines that have
full-sized keys.</para>

<para>Second: with present flatscreens, 1920x1200 color is the best you're
going to do (and that is on a 17in widescreen, which translates to a large
notebook.  On normal size notebooks, a maximum of 1440x900 is more common).
On travel machines like the Lenovo X serties, you're still stuck with
1024x768.  If you want more than that (for X, for example) you have to
either fall back to a desktop or make sure there's an external-monitor port
on the laptop (and many laptops won't support higher resolution than the
flatscreen's).</para>

<para>Third: about those vendor-supplied time-between-recharge
figures; <emphasis>don't believe them</emphasis>.  They collect those
from a totally quiescent machine, sometimes with the screen or hard
disk turned off.  Under Windows, you'd be lucky to get half the endurance
they quote; under Unix, which hits the disk more often, it may be less
yet.  Figures from magazine reviews are more reliable.</para>

<para>Fourth: You can now avoid many of the driver hassles involved in
getting some devices on your notebook to work (or week well) under Linux by
purchasing a notebook with Linux pre-installed.  Dell has recently started
to make noise in this regard in the Linux community.  Taking this approach
limits the set of notebooks you can consider, but the one you get is likely
to "just work" (including sound, useful capabilities like suspend/resume,
and even hotplugging of external displays and projectors) to a much higher
degree under Linux than others.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="howtobuy"><title>How to Buy</title>

<sect2 id="whentobuy"><title>When to Buy</title>

<para>It used to be that good configurations for Unix were what the market
called &lsquo;server&rsquo; machines, with beefed-up I/O subsystems and
fast buses.  No longer; today's &lsquo;servers&rsquo; are monster boxes
with multiple power supplies and processors, gigabytes of memory, and
industrial-grade air cooling &mdash;they're not really suitable as personal
machines. A typical SCSI desktop workstation is as much as you'll
need.</para>

<para>Prices keep dropping, so there's a temptation to wait forever to
buy.  A good way to cope with this is to configure your system on paper, get
a couple of initial estimates, then set a trigger price, below the
lowest one, at what you're willing to pay.  Then watch and wait.  When
the configuration cost hits your trigger price, place your order.</para>

<para>The advantage of this method is that it requires you to settle in your
mind, well in advance, what you're willing to pay for what you're
getting.  That way, you'll buy at the earliest time you should, and
won't stress too much out afterwards as it depreciates.</para>

<para>Before you shop, do your homework.  Publications like "Computer
Shopper" (and their web site at <ulink
url="http://www.computershopper.com">
http://www.computershopper.com</ulink>) are invaluable for helping you
get a feel for prices and what clonemakers are doing.  Another
excellent site is <ulink
url="http://www.computeresp.com">ComputerESP</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="wheretobuy"><title>Where to Buy</title>

<para>The most important where-to-buy advice is negative.  Do
<emphasis>not</emphasis> go to a traditional, business-oriented
storefront dealership.  Their overheads are high.  So are their
prices.</para>

<para>Especially, run &mdash;do not walk &mdash;away from any outfit that
trumpets &lsquo;business solutions&rsquo;.  This is marketing code for the
kind of place that will justify a heavy price premium by promising
after-sale service and training which, nine times out of ten, will turn out
to be nonexistent or incompetent.  Sure, they'll give you plush carpeting
and a firm handshake from a guy with too many teeth and an expensive watch
&mdash;but did you really want to pay for that?</para>

<para>There are two major alternatives to storefront dealerships and one
minor one.  The major ones are mail order and computer superstores.
The minor one is computer fairs.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="fairs"><title>Computer Fairs</title>

<para>I used to be a big fan of hole-in-the-wall stores run by immigrants
from the other side of the International Date Line, but most of those
places have been driven out of the regular retail game by the superstores
and the Web.  If you still have one in your neighborhood, you're lucky.  I
do, as it happens, but that is now unusual; the only place you normally
find diaspora Chinese and Indians selling cheap PCs over the counter
anymore is at computer fairs.  (Usually they're doing it to publicize an
Internet/mail-order business.)</para>

<para>You can find good loss-leader deals on individual parts at these
fairs (they're especially good places to buy disk drives cheap). But I call
them a minor alternative because it's hard to get a custom configuration
tuned for Unix built for you at a fair.  So you end up, effectively, back
in the mail-order or Web channel.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="mailorder"><title>Mail Order</title>

<para>Internet buying makes a lot of sense today for anyone with
more technical savvy than J. Random Luser in a suit.  Even from no-name
vendors, parts and system quality tend to be high and consistent,
so conventional dealerships don't really have much more to offer than a
warm fuzzy feeling.  Furthermore, competition has become so intense that
even Internet/mail-order vendors today have to offer not just lower prices
than ever before but warranty and support policies of a depth that would
have seemed incredible a few years back.  For example, many bundle a year
of on-site hardware support with their medium- and high-end
<quote>business</quote> configurations for a very low premium over the bare
hardware.</para>

<para>Note, however, that assembling a system yourself out of parts is
<emphasis>not</emphasis> likely to save you money over dealing with the
Internet/mail-order systems houses.  You can't buy parts at the volume they
do; the discounts they command are bigger than the premiums reflected in
their prices.  The lack of any system warranty or support can also be a
problem even if you're expert enough to do the integration yourself &mdash;
because you also assume all the risk of defective parts and integration
problems.</para>

<para>Watch out for dealers (Spectrum Trading for one) who charge ridiculous
shipping fees. One of our spies reports he bought a hotswappable hard
disc drive tray that weighed about 3 lbs. and cost $250 and they
charged $25 to ship it UPS groud.</para>

<para>Don't forget that (most places) you can avoid sales tax by buying from an
out-of-state outfit, and save yourself 6-8% depending on where you
live.  If you live near a state line, buying from a local outfit you can often
win, quite legally, by having the stuff shipped to a friend or relative just
over it.  Best of all is a buddy with a state-registered dealer number; these
aren't very hard to get and confer not just exemption from sales tax but
(often) whopping discounts from the vendors.  Hand him a dollar afterwards to
make it legal.</para>

<para>(Note: I have been advised that you shouldn't try the latter tactic in
Florida &mdash;they are notoriously tough on "resale license" holders).</para>

<para>(Note II: The Supreme Court has ruled that states may not tax
out-of-state businesses under existing law, but left the way open for
Congress to pass enabling legislation.  Let's hope the mail-order
industry has good lobbyists.)</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="superstores"><title>Computer Superstores</title>

<para>Big chain superstores like CompUSA give you a reasonable alternative
to the Web.  And there are good reasons to explore it &mdash; these stores
buy and sell at volumes that allow them to offer prices not far above the
Web.  (They make back a lot of their margin on computer games and small
accessories like mouse pads, cables, and floppy disks.)</para>

<para>Note, however: <emphasis>Avoid Best Buy</emphasis>.  Horror stories 
about them are legion &mdash; predatory salescritters, incompetent
service, routine bait-and-switch tactics.</para>

<para>One thing you should not buy remotely if you can avoid it is a
monitor.  Monitors are subject to significant quality variations even
within the same make and model.  Flatscreens haver this [roblem less than
CRTs did, but you don't want a flatscreen with dead pixels.  So buy your
monitor face-to-face, picking the best out of three or four.</para>

<para>Another good argument for buying at a superstore is that you may
have to pay return postage if you ship a system back to the vendor.  On a
big, heavy system, this can eat your initial price savings.</para>

<para>The only major problem with superstores is that the salespeople who
staff them aren't very bright or very clueful (it's a sort of Darwinian
reverse-selection effect; these are the guys who are fascinated by computer
technology but not smart enough to be techies).  Most of them don't know
from Linux and are likely to push things like two-button mice that you
can't use.  Use caution and check your system manifest.</para>

<para>But if you shop carefully and don't fall for one of their name-brand
"prestige" systems, you can get prices comparable to Internet/mail-order
with the comfort of knowing there's a trouble desk you can drive back to in
a pinch.  (Also, you <emphasis>can</emphasis> see your monitor before you
buy!)</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="buying_tips"><title>Other Buying Tips</title>

<para>You can often get out of paying tax just by paying cash,
especially at computer shows.  You can always say you're going to ship
the equipment out of the state.</para>

<para>A lot of vendors bundle Windows and variable amounts of apps
with their hardware.  If you tell them to lose all this useless cruft
they may shave $50 or $100 off the system price.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="questions"><title>Questions You Should Always Ask Your Vendor</title>

<sect2 id="warranty"><title>Minimum Warranty Provisions</title>

<para>The weakest guarantee you should settle for in the mail-order
market should include:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>72-hour burn-in to avoid that sudden infant death
syndrome.  (Also, try to find out if they do a power-cycling test and
how many repeats they do; this stresses the hardware much more than
steady burn-in.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>30 day money-back guarantee.  Watch out for fine print
that weakens this with a restocking fee or limits it with
exclusions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>1 year parts and labor guarantee (some vendors give 2
years).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>1 year of 800 number tech support (many vendors give
lifetime support).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Additionally, many vendors offer a year of on-site service free.  You
should find out who they contract the service to.  Also be sure the free
service coverage area includes your site; some unscrupulous vendors weasel
their way out with <quote>some locations pay extra</quote>, which
translates roughly to <quote>through the nose if you're further away than
our parking lot</quote>.</para>

<para>If you're buying store-front, find out what they'll guarantee beyond
the above.  If the answer is <quote>nothing</quote>, go somewhere
else.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="documention"><title>Documentation</title>

<para>Ask your potential suppliers what kind and volume of documentation
they supply with your hardware.  You should get, at minimum,
operations manuals for the motherboard and each card or peripheral;
also an IRQ list.  Skimpiness in this area is a valuable clue that
they may be using no-name parts from Upper Baluchistan, which is not
necessarily a red flag in itself but should prompt you to ask more
questions.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="quality"><title>A System Quality Checklist</title>

<para>There are various cost-cutting tactics a vendor can use which
bring down the system's overall quality.  Here are some good questions
to ask:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>If you're buying a factory-configured system, does it
have FCC certification?  While it's not necessarily the case that a
non-certified system is going to spew a lot of radio-frequency
interference, certification is legally required &mdash; and becoming
more important as clock frequencies climb.  Lack of that sticker may
indicate a fly-by-night vendor, or at least one in danger of being
raided and shut down! (For further discussion, see the section on <link
linkend="rfi">Radio Frequency Interference</link>
above.)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Are the internal cable connectors keyed, so they can't
be put in upside down?  This doesn't matter if you'll never, ever
<emphasis>ever</emphasis> need to upgrade or service your system.
Otherwise, it's pretty important; and, vendors who fluff this detail
may be quietly cutting other corners.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="mailtips"><title>Things to Check when Buying</title>

<sect2 id="tricks"><title>Tricks and Traps in Warranties</title>

<para>Reading warranties is an art in itself.  A few tips:</para>

<para>Beware the deadly modifier <quote>manufacturer's</quote> on a warranty;
this means you have to go back to the equipment's original
manufacturer in case of problems and can't get satisfaction from the
mail-order house.  Also, manufacturer's warranties run from the date
<emphasis>they</emphasis> ship; by the time the mail-order house
assembles and ships your system, it may have run out!</para>

<para>Watch for the equally deadly <quote>We do not guarantee
compatibility</quote>.  This gotcha on a component vendor's ad means you may
not be able to return, say, a video card that fails to work with your
motherboard.</para>

<para>Another dangerous phrase is <quote>We reserve the right to substitute
equivalent items</quote>.  This means that instead of getting the
high-quality name-brand parts advertised in the configuration you just
ordered, you may get those no-name parts from Upper Baluchistan
&mdash; theoretically equivalent according to the spec sheets, but
perhaps more likely to die the day after the warranty expires.
Substitution can be interpreted as <quote>bait and switch</quote>, so most
vendors are scared of getting called on this.  Very few will hold
their position if you press the matter.</para>

<para>Another red flag: <quote>Only warranted in supported
environments</quote>.  This may mean they won't honor a warranty on a
non-Windows system at all, or it may mean they'll insist on installing the Unix
on disk themselves.</para>

<para>One absolute show-stopper is the phrase <quote>All sales are
final</quote>.  This means you have <emphasis>no</emphasis> options if a
part doesn't work.  Avoid any company with this policy.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="mail_questions"><title>Special Questions to Ask Web/Mail-Order
Vendors Before Buying</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Does the vendor have the part or system presently in
stock?  Mail order companies tend to run with very lean inventories;
if they don't have your item in stock, delivery may take longer.
Possibly <emphasis>much</emphasis> longer.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Does the vendor pay for shipping?  What's the delivery
wait?</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If you need to return your system, is there a
restocking fee? and will the vendor cover the return freight?  Knowing
the restocking fee can be particularly important, as they make keep
you from getting real satisfaction on a bad major part.  Avoid dealing
with anyone who quotes more than a 15% restocking fee &mdash; and it's
a good idea, if possible, to avoid any dealer who charges a restocking
fee at all.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Warranties are tricky.  There are companies whose warranties are
invalidated by opening the case.  Some of those companies sell
upgradeable systems, but only authorized service centers can do
upgrades without invalidating the warranty.  Sometimes a system is
purchased with the warranty already invalidated.  There are vendors
who buy minimal systems and upgrade them with cheap RAM and/or disk
drives.  If the vendor is not an authorized service center, the
manufacturer's warranty is invalidated.  The only recourse in case of
a problem is the vendor's warranty.  So beware!</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="payment"><title>Payment Method</title>

<para>It's a good idea to pay with AmEx or Visa or MasterCard; that way you
can stop payment if you get a lemon, and may benefit from a
buyer-protection plan using the credit card company's clout (not all cards
offer buyer-protection plans, and some that do have restrictions which may
be applicable).  However, watch for phrases like <quote>Credit card
surcharges apply</quote> or <quote>All prices reflect 3% cash
discount</quote> which mean you're going to get socked extra if you pay by
card.</para>

<para>Note that many credit-card companies have clauses in their
standard contracts forbidding such surcharges.  You can (and should)
report such practices to your credit-card issuer.  If you already paid
the surcharge, they will usually see to it that it is returned to you.
Credit-card companies will often stop dealing with businesses that
repeat such behavior.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="vendors"><title>Which Clone Vendors to Talk To</title>

<sect3 id="pans"><title>Some pans</title>

<para><emphasis>Gateway</emphasis>: may also be a vendor to avoid.
Apparently their newer machines don't have parity bits in their
memories; memory is tested only on reboot.  This is dubious design
even for Windows, and totally unacceptable for Unix.</para>

</sect3>
<sect3><title>Some picks</title>

<para>In early August 2001 I designed an `Ultimate Linux Box' with Gary
Sandine and John Pearson of <ulink url="http://lanm-pc.com">Los Alamos
Computers</ulink>; you can <ulink
url="&home;writings/ultimate-linux-box/">read all about it</ulink> These
guys know what they are doing and are fun to work with.  If you need a
high-end Linux workstation, or your laboratory needs a computer cluster,
talk with them.</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1><title> After You Take Delivery</title>

<para>Your configuration is custom and involves slightly unusual
hardware.  Therefore, keep a copy of the configuration you wrote down,
and check it against the invoice and the actual delivered hardware.
If there is a problem, calling back your vendor right away will
maximize your chances of getting the matter settled quickly.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="software"><title>Software to go with your hardware</title>

<para>I used to maintain an entire separate FAQ on Unixes for 386/486 and
Pentium hardware.  Times change, industries evolve, and I can now
replace that FAQ with just three words:</para>

<para><emphasis role="strong">Go get Linux!</emphasis></para>

<note><para>FreeBSD or OpenSolaris are currently niche choices, but if they
offer something you need that Linux doesn't, don't let me stop you from
trying one or both of them.</para></note>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="links"><title>Other Resources on Building Linux PCs</title>

<para>The <ulink url="http://www.pctechguide.com/">PC Tech Guide</ulink>
offers pretty comprehensive descriptions of PC hardware technologies.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="http://hawks.ha.md.us/hardware/">Caveat
Emptor</ulink> guide has an especially good section on evaluating
monitor specifications. </para>

<para>Anthony Olszewski's <ulink
url="http://www.computercraft.com/docs/pcbuild.html"> Assembling A
PC</ulink> is an excellent guide to the perplexed.  Not
Linux-specific.</para>

<para><ulink url="http://www.sysdoc.pair.com/">Tom's Hardware
Guide</ulink> covers many hardware issues exhaustively. It is
especially good about CPU chips and motherboards.  Full of ads and
slow-loading graphics, though.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="http://www.sysopt.com">System Optimization
Site</ulink> has many links to other worthwhile sites for hardware
buyers.</para>

<para>Christopher B. Browne has a page on <ulink
url="http://linuxfinances.info/info/linuxvars.html#VARS">Linux VARs</ulink>
that build systems. He also recommends the <ulink
url="http://en.tldp.org/HOWTO/VAR-HOWTO.html">Linux
VAR HOWTO</ulink>.</para>

<para>There's a <ulink
url="http://www.aplus.net/docs/facts/the-ultimate-guide-to-building-your-own-pc.htm">Building
Your Own PC</ulink> page.  It's more oriented towards building from parts
than this one.  Less technical depth in most areas, but better coverage of
some including RAM, soundcards and motherboard installation.  Features
nifty and helpful graphics, one of the better graphics-intensive pages I've
seen.  However, the hardware-selection advice is out of date.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="http://en.tldp.org/HOWTO/Hardware-HOWTO">Linux Hardware
Database</ulink> .</para>

<para>The <ulink url='http://www.silentpcreview.com/'>Silent PC
Reviews</ulink> site has lots of good material on building quiet PCs.</para>
</sect1>
</article>

<!--
The following sets edit modes for GNU EMACS
Local Variables:
fill-column:75
compile-command: "mail -s \"Unix Hardware Buyer HOWTO update\" submit@en.tldp.org <Unix-Hardware-Buyer-HOWTO.xml"
End:
-->
