<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" []>

<book>
<bookinfo>
<title>USB Digital Camera HOWTO</title>
<author>
      <firstname>Dave</firstname><surname>Kelly</surname>
      <affiliation><address><email>daveekelly@earthlink.net</email></address>
</affiliation>
</author>
<pubdate>April 2002</pubdate>

<revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
	<date>2002-06-02</date>
	<authorinitials>tab</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Converted to Docbook XML 4.1.2</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2002-04-13</date>
	<authorinitials>dek</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial release</revremark>
      </revision>
</revhistory>

<!--Changelog

USB Digital Camera HOWTO 1.0 History:

2002/02/04 First draft;dek
2002/02/10 Final draft for proof;dek
2002/03/07 Submitted to LDP for review;dek
2002/03/19 Made changes suggested by reviewer;dek
2002/03/19 Added text to sections: 1.2, 6.0, 4.4.;dek
2002/03/19 Added appendix C.;dek
2002/04/13 Converted to HTML;dek
2002/04/15 Submited to LDP;dek
-->
</bookinfo>

<toc></toc>

<chapter>
<title>License</title>

<sect1>
<title>Copyright</title>
<para>Copyright 2001 Dave Kelly, et al.</para>

<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in <xref linkend="gfdl">.</para>
</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>Intent</title>

<para>This HOWTO is intended for the new Linux user who 
already has a camera with Universal Serial Bus (USB) mass storage capabilities 
or wants to buy one. If you were like me, someone gave you one for your 
birthday, and you just could not take it back without hurting some feelings. So, 
you get into your Linux documentation and make it work. There is nothing we 
can't do, and there are no dumb questions, only information we don't have 
yet.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Scope of Devices</title>
<para>This procedure works with the Linux 
kernel version 2.4.8, and I tested it with a Sony P-50 Cybershot with a 4 MB and 
64 MB memory stick, and a USB smart card reader for an Olympus camera. I have 
read that the procedure will also work on kernel versions back to 2.2.19, but 
there are no guarantees. I know the procedure does not work on my old kernel 
version of 2.2.15.</para>

<para>The information in this document is how I solved my problems. There are other 
way to do this but it may require recompiling the kernel, which I did not want 
to do. This document should give you the necessary information to make USB mass 
storage active at boot time.</para>
 
<para>Also, Linux is an evolving technology, a hands on technology, and while this 
document may not give you the answers to your specific question, it should give 
you a place to start exploring for those answers. Plus the serendipity of 
discovering new thing along the way.</para>
 
<para>The following excerpt from the "gphoto2 README" might give you some insight 
to other cameras that will work with this procedure. I don't know who to give 
credit for this, as I could not find a name.)  Check the <quote>gphoto</quote> link for 
updated information: <ulink url="http://www.gphoto.org">http://www.gphoto.org</ulink></para>

<blockquote>
<para>Then, there are cameras supporting the 
so-called USB Mass Storage protocol. This is a protocol that has been published 
and lets you access any storage device, be it a camera or a disk connected via 
USB to your computer. As there are already drivers for this protocol out there, 
you don't need an additional program like gphoto2.</para>

<para> As of now, the following cameras seem to support the USB Mass Storage protocol:</para>
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Casio QV [2x00,3x00,8000]</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Fuji FinePix S1 Pro, [1400,2400,4700]Zoom, 1300, 4500</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>HP PhotoSmart 315, 618, 912</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Leica Digilux 4.3</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Konica KD300Z</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Kyocera Finecam s3</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Minolta Dimage 7</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Nikon Coolpix 995</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Olympus C-100, C-200Z, C-700, C-860L, C-2040, C-3020Z, C-3040Z, C-4040Zoom, D-510, E-10</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Pentax Optio 330</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Sony DSC-F505(V), DSC P5, DSC-F707</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Again, those cameras cannot be accessed through gphoto2.</para>

<para>Other cameras support a protocol called PTP or USB Imaging Devices that has 
been developed by Kodak and other. gphoto2 does not support PTP yet, but <ulink url="http://jphoto.sourceforge.net">jPhoto</ulink> does. Here is a short list of cameras that use this protocol:</para>

<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Kodak DC-4800, DX-3215, DX-3500, DX-3600, DX-3700, DX-3900, 
MC3 and all the cameras that use Kodak Easy Share&trade; system.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Sony DSC-P5, DSC-F707 (both need user configuration of the camera)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>These cameras won't be supported until gphoto2 implements PTP.</para>
</blockquote>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Reading Material</title>
<para>You are encouraged to read the following manuals and HOWTOs. The information in them is helpful.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Man Pages</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para><command>lsmod</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>modprobe</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>mount</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>mv</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>su</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>fstab</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>mtab</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>dir</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>install</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>mknod</command></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><command>chown</command></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para><citetitle>Module-HOWTO</citetitle></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><citetitle>Bash-Prog-Intro-HOWTO</citetitle></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><citetitle>SCSI-2.4-HOWTO</citetitle></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><citetitle>Hardware-HOWTO</citetitle></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    
	<para>Most distros come with all the HOWTOs. If yours did not, they are available at:<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Websites</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www2.one-eyed-alien.net/~mdharm/Linux-usb/">http://www2.one-eyed-alien.net/~mdharm/Linux-usb/</ulink></para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.Linux-usb.org/USB-guide/book1.html">http://www.Linux-usb.org/USB-guide/book1.html</ulink></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Assumptions</title>

<para>My system is a Athlon 900 with a 40 gig hard 
drive. I have no SCSI or USB devices. My kernel was compiled without any of the 
SCSI or USB drivers. I compiled the SCSI and USB drivers as modules. I have 
version 2.4.8_26mdk of the Linux kernel with Mandrake 8.1. Since we are working 
on the kernel level, this document should be applicable to any distro.</para>

<para>I also make the following assumptions in this document:</para>
<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>You do not have any SCSI or USB modules loaded or mounted.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>You are the superuser and have the root password.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>The word camera can refer to a device of type camera, card reader, any USB mass storage device.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>The mount point <quote>camera</quote>, <filename>/mnt/camera</filename>, does not refer to a device in the aforementioned context. Look in the directory <filename>/mnt</filename> and you will probably see cdrom, disk, floppy, and maybe several others device names. In 
mine, you will see these plus <quote>camera</quote>. These are directories, and they are 
mount points.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>The symbol <quote>[bash]$</quote> means the command line prompt. Do not type 
it when you are entering a command. It is where you type the command line to 
give user input to the computer.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Preliminary Setup</title>

<para>At this point you need to make some 
decisions. You will need to create a directory for a mount point, and you will 
need a name for this directory. I use camera and place it in <filename>/mnt</filename>. The name of 
the directory (<filename>camera</filename> in my case) can be any word of your choice. The command 
for creating this directory is:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ mkdir -m 777 /mnt/camera
</screen>

<para>I prefer for all my pictures to be in one directory with subdirectories by 
subject matter, so I also created a directory named <filename>picture</filename>, and placed it in 
my home directory. The name of the directory (<filename>picture</filename> in my case) can be any 
word of your choice.  The command for creating this directory is:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ mkdir -m 777 ~/picture
</screen>

<para>See <xref linkend="part_1">, listed at the end of this document.</para>

<para>The big decision! Are you going to do this as <quote>user</quote> or 
<quote>superuser/root</quote>?</para>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Script Files</title>

<para>The following script file is the result 
of reading several of the Linux newsgroups and a lot of HOWTOs and manuals. I 
take no credit for originality but confess that this is a compilation of what 
those more experienced have told me. A very big thank you to all those in the 
newsgroups who responded to my questions and the ones posted by others who were 
seeking this information.</para>

<para>To get started, using your favorite text editor select a name for the file 
and, type in the following script for a user or superuser.</para>

<sect1>
<title>If You Login as User</title>

<para>Type in the following script file:</para>

<screen>
echo "Please enter a directory name for the pictures."
read DIRPATH
mkdir ~/picture/$DIRPATH
su -c "/sbin/modprobe usb-storage; mount -t vfat /dev/sda1 /mnt/camera;
/etc/rc.d/init.d/usb start;
mv /mnt/camera/dcim/100msdcf/*.jpg ~/picture/$DIRPATH;
umount /mnt/camera;
chown -R your_login_name ~/picture/$DIRPATH"
</screen>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>If You Login as Superuser</title>

<para>If you are not creating this script for use as superuser, go to <xref linkend="executable">.</para>

<para>Type in the following script file.</para>

<screen>
echo "Please enter a directory name for the pictures."
read DIRPATH
mkdir picture/$DIRPATH
/sbin/modprobe usb-storage
mount -t vfat /dev/sda1 /mnt/camera
/etc/rc.d/init.d/usb start
mv /mnt/camera/dcim/100msdcf/*.jpg picture/$DIRPATH;
umount /mnt/camera
chown -R your_login_name picture/$DIRPATH
</screen>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="executable">
<title>Make it Executable</title>

<para>Now make the script file executable. The command for that is:</para>

<para>As user:</para>
<screen>
[bash]$ su -c "chmod a=r+w+x your_script_file_name"
</screen>

<para>As superuser:</para>
<screen>
[bash#] chmod a=r+w+x your_script_file_name
</screen>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>What is Happening while the script is running</title>

<para>When you run the script, it will create a subject matter directory. <varname>DIRPATH</varname> should describe the pictures and is entered at the prompt. If <filename>your_script_file_name</filename> = <filename>getcamJ</filename>,(J for getting the pictures with .jpg extensions) the command sequence would 
look like this:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ getcamJ
Please enter a directory name for the pictures.
bash]$ something
Password: 
[bash]$ your root password
</screen>

<para>If you run this script file in superuser mode the rest of this paragraph does 
not apply. You have to be superuser to run this. Consequently, the 'su' command. 
The <parameter class=option>-c</parameter> flag will let you execute one command and return to your present working directory. The quotation marks allow you to enter more that one command. 
And the semicolon allows one command to execute right after the last.</para>

<para><filename>/sbin/modprobe usb-storage</filename>:  <command>modprobe</command> will install the USB mass storage module along with any other modules or drivers needed. Mainly the SCSI driver. 
Make sure that you have in your /dev directory the following entries. <systemitem class="resource">sda0, 
sda1, sda2, sda3, sda4, sdb0, sdb1, sdb2, sdb3, sdb4</systemitem>. Set <systemitem class="resource">sda1</systemitem> to the appropriate device if you have other SCSI devices mounted, probably <systemitem class="resource">sdb1</systemitem>.</para>

<para>Mount your SCSI driver: <userinput>mount -t vfat /dev/sda1 /mnt/camera</userinput></para>

<para>Start your USB: <userinput>/etc/rc.d/init.d/usb start</userinput></para>

<para>Move your pictures from your camera to your hard drive.  <command>mv</command> will also remove your pictures from your camera: <userinput>mv /mnt/camera/dcim/100msdcf/*.jpg picture/$DIRPATH;</userinput></para>

<para>Unmount your SCSI driver: <userinput>umount /mnt/camera</userinput></para>

<para>Then: <userinput>chown -R your_login_name picture/$DIRPATH</userinput>.  When you do something as 
superuser (su) or root, root owns those files/pictures. Some of the things you 
may want to do to these files/pictures may give you a <errorname>permission denied</errorname> error. 
This allows the user to work without those errors. Read the manual for more information.</para>

<para>My system is set up with no USB or SCSI compiled into the kernel. All this 
was compiled as modules. This script file assumes your system is the same. If 
not, you will have to make some modifications. Please read the manuals and 
HOWTOs. Or ask on one of the Linux newsgroups.</para>

</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Exploring and Fine Tuning</title>

<para>OK, you should be set up and 
ready to do some exploring. Go take some trash pictures with your camera in all 
the different formats. Mine will take in 4 formats, TIFF, GIF, JPEG, and MPEG, 
and it also provides a thumbnail of each picture. In my Sony P-50 these will be 
stored on the memory media in 4 different sub-folders, 100msdcf, imcif100, thm, 
and moml0001. These are in 2 folders, dcim, and mssony. You need to find how 
your camera names the directories. You can do this in the following 
manner:</para>

<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Copy the above script file to a working file name.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>With your text editor change line: <userinput>mv /mnt/camera/dcim/100msdcf/*.jpg picture/$DIRPATH</userinput> to <userinput>mv /mnt/camera/* picture/$DIRPATH</userinput></para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Run the script from a command line as follows:</para>
<screen>
[bash]$ ./your_script_file_name
</screen>

<para>(notice the dot and forward slash)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect1>
<title>DON'T PANIC</title>

<para><emphasis>THE MODIFIED SCRIPT FILE MAY GIVE YOU SOME 
ERRORS.</emphasis> Just ignore them for now. Before you panic and say it does not 
work, look and see if you have pictures. If you do, write down the directory 
path names. Go back to your text editor and substitute them for 
dcim/100msdcf/*.jpg in the script file. You may want to make several script 
files to handle the each of the different picture formats.</para>

<para>At this point the directory on your hard drive should look something like 
<xref linkend="part_2">. Enter this command to confirm it does:</para>
<screen>
[bash]$ dir -R name-of-your-picture-directory
</screen>

<para>The information in this document and the manuals and HOWTOs should get you up 
and running.</para>
<para>Good Luck.</para>
<para>Dave</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting or PANIC!</title>

<para>If nothing has gone right, let's do some troubleshooting. Use your camera and 
see if you still have pictures on it. If you do, skip the rest of this 
paragraph. If you don't, they should be someplace, check again. If not, and you 
can not find them, go take some more. Turn your camera off and plug it in and 
boot up again.</para>

<para>Check to see if the mount point unlinked by <command>mv</command>,<filename>/mnt/camera</filename> is there. If it's gone create it again. Sometimes the mount point disappears in modified 
mode. Also, I have notice on my system that sometimes the SCSI device in <filename>/dev</filename> 
(<systemitem class="resource">sda1</systemitem>) gets removed. Check that also and replace if needed.</para>

<para>Clean up all the extra directories you got from the script you ran that 
produced the errors and run your new script with the directories and see if it 
works. To make it easier to clean up all the directories and files you may have 
to <envar>su -</envar> if you're in user mode. Be sure to change back when you get through. 
See <xref linkend="appendix_c"> at the end of this document.</para>

<para>Type:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ dmesg
</screen>

<para>and you should see this somewhere:</para>

<screen>
hub.c: USB new device connect on bus1/1, assigned device number 2
usb.c: USB device 2 (vend/prod 0x54c/0x10) is not claimed by any active driver. (The 
0x54c/0x10 will be different for different vendors.)
</screen>

<para>If you see this, your USB mass storage device in recognized.</para>

<para>Now turn your camera on and run the script file (the modified one) and you 
should see something like this when you run dmesg again:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ dmesg

SCSI subsystem driver Revision: 1.00
Initializing USB Mass Storage driver...
usb.c: registered new driver usb-storage
scsi0 : SCSI emulation for USB Mass Storage devices
Vendor: Sony Model: Sony DSC Rev: 3.22
Type: Direct-Access ANSI SCSI revision: 02
WARNING: USB Mass Storage data integrity not assured
USB Mass Storage device found at 2
USB Mass Storage support registered.
Attached scsi removable disk sda at scsi0, channel 0, id 0, lun 0
SCSI device sda: 126848 512-byte hdwr sectors (65 MB)
sda: Write Protect is off
/dev/scsi/host0/bus0/target0/lun0: p1
usb-uhci.c: interrupt, status 3, frame# 1628
</screen>

<para>Now run this command and read <xref linkend="appendix_b">.</para>
<screen>
[bash]$ lsmod
</screen>

<para>If the information from running <command>lsmod</command> appears as in <xref linkend="appendix_b">,and your <command>dmesg</command> shows the information listed above, and there are no pictures, I don't 
know what is wrong. Unfortunately, the only thing I know to do is go thru the 
whole process again. Only this time use the re-direction option <userinput>&gt;filename</userinput>
to capture the results. Post this to one of these 2 newsgroups:</para>
<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>alt.OS.Linux.mandrake</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>comp.OS.Linux.hardware</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>telling what you've done and ask for help. Include everything you can think of, the more 
information the better, and e-mail me at the same time. My address is: <ulink url="mailto:daveekelly@earthlink.net">daveekelly@earthlink.net</ulink>.</para>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Last Things Last</title>

<para>After you have got everything working correctly and working just the way you want it to, this is something you can do if you want to. Not required. You can continue to run the executable script file 
from the directory you wrote it in with the dot slash option preceding the name 
(./) or you can install it in one of the directories that hold other executable 
applications. I would recommend <filename>/usr/sbin</filename>. The command for that is:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ install file_name /usr/sbin
</screen>
</chapter>

<appendix id="appendix_a">
<title>Appendix A</title>

<sect1 id="part_1">
<title>PART 1</title>

<para>This is the way I want my picture directory to be set up. A primary 
directory <filename>picture</filename> and a sub-directory describing the content <filename>smkbot</filename>.</para>

<screen>
picture/smkbot:
dsc00117.jpg dsc00120.jpg dsc00123.jpg dsc00126.jpg dsc00129.jpg 
dsc00118.jpg dsc00121.jpg dsc00124.jpg dsc00127.jpg dsc00130.jpg 
dsc00119.jpg dsc00122.jpg dsc00125.jpg dsc00128.jpg dsc00131.jpg
</screen>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="part_2">
<title>PART 2</title>

<para>With the modified version of the script file you have the pictures 
scattered over several directories. But right now, this is what we want.</para>

<screen>
picture/trash:
camera

picture/trash/camera:
dcim mssony

picture/trash/camera/dcim:
100msdcf

picture/trash/camera/dcim/100msdcf:
dsc00357.jpg dsc00360.jpg dsc00363.jpg txt00365.gif
dsc00358.jpg dsc00361.jpg dsc00364.jpg txt00365.thm
dsc00359.jpg dsc00362.jpg dsc00366.jpg

picture/trash/camera/mssony:
imcif100

picture/trash/camera/mssony/imcif100:
dsc00364.jpg dsc00366.tif
</screen>
</sect1>
</appendix>

<appendix id="appendix_b">
<title>Appendix B</title>

<para>What we want to see here is the word usb-storage under the Used by 
column:</para>

<screen>
Module       Size      Used by
nls_iso8859-12880  0   (autoclean)
nls_cp437 4400  0   (autoclean)
sd_mod11792  0   (autoclean)
vfat 9968  0   (autoclean)
fat 32192  0  (autoclean) [vfat]
usb-storage 52528 0
scsi_mod 91072 2 [sd_mod usb-storage]
ppp_deflate 42208 0  (autoclean)
bsd_comp  4576  0  (autoclean)
ppp_async 6672  0  (autoclean)
ppp_generic 19616  0  (autoclean) [ppp_deflate bsd_comp ppp_async]
slhc 5136  0  (autoclean) [ppp_generic]
parport_pc  20240 1  (autoclean)
lp 5808  0  (autoclean)
parport  24768  1 (autoclean) [parport_pc lp]
es1371 26768  1
soundcore 4208  4 [es1371]
ac97_codec  9312  0  [es1371]
gameport  1856  0  [es1371]
af_packet  12560  0 (autoclean)
ip_vs 62000  0  (autoclean)
usb-uhci  21232  0  (unused)
usbcore  50752  1 [usb-storage usb-uhci]
rtc 5600  0  (autoclean)
</screen>
</appendix>

<appendix id="appendix_c">
<title>Appendix C</title>

<para>When you go to clean up all those test directories, use the following 
command. <emphasis>BUT BE VERY VERY CAREFUL</emphasis>:</para>

<screen>
[bash]$ rm -Rf picture/test_directory
</screen>

<para>You could lose more than you bargin for, <filename>test_directory</filename> 
should be what you entered for <envar>$DIRPATH</envar> in the scripts above. (It 
never hurts for first time user to slip over somewhere else and create a 
directory tree, copy file to it, and test this command line before using it on 
something irreplacable.) Again read the manual.</para>

</appendix>

<appendix id="gfdl">
<title>Gnu Free Documentation License</title>

<para>Version 1.1, March 2000</para>

<blockquote>
<para>Copyright (C) 2000  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
</blockquote>

<sect1 id="gfdl-0">
<title>PREAMBLE</title>

<para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook,
    or other written document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
    assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
    with or without modifying it, either commercially or
    noncommercially.  Secondarily, this License preserves for the
    author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not
    being considered responsible for modifications made by
    others.</para>

<para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that
    derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the
    same sense.  It complements the GNU General Public License, which
    is a copyleft license designed for free software.</para>

<para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals
    for free software, because free software needs free documentation:
    a free program should come with manuals providing the same
    freedoms that the software does.  But this License is not limited
    to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
    regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
    printed book.  We recommend this License principally for works
    whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-1">
<title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

<para>This License applies to any manual or other work that
    contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License.  The "Document",
    below, refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the
    public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you".</para>

<para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work
    containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
    verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
    language.</para>

<para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter
    section of the Document that deals exclusively with the
    relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
    Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains
    nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject.
    (For example, if the Document is in part a textbook of
    mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.)
    The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with
    the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
    philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
    them.</para>

<para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections
    whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections,
    in the notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

<para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that
    are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the
    notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

<para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a
    machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification
    is available to the general public, whose contents can be viewed
    and edited directly and straightforwardly with generic text
    editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs
    or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
    translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
    formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
    whose markup has been designed to thwart or discourage subsequent
    modification by readers is not Transparent.  A copy that is not
    "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>

<para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
    plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
    format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
    standard-conforming simple HTML designed for human modification.
    Opaque formats include PostScript, PDF, proprietary formats that
    can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML
    or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML produced by some word
    processors for output purposes only.</para>

<para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page
    itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly,
    the material this License requires to appear in the title page.
    For works in formats which do not have any title page as such,
    "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of
    the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
    text.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-2">
<title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

<para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium,
    either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this
    License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this
    License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and
    that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
    License.  You may not use technical measures to obstruct or
    control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
    distribute.  However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
    copies.  If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

<para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
    above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-3">
<title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

<para>If you publish printed copies of the Document numbering more
    than 100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts,
    you must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and
    legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front
    cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover.  Both covers must
    also clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these
    copies.  The front cover must present the full title with all
    words of the title equally prominent and visible.  You may add
    other material on the covers in addition.  Copying with changes
    limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the
    Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim
    copying in other respects.</para>

<para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to
    fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
    reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
    adjacent pages.</para>

<para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
    numbering more than 100, you must either include a
    machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or
    state in or with each Opaque copy a publicly-accessible
    computer-network location containing a complete Transparent copy
    of the Document, free of added material, which the general
    network-using public has access to download anonymously at no
    charge using public-standard network protocols.  If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you
    begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that
    this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
    location until at least one year after the last time you
    distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or
    retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

<para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the
    authors of the Document well before redistributing any large
    number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an
    updated version of the Document.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-4">
<title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

<para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the
    Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided
    that you release the Modified Version under precisely this
    License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the
    Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
    Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it.  In addition,
    you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
<listitem><para>Use in the Title Page
      (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from that of the
      Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if
      there were any, be listed in the History section of the
      Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version if
      the original publisher of that version gives permission.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>List on the Title Page,
      as authors, one or more persons or entities responsible for
      authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version,
      together with at least five of the principal authors of the
      Document (all of its principal authors, if it has less than
      five).</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>State on the Title page
      the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, as the
      publisher.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve all the
      copyright notices of the Document.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Add an appropriate
      copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the other
      copyright notices.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Include, immediately
      after the copyright notices, a license notice giving the public
      permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this
      License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve in that license
      notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and required Cover
      Texts given in the Document's license notice.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Include an unaltered
      copy of this License.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve the section
      entitled "History", and its title, and add to it an item stating
      at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the
      Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If there is no
      section entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating
      the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given
      on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
      Version as stated in the previous sentence.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve the network
      location, if any, given in the Document for public access to a
      Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network
      locations given in the Document for previous versions it was
      based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.  You
      may omit a network location for a work that was published at
      least four years before the Document itself, or if the original
      publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>In any section entitled
      "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", preserve the section's
      title, and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of
      each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications
      given therein.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve all the
      Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their text and
      in their titles.  Section numbers or the equivalent are not
      considered part of the section titles.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Delete any section
      entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section may not be included in
      the Modified Version.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Do not retitle any
      existing section as "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with
      any Invariant Section.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections
    or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no
    material copied from the Document, you may at your option
    designate some or all of these sections as invariant.  To do this,
    add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified
    Version's license notice.  These titles must be distinct from any
    other section titles.</para>

<para>You may add a section entitled "Endorsements", provided it
    contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by
    various parties--for example, statements of peer review or that
    the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
    definition of a standard.</para>

<para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover
    Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the
    end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one
    passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be
    added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the
    Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
    previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity
    you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
    publisher that added the old one.</para>

<para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by
    this License give permission to use their names for publicity for
    or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-5">
<title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

<para>You may combine the Document with other documents released
    under this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for
    modified versions, provided that you include in the combination
    all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original documents,
    unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your
    combined work in its license notice.</para>

<para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this
    License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced
    with a single copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with
    the same name but different contents, make the title of each such
    section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the
    name of the original author or publisher of that section if known,
    or else a unique number.  Make the same adjustment to the section
    titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of
    the combined work.</para>

<para>In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled
    "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
    entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections entitled
    "Acknowledgements", and any sections entitled "Dedications".  You
    must delete all sections entitled "Endorsements."</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-6">
<title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

<para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and
    other documents released under this License, and replace the
    individual copies of this License in the various documents with a
    single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you
    follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of
    the documents in all other respects.</para>

<para>You may extract a single document from such a collection,
    and distribute it individually under this License, provided you
    insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
    follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
    copying of that document.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-7">
<title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
<para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
    separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of
    a storage or distribution medium, does not as a whole count as a
    Modified Version of the Document, provided no compilation
    copyright is claimed for the compilation.  Such a compilation is
    called an "aggregate", and this License does not apply to the
    other self-contained works thus compiled with the Document, on
    account of their being thus compiled, if they are not themselves
    derivative works of the Document.</para>

<para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to
    these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than
    one quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts
    may be placed on covers that surround only the Document within the
    aggregate.  Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole
    aggregate.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-8">
<title>TRANSLATION</title>

<para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section
    4.  Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires
    special permission from their copyright holders, but you may
    include translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition
    to the original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may
    include a translation of this License provided that you also
    include the original English version of this License.  In case of
    a disagreement between the translation and the original English
    version of this License, the original English version will
    prevail.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-9">
<title>TERMINATION</title>
<para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the
    Document except as expressly provided for under this License.  Any
    other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the
    Document is void, and will automatically terminate your rights
    under this License.  However, parties who have received copies, or
    rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
    terminated so long as such parties remain in full
    compliance.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-10">
<title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

<para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised
    versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.
    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present
    version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or
    concerns.  See <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.</para>

<para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing
    version number.  If the Document specifies that a particular
    numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to
    it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
    either of that specified version or of any later version that has
    been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
    If the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
    you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the
    Free Software Foundation.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="gfdl-11">
<title>How to use this License for your documents</title>

<para>To use this License in a document you have written, include
    a copy of the License in the document and put the following
    copyright and license notices just after the title page:</para>

<blockquote><para>
Copyright (c)  YEAR  YOUR NAME.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
      Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".
</para></blockquote>

<para>If you have no Invariant Sections, write "with no Invariant
    Sections" instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have
    no Front-Cover Texts, write "no Front-Cover Texts" instead of
    "Front-Cover Texts being LIST"; likewise for Back-Cover
    Texts.</para>

<para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program
    code, we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
    choice of free software license, such as the GNU General Public
    License, to permit their use in free software.</para>
</sect1>
</appendix>

</book>