<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
     "http://docbook.org/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" []>

<article>

  <articleinfo>

    <title>Windows Newsreaders under Linux HOWTO</title>

     <author>
       <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
       <surname>Quintiliani</surname>
       <affiliation>
          <address><email>coredump0@mercurylink.net</email></address>
       </affiliation>
     </author>

     <pubdate>2004-02-07</pubdate>

     <!-- Most recent revision goes at the top; list in descending order -->
     <revhistory>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>2.22</revnumber>
          <date>2004-02-07</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated to say that Xnews with a Windows 98SE configuration also works with Windows ME files. Thanks to Marty Hillman &gt;mehillman@comcast.net&lt; for discovering this.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>2.21</revnumber>
          <date>2004-01-26</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated with more clear language as to what exactly would go wrong with older versions of Wine under more recent Linux setups.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>2.2</revnumber>
          <date>2004-01-24</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated to say that Wine version 20031212 might be required for more modern Linux setups, but there will be more bugs. Updated each newsreader with its respective problems under 20031212, including the fact that Dialog will not work with Wine versions greater than 20030813.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
	  <revnumber>2.11</revnumber>
          <date>2003-12-24</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated to say that Xnews event sounds work properly, and updated with instructions to get event sounds to work properly under KDE.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>2.1</revnumber>
          <date>2003-12-12</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated to cover Forte Free Agent as well as Xnews and Dialog. Added a Dialog problem.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
	  <revnumber>2.02</revnumber>
	  <date>2003-12-11</date>
	  <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
	  <revremark>Updated &quot;Window sizing problems&quot; in Xnews and added another Xnews problem. TODO updated with what the document will not cover.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>2.01</revnumber>
          <date>2003-10-24</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated with another Xnews problem and another Dialog
problem. TODO now contains other newsreaders this document will cover. 
Update &quot;Erasing sections of text&quot; Xnews problem to say that the text 
is deleted but requires the Rewrap button to be pressed to fix it, as well as 
that it affects KDE also. Updated to say that Wine 20030813 is required, 
since later versions seem to cause problems.
</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
          <date>2003-09-16</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Updated with new name 
&quot;Windows-Newsreaders-under-Linux-HOWTO,&quot; since the document now
discusses configuration and use of 40tude Dialog as well. Windows XP 
instructions updated for Xnews. Problems and Issues for Xnews updated. 
Acknowledgements updated. Xnews copying instructions updated for clarity. 
Xnews copying section renamed. Prerequisites updated to say that the standard 
unzip program might be necessary.</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>    
          <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
          <date>2003-09-07</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
      <revremark>Updated with more Problems and Issues, including binary usage.
Updated with more DLL files to copy and configure (when using a Windows 98SE 
configuration) for better results. Updated to say that a Windows 98SE 
configuration is preferred, since there are some problems with Windows XP 
&quot;emulation.&quot;
</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
          <date>2003-09-01</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>initial LDP release, some updates</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>0.12</revnumber>
          <date>2003-08-31</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>conversion to XML (thanks to Greg Ferguson), various 
updates </revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>0.11</revnumber>
          <date>2003-08-22</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>various updates
          </revremark>
       </revision>
     </revhistory>

     <!-- Provide a good abstract; a couple of sentences is sufficient -->
     <abstract>
        <para>
This document describes how to set up and use several different Windows Usenet 
newsreaders under the Linux operating system using the Wine 
&quot;emulator.&quot; This document was formerly known as the Xnews under 
Linux HOWTO. 
        </para>
        <para>
The latest version of this document is always available at 
<ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/core_dump_000/Windows-Newsreaders-under-Linux-HOWTO.xml">
http://www.geocities.com/core_dump_000/Windows-Newsreaders-under-Linux-HOWTO.xml</ulink>
       </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>

<sect1 id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
One of the problems with Linux today is the lack of variety and choice in 
newsreader software, where Windows has several newsreader programs with better
features and better stability. Under Windows, three of the most popular 
newsreaders are Xnews, Dialog, and Free Agent.
</para>
<para>
Xnews, created by Luu Tran, is a freeware newsreader for Windows,
available from the website
<ulink url="http://xnews.newsguy.com/">http://xnews.newsguy.com</ulink>. Here 
is a list of Xnews' features listed on the website:
</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     100% GNKSA 2.0 (Good Net Keeping Seal of Approval) compliant.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Plonk file (aka bozo bin).
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Quick filter (type in a regex and only articles whose
     subject/author match it will be shown).
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Score file for advanced filtering.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Support for multiple servers/identities.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Subscribed groups can be organized into categories.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Remappable keyboard.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Binaries handling (mime, base64, uuencode, what have you).
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Optional header and article caching; plus: folders for permanent
     archival.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     more...
     </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>
Unfortunately, Luu Tran has decided neither to make his newsreader
open-source nor to release a Linux version. However, there is a way to get
Xnews to work under Linux, although it takes a bit of work.
</para>

<para>
Dialog is a newsreader by 40tude. It is available at
<ulink url="http://www.40tude.com/dialog/">http://www.40tude.com/dialog/</ulink>.
According to the website, &quot;it supports multiple servers and identities, has
filtering/scoring support, integrated email functionality and binary support
including support for multiparts.&quot; The newsreader is &quot;shareware for
commercial users and freeware for private users.&quot; It works excellently
under Linux. 
</para>

<para>
Free Agent is the feature-slimmed freeware version of Forte's commercial 
e-mail and Usenet client Agent. It is available at
<ulink url="http://www.forteinc.com/agent">http://www.forteinc.com/agent/</ulink>.
According to the Features section of the website, the program has basic
newsreader functions, message threading, multi-part binaries, translations,
internal multi-tasking, and URL detection. It also has partial support for
offline data storage, group properties, UI configuration, searching, and
sorting. It runs with few problems under Linux after almost no extra 
configuration, except under Wine versions later than 20030813. 
</para>

<sect2 id="prereqs">
<title>Prerequisites</title>

<para>
This HOWTO assumes that:
</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para>
The InfoZIP utilities are installed on the Linux machine. These are available
at <ulink url="http://www.info-zip.org/pub/infozip/">InfoZIP's web site.</ulink>
The unzip program is required if the reader wants to install Xnews or Dialog 
without copying from an existing installation. This is a standard part 
of most Linux distributions, but may not be automatically installed.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
The Wine "emulator" is installed properly on the Linux machine. To
download Wine, visit 
<ulink url="http://www.winehq.com/">http://www.winehq.com</ulink>. 
The version used at the
time of this writing was 20031212.
UPDATE (version 2.01): Wine versions later than 20030813 will not work. 
UPDATE (version 2.2): Wine version 20031212 may be required under more modern 
Linux setups. There are more problems with this version, and Dialog will not
work, but older Wine versions will not &quot;emulate&quot; properly without it 
and will cause a crash upon trying to access NNTP servers. Try 20030813 first,
and then try version 20031212 if you have problems.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
The reader of this document has access to a Windows machine. Certain files are 
needed from the Windows operating system. Access to Windows 98SE is preferred. 
This HOWTO covers Windows 98SE and Windows XP. Windows ME files will also work
when running Xnews if a Windows 98SE configuration is used.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
Xnews stable version 5.04.25 is used (the beta version was not
tested at the time of this writing). The website for Xnews is
<ulink url="http://xnews.newsguy.com/">http://xnews.newsguy.com/</ulink>
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
Dialog version 2.0 Beta 28 is used. The website for Dialog is
<ulink url="http://www.40tude.com/dialog/">http://www.40tude.com/dialog/</ulink>
Note that Wine versions greater than 20030813 will not work with Dialog.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
Free Agent version 1.xx is being used. The website for Free Agent is
<ulink url="http://www.forteinc.com/agent/">http://www.forteinc.com/agent/</ulink>
     </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  </para>
</sect2>
 

  <!-- Legal Sections -->
  <sect2 id="copyright">
    <title>Copyright and License</title>

    <!-- The LDP recommends, but doesn't require, the GFDL --> 
    <para>
     This document, <emphasis>Windows Newsreaders under Linux HOWTO</emphasis>,
     is copyrighted (C) 2003 by <emphasis>Daniel Quintiliani</emphasis>.
     Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
     document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
     License, Version 1.2 or any later version published
     by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections,
     with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts.
     A copy of the license is available at
     <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">
     http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
     Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="disclaimer">
    <title>Disclaimer</title>

    <para>
     No liability for the contents of this document can be accepted.
     Use the concepts, examples and information at your own risk.
     There may be errors and inaccuracies that could be damaging to
     your system, although any damage is highly unlikely.  Proceed with 
     caution; the author(s) do not take any responsibility.
    </para>

    <para>
     All copyrights are held by their by their respective owners,
     unless specifically noted otherwise.  Use of a term in this
     document should not be regarded as affecting the validity of any
     trademark or service mark.  Naming of particular products or
     brands should not be seen as endorsements.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="TODO">
    <title>TODO for this document</title>
    
    <para>
    This document may eventually contain:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This document may be expanded to cover other Windows newsreaders
          such as MicroPlanet Gravity.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
    This document will not cover the following newsreaders: XanaNews (I cannot
    get this to work) and newsreaders included in web browsers (Outlook Express,
    Netscape/Mozilla Mail and News, etc)
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="Xnews">
<title>Xnews</title>

<sect2 id="x-setup">
<title>Setting up Xnews</title>

<sect3>
<title>Configuring Wine for Xnews</title>

<para>
Wine is capable of &quot;emulating&quot; many different versions of Windows. 
Wine is not perfect, however; it runs slower than a normal Windows installation
and it is not a stable product. Certain problems occur when running Xnews; 
these are discussed in the 
&quot;<link linkend="x-problems" endterm="x-problems.title"/>&quot; section of 
the document.
</para>

<para>
Before Xnews can run under Linux, certain files from a Windows installation 
need to be copied to the Xnews root directory. Depending on which version of 
Windows you have access to, there will be different files to copy and different
instructions for configuring Wine. This document currently covers a Windows 
98SE/Windows ME and a Windows XP configuration. A Windows 98SE/Windows ME 
configuration is preferred, since there are some more problems with a Windows 
XP configuration. Below are the instructions describing how to configure Wine 
for Xnews.
</para>

<sect4>
<title>Windows 98SE / Windows ME</title>

<para>
If you have access to a Windows 98SE or Windows ME machine, you must set up 
the Wine configuration file (found at <filename>$HOME/.wine/config</filename>) 
according to these instructions.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in the 
<filename>.wine/config</filename> file, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>win98</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;win98&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Second, update the &quot;<literal>DllOverrides</literal>&quot; section
which will tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather than Wine.
<screen>
     [DllOverrides]
     ; some dlls you may want to change
     &quot;shell&quot;        = &quot;native, builtin&quot;
     &quot;shell32&quot;      = &quot;native, builtin&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Third, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot; 
section which will also tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather 
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\Xnews.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;commctrl.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;comctl32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;shell.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;shell32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;comdlg32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Windows XP</title>

<para>
If you have access to a Windows XP machine, you must set up the Wine 
configuration file (found at <filename>$HOME/.wine/config</filename>) according
to these instructions.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in the 
<filename>.wine/config</filename> file, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>win98</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;win98&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Second, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot; 
section which will tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather 
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\Xnews.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;comctl32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched20.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Copying and/or Extracting Required Files</title>

<para>
Several DLL files must first be copied to the root Xnews directory from
an existing Windows installation.
</para>

<para>
If Xnews lies on a Windows partition on the same machine, you must copy the DLL
files to the Xnews root directory. Xnews will be run from this directory 
on the Windows partition.
</para>

<para>
If Xnews is being run on a Linux-only machine, you must download Xnews to
your fake C drive (usually <filename>$HOME/c</filename>) and extract it
into a directory there. Open up a terminal window, navigate to your fake C
drive, and type the following commands:
<screen>
     mkdir Xnews
     mv xnews.zip Xnews
     cd Xnews
     unzip xnews.zip
</screen>
Alternatively, you may copy an existing Xnews folder to your fake C drive. The
root Xnews directory must include the DLL files mentioned in the following 
subsections.
</para>

<sect4>
<title>Windows 98SE</title>
<para>
If you have access to a Windows 98SE machine, copy the files 
<filename>commctrl.dll</filename>, <filename>comctl32.dll</filename>,
<filename>riched32.dll</filename>, <filename>comdlg32.dll</filename>,
<filename>shell.dll</filename>, and <filename>shell32.dll</filename> 
(usually in <filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM</filename>) to the root Xnews directory.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Windows XP</title>
<para>
If you have access to a Windows XP machine, copy the files 
<filename>comctl32.dll</filename>, <filename>riched20.dll</filename>,
and <filename>riched32.dll</filename> (usually in 
<filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM32</filename>) to the root Xnews directory.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="run_xnews">
<title>Running Xnews</title>

<para>
Using a terminal window, navigate to the root Xnews directory and type:
<screen>
     wine Xnews.exe
</screen>
</para>
<para>
Use Xnews normally, noting the exceptions in the next section, entitled
&quot;<link linkend="x-problems" endterm="x-problems.title"/>&quot; 
Note that these are problems with Wine's &quot;emulation,&quot; not
Xnews.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="x-problems">
<title id="x-problems.title">Problems and Issues</title>

<sect3>
<title>Fixed-width fonts and alt.ascii-art</title>
<para>
ASCII art requires fixed-width fonts to view. Clicking the fixed font button 
above the message headers will simply lock the message so that the vertical 
scrollbar will not work.
</para>
<para>
The easiest way to deal with this is to go into
&quot;Special -&gt; Setup Xnews -&gt; Fonts and Colors&quot;
and select a fixed font for all types
of text. The default &quot;Fixed&quot; will not work; 
use &quot;Misc Fixed&quot;, size 12.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Erasing sections of text</title>
<para>
Selecting sections of text with the mouse and pressing Backspace or Delete
will delete the text from the screen, but for some reason it might still look 
like it's there when the message is sent or posted.
</para>
<para>
To solve this problem, press the "Rewrap" button below the message headers.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Window sizing problems</title>
<para>
There are several problems relating to the sizing of the windows. When the
CatchUp button is clicked, the main groups list window shrinks and must be
maximized. These are mostly minor annoyances, except...
</para>

<sect4>
<title>Closing Xnews</title>
<para>
Depending on the window manager (Sawfish has problems with this), it may be 
impossible to close the Xnews window, and there is no &quot;Exit&quot; option 
in the main menu. To get around this, make sure that the window is sized so 
that the terminal used to launch Xnews is accessible, and close that
terminal.  Do not press 
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>, 
etc as this will cause problems. Be
sure to click the Save button to save the newsrc first.

</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Binary newsgroups</title>
<para>
The posting of binaries to newsgroups does not currently work. An attempted
post will lock at 1% completion and give an error message when the post is
aborted, posting only the text portion of the message. However, the combining
and decoding of binaries works with no problems at all.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Text on some tabs are indented</title>
<para>
If Windows XP is &quot;emulated,&quot; certain tabs will have text indented,
leaving some of it out of visibility. The solution is to use Windows 98SE files
instead of XP files. It isn't that important. UPDATED: Version 2.0 of this
document includes new instructions which solve this problem when Windows XP
files are used.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>No sample text in font selection dialog</title>
<para>
If Windows XP is &quot;emulated,&quot; the font selection dialog will not show
sample text. According to a
<ulink url="http://www.winehq.com/hypermail/wine-devel/2003/07/0476.html">Wine
mailing list message</ulink>, there are certain un-&quot;emulated&quot; 
functions in Windows XP &quot;emulation.&quot; Version 1.1 of this document was
updated with new files to copy and configure when using Windows 98SE 
&quot;emulation&quot; in order to solve this problem. Until the Wine developers
implement these Windows XP functions, use a Windows 98SE configuration to get 
around this issue. If a Windows 98SE computer is not available, just apply 
changes and look at the main window.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Web links can not be executed</title>
<para>
Web links can not be executed from within the Xnews message window. This is
pretty obvious as there is no integrated Web browser in Wine. However, Wine's
clipboard works with no problem. Select the link and copy and paste into an open
web browser window.
</para>

<sect4>
<title>Web link doesn't always copy</title>
<para>
When you try and copy a Web link to the clipboard, it may not copy. This
occurs when the link as a whole is copied rather than selected text. The
solution to this is to make sure that as you are selecting the text, the rest
of the link is not automatically selected. If this continues, select the blank
space before the link and copy with the preceding blank space.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Sound does not work</title>
<para>
Event sounds in Xnews do not currently work. Updated instructions for this may 
be included in future versions of this document. 
</para>
<para>
UPDATED (version 2.11): Event sounds work properly. If you run KDE, you first 
need to turn off the aRts soundserver by going into Settings -&gt; Control 
Center -&gt; Sounds &amp; Multimedia -&gt; Sound System and unchecking 
&quot;Start aRts soundserver on KDE Startup&quot; (instructions were tested on 
version 3.1.3; may be different for other versions). Note that this will 
disable event sounds for KDE applications which depend on the aRts soundserver.
Xnews sounds work properly under the Gnome sound server.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>&quot;Compose&quot; message body does not automatically wrap</title>
<para>
In some cases, the message body of a Compose window does not automatically
wrap. Simply clicking &quot;Rewrap Text&quot; as this happens will fix the
problem.
</para>
</sect3> 

<sect3>
<title>XFaces are not visible</title>
<para>
When a Wine version greater than 20030813 is being used, the XFace is not
visible when a message is being composed or read, and the box where the XFace 
would be is colored black. Ignore this, since the correct XFace is being posted
anyway. Try to use Wine version 20030813 if you can.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="Dialog">
<title>Dialog</title>
<sect2 id="d-setup">
<title>Setting up Dialog</title>

<sect3>
<title>Configuring Wine for Dialog</title>

<para>
Wine is capable of &quot;emulating&quot; many different versions of Windows.
Wine is not perfect, however; it runs slower than a normal Windows installation
and it is not a stable product. Certain problems occur when running Dialog;
these are discussed in the
&quot;<link linkend="d-problems" endterm="d-problems.title"/>&quot; section of 
the document. Note that Wine versions greater than 20030813 will not
&quot;emulate&quot; Dialog properly. 
</para>

<para>
Before Dialog or its installer can run under Linux, certain files from a 
Windows installation need to be copied to the directory containing Dialog's
installer, and after installation, Dialog's root directory. Depending 
on which version of Windows the reader of this document has access to, there 
will be different files to copy and different instructions for configuring 
Wine. This document currently covers a Windows 98SE and a Windows XP 
configuration. Below are the instructions describing how to configure Wine for 
Dialog.
</para>

<sect4>
<title>Windows 98SE</title>

<para>
If you have access to a Windows 98SE machine, the Wine configuration file 
(found at <filename>$HOME/.wine/config</filename>) must be set up
according to these instructions.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in the
<filename>.wine/config</filename> file, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>win98</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;win98&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Next, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot;
section which will also tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\dialog.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;commctrl.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;comctl32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Windows XP</title>

<para>
If you have access to a Windows XP machine, you must set up the Wine
configuration file (found at <filename>$HOME/.wine/config</filename>) according
to these instructions.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in the
<filename>.wine/config</filename> file, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>win98</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;win98&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Second, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot;
section which will tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\dialog.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;comctl32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched20.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Copying and/or Installing Required Files</title>

<para>
Several DLL files must first be copied to the root Dialog directory from
an existing Windows installation.
</para>

<para>
If Dialog lies on a Windows partition on the same machine, you must copy the DLL
files to the Dialog root directory. Dialog will be run from this directory
on the Windows partition.
</para>

<para>
If Dialog is being run on a Linux-only machine, you must download Dialog to
your fake C drive (usually <filename>$HOME/c</filename>). You must then use 
the supplied installer according to the instructions in the subsection below 
entitled &quot;<link linkend="d-installer" endterm="d-installer.title"/>.&quot;
Alternatively, you may copy an existing Dialog folder to your fake
C drive. The root Dialog directory must include the DLL files mentioned in the 
following subsections.
</para>

<sect4 id="d-installer">
<title id="d-installer.title">Using the Installer</title>

<para>
To extract the archive which contains the Dialog installer, open up a terminal
window, navigate to your fake C drive (where Dialog was downloaded to) and type:
<screen>
     unzip 40td2b28.zip
</screen>
The name of the file may be different depending on the version of Dialog 
downloaded.
</para>

<para>
In order for the installer to work correctly, certain DLL files from Windows
need to be copied to the directory where the installer is located. If you
have access to a Windows 98SE machine, copy the file 
<filename>riched32.dll</filename> to your fake C drive. If you have access to
a Windows XP machine, copy the files <filename>riched20.dll</filename> and
<filename>riched32.dll</filename> to your fake C drive. 
</para>

<para>
Finally, to install Dialog, open up a terminal window, navigate to your fake
C drive, and type:
<screen>
     wine SETUP.EXE
</screen>
Installation of Dialog should work fine from here. Be sure to copy the DLL
files mentioned in the rest of this section to your Dialog root directory
before running the program.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Copying required files - Windows 98SE</title>
<para>
If you have access to a Windows 98SE machine, copy the files
<filename>commctrl.dll</filename>, <filename>comctl32.dll</filename>,
and <filename>riched32.dll</filename> (usually in 
<filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM\</filename>) to your root Dialog directory.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Copying required files - Windows XP</title>
<para>
If you have access to a Windows XP machine, copy the files
<filename>comctl32.dll</filename>, <filename>riched20.dll</filename>,
and <filename>riched32.dll</filename> (usually in
<filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM32\</filename> to your root Dialog directory.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="run_dialog">
<title>Running Dialog</title>
<para>
Using a terminal window, navigate to the root Dialog directory and type:
<screen>
     wine dialog.exe
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Use Dialog normally, noting the exceptions in the next section, entitled
&quot;<link linkend="d-problems" endterm="d-problems.title"/>&quot;
Note that these are problems with Wine's &quot;emulation,&quot; not
Dialog.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="d-problems">
<title id="d-problems.title">Problems and Issues</title>

<sect3>
<title>Dragging the vertical scrollbar's placeholder doesn't work</title>
<para>
Dragging the vertical scrollbar's placeholder within the message list will
cause it to bounce back to its original position. To get around this, hold 
down the mouse at the down arrow of the scrollbar, or use your mouse's wheel
if it has one.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Strange error message about fontinfo.dat</title>
<para>
You may occasionally get an error message about the file 
<filename>fontinfo.dat</filename> needing
to be rebuilt. Ignore this, as it doesn't seem to affect the program in any
way.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Window sizing problems</title>
<para>
Depending on the window manager used, the window may need to be re-maximized
after switching to another window. Other sizing problems might be present
as well.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Fixed-width fonts and alt.ascii-art</title>
<para>
ASCII art requires fixed-width fonts to view. Only the font &quot;Misc
Fixed&quot; will work.
</para>

<para>
To change the font, go into Settings -&quot; General Settings -&quot; 
Fonts/Colors. Change the &quot;Bodies (monospaced)&quot; font to &quot;Misc
Fixed.&quot;
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="agent">
<title>Free Agent</title>

<sect2 id="a-setup">
<title>Setting up Free Agent</title>

<sect3>
<title>Configuring Wine for Free Agent</title>

<para>
Wine is capable of &quot;emulating&quot; many different versions of Windows.
Wine is not perfect, however; it runs slower than a normal Windows installation
and it is not a stable product. Certain problems occur when running Free Agent;
these are discussed in the 
&quot;<link linkend="a-problems" endterm="a-problems.title"/>&quot; section of
the document.
</para>

<para>
Before Free Agent can be run under Linux, a certain file from a Windows 
installation need to be copied to Free Agent's root directory. The 
instructions are similar for both Windows 98SE and Windows XP configurations. 
Below are the instructions describing how to configure Wine for Free Agent.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in the
<filename>.wine/config</filename> file, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>win98</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;win98&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Next, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot;
section which will also tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\agent.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;comdlg32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Copying and/or Installing Required Files</title>

<para>
Several DLL files must first be copied to the root Free Agent directory from
an existing Windows installation.
</para>

<para>
If Free Agent lies on a Windows partition on the same machine, you must copy
the DLL files to the Free Agent root directory. Free Agent will be run from
this directory on the Windows partition.
</para>

<para>
If Free Agent is being run on a Linux-only machine, you must download Free
Agent to your fake C drive (usually <filename>$HOME/c</filename>). You must 
then use the supplied installer according to the instructions in the 
subsection below entitled 
&quot;<link linkend="a-installer" endterm="a-installer.title"/>.&quot;
Alternatively, you may copy an existing Free Agent folder to your fake
C drive. The root Free Agent directory must include the DLL files mentioned in 
the following subsections.
</para>

<sect4 id="a-installer">
<title id="a-installer.title">Using the Installer</title>

<para>
To install Free Agent, simply download the installer to your fake C drive,
open up a terminal window, navigate to your fake C drive, and type:
<screen>
     wine <literal>installer</literal>.exe
</screen>
(where <literal>installer</literal> is the name of the installer). Installation
should work fine from here. Be sure to copy the DLL files mentioned in the rest
of this section to your Free Agent root directory before running the program.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4>
<title>Copying required files</title>
<para>
The Windows DLL file <filename>comdlg32.dll</filename> needs to be copied to 
the Free Agent root directory. Under Windows 98SE, the file is usually located 
in <filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM\</filename>. Under Windows XP, the file is 
usually located in <filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM32\</filename>.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="run_agent">
<title>Running Free Agent</title>
<para>
Using a terminal window, navigate to the root Free Agent directory and type:
<screen>
     wine agent.exe
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Use Free Agent normally, noting the exceptions in the next section, entitled
&quot;<link linkend="a-problems" endterm="a-problems.title"/>&quot;
Note that these are problems with Wine's &quot;emulation,&quot; not
Free Agent.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="a-problems">
<title id="a-problems.title">Problems and Issues</title>

<sect3>
<title>Fixed-width fonts and alt.ascii-art</title>
<para>
ASCII art requires fixed-width fonts to view. Only the font &quot;Misc
Fixed&quot; will work.
</para>

<para>
To change the font, go into Options -&gt; Display Preferences -&gt; Fonts -&gt;
Fixed-Pitch Body. Make sure the font &quot;Misc Fixed&quot; is being used.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Cannot post binaries</title>
<para>
If a Wine version greater than 20030813 is being used, an attempt to add an
attachment to a message will not open a file dialog box. Try to use Wine version
20030813 whenever possible.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Cannot save messages or binary attachments</title>
<para>
If a Wine version greater than 20030813 is being used, an attempt to save a 
message or binary attachment will not open a file dialog box. Try to use Wine 
version 20030813 whenever possible.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="ack">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>
First of all, I'd like to thank the creators of these newsreaders for keeping
Usenet alive. Hopefully they will release their products open-source. 
</para>

<para>
I'd also like to thank Vancouverite and the other people in the 
<ulink url="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=65884">Gentoo forum
message</ulink> who described how to
run Xnews under Wine using Windows 98SE files. I built this whole HOWTO on
that information. 
</para>

<para>
I'd like to thank Greg Ferguson, Tabatha Marshall, and Mark Garboden of the 
Linux Documentation Project for helping me submit my first HOWTO. Greg Ferguson
translated my first document from plain text to XML.
</para>

<para>
Also, thanks go out to the people in news.software.readers for working with
me on this HOWTO, and to Usenet users everywhere for keeping the protocol
alive in the midst of ad-filled, license-binding, scattered Web forums.
</para>
</sect1>

</article>

