<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<book>

<bookinfo>
    <title>ATI R200 + XFree86 4.x mini-HOWTO</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>H&aring;vard</firstname><surname>Stranden</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<address><email>havarden@cloudchaser.net</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>2003-09-21</pubdate>
    <revhistory id="revhistory">
	 <revision>
		 <revnumber>1.3.1</revnumber>
		 <date>2003-09-21</date>
		 <authorinitials>HS</authorinitials>
		 <revremark>Alternative 2 updated, minor errors corrected.</revremark>
	 </revision>
	 <revision>
		 <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
		 <date>2003-07-27</date>
		 <authorinitials>HS</authorinitials>
		 <revremark>Aternative 2 no longer deprecated. Several updates to this alternative.</revremark>
	 </revision>
	 <revision>
		 <revnumber>1.2.1</revnumber>
		 <date>2003-07-15</date>
		 <authorinitials>HS</authorinitials>
		 <revremark>Date fixes.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
	<date>2003-07-14</date>
	<authorinitials>HS</authorinitials>
	<revremark>General update + alternative 5. Alternative 2 deprecated.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>2002-09-30</date>
	<authorinitials>tab</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Reviewed by LDP</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2002-09-12</date>
	<authorinitials>HS</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial release</revremark>
      </revision>
</revhistory>

<abstract>
<para>This HOWTO is for anyone who owns an ATI Radeon 8xxx graphics card and wants it to
function in a certain way or, in general, properly with XFree86, the X Window System. 
It describes the procedure of making XFree 4.x run on an ATI R200
(Radeon 8xxx series). There are several ways of doing this, with various
results (further described below). If you know of any other ways (maybe
better as well) of achieving the goal of this document, please let me know.</para>
</abstract>
</bookinfo>

<toc></toc>

<chapter id="copyright">
<title>Copyright &amp; License</title>

<para>Copyright (c) 2002,2003  H&aring;vard Stranden</para>

<para>
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no 
      Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in <xref linkend="gfdl" />, 
      entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
</para>
</chapter>

<chapter id="sysreq">
<title>System Requirements</title>

<para>For this HOWTO to apply to you, you'll need the following hardware/software
up and running:</para>

<para>Hardware</para>
<itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>ATI R200 (Radeon 8xxx) based AGP card</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Software</para>
<itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Linux kernel 2.4.x (check with <userinput>uname -r</userinput>)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Glibc 2.2 (check with <userinput>/lib/libc.so.X</userinput> where X is a decimal number)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>XFree86 4.2.x for alternative 1 (check with <userinput>X -version</userinput>)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>XFree86 4.1.x for alternatives 2, 3 and 5 (check with <userinput>X -version</userinput>)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>XFree86 4.x for alternative 4 (check with <userinput>X -version</userinput>)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<important>
<para>If you run XFree86 4.1.x/4.0.x on your computer, you can NOT use alternative 1, as shown above.  Of course you can try it, but it won't work (or at least it didn't for me).  Also, if you read <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/">The XFree86 Project</ulink>'s <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/4.1.0/RELNOTES.html">release notes</ulink> for XFree 4.1.x, you'll see that the R200 chipset is not listed as a supported chipset for the <filename class="libraryfile">radeon_drv.o</filename> driver, which means that the Radeon 8xxx is NOT supported. However, if you read the <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/4.2.0/RELNOTES.html">release notes</ulink> for XFree 4.2.x, you'll see that the chipset IS supported by the same driver.</para>
</important>

<para>Once you have met the system requirements, it's time to decide which of
the available alternatives to choose.</para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="alternatives">
<title>The alternatives</title>

<para>As you could see in <xref linkend="sysreq" />, the alternatives you can
choose may be limited by the XFree86 version you are running.
It is very important that you check the dependencies first. If you don't meet
the requirements, this HOWTO will not apply to you, and you may and probably will
suffer a system crash if proceeding.</para>

<para>The various alternatives of this HOWTO will give variable results. I haven't
tested every possible use of the card, but I have had a few experiences, and the drivers
also provide some information.</para>

<sect1 id="alt1">
<title>Experiences with XFree86's driver</title>
<para>This alternative is by far the simplest and safest way to set up your Radeon if you
use XFree86. The bad news is that this driver only supports 2D (meaning DRI won't work).</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="alt2">
<title>Experiences with ATI's own driver</title>
<para>This alternative uses ATIs own drivers for the Linux operating system. The drivers are developed by 3rd party Linux developers for ATI. The driver supports some 3D acceleration, and works almost "out of the box".</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="alt3">
<title>Experiences with DRI's driver</title>
<para>This alternative seemed like a good idea after running tired on the DRI problems
with both previous driver alternatives. DRI is the 3D part of XFree86, and is an independent
project, releasing it's own drivers. XFree86 has DRI implemented, but the drivers aren't the
same. In fact, DRI has developed their own driver specifically for the R200 chipset, meaning
it is a driver that supports 3D and works fine with X. Still, the driver supports hardly any 
of the later GL extensions, meaning more recent games like UT2003 won't run with it.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="alt4">
<title>Experiences with the GATOS project's driver</title>
<para>This alternative is a 3rd party alternative, meaning it can result
in a much more unstable (and possibly damaged) system. I found this alternative to work rather well.
The 3D support was equivalent with that of DRI (at least when I tried it), meaning this and the DRI
alternative are almost equivalent.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="alt5">
<title>Thoughts on Schneider Digital's driver</title>
<para>This alternative is another 3rd party alternative, but this one's rather good. 
<ulink url="http://www.schneider-digital.de/">Schneider Digital</ulink> provides drivers for various 
cards, among them <ulink url="http://www.schneider-digital.de/html/download_ati.html">ATI R200/R300</ulink>. The drivers are made for XFree 4.1+, and seem rather well developed.
Note though that I haven't yet tried these drivers myself, but I still thinkt they look like a very 
decent alternative.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="choice_rec">
<title>Still Haven't Chosen One?</title>
<para>I'd recommend you to use the DRI driver. I've had great experiences with this driver, although 
its GL support is somewhat narrow. If a more worthy 3D system is what you want,
I'd recommend you to make the upgrades necesseary and go for Schneider Digitals driver or XFree86's 
own driver, but please give me some feedback if you do.</para>

<para>Now that you've been given the information you need to choose a driver, choose one and move on!</para>

</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter id="instructions">
<title>Step-by-step instructions</title>

<sect1 id="using_xf_driver">
<title>Alternative 1: Using XFree86's Radeon driver</title>

<para>This alternative requires XFree 4.2 or later, and the installation or upgrade to this version is beyond the scope of this HOWTO (visit <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/">The XFree86 Project</ulink> for further information on how to upgrade or install XFree86). When XFree is installed and/or upgraded to the correct version, all you need to do is configure it. There are two ways of doing this that apply to all Linux distributions. You can either run <command>xf86onfig</command>, which is XFree86's own text-based configuration tool, or you can edit the configuration file by hand. Keep in mind that this HOWTO only describes how to configure the Radeon card, and XFree86 needs a lot more configuration than that to work.</para>

<para>If you choose to run <command>xf86config</command>, you will sooner or later come to the question, <quote>Do you want to look at the card database? (y/n)</quote>. Answer <userinput>y</userinput> (yes), and press <userinput>ENTER</userinput>.  Choose one of the cards that use the <literal>ati</literal> driver by keying in the number to its left and then pressing <userinput>ENTER</userinput>. Which card you choose does not matter, as long as you choose a card that runs the <literal>ati</literal> driver. You will then be asked to give an identifier string for your card. You can type anything you want, but I recommend you type something descriptive, such as <quote>Radeon card</quote>. Finish the configuration process.</para>

<para>If you want to edit the configuration file manually, locate it (usually <filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config</filename>), and open it in your favorite editor. Find the place that  says <literal>Section "Device"</literal>. In this section, there should be a line saying <literal>Driver "somedrivername"</literal>. Edit this line so it says <literal>Driver "ati"</literal>. Comment out all other lines in the Device section (add a # in front of them). Your device section should now look like this:
</para>

<screen>
Section "Driver"
Identifier "some_identifier" (the identifier is your choice, but if you edit it, 
make sure you update  every reference to it in the config file).
Driver "ati"

# ... 
# ...
</screen>

<para>You are now ready to run!</para>

<para>Configure the rest of XFree86, and you're ready to run!</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="using_ati_driver">
<title>Alternative 2: Using ATI's own R200 Driver</title>

<para>ATI's R200 driver comes in three distributions - one for XFree4.1, one for XFree4.2 and one for XFree4.3. You can download ATIs driver from <ulink url="http://mirror.ati.com/support/drivers/linux/radeon-linux.html">here</ulink>. Sadly, for those of us who do not use a RedHat-based or other RPM-supporting distribution, the package is only available in RPM format. For those of us who do not have RPM support, <literal>alien</literal> is the program to use. Alien converts between various package formats. To convert the ATI driver package to a <filename>.deb</filename> package, use <command>alien --to-deb packagename.rpm</command>. To convert it to a <filename>.tgz</filename> package, use <command>alien --to-tgz packagename.rpm</command>.</para>

<para>You are now ready to install the driver. To install it, use:</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para><command>rpm -i --force /path/to/packagename.rpm</command>, if you are installing the rpm package</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><command>dpkg -i --force-overwrite /path/to/packagename.deb</command>, if you made a .deb package</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><command>cd / &amp;&amp; tar zxvf /path/to/packagename.tgz</command>, if you made a .tgz package.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>You are now ready to configure the driver. To install it, issue the following commands as root:</para>

<screen>
cd /lib/modules/fglr200/build_mod/
./make.sh
cd /lib/modules/fglr200/
./make_install.sh
</screen>

<para>The driver is now ready for use.</para>

<important><para>The driver will not load unless you tell your Linux system to load it every time
at startup. To do this, you must find out where to tell your Linux which modules to load at startup. In Debian, you must add the followng line to <filename>/etc/modules</filename>:</para>
<screen>
fglr200
</screen>

<para>Add the line to the end of the file. You are now ready to configure XFree86.</para>
</important>

<para>XFree86 can be configured in two ways:  either by running <command>fglrxconfig</command> (supplied by the ATI driver), or by editing the <filename>XF86Config</filename> file manually.</para>

<para>If you choose to run <command>fglrxconfig</command>, the process is similar to a regular <command>xf86config</command> run, except for the choice of which screen card driver to use (which will automatically be set to the ATI Radeon driver).</para>

<para>If you want to edit the configuration file manually, locate it (usually <filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config</filename>), and open it in your favorite editor. Find the place saying <literal>Section "Device"</literal>. In this section, there should be a line saying <literal>Driver "somedrivername"</literal>. Edit this line so it says <literal>Driver "fglr200"</literal> and add the following lines right below that line: </para>

<screen>
Option "no_accel" "no"
Option "no_dri" "no"
Option "overlay" "off"
</screen>

<para>Comment out all other lines in the Device section (add a # in front of them). Your device section should now look like this:</para>

<screen>
Section "Driver"
Identifier "some_identifier" (the identifier is your choice, but if you edit it, 
make sure you update every reference to it in the config file).
Driver "fglr200"
Option "no_accel" "no"
Option "no_dri" "no"
Option "overlay" "no"

# ... 
# ...

</screen>

<para>You are now ready to run!</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="using_dri_driver">
<title>Alternative 3: Using DRI's Latest Radeon Driver</title>

<para>The first thing you must do is to download the driver. You can download it from <ulink url="http://dri.sourceforge.net/download.phtml">here</ulink> (make sure you download the <filename>r200-XXXXXXXX-i386.tar.bz2</filename> package). After you have downloaded the driver, go to the directory you saved it in and type <command>tar jxvf packagename.tar.bz2</command>.  Go to the new directory, (<command>cd dripkg/</command>), and type <command>./install.sh</command>. This will install the driver for you. You are now ready to configure XFree86, either by running <command>xf86config</command> or by editing the config file manually. The configuration process is exactly the same as in <xref linkend="using_xf_driver" />, so just follow the configuration steps there.</para>

<para>You are now ready to run XFree86!</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="using_gatos_drivers">
<title>Alternative 4: Using the GATOS Project's Latest Driver</title>

<para>The GATOS project is an independent developer team. They develop drivers and utilities for ATI cards. To install their driver with DRI-support, you need to download it from <ulink url="http://gatos.sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=12629">here</ulink>. Download the <filename>ati.2</filename> file for your appropriate XFree86 version. You also need a set of files to enable dri support. These files are called the drm-kernel module. They can only be downloaded from CVS. To download them, issue the following commands:</para>

<screen>
cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.gatos.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/gatos login
cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.gatos.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/gatos co drm-kernel
</screen>

<para>You are now ready to install the driver. Type the following commands to install it:</para>

<screen>
cd drm-kernel/
make -f Makefile.linux
cp radeon.o /lib/modules/`uname -r`/kernel/drivers/video/gatosdrm.o
modprobe gatosdrm
</screen>

<para>You now need to make Linux load the module gatosdrm each time at startup. To do this, find out where your Linux distribution keeps the list of modules to load at startup and add the line <literal>gatosdrm</literal> to the end of that file (in Debian, the file is <filename>/etc/modules</filename>).</para>

<para>You are now ready to install the GATOS driver for the Radeon card. To do so, type the following commands: </para>

<screen>
cd /usr
tar zxvf /path/to/name-of-ati.2-package.tar.gz
</screen>

<para>The driver is now installed.</para>

<para> You are now ready to configure XFree86. This can be done by running <command>xf86config</command>, or by editing the XFree86 configuration file manually.  The configuration process is the same as for XFree86's own driver in <xref linkend="using_xf_driver" />, so go back to that point and follow the XFree86 configuration process described there.</para>

<para>You are now ready to run XFree86!</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="using_schneider_drivers">
<title>Alternative 5: Using Schneider Digital's drivers</title>
<para>Schneider Digital's driver is the one driver I haven't tried myself, but it seems
like a serious attempt on making a decent ATI Radeon driver for Linux. Well, enough chatting, let's get down to business.</para>
<para>
First, download the driver file for either 
<ulink url="http://www.schneider-digital.de/download/ati/glx1_linux_X4.1.zip">XFree86 4.1.x</ulink>, 
<ulink url="http://www.schneider-digital.de/download/ati/glx1_linux_X4.2.zip">XFree86 4.2.x</ulink> or 
<ulink url="http://www.schneider-digital.de/download/ati/glx1_linux_X4.3.zip">XFree86 4.3.x.</ulink>.
</para>
<para>The installation instructions for this driver are exactly the same as for <xref linkend="using_ati_driver" />, so follow those.
</para>
<para>Congratulations, you are now up and running! Please let me know about your experiences with this driver, as I didn't try it myself.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter id="links">
<title>Links</title>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://mirror.ati.com/support/drivers/linux/radeon-linux.html">http://mirror.ati.com/support/drivers/linux/radeon-linux.html</ulink> - ATIs R200 driver for XFree86 4.1.x/4.2.x </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://gatos.sf.net/">http://gatos.sf.net/</ulink> - The GATOS Projects homepage - ATI drivers and utilities</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://gatos.sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=12629">http://gatos.sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=12629</ulink> - The download section of the GATOS project's website.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://dri.sf.net/">http://dri.sf.net/</ulink> - The DRI Project, the Direct Rendering Infrastructure for XFree86. 3D Support, drivers and documentation.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://dri.sourceforge.net/download.phtml">http://dri.sourceforge.net/download.phtml</ulink> - The download section of the DRI's website.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.cloudchaser.net/projects/ati-howto/">http://www.cloudchaser.net/projects/ati-howto/</ulink> - The homepage of the HOWTO</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.schneider-digital.de/">http://www.schneider-digital.de/</ulink>Schneider Digital's website</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</chapter>

<appendix id="gfdl">
<title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
<!-- - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) -->
<!-- LINK REV="made" HREF="mailto:webmasters@gnu.org" -->


  <!-- sect1>
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title -->

    <para>Version 1.1, March 2000</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Copyright (C) 2000  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
    </blockquote>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-0">
    <title>PREAMBLE</title>

    <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook,
    or other written document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
    assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
    with or without modifying it, either commercially or
    noncommercially.  Secondarily, this License preserves for the
    author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not
    being considered responsible for modifications made by
    others.</para>

    <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that
    derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the
    same sense.  It complements the GNU General Public License, which
    is a copyleft license designed for free software.</para>

    <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals
    for free software, because free software needs free documentation:
    a free program should come with manuals providing the same
    freedoms that the software does.  But this License is not limited
    to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
    regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
    printed book.  We recommend this License principally for works
    whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-1">
    <title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

    <para>This License applies to any manual or other work that
    contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License.  The "Document",
    below, refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the
    public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you".</para>

    <para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work
    containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
    verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
    language.</para>

    <para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter
    section of the Document that deals exclusively with the
    relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
    Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains
    nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject.
    (For example, if the Document is in part a textbook of
    mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.)
    The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with
    the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
    philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
    them.</para>

    <para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections
    whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections,
    in the notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

    <para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that
    are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the
    notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

    <para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a
    machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification
    is available to the general public, whose contents can be viewed
    and edited directly and straightforwardly with generic text
    editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs
    or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
    translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
    formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
    whose markup has been designed to thwart or discourage subsequent
    modification by readers is not Transparent.  A copy that is not
    "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>

    <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
    plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
    format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
    standard-conforming simple HTML designed for human modification.
    Opaque formats include PostScript, PDF, proprietary formats that
    can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML
    or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML produced by some word
    processors for output purposes only.</para>

    <para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page
    itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly,
    the material this License requires to appear in the title page.
    For works in formats which do not have any title page as such,
    "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of
    the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
    text.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-2">
    <title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

    <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium,
    either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this
    License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this
    License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and
    that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
    License.  You may not use technical measures to obstruct or
    control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
    distribute.  However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
    copies.  If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

    <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
    above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-3">
    <title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

    <para>If you publish printed copies of the Document numbering more
    than 100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts,
    you must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and
    legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front
    cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover.  Both covers must
    also clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these
    copies.  The front cover must present the full title with all
    words of the title equally prominent and visible.  You may add
    other material on the covers in addition.  Copying with changes
    limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the
    Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim
    copying in other respects.</para>

    <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to
    fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
    reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
    adjacent pages.</para>

    <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
    numbering more than 100, you must either include a
    machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or
    state in or with each Opaque copy a publicly-accessible
    computer-network location containing a complete Transparent copy
    of the Document, free of added material, which the general
    network-using public has access to download anonymously at no
    charge using public-standard network protocols.  If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you
    begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that
    this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
    location until at least one year after the last time you
    distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or
    retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

    <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the
    authors of the Document well before redistributing any large
    number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an
    updated version of the Document.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-4">
    <title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

    <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the
    Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided
    that you release the Modified Version under precisely this
    License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the
    Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
    Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it.  In addition,
    you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
      <listitem><para>Use in the Title Page
      (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from that of the
      Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if
      there were any, be listed in the History section of the
      Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version if
      the original publisher of that version gives permission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>List on the Title Page,
      as authors, one or more persons or entities responsible for
      authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version,
      together with at least five of the principal authors of the
      Document (all of its principal authors, if it has less than
      five).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>State on the Title page
      the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, as the
      publisher.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve all the
      copyright notices of the Document.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Add an appropriate
      copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the other
      copyright notices.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Include, immediately
      after the copyright notices, a license notice giving the public
      permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this
      License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve in that license
      notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and required Cover
      Texts given in the Document's license notice.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Include an unaltered
      copy of this License.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve the section
      entitled "History", and its title, and add to it an item stating
      at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the
      Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If there is no
      section entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating
      the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given
      on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
      Version as stated in the previous sentence.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve the network
      location, if any, given in the Document for public access to a
      Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network
      locations given in the Document for previous versions it was
      based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.  You
      may omit a network location for a work that was published at
      least four years before the Document itself, or if the original
      publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>In any section entitled
      "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", preserve the section's
      title, and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of
      each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications
      given therein.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Preserve all the
      Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their text and
      in their titles.  Section numbers or the equivalent are not
      considered part of the section titles.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Delete any section
      entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section may not be included in
      the Modified Version.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Do not retitle any
      existing section as "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with
      any Invariant Section.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections
    or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no
    material copied from the Document, you may at your option
    designate some or all of these sections as invariant.  To do this,
    add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified
    Version's license notice.  These titles must be distinct from any
    other section titles.</para>

    <para>You may add a section entitled "Endorsements", provided it
    contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by
    various parties--for example, statements of peer review or that
    the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
    definition of a standard.</para>

    <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover
    Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the
    end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one
    passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be
    added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the
    Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
    previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity
    you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
    publisher that added the old one.</para>

    <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by
    this License give permission to use their names for publicity for
    or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-5">
    <title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

    <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released
    under this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for
    modified versions, provided that you include in the combination
    all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original documents,
    unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your
    combined work in its license notice.</para>

    <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this
    License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced
    with a single copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with
    the same name but different contents, make the title of each such
    section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the
    name of the original author or publisher of that section if known,
    or else a unique number.  Make the same adjustment to the section
    titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of
    the combined work.</para>

    <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled
    "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
    entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections entitled
    "Acknowledgements", and any sections entitled "Dedications".  You
    must delete all sections entitled "Endorsements."</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-6">
    <title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

    <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and
    other documents released under this License, and replace the
    individual copies of this License in the various documents with a
    single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you
    follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of
    the documents in all other respects.</para>

    <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection,
    and distribute it individually under this License, provided you
    insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
    follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
    copying of that document.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-7">
    <title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
    
    <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
    separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of
    a storage or distribution medium, does not as a whole count as a
    Modified Version of the Document, provided no compilation
    copyright is claimed for the compilation.  Such a compilation is
    called an "aggregate", and this License does not apply to the
    other self-contained works thus compiled with the Document, on
    account of their being thus compiled, if they are not themselves
    derivative works of the Document.</para>

    <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to
    these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than
    one quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts
    may be placed on covers that surround only the Document within the
    aggregate.  Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole
    aggregate.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-8">
    <title>TRANSLATION</title>

    <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section
    4.  Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires
    special permission from their copyright holders, but you may
    include translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition
    to the original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may
    include a translation of this License provided that you also
    include the original English version of this License.  In case of
    a disagreement between the translation and the original English
    version of this License, the original English version will
    prevail.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-9">
    <title>TERMINATION</title>
    
    <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the
    Document except as expressly provided for under this License.  Any
    other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the
    Document is void, and will automatically terminate your rights
    under this License.  However, parties who have received copies, or
    rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
    terminated so long as such parties remain in full
    compliance.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-10">
    <title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

    <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised
    versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.
    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present
    version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or
    concerns.  See <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing
    version number.  If the Document specifies that a particular
    numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to
    it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
    either of that specified version or of any later version that has
    been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
    If the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
    you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the
    Free Software Foundation.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gfdl-11">
    <title>How to use this License for your documents</title>

    <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include
    a copy of the License in the document and put the following
    copyright and license notices just after the title page:</para>

<blockquote><para>
      Copyright (c)  YEAR  YOUR NAME.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
      Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".
</para></blockquote>

    <para>If you have no Invariant Sections, write "with no Invariant
    Sections" instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have
    no Front-Cover Texts, write "no Front-Cover Texts" instead of
    "Front-Cover Texts being LIST"; likewise for Back-Cover
    Texts.</para>

    <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program
    code, we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
    choice of free software license, such as the GNU General Public
    License, to permit their use in free software.</para>
  </sect1>

</appendix>

</book>


