<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
     "http://docbook.org/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" []>

<article>

  <articleinfo>

    <title>Xnews under Linux HOWTO</title>

    <author>
       <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
       <surname>Quintiliani</surname>
       <affiliation>
          <address><email>coredump0@mercurylink.net</email></address>
       </affiliation>
     </author>

     <pubdate>2003-08-31</pubdate>

     <!-- Most recent revision goes at the top; list in descending order -->
     <revhistory>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
          <date>2003-09-01</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>initial LDP release</revremark>
          <revremark>some updates</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>0.12</revnumber>
          <date>2003-08-31</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>conversion to XML (thanks to Greg Ferguson)</revremark>
          <revremark>various updates</revremark>
       </revision>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>0.11</revnumber>
          <date>2003-08-22</date>
          <authorinitials>dq</authorinitials>
          <revremark>various updates</revremark>
       </revision>
     </revhistory>

     <!-- Provide a good abstract; a couple of sentences is sufficient -->
     <abstract>
        <para>
This document describes how to set up and use the Windows Usenet newsreader
Xnews under the Linux operating system using the Wine "emulator." 
        </para>
     </abstract>

        <para>
The latest version of this document is always available at 
<ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/core_dump_000/Xnews-under-Linux-HOWTO.xml">
http://www.geocities.com/core_dump_000/Xnews-under-Linux-HOWTO.xml</ulink>
       </para>
  </articleinfo>

<sect1 id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
One of the problems with Linux today is the lack of a decent newsreader, where
Windows has several. Under Windows, one of the most popular newsreaders is
Xnews.
</para>
<para>
Xnews, created by Luu Tran, is a free newsreader for Windows,
available from the website
<ulink url="http://xnews.newsguy.com/">http://xnews.newsguy.com</ulink>. Here is
a list of Xnews' features listed on the website:
</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     100% GNKSA 2.0 (Good Net Keeping Seal of Approval) compliant.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Plonk file (aka bozo bin).
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Quick filter (type in a regex and only articles whose
     subject/author match it will be shown).
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Score file for advanced filtering.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Support for multiple servers/identities.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Subscribed groups can be organized into categories.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Remappable keyboard.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Binaries handling (mime, base64, uuencode, what have you).
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     Optional header and article caching; plus: folders for permanent
     archival.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
     more...
     </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

<para>
Unfortunately, Luu Tran has decided neither to make his newsreader
open-source nor to release a Linux version. However, there is a way to get
Xnews to work under Linux, although it takes a bit of work.
</para>


<sect2 id="prereqs">
<title>Prerequisites</title>

<para>
This HOWTO assumes that:
</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para>
The Wine "emulator" is installed properly on the Linux machine. To
download Wine, visit 
<ulink url="http://www.winehq.com/">http://www.winehq.com</ulink>. 
The version used at the
time of this writing was 20030813.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
The reader has access to a Windows machine. Certain files are needed
from the Windows operating system. This HOWTO covers Windows 98SE and
Windows XP.
     </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para>
Xnews stable version 5.04.25 is used (the beta version was not
tested at the time of this writing). The website for Xnews is
<ulink url="http://xnews.newsguy.com/">http://xnews.newsguy.com</ulink>
     </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

</sect2>
 

  <!-- Legal Sections -->
  <sect2 id="copyright">
    <title>Copyright and License</title>

    <!-- The LDP recommends, but doesn't require, the GFDL --> 
    <para>
     This document, <emphasis>Xnews under Linux HOWTO</emphasis>,
     is copyrighted (C) 2003 by <emphasis>Daniel Quintiliani</emphasis>.
     Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
     document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
     License, Version 1.2 or any later version published
     by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections,
     with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts.
     A copy of the license is available at
     <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">
     http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
     Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="disclaimer">
    <title>Disclaimer</title>

    <para>
     No liability for the contents of this document can be accepted.
     Use the concepts, examples and information at your own risk.
     There may be errors and inaccuracies that could be damaging to
     your system, although any damage is highly unlikely.  Proceed with 
     caution; the author(s) do not take any responsibility.
    </para>

    <para>
     All copyrights are held by their by their respective owners,
     unless specifically noted otherwise.  Use of a term in this
     document should not be regarded as affecting the validity of any
     trademark or service mark.  Naming of particular products or
     brands should not be seen as endorsements.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="TODO">
    <title>TODO for this document</title>
    
    <para>
    This document may eventually contain:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Information on the use of binary newsgroups in Xnews. There
          may be some problems with the usage of binaries under Wine.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This document may be expanded to cover other Windows newsreaders
          such as 40tude Dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="setup">
<title>Setting up Xnews</title>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring Wine for Xnews</title>

<para>
Wine is capable of &quot;emulating&quot; many different versions of Windows. Wine is not perfect,
however; it runs slower than a normal Windows installation and it is not a stable product. Certain
problems occur when running Xnews; these are discussed in the 
&quot;<link linkend="problems" endterm="problems.title"/>&quot; section of the document.
</para>

<para>
Before Xnews can run under Linux, certain files from a Windows installation need to be copied to the
Xnews root directory. Depending on which version of Windows the reader of this document has access to,
there will be different files to copy and different instructions for configuring Wine. This document
currently covers a Windows 98SE and a Windows XP configuration. Below are the instructions describing
how to configure Wine for Xnews.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Windows 98SE</title>

<para>
If the reader of this document has access to a Windows 98SE machine, the Wine configuration
(found at <filename>$HOME/.wine/config</filename>) must be set up 
according to these instructions.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in your 
<filename>.wine/config</filename>, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>win98</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;win98&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Second, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot; 
section which will tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather 
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\Xnews.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;commctrl.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;comctl32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Windows XP</title>

<para>
If the reader of this document has access to a Windows XP machine, the Wine configuration
(found at <filename>$HOME/.wine/config</filename>) must be set up 
according to these instructions.
</para>

<para>
First, find the section &quot;<literal>[Version]</literal>&quot; in your
<filename>.wine/config</filename>, and make sure that
&quot;<literal>winxp</literal>&quot; is the version Wine will imitate:
<screen>
     [Version]
     ; Windows version to imitate (win95,win98,winme,nt351,nt40,win2k,winxp,win20,win30,win31)
     &quot;Windows&quot; = &quot;winxp&quot;
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Second, add an entry to the &quot;<literal>AppDefaults</literal>&quot; 
section which will tell Wine to use certain files from Windows rather 
than Wine.
<screen>
    ;; sample AppDefaults entries

    [AppDefaults\\Xnews.exe\\DllOverrides]
    &quot;comctl32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched32.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
    &quot;riched20.dll&quot; = &quot;native&quot;
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Copying Required Files</title>

<para>
Several DLL files must first be copied to the root Xnews directory from
an existing Windows installation.
</para>

<para>
If Xnews lies on a Windows partition on the same machine, the DLL files must
be copied to the Xnews root directory.
Xnews will be run from this directory on the Windows partition.
</para>

<para>
If Xnews is being run on a Linux-only machine, Xnews must be extracted (or
copied from a Windows machine) to the user's fake C drive (usually
<filename>$HOME/c</filename>), and the root Xnews directory must 
include the following DLL files.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Windows 98SE</title>
<para>
If the reader has access to a Windows 98SE machine, the files 
<filename>commctrl.dll</filename>, <filename>comctl32.dll</filename>,
<filename>riched32.dll</filename> (usually in 
<filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM</filename>) must be
copied to the root Xnews directory.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Windows XP</title>
<para>
If the reader has access to a Windows XP machine, the files 
<filename>comctl32.dll</filename>, <filename>riched20.dll</filename>,
<filename>riched32.dll</filename> (usually in
<filename>C:\WINDOWS\SYSTEM32</filename>) must be
copied to the root Xnews directory.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="run_xnews">
<title>Running Xnews</title>

<para>
Using a terminal window, navigate to the root Xnews directory and type:
<screen>
     wine Xnews.exe
</screen>
</para>
<para>
Use Xnews normally, noting the exceptions in the next section, entitled
&quot;<link linkend="problems" endterm="problems.title"/>&quot; 
Note that these are problems with Wine's &quot;emulation&quot;, not
Xnews.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="problems">
<title id="problems.title">Problems</title>

<sect2>
<title>Fixed-width fonts and alt.ascii-art</title>
<para>
ASCII art requires fixed-width fonts to view. Clicking the fixed font button above
the message headers will simply lock the message so the vertical scrollbar
won't work.
</para>
<para>
The easiest way to deal with this is to go into
&quot;Special -&gt; Setup Xnews -&gt; Fonts and Colors&quot;
and select a fixed font for all types
of text. The default &quot;Fixed&quot; will not work; 
use &quot;Misc Fixed&quot;, size 12.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Erasing sections of text</title>
<para>
Selecting sections of text with the mouse and pressing Backspace or Delete
will delete the text from the screen, but for some reason it might still be
there when the message is sent or posted, depending on the window manager.
KDE seems to work fine, but Gnome with Sawfish seems to cause problems.
</para>
<para>
The only way to guarantee deleting sections of text is to press Backspace or
Delete for each character. Be careful when holding down keys.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Window sizing problems</title>
<para>
There are several problems relating to the sizing of the windows. When the
CatchUp button is clicked, the main groups list window shrinks and must be
maximized. These are mostly minor annoyances, except...
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Closing Xnews</title>
<para>
Depending on the window manager (Sawfish has problems with this), it may be 
impossible to close the Xnews window, and there is no &quot;Exit&quot; option 
in the main menu. To get around this, make sure that the window is sized so 
that the terminal used to launch Xnews is accessible, and close that
terminal.  Do not press 
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>, 
etc as this will cause problems. Be
sure to click the Save button to save the newsrc first.

</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="ack">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>
First of all, I'd like to thank Luu Tran for releasing a great
newsreader; hopefully he will reconsider releasing it as open-source,
the demand does exist and is big.
</para>

<para>
I'd also like to thank Vancouverite and the other people in the 
<ulink url="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=65884">Gentoo forum
message</ulink> who described how to
run Xnews under Wine using Windows 98SE files. I discovered how to do
it using the XP files, and also how to deal with fixed-width fonts and other
problems.
</para>

<para>
I'd like to thank Greg Ferguson, Tabatha Marshall, and Mark Garboden of the Linux
Documentation Project for helping me submit my first HOWTO. Greg Ferguson
translated my document from plain text to XML.
</para>

<para>
Also, thanks go out to the people in news.software.readers for working with
me on this HOWTO, and to Usenet users everywhere.
</para>
</sect1>

</article>



