<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
>

<article id="index.html">

<articleinfo>

<title>The X Window User HOWTO</title>

<pubdate>v4.0 Jan.&nbsp;12th, 2010</pubdate>

<authorgroup>
 <author>
  <firstname>Christopher</firstname>
  <surname>Yeleighton</surname>
   <affiliation>
    <address>
     <email>x11user@tldp.org</email>
    </address>
   </affiliation>
 </author>
 <author>
  <firstname>Hal</firstname>
  <surname>Burgiss</surname>
   <affiliation>
    <address>
     <email>hal@foobox.net</email>
    </address>
   </affiliation>
 </author>
</authorgroup>

<revhistory>
<revision
><revnumber>v4.0</revnumber
><date>2010-01-12</date><authorinitials>cy</authorinitials
><revremark>Converted to XML docbook and to the new domain.</revremark 
></revision>
 <revision>
   <revnumber>v3.1</revnumber>
    <date>2002-10-10</date>
    <authorinitials>hb</authorinitials>
     <revremark>
      Some minor additions and updates.
     </revremark>
  </revision>
 <revision>
   <revnumber>v3.0</revnumber>
    <date>2002-03-06</date>
    <authorinitials>hb</authorinitials>
     <revremark>
       Rewrite of the original document. Convert to DocBook. Many, many changes.
     </revremark>
  </revision>
</revhistory>

<keywordset>
 <keyword>X</keyword>
 <keyword>X11</keyword>
 <keyword>XFree</keyword>
 <keyword>XFree86</keyword>
 <keyword>X Window</keyword>
 <keyword>GUI</keyword>
 <keyword>windows</keyword>
 <keyword>desktop</keyword>
 <keyword>display</keyword>
 <keyword>display manager</keyword>
 <keyword>xdm</keyword>
</keywordset>

<abstract>

<para>
 <remark><literallayout>
<![CDATA[
v4.x changes:
- artheader tag changed to articleinfo
- graphic tag is being depricated in DocBook 5.x. To prepare for
  this, you should instead use the mediaobject tag.
- file format for imagedata has to be in capital letters.
- added support for PNG (notation in the DTD)


  --s+ [ser@metalab.unc.edu]
  
 aspell -H -c ~/ldp/x-user/LDP/howto/docbook/XWindow-User-HOWTO.sgml
 submit@linuxdoc.org
 
 export CVSROOT=:pserver:hal@cvs.linuxdoc.org:/cvsroot
 cvs -d $CVSROOT login
 pword: XXXXXXXXXXXXXX

 $cvs get LDP/howto/docbook/XWindow-User-HOWTO.sgml

 upload...
 $ cvs commit XWindow-User-HOWTO.sgml      !!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
 (from the LDP/howto/docbook/ dir)

check here: http://cvs.pld.org.pl/LDP/howto/docbook/XWindow-User-HOWTO.sgml

====================================
Start 3.1:
 TODO:

Changes:
    http://www.plig.org/xwinman (plus freshmeat)
    VNC vs X for performance on network.
    lbxproxy, performance.
    Add fluxbox.

Start rewrite 01/13/02 Hal Burgiss.

Changes:
 Converted to DocBook
 Rewrite! Rewrite! 
 A zillion changes.

ToDo:
 $DISPLAY
 http://www.superant.com/cgi-bin/smalllinux.pl?smallX
 http://www.linuxgazette.com/issue27/kaszeta.html (xdm)
 http://linux.daphnis.com/RedHat/Custom-X-Tips.html#toc4 (Xclients, etc)
 http://www.linuxjournal.com/print.php?sid=5304 (X config, etc)
 log file
 
http://www.linux.gr/cgi-bin/man2html/usr/X11R6/man/man7/X.7.gz
http://www.x-docs.org/

startx &> log

_X11TransSocketUNIXConnect: Can't connect: errno = 111 giving up.
xinit:  Connection refused (errno 111):  unable to connect to X server
xinit:  No such process (errno 3):  Server error.

## Makefile to build this doc as HTML and TXT ####################

# X Windows User HOWTO Makefile
#
# Hal Burgiss hal@foobox.net
#

TITLE = XWindow-User-HOWTO
EXT = sgml
SRC_DIR = LDP/howto/docbook
HTML_DIR = X-USER
SRC = $(SRC_DIR)/$(TITLE).$(EXT)

BUILD = jade -t sgml -ihtml -d /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/ldp.dsl\#html
BUILD_TXT = jade -t sgml -i html -d /usr/lib/sgml/stylesheets/ldp.dsl\#html -V nochunks
SPELL_CMD = aspell -H -c
LINKS_CMD = /usr/bin/linkchecker *html
EDIT_CMD = /usr/bin/vim -g
TBROWSER = w3m
TMP_TXT = __tmp.sgml
WWW=/var/www/html/ldp/x-user
SRC_URL = http://feenix.burgiss.net/ldp/x-user/$(TITLE).$(EXT).gz

all: doc txt

doc: html

html:
	rm -fr $(HTML_DIR)
	mkdir -p __tmp_htmls
	mv -f *.html __tmp_htmls 2>/dev/null || :
	mkdir -p $(HTML_DIR) 
	$(BUILD) $(SRC) ||\
	 (rm -f *.html && mv -f __tmp_htmls/* . || : && rm -rf __tmp_htmls && false)
	mv -f *html $(HTML_DIR)
	mv -f __tmp_htmls/* .  2>/dev/null || :
	rm -fr __tmp_htmls

clean:
	rm -fr $(HTML_DIR) *~  __tmp_htmls

edit:
	$(EDIT_CMD) $(SRC)


spell:
	$(SPELL_CMD) $(SRC)

spellchecker: spell


links:
	cd $(HTML_DIR) && $(LINKS_CMD)

linkchecker: links

linkcheck: links

txt:
	$(BUILD_TXT) $(SRC) > $(TMP_TXT).html 
	$(TBROWSER) -dump $(TMP_TXT).html > $(TITLE).txt && gzip -f $(TITLE).txt && rm -f $(TMP_TXT).html

text: txt

www:
	cp -fv $(HTML_DIR)/* $(TITLE).txt.gz $(SRC) $(WWW)
	gzip -f $(WWW)/$(TITLE).sgml
	rsync -auv $(WWW)/* feenix://$(WWW)/

submit:
	@echo "Updated and ready:  $(SRC_URL)" |\
	mail -s "$(TITLE) update" submit@linuxdoc.org &&\
	echo " $(TITLE) Submitted!"
]]>
 </literallayout></remark>
</para>


<para>
 This document provides basic information on understanding and configuring the
 X Window System for Linux users. This is meant to be an introductory
 level document. A basic knowledge of software configuration is assumed, as is
 the presence of an installed and working X Window System.

</para>

</abstract>

</articleinfo>



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
 The <emphasis>X Window System</emphasis> is an advanced, graphical
 computing and network environment that was designed from the ground up as a
 multi-user system. <application>X</application> was first released in 1984.
 If you are not familiar with the basic concepts surrounding
 <application>X</application> and it's related components, you should first
 read the <citetitle>X Window System Architecture Overview HOWTO</citetitle>, <ulink
 url="http://linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/XWindow-Overview-HOWTO/index.html">http://linuxdoc.org/HOWTO/XWindow-Overview-HOWTO/index.html</ulink>,
 to get an idea of how the various pieces fit together. There is also 
 an attempt to define to various <application>X</application> related
 terminology in the <link linkend="terms">Appendix</link>, if concepts such 
 as <quote>displays</quote> and <quote>X clients</quote> in this context are
 confusing to you.

</para>

<para>
 This document will address basic X Window configuration and usage on Linux. We will
 also look at how <application>X</application> is commonly started in Linux,
 and how the start up can be configured, and related issues. We will
 <emphasis>not</emphasis> examine Window Manager (e.g.
 <application>fvwm</application>), or Desktop Environment
 (<application>KDE</application> and <application>GNOME</application>)
 configuration. There are just too many variables there, and the pace of
 change moves too quickly. Of course, to a large extent the user interacts
 more directly with these components than the X server itself, so additional
 reading would be worthwhile. Check your locally installed documentation, and
 the respective home pages for more information.

</para>

<para>
 Some other important points to remember here:

</para>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

 <listitem>
  <para>
    <application>X</application> is a client-server, multi-user system in
    every respect, and not just a GUI.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
 
 <listitem>
  <para>
   <application>X</application> is not integrated into the operating system,
   and rides on top of it, like other servers.
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   <application>X</application> is an open standard, and runs on many platforms. 
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
    What you actually see on the screen is the result of various components,
    all working together: operating system, <application>X</application>,
    Window Manager, and optionally, a desktop environment like
    <application>GNOME</application> or <application>KDE</application>. These
    are all <quote>plug and play</quote> components, meaning you can
    interchange an individual component without touching the other components.
    
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
    Each of the various components has its own configuration. This makes for a
    very flexible, and potentially very robust, system. It also adds 
    complexity.
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
 The discussion here will be limited to <application>X</application> as
 implemented by <ulink url="http://xfree86.org">The XFree86 Project,
 Inc.</ulink> on Linux. There are other implementations, including
 commercial ones. XFree86 v4.x has been out for some time now, so we will be
 assuming that version. Much of the discussion applies to the previous 3.x
 version as well, but there are some occasional differences.

</para>

<para>
 It is also worth noting that there are conceivably many ways to start
 <application>X</application>, and to set up a Linux system. We will focus on
 the common methods found in Linux distributions. Also, vendors may vary on
 where they put configuration files, and how they name them. Keep this in mind
 if you see such discrepancies in this document. If this is a problem, your
 vendor surely has their own documentation. And as always, hopefully the man
 pages will conform to your installation.

</para>

<para>
 Also, we will look at various configuration files in the following sections.
 These are all plain text files, and can be edited with your favorite editor.
 Always make a backup copy before editing important files, in case Murphy pays
 a visit (e.g. <quote>cp /etc/X11/XF86Config-4  /etc/X11/XF86Config-4.bak</quote>).

</para>

<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>New Versions and ChangeLog</title>

<para>
 
The <ulink
 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XWindow-User-HOWTO.html"
>current official version of this HOWTO </ulink>
may be found at the Linux Documentation Project.
</para>

<para>
 v3.1: This is just some small, minor updates. Include link 
 to <ulink url="http://www.plig.org/xwinman/">http://www.plig.org/xwinman/</ulink>
 as a good resource for shopping Window Managers. Add link for fluxbox, 
 a Window Manager with Tabbed windows. And add a brief section on improving 
 network performance. Verify links all work.
</para>

<para>
 v3.0: This is a major rewrite with several new sections. Some
 sections were removed, with the focus more now on just
 <application>X</application> itself (and not clients like Window Managers).
 New maintainer too :-)
</para>

<para>
 v2.0: includes corrections from Guus Bosch, Brian J.
 Miller, and myself, as well as lots of new updates and info.
</para>

<para>
 v1.4: include corrections and additions from Anthony J., and
 some very good security tips from Tomasz Motylewski.
</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>To Do</title>
<para>
 A rudimentary troubleshooting section. Probably for v3.2.

</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Feedback</title>

<para>
 If you have questions or comments about this document, please feel free to
 email me, Hal Burgiss at <email>hal@foobox.net</email>. I welcome any
 suggestions, corrections, or additions. If you have information you would
 like to see in future revisions, or you would like to contribute to a future
 revision, please drop me a note.  

</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Help!</title>

<para>
 I have assumed maintainership of this document because it was abandoned, and
 I had wanted to offer a suggested change. Well, to make a long story short,
 this led to a major re-write. You can help make this a better document by
 correcting inaccuracies, clarifying the unclear, and suggesting improvements.
 There is much about this topic I may not know, or not have explained well. Your
 help will improve this document and help other users. This document 
 <emphasis>needs</emphasis> your help!
 
</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>

<para>
 Thanks to the XFree86 development team for their efforts in providing a
 robust and flexible GUI. And to the whole GNU/Linux and Open Source
 community for making it all possible.
 
</para>

<para>
 Also, the original author, Ray Brigleb.

</para>

<para>
 Various users on comp.os.linux.x that have helped in one way or another, 
 whether they know it or not.

</para>

<para>
 Lastly, <ulink url="http://google.com/linux">http://google.com/linux</ulink>, 
 who saved me much time with their incredible repository of information. Use 
 it to answer questions not answered here!

</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Copyright</title>

<para>
 Copyright &copy; 2002, Hal Burgiss. 
</para>

<para>
 Unless otherwise stated, Linux HOWTO documents are copyrighted by their
 respective authors. Linux HOWTO documents may be reproduced and distributed
 in whole or in part, in any medium physical or electronic, as long as this
 copyright notice is retained on all copies. Commercial redistribution is
 allowed and encouraged; however, the author would like to be notified of any
 such distributions.
</para>

<para>
 All translations, derivative works, or aggregate works incorporating any
 Linux HOWTO documents must be covered under this copyright notice. That is,
 you may not produce a derivative work from a HOWTO and impose additional
 restrictions on its distribution. Exceptions to these rules may be granted
 under certain conditions; please contact the Linux HOWTO coordinator for more
 information. 
 
</para>

<para>
 In short, we wish to promote dissemination of this information through as
 many channels as possible. However, we do wish to retain copyright on the
 HOWTO documents, and would very much like to be notified of any plans to
 redistribute the HOWTOs, this one in particular!
</para>

<para>
 Some of the terms mentioned in this document are trade names. Unless
 otherwise stated, all trademarks are property of their respective owners.
</para>

<para>
 <quote>X Window System</quote> is a trademark of the X Consortium, Inc 
 [now the OpenGroup?].

</para>

<para>
 <quote>XFree86</quote> is a trademark of <ulink url="http://xfree86.org">The
 XFree86 Project, Inc</ulink>.

</para>

<para>
 <quote>Linux</quote> is a Registered Trademark of Linus Torvalds.
</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect2>
<title>Standard Disclaimer</title>
<para>
 The information and examples given here are for illustrative purposes. Use at
 your own risk. Every attempt has been made to insure that the content of this
 document was accurate when written. If you find inaccuracies, please send me 
 clarifications.

</para>

<para>
 References to any particular company, product or brand name should not be
 construed as an endorsement.

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="xfree86">
<title>XFree86</title>
<para>
 Virtually every Linux distribution comes with XFree86's
 <application>X Window System</application> implementation. This project, of
 course, provides us the X server, but also includes an extensive suite of
 utilities and applications to help implement a fully functional GUI
 environment.

</para>

<para>
 In fact, the list would be just too long to list everything that
 comes with XFree86. In addition to the X server itself, here are a few of the
 noteworthy utilities:
</para>

<simplelist>
 <member>
   <command>xdm</command> - the X Display Manager.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
   <command>xfs</command> - the X Font Server.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>twm</command> - a lightweight Window Manager.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xterm</command> - the best known terminal emulator. Also,
  <command>xterm3d</command> and <command>nxterm</command>.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xwd</command> - a screen and window image capturer.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xf86config</command> - X server configuration utility.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xdpyinfo</command> - X display information utility. This
  shows great detail about the X server.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xlsclients</command> - lists currently connected X server
  clients.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xlsfonts</command> - lists fonts available to
  <application>X</application>.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>appres</command> - lists the X <quote>resources</quote> that a
  program will use.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xfontsel</command> - an application for viewing or
  selecting fonts.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xprop</command> - a tool for displaying window  
  <quote>properties</quote>, such as the Class name of the client.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xset</command> - sets user preferences for many things,
  including mouse, keyboard, sound (bell), etc.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xsetroot</command> - a program for changing the
  <quote>root window</quote> appearance, e.g. setting a background color.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xvidtune</command> - an application to adjust X server 
  video modes and monitor related settings.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xwininfo</command> - displays information about a selected
  <quote>window</quote>.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <command>xmodmap</command> - a utility for manipulating keyboard and mouse
  button mappings.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
   Many, many fonts. And quite a bit of documentation as well.
 </member>
</simplelist>


<para>
 There are many more. We'll just touch on a few of these utilities here. But
 feel free to explore the others. Most should have their own man pages.

</para>


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Hardware</title>

<para>
 The X server controls both input (keyboard, mouse, etc) and output (display,
 monitor) devices.

</para>

<para>
 Compatible hardware is a tough topic, since it is very much a moving target.
 We are forced here to avoid specifics, since this would surely change by the
 time you read this. And would be tediously lengthy anyway.

</para>

<para>
 So let's settle for some generalities. <emphasis>Most</emphasis> PC type
 hardware is supported to one degree or another. Big help ;-)

</para>

<para>
 Rule of thumb: if it is a device that uses a long-standing, commonplace
 protocol (e.g. PS/2), it should be well supported. Conversely, if it is
 something relatively new, with  ground-breaking technology, the odds 
 are not as good. This is just the nature of the beast with open source 
 development versus manufacturers that cater more to the most popular
 platforms. Some manufacturers are more co-operative than others too.

</para>

<para>
 Now, some general guidelines:

</para>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
   <para>
     Monitors - This is easy. Linux does not really need to be compatible with
     the monitor per se. That is the job of the video card. Any monitor that
     your graphics card can drive should do fine. Including, flat panel 
     monitors.
   </para>
  </listitem> 

  <listitem>
   <para>
     Video cards - This is much tougher. The X server is determined by the 
     the chipset. Many, many are supported. But inevitably there are always 
     some newer cards, or even revised cards, that are not. And some may have
     better support and better optimization than others. Advanced
     features such as multi-headed displays, 3D, TV out, DRI, etc., have some
     support as well, though this should be researched first, as the support
     may be limited. Supported cards are listed: <ulink
     url="http://xfree86.org/cardlist.html">http://xfree86.org/cardlist.html</ulink>.

   </para>

   <para>
     Open source drivers are often developed incrementally. For instance, a
     particular card may work well for basic display purposes, but specialized 
     features such as 3D may come much later in the development cycle. This
     is a quite different development model than with proprietary drivers from 
     the manufacturer.

   </para>
  </listitem> 

  <listitem>
   <para>
    Keyboards -- Any standard PC type keyboard should do fine,
    including PS/2, USB and many infra-red devices. Probably many 
    <quote>non-standard</quote> ones too ;-)

   </para>
  </listitem> 

  <listitem>
   <para>
    Mice and other pointer devices -- Most should be supported including 
    PS/2, bus, serial, USB and many infra-red devices. Optical mice also. Unix
    has long preferred three button mice, though more buttons is supported as
    well. Many wheeled mice have X server support via the
    <quote>IMPS/2</quote> (IntelliMouse), or other specific protocols, though
    may require supplemental configuration for some individual applications.
    (See the <link linkend="links">Links</link> section.)
   
   </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   Laptops have their own unique set of problems since the hardware tends to
   be very specialized, and often different from what is commonly found on
   desktop style systems. <application>X</application> is supported by many.
   Check for details at <ulink
   url="http://www.linux-laptop.net/">http://www.linux-laptop.net/</ulink>.
  
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
 You can check the <quote>hardware compatibility list</quote> at your
 distribution's web site too. This should give a very good idea of what 
 <emphasis>should work</emphasis> with your release.

</para>

<para>
 Newer versions of XFree86 obviously will have better hardware support. If you
 are using an older Linux version and don't have full hardware support, see
 about upgrading XFree86. Check first to see if your distribution has updates 
 for your release.

</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect2>
<title>XF86Config</title>
<para>
 The primary configuration file for XFree86 is
 <filename>XF86Config</filename>, which may exist on your system as
 <filename>XF86Config-4</filename> for XFree86 v4.x, or possibly other
 variations (see man page). It is typically located as
 <filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config</filename>, though again, there may be
 variations in the path. If both a <filename>XF86Config-4</filename> 
 and <filename>XF86Config</filename> exist, XFree86 v4.x will use the former.
 This is a required file.

</para>

<para>
 <filename>XF86Config</filename> file defines hardware devices, and other
 critical components of the X server environment. 

</para>

<para>
 While this is a plain text file, and is editable, it is most often created
 during installation by whatever utility your vendor uses for this purpose. 
 XFree86 also includes the <command>xf86config</command> utility for this, 
 but many distributions have their own such utilities. These utilities can be
 run after installation if need be, to alter the configuration, or if new
 hardware is installed. Read your locally installed documentation first. If
 you attempt to hand edit this file, be sure to make a backup copy first since
 <application>X</application> will not start if this file is not to its liking
 ;-)

</para>

<para>
 This file contains various <quote>sections</quote>. Each section defines some
 fundamental aspect of XFree86, such as <quote>InputDevice</quote> (mouse,
 keyboard, joystick, etc), <quote>monitor</quote>, or <quote>screen</quote>. The 
 <filename>XF86Config</filename> man page describes the sections and
 common values for each. Note that the values listed in the man page is not a
 comprehensive listing. There are many device specific <quote>options</quote>.
 Check <ulink url="http://xfree86.org">http://xfree86.org</ulink> for notes
 and tips on your hardware.

</para>

<para>
 The author's current <filename>XF86Config-4</filename>, as generated by Red
 Hat's installer for XFree86 4.1:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

Section "ServerLayout"
	Identifier "XFree86 Configured"
	Screen      0  "Screen0" 0 0
	InputDevice    "Mouse0" "CorePointer"
	InputDevice    "Keyboard0" "CoreKeyboard"
EndSection

Section "Files"
   # The location of the RGB database.
   RgbPath     "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/rgb"

   # Multiple FontPath entries are allowed (they are concatenated together)
   # By default, Red Hat 6.0 and later now use a font server independent of
   # the X server to render fonts.
   FontPath "unix/:7100"
EndSection

# Module loading section

Section "Module"
	Load  "dbe"		# Double-buffering
	Load  "GLcore"		# OpenGL support
	Load  "dri"		# Direct rendering infrastructure
	Load  "glx"		# OpenGL X protocol interface
	Load  "extmod"		# Misc. required extensions
	Load  "v4l"		# Video4Linux
#    Load  "fbdevhw"
     Load  "pex5"
     Load  "record"
     Load  "xie"
EndSection


Section "InputDevice"
	Identifier  "Keyboard0"
	Driver      "keyboard"
	Option      "XkbLayout"	"us"

#    Option  "AutoRepeat"    "500 5"

# when using XQUEUE, comment out the above line, and uncomment the
# following line
#    Option  "Protocol"      "Xqueue"

# Specify which keyboard LEDs can be user-controlled (eg, with xset(1))
#    Option  "Xleds"         "1 2 3"

# To disable the XKEYBOARD extension, uncomment XkbDisable.
#    Option  "XkbDisable"

# To customize the XKB settings to suit your keyboard, modify the
# lines below (which are the defaults).  For example, for a non-U.S.
# keyboard, you will probably want to use:
#   Option  "XkbModel"      "pc102"
# If you have a US Microsoft Natural keyboard, you can use:
#   Option  "XkbModel"      "microsoft"
EndSection

Section "InputDevice"
	Identifier  "Mouse0"
	Driver      "mouse"
	Option      "Device" "/dev/mouse"
	Option      "Protocol" "IMPS/2"
	Option      "Emulate3Buttons" "off"
	Option      "ZAxisMapping" "4 5"
EndSection

Section "Monitor"
	Identifier "Sylvania F74"
	VendorName "Unknown"
	ModelName  "Unknown"
	HorizSync   30 - 70
	VertRefresh 55 - 120
	Option "dpms"
#    Modelines go here if necessary. Use xvidtune to get proper values.
EndSection

Section "Device"
	Identifier "ATI Rage 128"
	Driver "r128"
	BoardName "Unknown"
EndSection

Section "Device"
	Identifier "Linux Frame Buffer"
	Driver "fbdev"
	BoardName "Unknown"
EndSection

Section "Screen"
	Identifier "Screen0"
	Device "ATI Rage 128"
	Monitor "Sylvania F74"
	DefaultDepth 24
	Subsection "Display"
		Depth 24
		Modes "1400x1050" "1280x1024" "1152x864" "1024x768" "800x600"
	EndSubSection
	Subsection "Display"
		Depth 16
		Modes "1600x1200" "1400x1050" "1280x1024" "1152x864" "1024x768" "800x600"
	EndSubSection
	Subsection "Display"
		Depth 8
		Modes "1024x768" "800x600" "640x480"
	EndSubSection
EndSection

Section "DRI"
	Mode 0666
EndSection

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Yours may look quite different. This is just one possible configuration with
 gratuitous comments from Red Hat (and me), and is for a fairly ordinary set
 up. There is nothing exotic here like multiple screens or displays.

</para>

<para>
 It is beyond the scope of this document to explain this in detail. See the 
 <filename>XF86Config</filename> man page. Also, consider visiting 
 <ulink url="http://xfree86.org">xfree86.org</ulink>
 and look for specific options that might apply to your card or other
 hardware.

</para>

<para>
 Just one quick note on the <quote>Screen</quote> section above. Notice there are
 three sub-sections, identified as <quote>Display</quote>. Each sub-section
 has a different <quote>Depth</quote> specified, (a.k.a. ColorDepth). The
 <quote>Modes</quote> also vary somewhat according to the respective
 <quote>Depth</quote> setting. The active <quote>Display</quote> sub-section
 that will be used, is determined by the <quote>DefaultDepth</quote> setting 
 (unless over-ridden by command line options). The default in this example is
 defined as <quote>24</quote>, so the first sub-section will be used. Also,
 the highest <quote>Mode</quote> listed in this sub-section will be the default
 mode (resolution), which here is the first one listed. The first listed mode 
 also determines the viewable screen area, which can be smaller than the mode
 (resolution) itself. In which case, you would have a virtual desktop that is
 larger than the viewable screen. To have the viewable screen, and resolution 
 match, have the largest value as the first value listed for each
 <quote>Mode</quote>.

</para>

<para>
 Another note on the <quote>Modes</quote> here: what you see is the result of
 my choices during Red Hat's <command>Xconfigurator's</command> configuration. These 
 are standard resolutions, but do not have to be! This is only limited by what
 your hardware can support. And you don't have to use standard width x height 
 ratios either. Something like <literal>1355x1112</literal> is a valid setting (if
 your hardware supports it and it floats your boat!).

</para>

<para>
 The X server will reject any <quote>Modes</quote> it thinks are invalid. You
 can cycle through valid modes to change screen resolution with
 <literal>Ctrl-Alt-+</literal> and <literal>Ctrl-Alt--</literal> (that's the
 keypad plus and minus keys).

</para>

<para>
 In versions prior to v4.x, you would also see many <quote>Modeline</quote> 
 statements that attempted to define the monitor's capabilities. These
 statements would look something like:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 # 1024x768 @ 100Hz, 80.21 kHz hsync
 Modeline "1024x768"  115.5  1024 1056 1248 1440  768  771  781  802 -HSync -VSync

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Explicit <quote>Modeline</quote> definitions are not required as of 4.x ;-)
 This sometimes required hand editing to get optimal values in earlier versions of 
 
XFree86, though is generally not necessary with v4.x. 
<ulink
 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/index.html"
>The XFree86 Video
 Timings HOWTO
</ulink>
 has a nice, but rather technical, explanation of this.

</para>

<para>
 If whatever configuration utility you are using, does not automatically
 recognize your video card or monitor specifications correctly, you are
 unlikely to get an optimal configuration. In such cases, you may have to
 manually supply the correct values. This should be available from your 
 owner's manual (you kept that, right?). Or, check the manufacturer's web site.

</para>

<para>
 Again, hand editing of this file is generally unnecessary. Should you decide
 this is indeed necessary, be careful. One small error may cause
 <application>X</application> to fail. Any changes to this file will require
 restarting <application>X</application> for the changes to take
 effect.

</para>

<para>
 Using somebody else's <filename>XF86Config</filename> file, is generally a
 bad idea since they are unlikely to have identical hardware.

</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>xvidtune and Monitor Tuning</title>

<para>
 You probably want to get the most out of your hardware. If
 <application>X</application> isn't configured optimally, consider re-running
 your vendor's <application>X</application> configuration utility and try to
 get better results. It is highly unlikely that you could hurt anything by
 experimenting. Most modern monitors now have safeguards that prevent a
 meltdown ;-)
 
</para>

<para>
 If you over-do it though <application>X</application> may not be able to
 start. For this reason, I prefer to use the <quote>startx</quote> way of
 starting <application>X</application> (see below) while
 <quote>experimenting</quote>. This way if <application>X</application>
 crashes, the display manager (GUI login) will not loop and cause you severe
 headaches. <command>startx</command> just gracefully goes back to a text
 console screen, where an error message may be visible.

</para>

<para>
 Another way of tweaking monitor related settings is with XFree86's 
 <command>xvidtune</command> program. This is run interactively and can be
 used to adjust various settings (see man page). The simple dialog box has
 sliders and buttons that allow user input and adjustment. The top part has
 horizontal monitor settings on the left, and vertical settings on the right.
 The buttons just below the sliders can be used to adjust each.

</para>

<para>
 This is sometimes used to adjust the viewable screen area, such as to center
 it, or increase its size to fill the monitor's viewport. When
 <command>xvidtune</command> is launched, it defaults to the current settings.

</para>

<para>
 The bottom left corner has buttons that can <quote>Apply</quote> new
 settings, <quote>Test</quote> new settings, or <quote>Show</quote> current
 settings (i.e. dump to screen), among other things. Any changes made here are
 not saved. If new settings are <quote>Applied</quote>, it is just for
 the current session. Example output of <command>xvidtune</command>
 <quote>Show</quote>:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 Vendor: Unknown, Model: Unknown
 Num hsync: 1, Num vsync: 1
 hsync range 0:  30.00 -  70.00
 vsync range 0:  55.00 - 120.00
 "1400x1050"   122.00   1400 1488 1640 1880   1050 1052 1064 1082 +hsync +vsync

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 The last line is the <quote>Modeline</quote> being used to drive the current
 screen. See <ulink
 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/index.html"
>The XFree86 Video
 Timings HOWTO
</ulink>, 
 for more on <quote>Modelines</quote>.


</para>

<para>
 You can test modifications, and apply them to the current session.
 For changes to be made permanent, they will have to be added manually to 
 the <quote>Monitor</quote> section of <filename>XF86Config</filename> (or
 <filename>XF86Config-4</filename> for v.4.x) with a text editor.

</para>

<para>
  <command>xvidtune</command> will dutifully warn of you of the hazards of
  playing with the monitor settings. It is unlikely you can hurt anything 
  with modern monitors. But it is best used to make minor adjustments. Use at
  your own risk!

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="runningx">
<title>Running X</title>

<para>
 Starting an <application>X</application> session is typically done in one of
 two ways: the <application>X</application> session is started via a display
 manager (like <command>xdm</command>), and the user logs in at a GUI screen.
 Or, the user starts <application>X</application> manually after logging in to
 a text console. The latter is typically done with the
 <command>startx</command> command, which is a simple shell script wrapper
 for <command>xinit</command>. <application>X</application> runs with root
 privileges in either case, since it needs raw access to hardware devices.

</para>

<para>
 Typically, which method is used, is determined by the system 
 <quote>runlevel</quote>. The default runlevel to launch at boot is
 generally set in <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> on Linux: 

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 # Run xdm in runlevel 5
 x:5:respawn:/etc/X11/xdm -nodaemon

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 That would start <command>xdm</command>, and thus
 <application>X</application>, at runlevel 5. It will <quote>respawn</quote>,
 if it dies or is stopped for any reason. You can also use the
 <quote><command>init</command></quote> command to change runlevels without
 rebooting (see man page).

</para>

<para>
 Let's look briefly at both approaches, and then some additional configuration 
 to set up the user's working environment.

</para>

<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>startx</title>

<para>
 <command>startx</command> will start <application>X</application> by first
 invoking <command>xinit</command>. By itself, this would put you at a blank,
 fuzzy looking, bare-bones desktop with no Window Manager loaded.
 <command>xinit</command> basically takes two sets of command line
 arguments: client specifications (programs to run, etc), and server
 specifications (X server options), separated by <quote>--</quote>. If no
 client program is specified on the command line, <command>xinit</command>
 will look for a <filename>.xinitrc</filename> file in the user's home
 directory, to run as a shell script. If found, this then would in turn run
 whatever user specified commands to set up the environment, or launch
 programs that the file contained. If this file does not exist,
 <command>xinit</command> will use the following initial command:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>
 
 xterm -geometry +1+1 -n login -display :0
 
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 If no <filename>.xserverrc</filename> is found in the user's home directory, 
 <application>X</application> itself will be started with the following command:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 X :0

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 As you see, this is not overly helpful as it just launches one
 <application>xterm</application>. The <command>startx</command>
 shell wrapper provides additional functionality and flexibility to 
 <command>xinit</command>. <command>startx</command> will invoke 
 <command>xinit</command> for us, and provide some simple configuration
 options as well. You can also issue commands such as the following, for
 instance:
 
</para>

<para>
 <screen>
 
 startx -- -dpi 100 -depth 16   #force X to 100 dots per inch
                                #and colordepth of 16 (X v4 syntax)
 
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Anything after the double dashes are passed as arguments directly to the X
 server via <command>xinit</command>. In this example, you can force
 <application>X</application> to the resolution of your preference, and still
 have it use the configuration files we will cover later in this document. See
 the Xserver man page for more command line options.

</para>

<para>
 Instead of issuing the same command line every time, it is easier to use the
 configuration files to store this type of information for us.

</para>

<para>
 If you take a look at the <command>startx</command> script
 (<filename>/usr/X11R6/bin/startx</filename> on my system), you see it uses
 two default configuration files to help set up the
 <application>X</application> environment: <filename>xinitrc</filename> and
 <filename>xserverrc</filename>. It looks first in
 <filename>/etc/X11/xinit/</filename>, for the system wide files. It then
 checks the user's home directory for similar files, which will take
 precedence if found. Note that the latter are Unix style <quote>dot</quote> files
 (e.g. <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename>), and are executable shell scripts.

</para>

<para>
 You normally would not want to edit the system wide files, but you can freely
 copy these to your home directory as a starting point, or just start from
 scratch. As you can tell by the names, one helps set up the X server, and one
 sets up <command>xinit</command> by executing commands, preparing the
 environment and possibly starting client programs like
 <command>xterm</command> or a Window Manager (yes, it's a client too).

</para>



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>xserverrc</title>
<para>
 As with all XFree86 configuration files, this is a plain text file, and is
 usually a simple, one line statement to start the X server. It can include
 any valid command line options supported by your <application>X</application>
 installation. If you always start <application>X</application> with your own
 options, this should be easier than typing the options each time. One
 possible <filename>~/.xserverrc</filename>:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 exec X :0 -dpi 100 -nolisten tcp

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This will start <application>X</application> on display :0, the first
 <quote>display</quote>, at a dots-per-inch resolution of 100, and disables
 TCP connections. See the Xserver man page for other valid options. This is
 just an example.

</para>

</sect3>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect3>
<title>xinitrc</title>
<para>
 <filename>xinitrc</filename> is used to set up a suitable
 <application>X</application> environment, and to launch other programs, a.k.a
 <quote>clients</quote> that we may want available as soon as
 <application>X</application> is started. You likely have a system wide
 <filename>xinitrc</filename> to start a predefined set off programs. To
 customize this, create your own in your home directory. Name it
 <filename>.xinitrc</filename>, make sure it is an executable script, and
 <command>chmod +x</command>. An example (slightly modified from the original
 on my system):

</para>

<para>
 <screen>
<![CDATA[
#!/bin/sh
# $XConsortium: xinitrc.cpp,v 1.4 91/08/22 11:41:34 rws Exp $

userresources=$HOME/.Xresources
usermodmap=$HOME/.Xmodmap

# merge in defaults and keymaps
if [ -f $userresources ]; then
    xrdb -merge $userresources
fi

if [ -f $usermodmap ]; then
    xmodmap $usermodmap
fi

if [ -z "$BROWSER" ] ; then
	# we need to find a browser on this system
	BROWSER=`which netscape`
	if [ -z "$BROWSER" ] || [ ! -e "$BROWSER" ] ; then
	# not found yet
		BROWSER=
	fi
fi
if [ -z "$BROWSER" ] ; then
	# we need to find a browser on this system
	BROWSER=`which lynx`
	if [ -z "$BROWSER" ] || [ ! -e "$BROWSER" ] ; then
	# not found yet
		BROWSER=
	else
		BROWSER="xterm -font 9x15 -e lynx"
	fi
fi

export BROWSER

# start some nice programs
if [ -f $HOME/.Xclients ]; then
    exec $HOME/.Xclients
else
    xclock -geometry 50x50-1+1 &
    xterm -geometry 80x50+494+51 &
    if [ -f /usr/X11R6/bin/fvwm ]; then
        exec fvwm
    else
        exec twm
    fi
fi

#eof
]]>
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Briefly, what this script does, is set up our working environment, with
 <command>xmodmap</command> (keyboard) and <command>xrdb</command>
 (application resource settings). More on these below.  Then the shell variable
 <literal>$BROWSER</literal> is set for a GUI environment (Netscape in this
 example) so that any applications that might expect this, have a reasonable
 choice available. Then the presence of the file <filename>Xclients</filename>
 is checked, both as a system wide file and in the user's home directory. In
 this particular example, this is where any client applications are to be
 started, including a Window Manager (see below). These could just have as
 easily been started here if we had wanted to. If an
 <filename>Xclients</filename> file can't be found, then a Window Manager is
 started for us. Either <command>fvwm</command>, if available, or XFree86's
 minimalist <command>twm</command> if not. If for some reason, neither of
 these can be started, the script would exit, and <application>X</application>
 would fail to start.

</para>

</sect3>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->

<sect3>
<title>Xclients</title>

<para>
 Everything up to this point has followed pretty much a standard and
 predictable sequence of events. To summarize, we have invoked
 <command>startx</command>, which in turn invoked <command>xinit</command>, 
 which has parsed <filename>xinitrc</filename> for initial settings. Most
 Linuxes should follow this same sequence, though the various values and
 settings may differ.

</para>

<para>
 We now are at the last link in the chain where the user normally would 
 specify his or her preferences, including the Window Manager and/or 
 desktop environment to be used. The system will provide sane, though possibly
 uninteresting, defaults if the user has not done so. Presumably, this is why
 you are here ;-)

</para>

<para>
 The Window Manager, or desktop environment, is typically the last application
 started. If you want other programs (like <command>xterm</command>) started,
 they should be started before the Window Manager and
 <quote>backgrounded</quote> with an <quote>&#38;</quote>. This can all be
 done in the user's <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename>. Or as in the above
 example, the actual applications are started from yet another script. Let's
 look at one short, hypothetical such script, <filename>.Xclients</filename>:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>
<![CDATA[ 
#!/bin/bash
# ~/.Xclients, start my programs.

xset s off s noblank
xset m 30/10 4
xset r rate 200 40

xscreensaver & 
rxvt -geometry 80x50-50+150 &

echo Starting Window Manager...

if [ -x /usr/X11R6/bin/wmaker ]; then
  echo `date`: Trying /usr/X11R6/bin/wmaker... |tee -a ~/.wm-errors 2>&1
  exec /usr/X11R6/bin/wmaker >> ~/.wm-errors 2>&1
fi 

echo `date`: Failed, trying fvwm... |tee -a ~/.wm-errors 2>&1

# let's try regular fvwm (AnotherLevel doesn't work with fvwm1).
if [ -n "$(type -path fvwm)" ]; then
  # if this works, we stop here
  exec fvwm >> ~/.wm-errors 2>&1
fi

echo `date`: Failed, trying twm... |tee -a ~/.wm-errors 2>&1

# wow, fvwm isn't here either ... 
# use twm as a last resort.
exec twm >> ~/.wm-errors 2>&1

# Dead in the water here, X will exit as well, sigh...
echo `date`: Unable to start a Window Manager ... |tee -a ~/.wm-errors 2>&1

# eof
]]>
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This really isn't so different than what <filename>xinitrc</filename> was
 doing at all. We added a few wrinkles, including starting a screen saver, a
 different terminal emulator that this user prefers (<command>rxvt</command>),
 with even more setting up of the environment (monitor, mouse and keyboard) using
 <command>xset</command> this time, and a different Window Manager than was
 available with the system defaults. This is in the user's home directory, so
 it will not be overwritten during upgrades too.

</para>

<para>
 Actually, <application>X</application> has already started at this point, and
 we are just putting the finishing touches on the configuration. Notice the
 Window Managers are not <quote>backgrounded</quote> with <quote>&#38;</quote>
 here. This is important! Something has to run in the foreground, or
 <application>X</application> will exit. We didn't start a desktop environment
 in this example, like <application>KDE</application> or
 <application>GNOME</application>, but if we did, this final application
 would have to be <command>gnome-session</command> or
 <command>startkde</command> instead. Since we are rolling our own here, if we
 wanted to change Window Managers, all we have to do is edit this file, and
 restart <application>X</application>. Vendor supplied configurations may be
 more complex than this, but the same principles apply.

</para>

<para>
 As an afterword, do not think that any initial client applications
 <emphasis>must</emphasis> be started as we've done here. This is how it has
 been traditionally done, and some may prefer this approach. Most window
 managers have their own built-in ways to start initial programs, as do 
 <application>KDE</application> and <application>GNOME</application>. See 
 the respective documentation.

</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Display Managers</title>

<para>
 The other, more common, approach is the <quote>GUI log-in</quote>, where
 <application>X</application> is running before log-in. This is done with the
 help of a <quote>display manager</quote>, of which there are various
 implementations. XFree86 includes <command>xdm</command> (X Display Manager)
 for this purpose, though your distribution may use one of the others such as
 <command>gdm</command> (<application>GNOME</application>) or <command>kdm</command>
 (<application>KDE</application>).

</para>

<para>
 Display managers really do much more than enable GUI style log-ins. They 
 are also used to manage local as well as remote <quote>displays</quote> on a
 network. We shall not get into details on this here, but it is nicely covered in
 the <citetitle>Remote X Apps Mini HOWTO</citetitle> and the <citetitle>XDMCP
 HOWTO</citetitle> (see the <link linkend="links">links section</link>). For
 our purposes here, they provide similar services to <command>getty</command>
 and <command>login</command>, which allow users to log into a system and
 start their default shell, but in a GUI environment. 

</para>

<para>
 Here is an example of a more advanced usage of what else a display manager
 might be used for, from Diego Zamboni:

</para>

<blockquote>

<para>
 I have two X sessions running with different resolutions. I switch between
 them depending on whether my laptop is connected to an external monitor or
 using its own LCD display.

</para>

<para>
 Here's my <filename>/usr/lib/X11/xdm/Xservers</filename> file that initiates 
 both displays:
</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 :1 local /usr/X11R6/bin/X :1 -layout 1024x768
 :0 local /usr/X11R6/bin/X :0 -layout 1600x1200

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Then I have <quote>1024x768</quote> and <quote>1600x1200</quote> defined as
 <quote>server layouts</quote> in my
 <filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config-4</filename>, as follows:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 Section "ServerLayout"
         Identifier     "1600x1200"
         Screen         "Screen0" 0 0
         InputDevice    "Mouse0" "CorePointer"
         InputDevice    "Keyboard0" "CoreKeyboard"
 EndSection
 
 Section "ServerLayout"
         Identifier     "1024x768"
         Screen         "Screen1" 0 0
         InputDevice    "Mouse0" "CorePointer"
         InputDevice    "Keyboard0" "CoreKeyboard"
 EndSection
 
 ## snip ...
 
 Section "Screen"
         Identifier   "Screen0"
         Device       "S3 Savage/MX"
         Monitor      "Monitor0"
         DefaultDepth 16
         
         Subsection "Display"
                 Depth  16
                 Modes  "1600x1200" "1280x1024" "1024x768"
         EndSubsection
 EndSection
 
 Section "Screen"
         Identifier   "Screen1"
         Device       "S3 Savage/MX"
         Monitor      "Monitor0"
         DefaultDepth 16

         Subsection "Display"
                 Depth  16
                 Modes  "1024x768" "800x600"
         EndSubsection
 EndSection

 </screen>
</para>

</blockquote>

<para>
 Note the use of <quote>Identifiers</quote> here. Diego is starting two
 separate <quote>displays</quote> here. Then he can choose which one he 
 wants when he logs in.

</para>

<para>
 Most display managers are derived from XFree86's venerable
 <command>xdm</command>, and add their own enhancements. Let's look at the
 most popular ones briefly. 

</para>


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect3>
<title>xdm</title>

<para>
 <command>xdm</command> can be configured with configuration files located in
 <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/</filename>,
 <filename>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/xdm</filename>, or similar locations depending
 on your system. These are system wide files. The file
 <filename>xdm-config</filename> is the main configuration file, and mostly
 describes where to find secondary configuration files:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 ! $XConsortium: xdm-conf.cpp /main/3 1996/01/15 15:17:26 gildea $
 DisplayManager.errorLogFile:	/var/log/xdm-errors
 DisplayManager.servers:		/etc/X11/xdm/Xservers
 DisplayManager.accessFile:	/etc/X11/xdm/Xaccess
 ! All displays should use authorization, but we cannot be sure
 ! X terminals will be configured that way, so by default
 ! use authorization only for local displays :0, :1, etc.
 DisplayManager._0.authorize:	true
 DisplayManager._1.authorize:	true
 ! The following three resources set up display :0 as the console.
 DisplayManager._0.setup:	/etc/X11/xdm/Xsetup_0
 DisplayManager._0.startup:	/etc/X11/xdm/GiveConsole
 DisplayManager._0.reset:	/etc/X11/xdm/TakeConsole
 !
 DisplayManager*resources:	/etc/X11/xdm/Xresources
 DisplayManager*session:		/etc/X11/xdm/Xsession
 !
 ! SECURITY: do not listen for XDMCP or Chooser requests
 ! Comment out this line if you want to manage X terminals with xdm
 DisplayManager.requestPort:	0

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 The <quote>!</quote> denotes comments. The command that starts the X server
 is in <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xservers</filename> in this particular example
 as defined by <quote>DisplayManager.servers</quote>, and is the equivalent to
 <filename>xserverrc</filename> that was used for <command>startx</command> X
 server start up commands, but the syntax is slightly different here. The
 contents of <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xservers</filename> on my system are simply:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 :0 local /usr/X11R6/bin/X 

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This starts <application>X</application> on the first local display
 (designated by 0). Any special command line arguments that you want to add go
 here at the end.

</para>

<para>
 Below is a sample <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xsetup&lowbar;0</filename> which is
 used to configure the log-in screen only. Notice that we're using a shell
 script here, and it's calling <command>xv</command> (a graphics display
 program) to set the background to a nice image (instead of the boring black
 and white background pattern), and if that fails,
 <command>xsetroot</command> is then invoked to at least try to set the
 background to a nicer blue color. This does not configure the login widget
 itself -- just other things that might be wanted on the screen during login.
 
</para>

<para>
 <screen>
 
 &num;!/bin/sh
 xconsole -geometry 480x100-0-0 -daemon -notify -verbose -fn \
   '-schumacher-clean-medium-r-*-*-10-*-*-*-*-*-*-*' -exitOnFail  &amp;
 
 /usr/X11R6/bin/xv -quit -root /usr/share/pixmaps/Backgrounds/InDreams.jpg \
   || xsetroot -solid darkblue
 
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xresources</filename> controls the X
 <quote>resources</quote> used during log in. In this context, <quote>resources</quote> 
 are user preferences for such items as fonts and colors (described in more
 detail below). Below is a snippet that sets up fonts for the log-in widget:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 #if WIDTH > 800
 xlogin*greetFont: -adobe-helvetica-bold-o-normal--24-240-75-75-p-138-iso8859-1
 xlogin*font: -adobe-helvetica-medium-r-normal--18-180-75-75-p-103-iso8859-1
 xlogin*promptFont: -adobe-helvetica-bold-r-normal--18-180-75-75-p-103-iso8859-1
 xlogin*failFont: -adobe-helvetica-bold-r-normal--18-180-75-75-p-103-iso8859-1
 #else
 xlogin*greetFont: -adobe-helvetica-bold-o-normal--17-120-100-100-p-92-iso8859-1
 xlogin*font: -adobe-helvetica-medium-r-normal--12-120-75-75-p-69-iso8859-1
 xlogin*promptFont: -adobe-helvetica-bold-r-normal--12-120-75-75-p-69-iso8859-1
 xlogin*failFont: -adobe-helvetica-bold-o-normal--14-140-75-75-p-82-iso8859-1
 #endif

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 As you can see this is using helvetica as the preferred font, with different
 point sizes and dots per inch depending on the screen size. This is
 customizable to suit individual needs. (See below for more on understanding X
 font naming conventions.) Various other aspects can similarly be configured.

</para>

<para>
 <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xsession</filename> is the rough equivalent to
 <filename>xinitrc</filename> for <command>startx</command>. It will similarly
 set up a default environment for keyboard, etc. And can also start either 
 <application>KDE</application> or <application>GNOME</application>, and other
 <application>X</application> client programs. This is the system wide
 configuration file. It should also check the user's home directory for
 <filename>~/.xsession</filename>, and possibly
 <filename>~/.Xclients</filename>, which would contain the user's preferred
 environment and start up programs, just as <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename>
 did with <command>startx</command>. Again, the files in a user's home
 directory may be created or modified by the user any time and must be
 executable shell scripts.

</para>

<para>
 We shall not include an <filename>~/.xsession</filename> example here, since it
 would be very similar to the <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename> and 
 <filename>~/.Xclients</filename> examples above.

</para>

<para>
 We've looked only briefly at the main <command>xdm</command> configuration files.
 Be sure to read the man page, and look at what is installed locally, for more 
 information. Let's look now at <command>gdm</command> and <command>kdm</command>. 
 We'll just highlight significant differences, since they essentially provide
 the same functionality.

</para>

</sect3>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>gdm</title>
<para>
 <command>gdm</command> is the default display manager for
 <application>GNOME</application>. <command>gdm</command> was written 
 from scratch, but functions similarly to <command>xdm</command>. The main
 configuration file is <filename>gdm.conf</filename>, typically located as
 <filename>/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf</filename>. This is quite different looking
 than <filename>xdm-config</filename>. Comments are denoted with a
 <quote>#</quote>, and the file has sections, with section headers enclosed
 in square brackets. The command to start <application>X</application> is in
 the <quote>[servers]</quote> section:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 [servers]
 0=/usr/bin/X11/X
 #1=/usr/bin/X11/X

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Notice this has potentially two displays set up, but the second one is
 commented out. Add any additional <application>X</application> startup
 options here, e.g. <quote>-dpi 100</quote>. The log-in screen and log-in
 widget are configured in the <quote>[greeter]</quote> section. 

</para>

<para>
 Start up clients and programs are determined by the <quote>SessionDir</quote>
 statement in the <quote>[daemon]</quote> section. On my installation, this
 points to <filename>/etc/X11/gdm/Sessions/</filename>, which contains several
 short scripts. If I look at my <filename>Default</filename> script, it
 actually executes <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xsession</filename>, which in turn
 would execute <filename>~/.xsession</filename>, if present. So at this final 
 stage, <command>gdm</command> acts very much like <command>xdm</command>.

</para>

<para>
 <application>GNOME</application> includes the <command>gdmconfig</command>
 utility to control many aspects of <command>gdm</command> behavior. 

</para>

</sect3>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>kdm</title>
<para>
 <command>kdm</command> is the display manager from <application>KDE</application>. 
 The main configuration file for <command>kdm</command> is
 <filename>kdmrc</filename> and is typically installed
 as <filename>/etc/kde/kdm/kdmrc</filename>. As is the case with
 <filename>gdm.conf</filename>, <filename>kdmrc</filename> uses
 <quote>#</quote> for comments, and has sections with section headers in
 similar square brackets. <command>kdm</command> configuration can also be
 edited with the <command>kcontrol</command> utility.

</para>

<para>
 The visible desktop is configured in the <quote>[Desktop*]</quote>
 section(s), and by the <quote>Setup</quote> directive which should point to a
 file like <filename>/usr/share/config/kdm/Xsetup</filename> or 
 <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xsetup_0</filename>. This will accomplish the same
 thing as <command>xdm</command>'s <filename>Xsetup_0</filename> does: namely
 running any programs the user might want such as <command>xconsole</command>.

</para>

<para>
 The command to launch the X server is the <quote>Xservers</quote> directive
 in the <quote>[General]</quote>. Again, this should point to a file such as 
 <filename>/etc/X11/xdm/Xservers</filename>, and uses the same syntax as
 <command>xdm</command>:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 :0 local /usr/X11R6/bin/X 

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Any command line options for the X server, go here.

</para>

<para>
 The login widget itself is configured in the <quote>[X-*-Greeter]</quote>
 section(s). Compiled in defaults are used if the user does not specify any.

</para>

<para>
 <application>KDE</application> includes the <command>kdmdesktop</command>
 utility to control some aspects of <command>kdm</command> behavior, mostly 
 just the login background.

</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="moreconfig">
<title>More X Configuration</title>

<para>
 Before taking a look at various configuration mechanisms for X servers and
 clients, it should be noted that the advent of Desktop Environments like 
 <application>KDE</application> have become popular in part because they can
 control much of the user interaction configuration themselves with nice, 
 <quote>user friendly</quote> GUI controls. And in fact,
 the compliant applications that are part of the respective Desktops will be
 best configured through the Desktop's configuration tools, or the
 application's own GUI configuration methods. So, for instance,
 <command>gtop</command>, a <application>GNOME</application> client
 application, is best configured via <application>GNOME</application> or 
 <command>gtop's</command> own menus. But this is not true of all 
 <application>X</application> applications. 

</para>


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect2 id="xresources">
<title>X Resources</title>

<para>
 The X server can store various configuration values for client programs
 so they are readily available when needed. If the application supports this,
 it will use these as defaults whenever that program is invoked. These are
 known as <quote>Resources</quote>, and are often used to define user preferences
 on a per application basis for fonts, colors, screen placement (geometry) and
 various other attributes. This makes it easy to customize applications.

</para>

<para>
 Resources are specified as text strings (e.g. Netscape*blinkingEnabled:
 False) that can be read from disk in various places when
 <application>X</application> is starting, or even interactively defined on the
 command line. Program components are named in a hierarchical fashion, with
 each object in the hierarchy identified by a class as well as an instance
 name. At the top level of the hierarchy is the class and instance name of the
 application itself. Typically, the class name of the application is the
 same as the program name, but with the first letter capitalized (e.g.  Vim or
 Emacs) although some programs that begin with the letter <quote>X</quote>
 also capitalize the second letter for historical reasons (e.g. XTerm). 
 Each definition  will specify a class (or instance), with corresponding
 resource and value. Below this in the hierarchy are the various attributes
 that make up the definable aspects of the application. 

</para>

<para>
 Traditionally, most <application>X</application> programs were  configured
 this way. This is not as true today with the advent of Desktop Environments
 which often have their own configuration mechanisms.

</para>

<para>
 As an example, say we prefer to run <command>xterm</command> with a blue
 background. So if we run it from the command line, we would run it as:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>
<![CDATA[
 xterm -bg blue &
]]>
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 If this is our preference, it would be easier to put this preference in a
 file somewhere, and have the system use our preference. That way whenever we
 started <command>xterm</command>, it would use our preferred value, and we 
 wouldn't need the command line options (unless as an override).

</para>

<para>
 The basic <application>X</application> resource syntax is expressed like:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 &lt;program&gt;&lt;binding&gt;&lt;widget&gt;&lt;binding&gt;&lt;widget&gt;&lt;...&gt;&lt;resource&gt;:&lt;value&gt;

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Which, in real life, typically looks something like:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 xterm*fontMenu*background: darkblue

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 It should be obvious what this does. The use of <quote>*</quote> in the
 definition, is called a <quote>loose binding</quote> and acts as a 
 wild-card. Meaning there may be gaps in the widget hierarchy. For instance:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 xterm*background: darkblue

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This would also give a dark blue background for the <command>xterm</command>
 fontMenu, but also any other <command>xterm</command> properties that also have a
 <quote>background</quote> attribute (e.g. window background, etc), no matter 
 where they may be in the widget hierarchy. Similarly:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 *background: darkblue

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This would define the background for any and all programs that support it -- not just
 <command>xterm</command>. Using a <quote>.</quote> in place of a
 <quote>*</quote> would be more precise, and will not allow for wild-card gaps
 in the hierarchy. Also, the application must support the particular widget 
 attribute. <quote>Background</quote> is a fairly safe bet, but many
 applications will have more specialized resources that are not so obvious. It
 is best to check local documentation (man pages, etc), or see if an
 application has an included examples. For instance, <command>Netscape</command> 
 generally comes with an <filename>Netscape.ad</filename> file that has an extensive 
 set of resource definitions that can be customized.

</para>

<para>
 <application>X</application> resources are typically stored in more than one
 place (see below) and are processed by the <command>xrdb</command> command (see man page).

</para>


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>App Defaults</title>
<para>
 One way of storing preferred application resources is via files named for the
 application in an <quote>app-defaults</quote> directory. For instance, on my
 system, these are in <filename>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/app-defaults/</filename>,
 though this may vary according to options your vendor has chosen. This
 directory contains a number of files for such well known
 <application>X</application> applications as <command>xterm</command>,
 <command>xclock</command>, <command>xcalc</command>,
 <command>xload</command>, and so on. All in all, it is a relatively small 
 number of applications in the overall scheme of things. So not all
 applications use this scheme. In fact, most do not.

</para>

<para>
 Each file will contain resource definitions for that application. The X
 server loads these by itself during start up. A brief example from 
 <filename>XTerm-color</filename>:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 ! $XFree86$

 #include "XTerm"

 *VT100*colorMode: on
 *VT100*dynamicColors: on

 ! Uncomment this use color for underline attribute
 !*VT100*colorULMode: on
 !*VT100*underLine: off

 ! Uncomment this to use color for the bold attribute
 !*VT100*colorBDMode: on

 *VT100*color0: black
 *VT100*color1: red3
 *VT100*color2: green3
 *VT100*color3: yellow3
 *VT100*color4: blue3
 *VT100*color5: magenta3
 *VT100*color6: cyan3
 *VT100*color7: gray90
 *VT100*color8: gray30
 *VT100*color9: red
 *VT100*color10: green
 *VT100*color11: yellow
 *VT100*color12: blue
 *VT100*color13: magenta
 *VT100*color14: cyan
 *VT100*color15: white
 *VT100*colorUL: yellow
 *VT100*colorBD: white

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This is mostly various color definitions. The application classname is not
 explicitly stated, and is assumed from the filename. So think of each line as
 starting: <literal>XTerm-color*</literal>. Also, notice at the top, the
 <literal>#include "XTerm"</literal> line, which <quote>includes</quote> the
 resource definitions for <command>XTerm</command>, a much longer file with a
 more diverse set of definitions. (Not included due to length, but worth
 looking at.) These files provide system wide defaults, and generally
 speaking, would not normally be edited by the user.
 
</para>

</sect3>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>Xdefaults</title>

<para>
 Another common method of reading in resource preferences, is with an
 <filename>Xdefaults</filename> file. Or, sometimes the naming 
 scheme may be <filename>Xresources</filename> instead. This may exist as a
 system wide file, such as <filename>/etc/X11/Xresources</filename>. 
 Of course, the user is free to create a personal version in his home
 directory, e.g. <filename>~/.Xdefaults</filename>. The user's version will 
 over-ride any system wide settings, and will remain after system upgrades. 
 Obviously, this is the place to put your own preferences.

</para>

<para>
 <filename>Xresources</filename> files are read into the resource database
 with the <command>xrdb</command> command. Example:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 xrdb -merge ~/.Xresources

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This can be done interactively at the command line, or placed in a script and
 run automatically as the <application>X</application> session is started. In
 the case of system wide files, this should be taken care of by the vendor
 supplied start up scripts. Generally, such scripts will also check the user's
 home directory as well (see the <filename>xinitrc</filename> example above).
 So probably all that need be done, is to create the file with a text editor.

</para>

<para>
 Here's an example to illustrate a very few of the many things that might
 be done with an <filename>.Xdefaults</filename> file:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 ! This is a comment ;-)

 #ifdef COLOR
 *customization: -color
 #endif

 !! Let's cast a wide net, for any app supporting these
 ! Blink instead of beeping
 *visualBell: True
 *scrollTtyOutput: False
 *scrollKey:       True

 ! See Netscape.ad for many settable resources
 Netscape*noAboutSplash:	True
 Netscape*documentFonts.sizeIncrement: 5
 Netscape*documentFonts.xResolution*iso-8859-1: 120
 Netscape*documentFonts.yResolution*iso-8859-1: 120
 netscape-navigator*geometry: 960x820+240+140

 emacs*Background: DarkBlue
 emacs*Foreground: Wheat
 emacs*pointerColor: Orchid
 emacs*cursorColor: Orchid
 emacs*bitmapIcon: on
 emacs*font: 10x20

 ! GVim colors, etc
 !! GTK versions of gvim will not use all these.
 Vim*useSchemes:         all
 Vim*sgiMode:            true
 Vim*useEnhancedFSB:     true
 Vim.foreground:         Black
 !Vim.background:        lightyellow2
 Vim*background:         white
 ! geometry: width x height
 Vim.geometry:  88x40
 Vim*font:  -misc-fixed-medium-r-normal--20-200-75-75-c-100-iso8859-15-*5
 Vim*menuBackground: yellow
 Vim*menuForeground: black

 rxvt*backspacekey: ^?
 rxvt*background: Black
 rxvt*foreground: wheat
 rxvt*cursorColor: Orchid
 rxvt*geometry: 100x18+40+300 
 rxvt*title: Linux
 rxvt*reverseVideo: false
 !rxvt*backgroundPixmap: ~/penguinitis.xpm
 rxvt*scrollBar: true
 rxvt*reverseWrap: true
 rxvt*font: -*-lucidatypewriter-medium-*-*-*-14-*-*-*-*-*-*-*
 rxvt*fullCursor: true
 rxvt*saveLines:  1500
 rxvt*menu: ~/rxvt.menu

 XTerm*saveLines:    1500
 ! Do not clear the screen after the program exits
 XTerm*VT100*titeInhibit: true

 ! Fix up xterm's keybindings 
 xterm*VT100.translations:	#override \
       &lt;Key&gt;BackSpace:    string(0x7F) \n\
       &lt;Key&gt;Insert:       string(0x1b) string("[2~")\n\
       &lt;Key&gt;Delete:       string(0x1b) string("[3~")\n\
       &lt;Key&gt;Home:         string(0x1b) string("[1~")\n\
       &lt;Key&gt;End:	     string(0x1b) string("[4~")\n\
       &lt;Key&gt;Page_Up:      string(0x1b) string("[5~")\n\
       &lt;Key&gt;Page_Down:    string(0x1b) string("[6~")\n\
       &lt;KeyPress&gt;Prior : scroll-back(1,page)\n\
       &lt;KeyPress&gt;Next : scroll-forw(1,page)

 ! Ghostview
 Ghostview*Font: *-helvetica-bold-r-normal--12-*-*-*-*-*-*
 Ghostview*BorderColor:  white
 Ghostview*Text*Font:    rk14
 Ghostview*Background:   #d9d9d9
 !Ghostview*Foreground:  white
 ghostview.form.pageview.page.background: white
 ghostview.form.pageview.page.foreground: black
 .ghostview.zoom.form.page.background: white
 .ghostview.zoom.form.page.foreground: black

 ! xscreensaver !
 ! Time out after 12 minutes, cycle mode after each 2
 xscreensaver.timeout: 12
 xscreensaver.cycle: 5
 ! Run low priority, and fade between modes
 xscreensaver.nice: 12
 xscreensaver.fadeSeconds: 2

 XFontsel.menu.options.showUnselectable: False
 
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Hopefully, these few examples will give you some ideas to build on.
 <application>X</application> does not need to be restarted if
 <command>xrdb</command> is used interactively from the command line after
 making changes. The effects are immediate.

</para>

<para>
 Resources are sometimes available also as command line options. See below. 
 Command line options will over-ride any existing resource definitions.

</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>xmodmap, the Keyboard and Mice</title>
<para>
 The keyboard and mouse, as well as other possible input devices, are defined
 in <filename>XF86Config</filename> (or <filename>XF86Config-4</filename>).
 There is a keyboard layout that is defined based on the preferred language:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 Section "InputDevice"
	Identifier  "Keyboard0"
	Driver      "keyboard"
	Option      "XkbLayout"	"us"
 EndSection

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This gives us our default keyboard layout. Valid layout labels are listed in
 <filename>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/xkb/symbols</filename>. Also, the
 <command>setxkbmap</command> utility can be used to change this
 interactively.

</para>

<para>
 <application>X</application> is highly customizable, and we can modify the
 keyboard and mouse pointer mappings to suit our own preferences. The utility
 to do this is <command>xmodmap</command> (see man page). You don't like where
 the capslock key is? So move it ;-)

</para>

<para>
 Like <command>xrdb</command>, <command>xmodmap</command> can be run from the
 command line. Or, preferred settings can be stored in a file. Typically this
 is <filename>~/.Xmodmap</filename>, or similar. If your
 <application>X</application> start up files don't parse this, then edit as
 appropriate so that they do (probably from <filename>~/.xinitrc</filename> or
 <filename>~/.xsession</filename>).

</para>

<para>
 You can view your current key and mouse mappings with: <command>xmodmap -pk
 -pp |less</command>. This will print out all active <quote>keycode</quote>
 values, with corresponding <quote>keysym</quote> values, and any keysym names
 that <command>xmodmap</command> knows about (e.g. <quote>BackSpace</quote>).
 And should also give you an idea of how <command>xmodmap</command>
 understands key and mouse events. There are two keysyms per keycode. The
 second is the shifted value. XFree86's <command>xev</command> utility can be
 used to dump a lot of information on key-presses and mouse events
 interactively. Pay attention to the <quote>keycode</quote> value. That is
 what you will need to know in order to re-map.

</para>

<para>
 <command>xmodmap</command> is often used to make minor keyboard adjustments,
 like proper Backspace/Delete mapping. Or can be used make major adjustments
 such as for international mappings. You can only re-map keys and mouse events
 -- you cannot assign macros to key events (your Window Manager or Desktop
 might have some of this functionality).

</para>

<para>
 A nice discussion of 
<ulink
 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Intkeyb/index.html"
>setting up international keyboards
</ulink>.
 
Also, 
<ulink url="http://google.com/linux"
>Google search</ulink> 
 will turn up many creative examples.

</para>

<para>
 The man page has many brief examples of various usages. Here is what an 
 one hypothetical <filename>~/.Xmodmap</filename> might look like:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 ! /home/hal/.Xmodmap, last change 10/03/01
 !
 ! Force backspace to 22 and Delete to 111
 keycode 22 = BackSpace
 keycode 111 = Delete
 !
 ! My keyboard handles right and left Alt differently. Make the 
 ! Right act like the Left to avoid digital gymnastics.
 keycode 63 = Alt_L
 keycode 113 = Meta_L
 !
 ! Hard-code the keypad to numeric values as if numlock is always on 
 ! since I never use it for anything else.
 keycode 79=7
 keycode 80=8
 keycode 81=9
 keycode 83=4
 keycode 84=5
 keycode 85=6
 keycode 87=1
 keycode 88=2
 keycode 89=3
 keycode 90=0
 keycode 91=period
 keycode 86 = plus
 ! deactivate Num_Lock key since we don't need it now.
 keycode 77 =
 !
 ! My capslock is next to tab. I hit it by mistake sometimes, 
 ! and don't use it anyway. So make capslock act like Tab.
 keycode 66 = Tab
 clear lock
 !
 ! Reverse mouse buttons for left-handed people
 pointer = 3 2 1

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 As with many XFree86 files, the <quote>!</quote> represents a comment. 
 Another possible use, is to redefine those annoying <quote>Windows</quote>
 keys to something useful. Hopefully this gives an idea of some things one
 might want to do to make the keyboard more agreeable to us.

</para>

<para>
 Speaking of the <literal>Numlock</literal> key, <application>X</application>
 will typically disable this when it starts up. No matter how you have the
 BIOS set up, or Linux set up before <application>X</application> starts. So the
 trick above is one way. There is also a utility available as either
 <application>numlockx</application>, or
 <application>setnumlock</application>, that can be found on the Net, if
 your distribution does not include one or the other. This can be put in a
 start up file to turn <literal>Numlock</literal> on automatically if you would
 prefer.

</para>

<para>
 Window Managers and Desktop Environments will also allow customization of the
 keyboard and mouse (as long as it is recognized correctly by
 <application>X</application>). This may be an easier way to configure certain 
 customizations.

</para>



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>Special Key Mappings</title>
<para>
 There are several special key mappings traditionally used in
 XFree86.

</para>

 <variablelist>

  <varlistentry><term ><keycombo ><keycap >Ctrl</keycap > 
<keycap >Alt</keycap > <keycap >BackSpace</keycap ></keycombo 
></term > 
   <listitem ><para>
     Will kill the <application>X</application> server process in an orderly
     fashion. This is a quick, easy, legitimate way to restart
     <application>X</application>. Note it does not restart the display
     manager (if used) &mdash; just <application>X</application> itself.
   </para>
  </listitem> </varlistentry >

  <varlistentry ><term ><keycombo ><keycap >Ctrl</keycap > 
<keycap >Alt</keycap > 
<keycap >F<replaceable >n</replaceable ></keycap ></keycombo 
></term ><listitem>
   <para>
    
where <replaceable >n</replaceable > 
corresponds to a valid <acronym >TTY</acronym > number
    (typically 1&ndash;6). 
This is typically used to jump to a text console login,
    while <application>X</application> remains running. To get back to
    <application>X</application>, 
press 
<keycombo ><keycap >Alt</keycap > 
<keycap >F<replaceable >n</replaceable ></keycap ></keycombo >. In this
    case, <replaceable >n</replaceable> 
represents one plus the last <acronym >TTY</acronym > 
(e.g. <keycombo ><keycap >Alt</keycap > <keycap >F7</keycap ></keycombo > if
    there are six available <acronym >TTY</acronym >&rsquo;s). 
   </para>
  </listitem> </varlistentry >

  <varlistentry 
><term 
><keycombo 
><keycap 
>Ctrl</keycap > <keycap >Alt</keycap > <keycap >+</keycap ></keycombo > 
and <keycombo 
><keycap 
>Ctrl</keycap > <keycap >Alt</keycap > <keycap >-</keycap ></keycombo ></term 
><listitem>
   <para>
    That is the plus and minus keys on
    the keypad. This will cycle through any existing valid screen resolution 
    modes, e.g. 1024&times;768 &rarr; 600&times;800. Note the actual screen
    size is the same &mdash; just the view and resolution changes. 
Not all that
    useful for most purposes. You cannot permanently change the screen 
    resolution without restarting <application>X</application>.
    
   </para>
  </listitem> </varlistentry >

 </variablelist>

<para>
 It's possible your Window Manager, Desktop Environment or other system
 component may trap these, and alter the standard behavior. In addition, the
 <keycombo
 ><keycap >Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Alt</keycap> 
 <keycap >Delete</keycap></keycombo> may be trapped as well. This should shut
 <application>X</application> (and the system) down orderly, if it is
 available.

</para>

</sect3>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>Mice and Pointers</title>

<para>
  As mentioned, Linux and Unix make heavy use of three mouse buttons. If a
  mouse only has two buttons, then the third (i.e. the middle) button can
  be simulated by pressing both buttons simultaneously. This is a
  configuration option set in <filename>XF86Config</filename> as the 
  <quote>Emulate3Buttons</quote> directive:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 Section "InputDevice"
	Identifier  "Mouse0"
	Driver      "mouse"
	Option      "Device" "/dev/mouse"
	Option      "Protocol" "PS/2"
	Option      "Emulate3Buttons" "on"
 EndSection

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 When all is said and done, a third button is quite handy and I would personally recommend
 having one. On wheeled mice, the <quote>wheel</quote> acts as the third
 button, if pressed. Many standard wheel mice seem to work with the
 <quote>IMPS/2</quote> protocol option.

</para>

<para>
 Specifically, the third button (middle) is the <quote>paste</quote> button in
 virtually all Linux applications. Copy and paste works a little different in
 Linux. The left button is the copy button. Just hold it down, and drag over
 text. It is automatically copied to the <application>X</application>
 <quote>clipboard</quote>. Then, the middle button will paste from there. A
 very simple process. A double-click should copy individual words, and a
 triple-click individual lines of text. If for some reason, this does not
 work, it is either a poorly implemented application, or a bug of some kind.
 Some older versions of <application>Netscape</application> were not
 consistent about this, for instance. To paste from the keyboard, this should 
 be shift+insert.

</para>

<para>
 <quote>Drag and Drop</quote> is not natively supported by
 <application>X</application> itself. But, is implemented by some toolkits and
 Desktop Environments. One should not expect this to work with non-compliant
 applications (i.e non-<application>KDE</application> aware applications in 
 <application>KDE</application> for example).

</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>xset</title>
<para>
 <command>xset</command> is yet another XFree86 utility to set user
 preferences. <command>xset</command> is a bit of a catch-all and is used 
 to change various, unrelated X server settings. Mostly this is a command 
 line way of configuring some of the same things that are defined in 
 <filename>XF86Config</filename> (but not everything!).

</para>

<para>
 Common usages of <command>xset</command> are to set DPMS on or off and
 preferred intervals, to dynamically change the FontPath or re-read it, to
 control keyboard LEDs, to adjust mouse (or other pointer) movement speed,
 set keyboard <quote>autorepeat</quote> and <quote>repeat</quote> rates, and
 to control <application>X's</application> built in screen blanking. See the
 man page, of course, for detailed explanations, and other
 <command>xset</command> usages.

</para>

<para>
 Again, <command>xset</command> can be used interactively from the command
 line. But most often preferred settings are stored in one of the start up 
 configuration files, like <filename>.xinitrc</filename> or
 <filename>.xsession</filename>. A very brief example:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 # Turn off screen blanking
 xset s off
 
 # Enable DPMS energy saving
 xset +dpms
 
 # Tweak the rodent
 xset m 30/10 4
 
 # Speed up keyboard
 xset r rate 200 40

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Your desktop may have a GUI front-end for <command>xset</command>.

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="fontscolors">
<title>Fonts and Colors</title>

<para>
 Understanding fonts and colors can be more complex in
 <application>X</application> than on other platforms. 
</para>


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Fonts Demystified</title>

<para>
 <application>X</application> knows about various font types, including
 bitmaps, Type 1, and as of v4.x, TrueType. The X server can either handle
 fonts itself, or sometimes this duty is forked to a font server (of which
 there are several). <command>xfs</command> (X Font Server) is the most common
 font server in use on Linux.

</para>

<para>
 A font server is not required, as <application>X</application> can handle
 most font rendering itself. Font servers are traditionally used for serving
 fonts to multiple hosts on a network, but sometimes are also used to provide 
 enhanced functionality. Additionally, a font server may provide a modest
 performance boost by off-loading font rendering to a separate process.

</para>

<para>
 <application>X</application> knows about fonts according to fonts that are in
 the <quote>FontPath</quote>. This is set initially in
 <filename>XF86Config</filename>. If the X server is handling font duties
 itself (i.e. no font server), this will be a list of directories that contain
 font files, like:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/misc:unscaled"
 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi:unscaled"
 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi:unscaled"
 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/Type1"
 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/misc"
 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/100dpi"
 FontPath        "/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/75dpi"

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 If a font server is being used, the <quote>FontPath</quote> will point to the
 socket where the font server is serving (this is just one possible example):

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 FontPath "unix/:7101"

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 In this latter case, the actual font directories that are available will be
 configured with the font server (see local documentation), which will use a
 similar directory type scheme as shown for <filename>XF86Config</filename>.

</para>

<para>
 Once suitable fonts have been installed, they must be
 <quote>prepared</quote>. For most fonts, this means running the 
 <command>mkfontdir</command> utility (see man page) in the directory where
 the fonts are (as root). Type 1 and TrueType require additional steps (see
 below). Your vendor has done this for any fonts that were included with your
 distribution. So, this will only need to be done for fonts that you add. For
 newly added fonts to become visible to <application>X</application>, 
 you will need to run the appropriate
 <command>xset</command> commands to either modify the existing FontPath, or
 re-read it (see man page). Or, re-initialize your font server.

</para>

<para>
 Example: Preparing fonts, and re-initializing font server after adding new
 fonts:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 su 
 &lt;password&gt;
 mkfontdir /usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/my_new_fonts/
 /etc/init.d/xfs restart

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 The first command may not be necessary on newer distros (since it's done by
 the init script in some cases). And the font server configuration would need
 to be modified, if this is a new directory. Example: re-initializing with no
 font server:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 su 
 &lt;password&gt;
 mkfontdir /usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/my_new_fonts/
 xset +fp /usr/X11R6/lib/X11/fonts/my_new_fonts/
 xset fp rehash

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 The <quote><command>xset +fp</command></quote> would not be necessary if the
 directory is already part of the FontPath.

</para>

<para>
 <command>xlsfonts | less</command> can be used to list what fonts are known,
 and thus available, to <application>X</application> and its clients. Run
 <command>xlsfonts | less</command>, and you also can get an idea of the font
 definition as understood by <application>X</application>. Font resources are
 specified quite explicitly, and it may seem complex at first. The <emphasis>X
 Logical Font Description</emphasis> (<quote>XLFD</quote>) is the full
 description for any given font. The XLFD looks like: 
 
</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 -adobe-helvetica-medium-r-normal-*-*-120-*-*-p-*-iso10646-1

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Where each field, left to right is:

</para>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">fndry</literal> - font foundry, the company or individual
  which made the font.
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">fmly</literal> - font family, the popular nickname of the font
 </member>
</simplelist>


<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">wght</literal> - font weight (bold, medium, etc.)
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">slant</literal> - font slant (italics, oblique, roman
  (normal), etc.)

 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">sWdth</literal> - font width (normal, condensed, extended, etc.)
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">adstyl</literal> - additional style (sans serif, serif, etc.)
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">pxlsz</literal> - pixel size, the number of pixels
  vertically in a character
 </member>
</simplelist>


<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">ptSz</literal> - approximate point size of the text
  (similar to pxlsz)
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">resx</literal> - horizontal resolution, in dpi
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">resy</literal> - vertical resolution, in dpi
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">spc</literal> - spacing, only useful, apparently, in the
  Schumacher fonts
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">avgWidth</literal> - average character width of the font
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">rgstry</literal> - the recognized registry that lists
  the font 
 </member>
</simplelist>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  <literal remap="tt">encdng</literal> - nationality encoding
 </member>
</simplelist>

<para>
 The <quote>*</quote> acts as a wild-card character. In fact, if not every
 field is specified, the X server will take the first match it finds in 
 the FontPath. This is why it is best to order the FontPath with preferred
 fonts coming first since some programs will deliberately specify fonts 
 <quote>loosely</quote> so that your system has some discretion.

</para>

<para>
 The program <command>xfontsel</command> (<application>X</application> 
 Font Selector) may be useful. Try launching it now. You will see 
 nothing helpful in the main window at first, but try holding the left button
 down on the <literal remap="tt">fndry</literal> button. If all your fonts are
 in order, you will see a menu of selections such as <literal
 remap="tt">adobe</literal> and <literal remap="tt">b&amp;h</literal> and
 <literal remap="tt">bitstream</literal> and so forth. Select one such as
 <literal remap="tt">b&amp;h</literal> and you will notice that the font in
 the lower window changes to something intelligible. This is the way 
 fonts are selected with this program; starting from the left, which is the
 most general selection, and moving toward the right, to the more specific
 options. Selecting an option toward the rightmost end will not make much
 sense before the foundry, for instance, is selected, because the options are
 generally ordered by their dependence on each other. 
 
</para>

<para>
 When you select from the <literal remap="tt">fmly</literal> selection,
 you will see most of the options grayed out, and only three remaining. That
 means that these three are the only families of font made by this foundry.
 Some families appear under more than one foundry, for instance, both
 <emphasis>Adobe</emphasis> and <emphasis>Bitstream</emphasis> make a
 variation of the Courier font. Now you can select the <literal
 remap="tt">wght</literal>, and so forth. After you get far enough you will
 have narrowed it down to the font that you want. You don't necessarily have
 to fill in all the options to choose a single font, there's not
 <emphasis>that</emphasis> many fonts on your system! The options that you do
 not select will be represented by a <literal remap="tt">*</literal>
 indicating that any option will do in that spot, and gives X some leeway.
</para>

<para>
 When you are satisfied with your font selection, hit the select button,
 and your selection will be placed in the <application>X</application>
 clipboard, ready to be pasted into your document or whatever you are working
 on. For example, open an <emphasis remap="bf">xterm</emphasis> window and
 type in something like <literal remap="tt">xterm -font </literal> followed by
 an opening quotation mark. Then point to that spot on your screen, and click
 your middle mouse button (or click both the left and right, if you are
 middle-button impaired). This will paste the selection from the clipboard,
 which should be the font you just selected. Then enter the closing quote, and
 hit <literal remap="tt">Enter</literal>. For instance, a nice big <emphasis
 remap="bf">xterm</emphasis> with a Courier font specified would look like
 this: <literal remap="tt">xterm -font
 &quot;-adobe-courier-medium-r-*-*-14-*-*-*-*-*-*-*&quot;</literal>. 
</para>

<para>
 If you've found a font you prefer, this can permanently be used by placing the 
 font definition in the appropriate configuration file (see above).

</para>

<para>
  Note that you can also limit the number of fonts that you want 
  <command>xfontsel</command> to display with the command line option
 <emphasis>-pattern</emphasis>, followed by a quoted font specification, as
 discussed above.

</para>

<para>
 The <command>xfd</command> utility is also helpful for examining
 individual fonts. If launched with a command line such as <command>xfd
 -fn fixed</command>, it will show you the complete character set for that font.
</para>

<para>
 <application>KDE</application> and <application>GNOME</application> have
 their own utilities that are not quite as obtuse ;-)

</para>



<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect3>
<title>Type 1 and TrueType Fonts</title>

<para>
 The fonts provided with XFree86 are of limited use for many of us,
 considering that about the only place you'll find fonts of that kind, are
 used in the X Window System itself for the most part. Unfortunately many
 media junkies, web designers and fontaholics work in operating systems that
 rely on other formats. And then, there often does not seem to be much
 emphasis by some distributions on making the best of the default fonts
 either. 
</para>

<para>
 Type 1 fonts, most commonly used in conjunction with PostScript document
 formats, are the traditional standard in Unix and Linux environments. You
 should have a reasonably good starter selection installed already. Or, more
 can be found for free on the Internet with considerable ease, and Try <ulink
 url="ftp://ftp.cdrom.com/pub/os2/fonts/">ftp://ftp.cdrom.com/pub/os2/fonts/</ulink>
 for starters. Type 1 are scalable fonts, and have many of the same benefits
 of the better known TrueType fonts. If you don't have a good selection of
 TrueType fonts installed, then Type 1 is what you want for most GUI
 applications. But again, this is not standard on  other platforms, and can 
 present problems when viewing documents (e.g. web pages) that are designed 
 with <quote>other platforms</quote> in mind.

</para>

<para>
 TrueType fonts started with Apple, and later were licensed by Microsoft. So
 people migrating from non-Unix platforms are already familiar with these high
 quality fonts. Unfortunately, there are not many quality TrueType fonts under
 a suitable license, and thus there are not many included with Linux
 distributions. And the ones that are, often are not as high quality. Also
 unfortunately, TrueType has become somewhat of a standard on the Web and in
 other venues, and not having good TrueType fonts can be a detriment. 
 XFree86 also seems to render TrueType a little better than Type1.

</para>

<para>
 That is the bad news. The good news is that any TrueType font included with
 any version of Windows, or any Windows applications, should work on Linux.
 Though you will have to take some additional steps to integrate them. This 
 particularly helps web browsing where <application>X's</application>
 bitmapped fonts just don't scale well.

</para>

<para>
 
We shall not go into detail on installing and configuring these fonts here, 
as it is addressed in depth in other documents. See 
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Font-HOWTO.html">The Font HOWTO</ulink>
 for general font information, and Type 1 tips. 
See <citetitle>The Font De-Uglification 
 Mini HOWTO</citetitle>, 
<ulink
 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FDU/index.html"
>The Font De-Uglification 
 Mini HOWTO</ulink>,
 for various <application>X</application> related font tips, especially TrueType.

</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>


<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Colors</title>

<para>
 Let's go back to our terminal window and try something. Open an
 <command>xterm</command> with a command line like the following:
</para>

<para>
 <screen>
 
 xterm -fg DarkSteelBlue1 -bg red3 &amp;
 
 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Ouch! While that may not be pretty, and you may not do much of your best work
 in it, it demonstrates one interesting aspect of <application>X</application>
 configuration -- color names. While not particularly precise, this is a nice
 way to remember a variety of colors. Note that color names are never
 case-sensitive.

</para>

<para>
 The X server will actually deal with color values as a hexadecimal
 Red-Green-Blue (RGB) color notation. This would look something like
 <quote>#0aff0a</quote> in hex. Not so easy to remember. But
 <application>X</application> gives a more mnemonic way of remembering valid
 color definitions. These are stored in a text table, typically as
 <filename>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/rgb.txt</filename>, and is defined in 
 <filename>XF86Config</filename> in the <quote>Files</quote> section.

</para>

<para>
 If you are interested, have a look with a text editor. There are many, many
 shades defined. I count eighty-three shades of blue in mine, for instance. Brief
 snip:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 176 226 255             LightSkyBlue1
 164 211 238             LightSkyBlue2
 141 182 205             LightSkyBlue3
  96 123 139             LightSkyBlue4
 202 225 255             LightSteelBlue1
 188 210 238             LightSteelBlue2
 162 181 205             LightSteelBlue3
 110 123 139             LightSteelBlue4
 191 239 255             LightBlue1
 178 223 238             LightBlue2
 154 192 205             LightBlue3
 104 131 139             LightBlue4

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This file can be customized should you desire, but this is rarely needed for
 most of us. It is important to have though, since some applications depend on
 it. 

</para>

<para>
 Desktop Environments will have a GUI utility for selecting colors.

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="windowman">
<title>Window Managers and Desktops</title>

<para>
 We shall not delve into configuring Window Manager's and Desktop Environments.
 There is just too much to try to cover in one document. It is important to
 realize that the two are not the same. There are many, many Window Managers
 available. 
</para>

<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Window Managers</title>

<para>
 Window Managers are highly configurable. Many aspects of user interaction can 
 be controlled by the Window Manager.

</para>

<para>
 Some of the most popular Window Managers:

</para>

<simplelist>
 <member>
  aewm: <ulink url="http://www.red-bean.com/~decklin/aewm/">http://www.red-bean.com/~decklin/aewm/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  AfterStep: <ulink url="http://www.afterstep.org/">http://www.afterstep.org/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  BlackBox: <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/blackboxwm">http://sourceforge.net/projects/blackboxwm</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  Enlightenment: <ulink url="http://www.enlightenment.org/pages/main.html">http://www.enlightenment.org/pages/main.html</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  Fluxbox: <ulink url="http://fluxbox.sourceforge.net/">http://fluxbox.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  fvwm: <ulink url="http://www.fvwm.org/">http://www.fvwm.org/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  IceWM: <ulink url="http://www.icewm.org/">http://www.icewm.org/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  olwm (OpenLook Window Manager): 
  <ulink url="http://www.plig.org/xwinman/olvwm.html">http://www.plig.org/xwinman/olvwm.html</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  Sawmill: <ulink url="http://sawmill.sourceforge.net/">http://sawmill.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  WindowMaker: <ulink url="http://www.windowmaker.org/">http://www.windowmaker.org/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>
<simplelist>
 <member>
  XFce: <ulink url="http://xfce.org/">http://xfce.org/</ulink>
 </member>
</simplelist>

<para>
 There are many, many lesser known ones as well. 
 <ulink url="http://www.plig.org/xwinman/">http://www.plig.org/xwinman/</ulink> 
 has an updated list of Window Managers, and related information.
 There is always <ulink url="http://freshmeat.net">freshmeat</ulink> too.

</para>

<para>
 <application>GNOME</application> and <application>KDE</application>
 both have their default Window Manager, but support other, compliant Window
 Managers as well. Your distribution probably has included at least several.
 Try them all if you don't already have a favorite. Your distribution probably
 also has a method of switching dynamically between Window Managers (and Desktop
 Environments too).

</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Desktop Environments</title>

<para>
 Desktop Environments are not really new, but their popularity has increased
 with advent of the two big names: <application>KDE</application> and
 <application>GNOME</application>. To a certain extent, the Desktop
 Environment functionality overlaps the Window Manager's. They both can be
 responsible for the root window background, root window menu, icons,
 taskbars, etc. Generally speaking, if a Desktop Environment is running, it is
 controlling these aspects. That is the main idea behind them -- to integrate
 the various components into a cohesive, consistent whole. Desktop
 Environments also add some interoperability and ease-of-use features that a
 simple Window Manager cannot. 
</para>

<para>
 Oh, another point: Desktop Environments also try to do as much
 <application>X</application> session configuration as possible. Any of their
 compliant clients will more than likely be configured by the Desktop, or have
 it's own configuration that conforms to the Desktop's style. This is at
 least partly to avoid much of the seemingly helter-skelter text file
 configuration we looked at in the above sections, and make life a little
 easier for the user.

</para>

<para>
 There is a trade-off in this additional functionality, and that is that it
 takes memory and system resources to oversee all this. If you have plenty of
 memory and a fast computer, this is no problem. But in low memory situations,
 this can cause a slowdown (see the <link linkend="performance">performance
 section</link> below). 64M of RAM is probably borderline with either 
 <application>KDE</application> or <application>GNOME</application>.

</para>

<para>
 So do you need a Desktop Environment? That is up to the user. They are
 certainly not required to run <application>X</application>, but do add
 features that many users want or expect in a GUI. Which one is better? Ah,
 but that is up to you to decide!

</para>


<para>
 <application>KDE</application> has been around longer than
 <application>GNOME</application>, and some would say maybe a little more
 mature. <application>KDE</application> is based on the QT widget toolkit. A
 quote from the <ulink url="http://kde.org">KDE home page</ulink>:

</para>

<blockquote>
 <para> 
  KDE is a powerful Open Source graphical desktop environment for Unix
  workstations.  It combines ease of use, contemporary functionality, and
  outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
  operating system.
</para>

<para>
 KDE is a mature desktop suite providing a solid basis to an ever growing
 number of applications for Unix workstations.  KDE has developed a high
 quality development framework for Unix, which allows for the rapid and
 efficient creation of applications.
</para>

</blockquote>


<para>
 <application>GNOME</application> is based on the GTK+ toolkit.
 And a quote from the <ulink url="http://gnome.org">GNOME home page</ulink>:
</para>

<blockquote> 
 <para>
 GNOME stands for GNU Network Object Model Environment. The GNOME project
 intends to build a complete, user-friendly desktop based entirely on free
 software. GNOME is part of the GNU project, and GNOME is part of the Open
 Source(tm) movement. The desktop will consist of small utilities and larger
 applications which share a consistent look and feel. GNOME uses GTK+ as the
 GUI toolkit for all GNOME-compliant applications.
 </para>
</blockquote> 

<para>
 <application>XFce</application> is a lighter weight, less featureful Desktop
 Environment that does not get as much attention as the others.
 <application>XFce</application> is also based on the GTK+ toolkit. And a
 quote from the <ulink url="http://xfce.org">XFce home page</ulink>:
</para>

<blockquote> 
 <para>
  The XFce project was first started because I needed a simple, light and
  efficient environment for my Linux System.
 </para>
 <para>
  I believe that the desktop environment should be made to increase user
  productivity. Therefore, the goal is keep most system resources for the
  applications, and not to consume all memory and CPU usage with the desktop
  environment.
 </para>
</blockquote> 

<para>
 All these have their own extensive documentation. If you can't find what you
 need installed on your system, check the respective home pages.

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="cli">
<title>X and the Command Line</title>

<para>
 What would a Unix-like operating system be without a command line 
 interface?  The command line can be useful, and is readily available with
 <application>X</application>. In fact, for many it is an integral part 
 of their <application>X</application> working environment. 

</para>

<para>
 Any <application>X</application> program can be started directly from the
 command line just by typing the program name at a shell prompt in an
 <command>xterm</command>, or other terminal window. Most applications will
 have a very rich set of command line <quote>options</quote>, such as
 background color, font, geometry (screen placement), etc, etc. Command line
 options over-ride compiled in defaults, or other system enabled
 <quote>resources</quote>.
 
</para>

<para>
 Many traditional <application>X</application> programs will use the same
 basic names for command line options. All applications written using the 
 MIT X Toolkit Intrinsics (Xt) (such as those included with XFree86)
 automatically accept the following options. Some non-Xt applications also use
 these, or something similar. For instance, <quote>geometry</quote> is close 
 to a universally accepted option.
</para>

<para>
 <variablelist>
 
<varlistentry>
 <term>-display <emphasis>[host]:display[.screen]</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    This option specifies the X server display to use. This is often used 
    where applications are run on one system, and displayed on another. The 
    application needs to know <emphasis>where</emphasis> to display. This 
    is sometimes also accomplished by setting the <quote>$DISPLAY</quote> 
    variable, which uses the same syntax.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-geometry <emphasis>geometry</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The initial size and location of the window, in a format such as
    <literal>width x height +horz_offset +vert_offset</literal> or
    <literal>+horz_offset -vert_offset</literal>. Note that if you put in a
    negative horizontal or vertical offset, the window will be placed counting
    backward from the right or the bottom of the screen, respectively, instead
    of from the top left corner.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-font <emphasis>fontname</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The font to use for displaying the text in your window (see font section
    below).
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-bg <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The color to use for the window background. Typically this is a
    <quote>color name</quote> (see below).
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-fg <emphasis>color</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The color to use for the window foreground (i.e. fonts, etc).
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-name <emphasis>resource-name</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Useful for specifying the name under which the resources for this
    application will be found (e.g. as specified in
    <filename>.Xdefaults</filename>). This is useful to distinguish between
    invocations of the same application. For example, two
    <command>xterms</command> can be <quote>named</quote> differently so that
    they may inherit different resources based upon the specified names in
    the resource database.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-title <emphasis>string</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    This is the title to be used for the window on your display, generally used
    by the Window Manager to put a descriptive title at the top of the window.
    Not to be confused with the <quote>-name</quote> option.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-iconic</term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Open window in an iconified state.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>-xrm <emphasis>resource-string</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    This option specifies a resource name and value to override any defaults
    that may already be set (i.e. via <filename>.Xresources</filename> or
    similar). Also useful for setting <application>X</application> resources
    that do not have explicit command line options. For example, the command
    line <quote>xterm -xrm xterm*background: blue &#38;</quote> is
    functionally the same as <quote>xterm -bg blue &#38;</quote>.
   </para>
 </listitem> 
</varlistentry>

 </variablelist>
</para>

<para>
 These are the most noteworthy. There are others. Many programs will have
 their own additional options that are application specific. Many newer
 applications today don't necessarily adhere to the Xt standards, and will use
 their own options, or those provided by their respective toolkit.
 If nothing else, man pages are a good reference for command syntax, and are
 your friends here. Or, the application will have a <quote>--usage</quote> or 
 <quote>--help</quote> command line switch to list available options:
 
</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 $ gnome-terminal --usage
 Usage: gnome-terminal [-?] [--disable-sound] [--enable-sound]
   [--espeaker=HOSTNAME:PORT] [--version] [--usage] [--gdk-debug=FLAGS]
   [--gdk-no-debug=FLAGS] [--display=DISPLAY] [--sync] [--no-xshm]
   [--name=NAME] [--class=CLASS] [--gxid_host=HOST] [--gxid_port=PORT]
   [--xim-preedit=STYLE] [--xim-status=STYLE] [--gtk-debug=FLAGS]
   [--gtk-no-debug=FLAGS] [--g-fatal-warnings] [--gtk-module=MODULE]
   [--disable-crash-dialog] [--sm-client-id=ID] [--sm-config-prefix=PREFIX]
   [--sm-disable] [--tclass=TCLASS] [--font=FONT] [--nologin] [--login]
   [--geometry=GEOMETRY] [-e COMMAND] [-x COMMAND] [--foreground=COLOR]
   [--background=COLOR] [--solid] [--pixmap=PIXMAP] [--bgscroll]
   [--bgnoscroll] [--shaded] [--noshaded] [--transparent] [--utmp]
   [--noutmp] [--wtmp] [--nowtmp] [--lastlog] [--nolastlog] [-t TITLE]
   [--icon=ICON] [--termname=TERMNAME] [--start-factory-server]
   [--use-factory]

 </screen>
</para>


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>xterm and friends</title>

<para>
 Sooner or later, most of us need to access the <quote>command line</quote> 
 for one reason or another. For some, this might even be a common way of
 working in <application>X</application>. In addition to being able to launch 
 <application>X</application> applications from the command prompt, there
 is also a wealth of programs that run in <quote>text mode</quote> for
 Linux. 

</para>

<para>
 This is possible via <quote>terminal emulators</quote> such as
 <command>xterm</command>. The closest counterpart from Microsoft is the
 so-called DOS-box, which is child's play by comparison. Linux terminals support
 color, full mouse copy/paste (and some wheeled mice), pseudo-transparency and
 pixmap backgrounds, scrollbars, menus and generally a slew of other 
 features. While <command>xterm</command> is the best known such terminal 
 emulator, there are many similar programs. To name a few:
 <command>Eterm</command>, <command>rxvt</command>,
 <command>aterm</command>, <command>konsole</command>
 (<application>KDE</application>) and <command>gnome-terminal</command>.

</para>

<para>
  In typical usage, when a terminal emulator window is opened, a shell is
  started for the user to interact with. The default for essentially all
  Linuxes, is the <application>bash</application> shell. So when all is said
  and done, the user is interacting with <application>X</application>, the
  terminal, and the shell all at once. Each may have it's own influence. For
  example, how keystrokes are handled since they move from hardware to X
  server to terminal to the shell and finally echoed back to the user.

</para>

<para> 
 Quick and easy terminal configuration is done via the <quote>$TERM</quote> 
 variable, which is typically set in one of the user's shell configuration
 files. Or the terminal itself will have a compiled in default. The default
 value for this is most often <quote>xterm</quote>:

</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 $ echo $TERM
 xterm

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 Normally this is sufficient, as your vendor has already set this up in a
 reasonable way. The <quote>$TERM</quote> variable is actually a reference to
 an entry in the <quote>termcap</quote> database (man termcap), which is
 typically installed as <filename>/etc/termcap</filename>. Unless you are
 doing something really unusual, you probably will not need to change this.
 Some additional terminal configuration can be done with the
 <command>stty</command> command (see man page). Terminal configuration is
 really beyond the scope of this document.

</para>

<para>
 The terminal application itself (e.g. <command>xterm</command>) will also
 have various configuration options. Permanent settings are best stored in 
 a <filename>~/.Xdefaults</filename> or similar file for those applications 
 that support this. Generally speaking, applications with a GUI configuration 
 (such as <command>gnome-terminal</command>), will be configured by their own
 menu driven configuration instead.

</para>

<para>
 Also, you are interacting with the shell too, which can have it's own impact,
 particularly on how keystrokes are handled at the shell prompt. For
 <application>bash</application>, this can be adjusted in
 <filename>~/.inputrc</filename>. Again, this is beyond the scope of this
 document, but check with either local or on-line
 <application>bash</application> (or other shell) references.

</para>

<para>
 Terminal emulators like <command>xterm</command> require a monospaced font.
 So forget about TrueType or Type 1 fonts. 

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="xsecurity">
<title><application>X</application> Networking and Security</title>

<para>
 As mentioned, <application>X</application> is essentially a networking
 protocol with graphical displaying capabilities. This makes for some
 interesting usage possibilities. And also means there are inherent security
 considerations, as there is with any networking environment. And if you ever
 connect to the Internet, you are in the midst of one very large, hostile
 network ;-)

</para>

<para>
 X clients connect to X servers via various networking protocols, including
 TCP/IP. Even with just local connections. Possible usages here are to run an
 application on one computer, and display it on another. Or, to actually log
 in to a remote system, and have it display to your local screen, with the
 client apps using the remote system's CPU and RAM.

</para>

<para>
 Without any precautions, this can leave you wide open to various types of
 mischief and abuse. For instance, anyone logged into to your system can
 access your <quote>display</quote>, meaning they can see what you are doing
 if they want to. Thankfully, most recent Linux releases come with some
 default security precautions enabled. But it is best to make sure for
 yourself that you are protected.

</para>

<para>
 Both <application>X</application> networking and security are nicely covered 
 in <ulink
 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Remote-X-Apps.html"
>The Remote X Apps Mini HOWTO
</ulink>, 
 so we shall not need to try to rehash it here. Recommended reading. See other
 references in the <link linkend="links">Links section</link> of the
 Appendix below.

</para>

<para>
 A few recommended precautions:

</para>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

 <listitem>
  <para>
   Never, ever run <application>X</application> as root. The number of bad
   things that can happen, dramatically increases when logged in as root.
   Learn to run as much as possible as a regular user, and su to root only
   when needed. This may sound like a lot of extra work (and probably is at
   first), but once the <quote>right</quote> way of doing things is learned,
   it soon becomes second nature.
   
  </para>
  <para>
   A brief anecdote from a friend: he had a client who's new system stopped 
   <quote>working</quote>. Curiously, he found the entire
   <filename>/dev</filename> directory was missing, which he re-installed and
   all was well again. He was back a few days later and found the system
   logged in as root to <application>X</application>, and someone had clicked
   on <filename>/dev</filename> in the file manager, and dragged it onto the
   desktop. Smooth move!

  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   If you ever connect to a network with untrusted users, be sure to have a 
   firewall between you and them. This goes double for the Internet.
   Firewalling is beyond the scope of this document, but is covered in many
   other places, including your vendor's website. <ulink
   url="http://linuxdoc.org">http://linuxdoc.org</ulink> has several security
   HOWTOs that can help as well. <ulink
   url="http://linuxsecurity.com/docs/">http://linuxsecurity.com/docs/</ulink>
   is another good place to look.

  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   You can disable TCP connections with  the <quote>-nolisten tcp</quote>
   command line X server switch. This does not help for local connections
   though. For <command>xinit/startx</command>:
  </para>

  <para>
   <screen>

 exec X :0 -dpi 100 -nolisten tcp

   </screen>
  </para>

  <para>
   Placed in <filename>~/.xserverrc</filename>. And for <command>xdm</command>, 
   in <filename>/usr/lib/X11/xdm/Xservers</filename>:
  
  </para>

  <para>
   <screen>

 :0 local /usr/X11R6/bin/X :0 -nolisten tcp

   </screen>
  </para>

</listitem> 

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->




<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="performance">
<title>Performance Considerations</title>

<para>
 As has been discussed, what we call <application>X</application>, is actually
 a convergence of various components: X server, Window Manager, Desktop, etc.
 With MS Windows, the GUI desktop is tightly integrated with the operating
 system itself. This is not the case in Linux which follows the Unix tradition
 of combining various independent components to achieve some end result. So we
 have choices with each component and it's attendant configuration and
 implementation. In short, much flexibility. This is where you come in. You
 can try various possibilities and decide what you gives you the most bang for
 the buck.

</para>

<para>
 On low end hardware, this gives us much latitude to decrease the demand on
 available system resources. This is good because, if given the opportunity,
 <application>X</application> can be quite greedy with system resources. If
 you've recently installed a new Linux distribution, you've probably been
 given a default Desktop with many bells and whistles. And something
 that will probably need a fair amount of memory and CPU to achieve a
 reasonable level of performance. If you have the horse power, this should not
 be a problem.

</para>

<para>
 It is often said that Linux functions very well with relatively little
 memory. This is true to a point. It does not mean though that every possible
 configuration will run with low memory. So if you want to use memory hungry
 applications, then you will have to have the memory. Or you will have to make
 sacrifices to achieve a satisfactory level of performance. It is quite
 possible to run <application>X</application> with reasonable performance on
 16 Meg of RAM, and even less if you really want to push it. But you would
 have to live with some real limitations.

</para>

<para>
 Let's look at some of the components and ways to decrease the demand on
 system resources, in case you are at the low end on hardware, or performance
 is not up to expectations.
</para>



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Hardware</title>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

<listitem>  
 <para>
 No big surprise, but overall system performance will be best with a fast
 graphics card, a fast hard drive, and lots and lots of memory -- if you want
 <emphasis>both</emphasis> a fast and flashy system.

 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Graphics cards are of course necessary, and the X server's video performance
 is tied to the card's chipset, and the corresponding XFree86 driver. Just
 because a given card is supported by XFree86 does not necessarily mean it is
 as well optimized as other cards! It may also perform better at a lower color
 depth (see below). It may well be worth the trip to xfree86.org to see if
 there are any notes related to your card with respect to performance or other
 issues.

 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
  And you might try other versions of XFree86. At this time v4.2 was just
  recently released. Some cards may still perform better with 3.3.6 due to the
  way v4.x is being incrementally developed. If you are using x4.x and
  performance is not good, then make sure you are using the latest available
  version.

 </para>
</listitem>

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect2>
<title>Memory</title>

<para>
 The more memory, the better. <application>X</application> will do a lot
 caching to help performance. But caching requires memory, and if there isn't
 much to start with, then we would need to reduce memory requirements. Some
 tips for those with low memory or performance problems:
</para>


<para>
 <itemizedlist>
  
<listitem>
 <para>
 Use the <command>free</command> command to make sure all memory and swap is
 recognized. 

 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Make sure you don't have other system services that are hogging memory or
 CPU. Use <command>top</command> or <command>ps</command> to see what is
 running, and disable anything you can to free up memory and CPU. Again, a
 default installation may have many things running that you don't really
 need.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Make sure you have plenty of swap space. With low, or even modest, memory,
 swap is all the more important. A general rule of thumb is twice as much swap
 as physical memory. With low memory, this is not enough. Try four times real
 memory. Or more. If you can't create more swap partitions, see the
 <command>mkswap</command> man page about creating swap files instead.
 Constant disk churning is a symptom of insufficient swap space, and the
 system will be slowed as a result, sometimes drastically. Or, possibly this
 may be the symptom of a poorly behaved kernel VM system (try another kernel
 in this case).

 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Drive performance is important for swap performance. Make sure your drive has
 DMA enabled if the drive supports it, and is otherwise tuned and performing
 up to snuff. See the <command>hdparm</command> man page. Slow drive + slow
 card + low memory = slow system.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Don't use <application>KDE</application> or <application>GNOME</application>
 if memory is tight. These both require substantial memory, and are not
 required to just run <application>X</application>. Think of these as
 usability enhancements. 32M probably may not be enough. 64M may be decent,
 depending on what other applications are being used, and other variables. 128M
 <emphasis>should</emphasis> be adequate in most situations. 256M or more to
 be comfortable. File Managers like <application>Nautilus</application> and
 <application>gmc</application> can also be memory hungry. 
 
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Use a lightweight window manger. <application>WindowMaker</application>,
 <application>BlackBox</application>, <application>IceWM</application>,
 <application>fvwm</application> (and variants),
 <application>XFce</application>, all have reputations of performing well with
 low memory. There are surely others as well. Experiment.
 <application>fvwm</application> is generally considered the lightest of the
 light. 
</para>

<para>
 A very nice desktop is still very possible even without
 <application>KDE</application> or <application>GNOME</application>. In fact,
 most <application>KDE</application> and <application>GNOME</application>
 applications can still be used even if <application>KDE</application> and
 <application>GNOME</application> are not running themselves (assuming the
 right libs are installed).
 
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Don't use fancy themes or backgrounds. Plain and simple is easier on
 resources. Use a solid color background. Avoid pixmaps or gradients for any
 kind of background, including menus, title bars, etc.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Use a lesser screen size and color depth. 800x600x16 will not push
 <application>X</application> as hard and be easier on system resources than
 higher values. While a ColorDepth of 24 is preferred, you probably will not
 notice the difference of 16 with the majority of applications.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Some applications require much more memory than others. Some notable hogs are
 <command>Netscape</command>, <command>Mozilla</command>, office suites, and
 <command>the Gimp</command>. <command>Netscape</command> is faster than
 <command>Mozilla</command> (but not as nice).
 <command>Netscape-Navigator</command> uses less memory than
 <command>Netscape-Communicator</command>. Close any of these apps when not in
 use. Use text browsers like <command>lynx</command> or <command>w3m</command>
 wherever you can, like reading locally installed HTML documentation. Much
 faster, and much less memory is required. 
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Also, use text based clients for mail (<command>mutt</command> or
 <command>pine</command>) and news (<command>slrn</command> or
 <command>trn</command>). Again, faster and much less memory is used, 
 and these are after all text based protocols at heart anyway.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 <command>rxvt</command> uses less memory than <command>xterm</command>,
 <command>konsole</command> or <command>gnome-terminal</command>.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 If you run an <application>X</application> session for long periods of time
 (like days or weeks), restart <application>X</application> occasionally to
 free memory tied up as cache.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>  
  Disable <quote>backing store</quote> and <quote>save-unders</quote> to
  reduce memory usage (performance penalty though). Check
  your Window Manager's settings too. See what modules are being loaded 
  in the <quote>Modules</quote> section of <filename>XF86Config</filename> as
  well. Your installation may have many unnecessary ones enabled, or ones you
  can't take advantage of (e.g. <quote>v4l</quote>, aka
  <quote>Video4Linux</quote>).
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>  
  Font servers may provide a slight performance boost by off-loading font
  rendering to the font server, while freeing the X server to do other things.
  But, the font server will use a small additional amount of memory as well.
  So, you can try it either way to see if it makes a difference.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 Lastly, RAM is cheap now. Buy some ;-) A new drive too.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 RAM is still just too low for <application>X</application>? Check out
 <application>tinyX</application>: 
 <ulink url="http://www.superant.com/smalllinux/tinyX01.html">http://www.superant.com/smalllinux/tinyX01.html</ulink>.
 Reportedly runs in as little as 4 Meg of RAM.

 </para>
</listitem>

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->
<sect2>
<title>X over the Network</title>
<para>
 X is not particularly network friendly. In other words, it is a bandwidth
 hog. This should not be a problem in LAN situations, but may be if trying to
 use X over the Internet.
</para>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
   <para>
     <command>lbxproxy</command>, the low bandwidth X proxy, utilizes 
     various optimizations to improve performance in low bandwidth, or 
     high latency situations. See the man page.
   </para>
  </listitem> 

  <listitem>
   <para>
     VNC (Virtual Network Computing), has some of the same advantages as 
     X for displaying applications on remote systems, but is more network
     friendly. Your Linux installation should have both VNC client and server
     packages available.
   </para>
 </listitem> 

 </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2>
<title>Other Tips</title>
<para>
 Other tips to eek out better performance:
</para>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>
  
<listitem>
 <para>
 Use <command>xset</command> to speed up the keyboard. This can make the
 system feel more responsive even if it isn't really. The default always
 seemed sluggish to me. 
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
 <command>renice</command> <application>X</application> to give it a higher
 priority. Other platforms give the GUI high scheduling priority to achieve
 better responsiveness. But this is at a cost to other processes. Linux is a
 blank slate. You might include the font server (if being used), and key
 <application>KDE</application> and <application>GNOME</application> processes
 as well. 
</para>

<para>
 <screen>

 nice -n -10 X :0

 </screen>
</para>

<para>
 This will not do much on systems that are mostly idle.

</para>

<para>
 This does not work so well with <command>startx</command> since
 <application>X</application> runs as root, and you are not root, right? So
 you would have to use something like <command>sudo</command> to have this done
 automatically.

 </para>
</listitem>

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="appendix">
<title>Appendix</title>

<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2 id="terms">
<title>Terminology and Usage</title>


<para>
 There are a few basic concepts and terminologies you should be familiar with.
 These terms will appear here, in the manual pages, and in other help files and
 documentation. 
 
</para>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

 <listitem>
  <para>
   The <quote>X server</quote> is the low-level driver software that interacts
   with your video card and other system hardware, and manages the 
   <quote>display</quote> and the various components attached to the
   <quote>display</quote> (keyboard, mouse, etc.). And, of course, handles 
   requests from clients as well. There are different X servers for different
   chipsets.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   X Servers are referenced in the form of:
  </para>

  <para>
   <emphasis>host.domain:display_number.screen_number</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
   An example would look like: <emphasis>my_computer:0.0</emphasis>

  </para>

  <para>
   If host (and domain) is omitted, localhost is assumed. <quote>Host</quote>
   can be a remote host. If <quote>screen</quote> is omitted, then
   <quote>0</quote> (the first screen) is assumed. In it's shortest form, the
   X server is often represented as just <quote>:0</quote>, which would be the
   first local <quote>display</quote>. <application>X</application> supports
   multiple <quote>displays</quote> <emphasis>and</emphasis> multiple
   <quote>screens</quote>.

  </para>
  <para>
   <quote>Screen</quote> and <quote>Display</quote> have special meanings in
   relation to X servers, in addition to their more common usage.

  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
    When <application>X</application> is invoked, the X server will initialize 
    one or more <quote>displays</quote>. Yes, <application>X</application> can
    have more than one <quote>display</quote> available (though this is not a
    common configuration for the average user). Each <quote>display</quote> is
    a separate instance of <quote>X</quote>. The <quote>display</quote>
    includes not only the obvious video components, but also the keyboard,
    mouse and other input type components. The user can only access one
    <application>display</application> at a time via the same keyboard and
    monitor. <quote>Displays</quote> may reside locally, or on a networked
    host <quote>somewhere</quote>, or both. It is possible that if multiple
    <quote>displays</quote> are available, the user can choose which one he
    wants when he logs in. Each <quote>display</quote> may have its own
    unique configuration (e.g. resolution). But again, the most typical 
    configuration is just one <quote>display</quote> with one <quote>screen</quote>, 
    which is how most of us use <application>X</application>.
    
   </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>  
   In reference to X servers, <quote>screen</quote> means the primary video
   output with which you view <application>X</application>.
   And there can be more than one <quote>screen</quote>, just like you can
   have more than one <quote>display</quote>. Additional
   <quote>screens</quote> are used in <quote>multi-headed displays</quote> for
   instance. In fact you can even have more than one computer running off a
   single X server. This is beyond the scope of this document, but you should
   be aware of this degree of flexibility as it is an important ingredient of
   the <application>X</application> protocol.
   
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>
    <quote>Desktop</quote> can mean different things in different
    contexts. Often, <quote>desktop</quote> means what is more properly 
    called the <quote>Desktop Environment</quote>. Prime examples of this are
    <application>KDE</application>, <application>GNOME</application>, and the not 
    as well-known <application>CDE</application>, which are high level
    applications that control much of how the user interacts with the
    <application>X</application> session. They provide consistent look and
    feel, as well as consistent configuration and come bundled with their own
    set of utilities for common tasks.
  </para>

  <para>
   <quote>Desktop</quote> also sometimes just means the viewable screen area.
   This is more of the MS Window's meaning. <application>X</application>
   environments though are capable of having multiple virtual
   <quote>desktops</quote> that can be switched between as needed. This helps with
   organizing different tasks. Each <quote>desktop</quote> may its own windows
   and clients that are specific to it. Right now I have seven
   <application>WindowMaker</application> desktops
   (<application>WindowMaker</application> calls them
   <quote>WorkSpaces</quote>), and one of those I have dedicated to writing
   this document. This <quote>desktop</quote> has thirteen unique windows at
   the moment (man pages, browser windows, clock, gvim, xterms, etc).
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   <quote>Clients</quote> are any program that connect to the X server, and
   require an X server for some task (e.g. to display itself). Often, these
   are displayed in their own <quote>window</quote>, but not always. For
   instance, if I use <literal>CTRL-N</literal> to open a new
   <application>Mozilla</application> window, this is one
   <application>X</application> client but with two windows. If I run a command
   line <application>X</application> utility like <command>xev</command> to
   view key and mouse events, this runs in the <command>xterm's</command>
   window, so has none of its own, but is still a <quote>client</quote>.
   Clients can be locally running applications, or applications that are
   running on another system over the network, but are displayed locally.
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>  
   The <quote>Window Manager</quote> is a special type of client application 
   and a user definable component of the GUI. It is what the user interacts
   with to a large extent. The Window Manager provides such functionality as
   window borders and decorations, menus, icons, virtual desktops, button
   bars, tool bars, and allows the user to customize these. It is technically
   possible to run <application>X</application> without a window manager
   (though not very functional), but not the other way around. Window managers
   should not be confused with <quote>Desktop Environments</quote> like
   <application>KDE</application>. Desktop Environments include their own
   preferred Window Manager, but this is a configurable. There is some
   overlapping of responsibilities between Window Managers and Desktop
   Environments.
   
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>  
   The <quote>root window</quote> is the background of your screen. It is
   referred to as a window in name alone, it does not behave like any other
   window, but rather you run your applications on the root window, or put an
   image on it, or perhaps just a solid color. All other windows are children 
   of this parent window. The root window conceivably can be larger than the viewable 
   screen area.
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>  
   The <quote>pointer</quote> is the arrow or indicator of any
   given shape which represents the location of your mouse, or other pointing
   device. The pointer often changes to give you contextual feedback as to
   what will happen when you use the mouse at that point on the screen. 
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>  
   The <quote>window</quote> is a frame in which any given application runs
   and which is <quote>managed</quote> by the Window Manager. This includes
   pretty much anything except the so-called root window. Even windows which
   do not appear to have frames, titles, or normal borders of any kind are
   being managed by your window manger. The <quote>active window</quote> is
   the window you are currently using. This window will will respond to the
   keyboard when you type, and is traditionally denoted by the fact that your
   mouse cursor is pointing at it, though this is not always the case. The
   active window is said to have <quote>focus</quote>. Most Window Managers
   will somehow highlight the <quote>active</quote>, or focused, window to
   differentiate it from other windows.
  </para>
 </listitem>

 
 <listitem>
  <para>  
   <quote>Menus</quote>, <quote>icons</quote> and <quote>task bars</quote>
   behave in <application>X</application> similar to the way they behave in
   other windowing systems, and the same general principles apply. 
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>  
   Windows that run text only applications are called <quote>terminal
   emulators</quote>, such as <command>xterm</command> and various 
   similar applications. This is the well-known <quote>command line</quote> in
   an X environment. These basically emulate a console text-only display, and
   have some advantages due to their being used in
   <application>X</application>. These are much more complex and sophisticated
   applications than a simple <application>DOS</application> box on Windows.
  </para>
 </listitem>


 <listitem>
  <para>  
   <quote>Widgets</quote> is the term used to describe such GUI control
   components as buttons, sliders, menus, scrollbars, listboxes, checkboxes, etc.
   <quote>Toolkits</quote> are libraries containing a diverse set of widgets
   with the same look and feel. Some common examples are
   <application>GTK+</application> (used by <application>GNOME</application>,
   <application>Mozilla</application> and others), <application>Xaw</application> 
   (X Athena Widget set), <application>Tk</application>,
   <application>Motif</application> and <application>QT</application> (used
   by <application>KDE</application>). Applications are built with one toolkit
   or another. Sometimes the same application can be built with different
   toolkits, depending on compile time options.
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>
    Window <quote>geometry</quote> is a shorthand way of expressing a window's
    size and screen placement. This might look like
    <quote>60x20+10+50</quote>, which is <literal>WIDTH x HEIGHT +VERT_OFFSET
    +HORZ_OFFSET</literal>. While both pairs are often specified, it is
    permissible to use just one or the other pair. 
   </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
    In <application>X</application> lingo, <quote>resources</quote> are
    definable application attributes. Commonly available
    <quote>resources</quote> are fonts, colors, size, window title, etc,
    etc. 
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->



<!--   ~~~~~       New section      ~~~~~     -->

<sect2 id="links">
<title>Links and other References</title>

<para>
 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
   <para>
     The definitive source of information on XFree86 is, of course, 
     <ulink url="http://xfree86.org">http://xfree86.org</ulink>. Don't forget
     the man pages that you have installed already too (X, Xserver, XF86Config,
     XFree86, xdm, xinit, xmodmap, startx, xauth, Xsecurity, etc, etc). These are
     really mostly decent, though some are quite technical.
   </para>

   <para>
    Some pages at xfree86.org to check:

   </para>
   
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     Docs and support info: <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/support.html">http://www.xfree86.org/support.html</ulink> for 
     various versions and topics.
    </member>
   </simplelist>
   
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     README: <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/current/README.html">http://www.xfree86.org/current/README.html</ulink>
    </member>
   </simplelist>
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     Release Notes: <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/current/RELNOTES.html">http://www.xfree86.org/current/RELNOTES.html</ulink>
    </member>
   </simplelist>
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     DRI: <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/current/DRI.html">http://www.xfree86.org/current/DRI.html</ulink>
    </member>
   </simplelist>
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     Status: <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/current/Status.html">http://www.xfree86.org/current/Status.html</ulink>
    </member>
   </simplelist>
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     Mouse: <ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/current/mouse.html">http://www.xfree86.org/current/mouse.html</ulink>
    </member>
   </simplelist>
   <simplelist>
    <member>
     Supported card list: 
     <ulink url="http://xfree86.org/cardlist.html">http://xfree86.org/cardlist.html</ulink>
    </member>
   </simplelist>

  </listitem> 


  <listitem>
   <para>
    Other related documents from LDP:
   </para>

    <para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        If you are just starting out, you may find the 
        <ulink
        
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XWindow-Overview-HOWTO/index.html"
>X Window System Architecture Overview HOWTO</ulink>
        to be helpful. It covers all the basic concepts quite well.
  
       </para>
     </listitem> 
     
     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Remote-X-Apps.html"
>The Remote X Apps Mini HOWTO
</ulink>
        does a nice job of discussing running <application>X</application>
        remotely, and related security issues of <application>X</application> networking.
      </para>
     </listitem> 

     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XDMCP-HOWTO/index.html"
>The XDMCP HOWTO
</ulink>
        covers the X Display Manager Control Protocol, for running
        <application>X</application> remotely. Also, 
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XDM-Xterm/index.html"
>The XDM and X Terminal mini-HOWTO
</ulink>.
      </para>
     </listitem> 
     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-HOWTO/index.html"
>The XFree86 HOWTO
</ulink>
        succinctly covers installation, and initial configuration.
      </para>
     </listitem> 
     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/index.html"
>The XFree86 Video Timings HOWTO
</ulink>
       gets down and dirty with the finer points of monitor tuning. Generally
       not required for XFree86 v4.x.
      </para>
     </listitem> 
     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Xinerama-HOWTO.html"
>The Xinerama HOWTO</ulink>
       covers multi-headed displays.
      </para>
     </listitem> 
     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Font-HOWTO.html"
>The Font HOWTO</ulink>
        covers various font topics.
      </para>
    </listitem> 
     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FDU/index.html"
>The Font De-Uglification Mini HOWTO
</ulink>
        covers a range of <application>X</application> font issues.
      </para>
     </listitem> 

     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Intkeyb/index.html"
>The International Keyboard HOWTO
</ulink>
      </para>
     </listitem> 

     <listitem>
      <para>
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Infrared-HOWTO/index.html"
>The Linux Infrared HOWTO
</ulink>
      </para>
     </listitem> 
     </itemizedlist>
   </para> 
  
  </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
    Looking for information on a Window Manager, or wanting to try
    something new or different:
    <ulink url="http://www.plig.org/xwinman/">http://www.plig.org/xwinman/</ulink>
  </para>
 </listitem> 
 
 <listitem>
  <para>
    Wheel mice tips and configuration: 
    <ulink url="http://koala.ilog.fr/colas/mouse-wheel-scroll/">http://koala.ilog.fr/colas/mouse-wheel-scroll/</ulink>
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   Linux and Laptops: 
   <ulink url="http://www.linux-laptop.net/">http://www.linux-laptop.net/</ulink>
  </para>
 </listitem> 

 <listitem>
  <para>
   The O'Reilly series on X Window! Visit <ulink
   url="http://www.ora.com/">http://www.ora.com/</ulink> for the definitive books on <application>X</application>.
  </para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
 <para>
  The X Consortium's web site is <ulink
  url="http://www.x.org/">http://www.x.org/</ulink> ... or perhaps it's moved to
  <ulink url="http://www.opengroup.org/">http://www.opengroup.org/</ulink>.
 </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
 <para>
  <ulink url="http://www.x11.org/">http://www.x11.org/</ulink> is sort of a clearinghouse
  for all things X.
 </para>
</listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>
    And for everything else under the Sun: <ulink url="http://google.com/linux/">http://google.com/linux/</ulink>.
    An incredible resource in its own right.
  </para>
</listitem> 


 </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</article>

<!-- ~~~~~~~~~  finis ~~~~~~~~ --> 
