<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ch-advanced-routing">
  <title>Advanced IP Routing</title>
  <section id="adv-routing">
    <title>Introduction to Policy Routing</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="adv-overview">
    <title>Overview of Routing and Packet Filter Interactions</title>
    <para>
      One of the most difficult aspects of working with the advanced routing
      features of linux is gaining an understanding the sequence of events
      as a packet traverses the kernel space.  It is, in fact, the key
      knowledge needed to grasp the potential of advanced routing scenarios
      and to troubleshoot successfully when things don't go as planned.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are reading this for the first time, stop now and go visit and
      study 
      <ulink url="http://docum.org/stef.coene/qos/kptd/">the kernel
      packet traveling diagram</ulink> and
      <ulink url="http://open-source.arkoon.net/kernel/kernel_net.png">the
      kernel packet handling diagram</ulink> now.  These represent two
      different efforts to describe the order in which different
      networking subsystems inside the linux kernel have an opportunity to
      inspect, manipulate and redirect a packet.  Understanding this
      sequence of events is key to harnessing the power of linux networking.
    </para>
    <para>
      Now, let's examine some of the different commands you can use to
      manipulate packets at each of these stages.  The list below describes
      the sequence of events for a packet bound for a non-local destination.
    </para>
    <anchor id="adv-overview-kptd-forwarded"/>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Packet Traversal; Non-Local Destination</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          All of the PREROUTING netfilter hooks are called here.  This
          means that we get our first opportunity to inspect and drop a
          packet, we can perform DNAT on the packet to make sure that the
          destination IP is rewritten before we make a routing decision
          (at which time the destination address becomes very important).
          We can also set ToS or an fwmark on the packet at this time.  If
          we want to use an IMQ device for ingress control, we can put our
          hooks here.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If we are using ipchains, the input chain is traversed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Any traffic control on the real device on which the packet arrived
          is now performed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The input routing stage is traversed by any packet entering the
          local machine.  Here we concern ourselves only with packets which
          are routed through this machine to another destination
          Additionally, iproute2 NAT occurs here
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Leonardo calls this "dumb NAT" because the NAT performed by
              &iproute2; at the routing stage is stateless.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The packet enters the FORWARD netfilter hooks.  Here, the packet
          can be mangled with ToS or fwmark.  After the mangle chain is
          passed, the filter chain will be traversed.  For kernel 2.4-based
          routing devices this will be the location for packet filtering
          rules.  If we are using ipchains, the forward chain would be
          traversed here instead of the netfilter FORWARD hooks.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The output chain in an ipchains installation would be traversed
          here.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The POSTROUTING netfilter hooks are traversed.  These include
          packet mangling, NAT and IMQ for egress.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Finally, the packet is transmitted via the outbound device per
          traffic control configuration on that outbound device.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The above describes the sequence of events for packets passing through
      the linux routing device.  Let's look at a similar descriptions of the
      paths that packets bound for local destinations take through the
      kernel.
    </para>
    <anchor id="adv-overview-kptd-local-dest"/>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Packet Traversal; Local Destination</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          All of the PREROUTING netfilter hooks are called here.  This
          means that we get our first opportunity to inspect and drop a
          packet, we can perform DNAT on the packet to make sure that the
          destination IP is rewritten before we make a routing decision
          (at which time the destination address becomes very important).
          We can also set ToS or an fwmark on the packet at this time.  If
          we want to use an IMQ device for ingress control, we can put our
          hooks here.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If we are using ipchains, the input chain is traversed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Any traffic control on the real device on which the packet arrived
          is now performed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The input routing stage is traversed by any packet entering the
          local machine.  Here we concern ourselves with packets bound for
          local destinations only.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The INPUT netfilter hooks are traversed.  Commonly this is
          filtering for inbound connections, but can include packet
          mangling.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The local destination process receives the connection.  If there
          is no open socket, an error is generated.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Naturally, packets need to go out from the machine as well, so let's
      look at the path for outbound packets which were locally generated.
    </para>
    <anchor id="adv-overview-kptd-local-gen"/>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Packet Traversal; Locally Generated</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The process with the open socket sends data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The routing decision is made.  This is frequently called output
          routing because it is only for packets leaving the system.  This
          routing code is (sometimes?) responsible for selecting the source
          IP of the outbound packet.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The netfilter OUTPUT hooks are traversed.  The basic filter, nat,
          and mangle hooks are available.  This is where SNAT can take
          place.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The output chain in an ipchains installation would be traversed
          here.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The POSTROUTING netfilter hooks are traversed.  These include
          packet mangling, NAT and IMQ for egress.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Finally, the packet is transmitted via the outbound device per
          traffic control configuration on that outbound device.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="adv-rpdb">
    <title>Using the Routing Policy Database and Multiple Routing
      Tables</title>
    <para>
      Understanding and practically applying the knowledge of how and when to
      harness the routing features of linux is a matter of experience.  The
      below is a set of examples for how to use the RPDB and multiple routing
      tables to solve different types of problems.  These are but a few simple
      examples which allude to the flexibility and power available with the
      complex policy routing system under linux.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <section id="adv-routing-tos">
      <title>Using Type of Service Policy Routing</title>
      <para>
        Type of Service (ToS) is a flag in the header of an IP packet
        which is sometimes honored by upstream routers.  Some routers on the
        Internet respect the ToS flag and others do not, however, the ToS flag
        can be used as part of the decision about where to route a given
        packet (for a refresher on the keys used for routing to a destination
        read
        <xref linkend="routing-selection"/>).  Because it can be used as part
        of the routing decision, ToS can be used to select a route separate
        from the route chosen for normal packets (packets not marked with any
        ToS).
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="adv-routing-fwmark">
      <title>Using fwmark for Policy Routing</title>
      <para>
        FIXME!! Don't forget to point out that fwmark with ipchains/iptables
        is a decimal number, but that iproute2 uses hexadecimal number.
        Thanks to Jose Luis Domingo Lopez for his <ulink
        url="http://mailman.ds9a.nl/pipermail/lartc/2002q3/005039.html">post</ulink>
        to the LARTC list!
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="adv-routing-nat">
      <title>Policy Routing and NAT</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="adv-multi-internet">
    <title>Multiple Connections to the Internet</title>
    <para>
      The questions summarized in this section should rightly be entered
      into the FAQ, since they are FAQs on the
      <ulink url="http://mailman.ds9a.nl/mailman/listinfo/lartc">LARTC
      list</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are many places where a linux based router/masquerading device
      can assist in managing multiple Internet connections.  We'll outline
      here some of the more common setups involving multiple Internet
      connections and how to manage them with <command>iptables</command>,
      <command>ipchains</command>, and &iproute2;.  One of
      the first distinctions you can make when planning how to use multiple
      Internet connections is what inbound services you expect to host and
      how you want to split traffic over the multiple links.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the discussion and examples below, I'll address the issues involved
      with two separate uplinks to two different providers.  I assume the
      following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You are not using BGP, and you do not have your own AS.  If you
          are using BGP and have your own AS, you have a different set of
          problems than the problems described here
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Anybody who has any experience with linux as a firewall behind
              a BGP device?  Linux as a firewall/router running BGP?
              Thoughts?  Things I should include here?  Yeah, I know about
              <ulink url="http://www.zebra.org/">Zebra</ulink>, but I
              haven't ever used it.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You have two netblocks from two different ISPs.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You are funneling your internal network through this routing
          device, which is performing masquerading/NAT to the Internet.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Additionally, I'll restrict my comments to statically assigned public
      IP address ranges unless I mention (in particular) dynamically
      allocated addresses.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the following sections we'll look at the use of multiple Internet
      connections first in terms of
      <link linkend="adv-multi-internet-outbound">outbound
      traffic only</link>, then in terms of
      <link linkend="adv-multi-internet-inbound">inbound traffic
      only</link>.  After that, we'll look at using multiple Internet
      connections for
      <link linkend="adv-multi-internet-bidirectional">handling both
      inbound and outbound services</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <section id="adv-multi-internet-outbound">
      <title>Outbound traffic Using Multiple Connections to the
        Internet</title>
      <para>
        There are two main uses for multiple Internet links connected to the
        same internal network.  One common use is to select an outbound link
        based on the type of outbound service.  The other is to split traffic
        arbitrarily across multiple ISPs for reasons like failover and to
        accommodate greater aggregate bandwidth than would be available
        on a single uplink.
      </para>
      <para>
        If your need is the latter, please consult the documentation on the
        <ulink url="http://lartc.org/howto/lartc.rpdb.multiple-links.html">LARTC
        site</ulink>, as it does a good job of summarizing the issues
        involved and describes how to accomplish this.  This type of use of
        multiple Internet connections means that (from the perspective of
        the linux routing device), there is a multipath default route.  The
        LARTC documentation remarks that Julian Anastasov's patches "make
        things nicer to work with."  The patches to which the LARTC
        documents are referring are Julian's dead gateway detection
        patches (at least) which can help the linux routing device provide
        Internet service to the internal network when one of the links is
        down.  See <ulink
        url="http://www.ssi.bg/~ja/#routes">here for
        Julian's route work</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
        In the remainder of this section, we'll discuss how to classify
        traffic for different ISPs, how to handle the packet filtering for
        this sort of classification scheme, and how to create routing tables
        appropriate for the task at hand.
        If anything at all seems unclear in this section, you may find a
        quick re-reading of <link linkend="adv-overview">the advanced
        routing overview</link> quite fruitful.
      </para>
      <para>
        The simplest way to split Internet access into two separate groups
        is by source IP of the outbound packet.  This can be done most
        simply with <command>ip rule</command> and a second routing table.
        We'll assume that &masq-gw; in the example network gets a second,
        low cost network connection through a DSL vendor.
      </para>
      <para>
        The DSL IP on &masq-gw; will be 67.17.28.12 with a gateway of
        67.17.28.14.  We'll assume that this is for outbound connectivity
        only, and that the IP is active on eth4 of the &masq-gw; machine.
        Before beginning let's outline the process we are going to follow.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Copy the main routing table to another routing table and set the
            alternate default route
            <footnote>
              <para>
                Sometimes it may not be quite proper to simply copy the main
                routing table to another routing table.  You may want a
                subset of hosts on the internal network to access the
                alternate link.  Anybody have any sage advice here for the
                newbie in multiple routing tables?
              </para>
            </footnote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use <command>iptables</command>/<command>ipchains</command> to
            mark traffic with fwmark.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Add a rule to the routing policy database.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Test!
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Here's a short snippet of shell which you may find handy for copying
        one routing table to another; see <ulink
        url="scripts/copy-routing-table.sh">the full script</ulink> for a
        more generalized example.
      </para>
      <example id="ex-adv-multi-internet-outbound-ip-routing">
        <title>Multiple Outbound Internet links, part I;
          <command>ip route</command></title>
        <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table main</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.100.0/30 dev eth3  scope link
67.17.28.0/28 dev eth4  scope link
205.254.211.0/24 dev eth1  scope link
192.168.100.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.99.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.98.0/24 via 192.168.99.1 dev eth0
10.38.0.0/16 via 192.168.100.1 dev eth3
127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  scope link 
default via 205.254.211.254 dev eth1</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush table 4</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table main | grep -Ev ^default \</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>  | while read ROUTE ; do</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>    ip route add table 4 $ROUTE</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>done</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add table 4 default via 67.17.28.14</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table 4</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.100.0/30 dev eth3  scope link
67.17.28.0/28 dev eth4  scope link
205.254.211.0/24 dev eth1  scope link
192.168.100.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.99.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.98.0/24 via 192.168.99.1 dev eth0
10.38.0.0/16 via 192.168.100.1 dev eth3
127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  scope link 
default via 67.17.28.14 dev eth4</computeroutput>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>
        Now, exactly what have we just done?  We have created two routing
        tables on &masq-gw; each of which has a different default gateway.
        We have successfully accomplished the first part of our
        preparations.
      </para>
      <para>
        Now, let's mark the traffic we would like to route in using
        conditional logic.  We'll use <command>iptables</command> to select
        traffic bound for destination ports 80 and 443 originating in the
        main office desktop network.
      </para>
      <example id="ex-adv-multi-internet-outbound-iptables">
        <title>Multiple Outbound Internet links, part II;
          <command>iptables</command></title>
        <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>iptables -t mangle -A PREROUTING -p tcp --dport 80 -s 192.168.99.0/24 -j MARK --set-mark 4</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>iptables -t mangle -A PREROUTING -p tcp --dport 443 -s 192.168.99.0/24 -j MARK --set-mark 4</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>iptables -t mangle -nvL</userinput>
<computeroutput>Chain PREROUTING (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source                destination         
    0     0 MARK       tcp  --  *      *       192.168.99.0/24       0.0.0.0/0          tcp dpt:80 MARK set 0x4 
    0     0 MARK       tcp  --  *      *       192.168.99.0/24       0.0.0.0/0          tcp dpt:443 MARK set 0x4 

Chain OUTPUT (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
  pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth4 -j SNAT --to-source 67.17.28.12</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth1 -j SNAT --to-source 205.254.211.179</userinput>
<computeroutput>Chain PREROUTING (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination         

Chain POSTROUTING (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination         
    0     0 SNAT       all  --  *      eth4    0.0.0.0/0            0.0.0.0/0          to:67.17.28.12
    0     0 SNAT       all  --  *      eth1    0.0.0.0/0            0.0.0.0/0          to:205.254.211.179

Chain OUTPUT (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination</computeroutput>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>
        With these <command>iptables</command> lines we have instructed
        netfilter to mark packets matching these criteria with the fwmark
        and we have prepared the NAT rules so that our outbound packets will
        originate from the correct IPs.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once again, it is important to realize that the fwmark added
        to a packet is only valid and discernible while the packet is
        still on the host running the packet filter.  The fwmark is stored
        in a data structure the kernel uses to track the packet.
        Because the fwmark is not a part of the packet itself, the fwmark is
        lost as soon as the packet has left the local machine.  For more
        detail on the use of fwmark, see
        <xref linkend="adv-routing-fwmark"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        &iproute2; supports the use of fwmark as a selector
        for rule lookups, so we can use fwmarks in the routing policy
        database to cause packets to be conditionally routed based on that
        fwmark.  This can lead to great complexity if a machine has multiple
        routing tables, packet filters, and other fancy networking tools,
        such as NAT or proxies.  Caveat emptor.
      </para>
      <para>
        A convention I find sensible is to use the same number for a routing
        table and fwmark where possible.  This simplifies the maintenance of
        the systems which are using &iproute2; and fwmark,
        especially if the table identifier and fwmark are set in a
        configuration file with the same variable name.  Since we are
        testing this on the command line, we'll just make sure that we can
        add the rules first.
      </para>
      <example id="ex-adv-multi-internet-outbound-ip-rule">
        <title>Multiple Outbound Internet links, part III;
          <command>ip rule</command></title>
        <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add fwmark 4 table 4</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32765:  from all fwmark        4 lookup 4 
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush cache</userinput>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>
        The last piece is in place.  Now, users in the 192.168.99.0/24 subnet
        who are browsing the Internet should be using the DSL line instead
        of the T1 line for connectivity.
      </para>
      <para>
        In order to verify that traffic is indeed getting marked and
        routed appropriately, you should use <command>tcpdump</command> to
        profile the outbound traffic on each link at the same time as you
        generate outbound traffic on both links.  
      </para>
      <para>
        The above is a cookbook example of categorizing traffic,
        and sending the traffic out across different
        providers.  To my knowledge, the commonest reason to use this sort
        of solution is to separate traffic by importance and use a reliable
        (and perhaps more costly) link for the more important traffic while
        reserving the less costly Internet connection for other connections.
        In the above illustrative case, we have simply selected the web
        traffic for the less reliable (DSL) provider.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once again, if you would like to split load over multiple links
        regardless of classification of traffic, then you really want a
        multipath default route, which is described and documented very well
        <ulink url="http://lartc.org/howto/lartc.rpdb.multiple-links.html">in
        the LARTC HOWTO</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="adv-multi-internet-inbound">
      <title>Inbound traffic Using Multiple Connections to the
        Internet</title>
      <para>
        There are many different ways to handle hosting servers to multiple
        ISPs, and most of them are out of the scope of this document.  If
        you are in need of this sort of advanced networking, you probably
        already know where to research.  If not, I'd suggest starting your
        research in load balancing, global load balancing, failover, and
        layer 4-7 switching.  These are networking tools which can
        facilitate the management of a highly available service.
      </para>
      <para>
        Publishing the same service on two different ISPs is can be
        formidable challenge.  While this is possible using
        some of the advanced networking features under linux, one should
        understand the greater issues involved with publishing a service on
        two public IPs, especially if the idea is to provide service to the
        general Internet even if one of the ISPs go down.  For a
        thorough examination of the topics involved with load balancing of
        all kinds, see Chandra Kopparapu's book Load Balancing Servers,
        Firewalls and Caches.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you are aware of the many difficult issues involved in handling
        inbound connections to a network, and still want to publish a
        service on two different ISPs (perhaps before you have a more robust
        load balancing/upper layer switching technology in place), you'll
        find the recipe below.
      </para>
      <para>
        Before we examine the recipe, let's look at a complex scenario to
        see what the crucial points are.  If you do not have the
        <ulink url="http://www.docum.org/stef.coene/qos/kptd/">kernel
        packet traveling diagram</ulink> memorized, you may wish to refer to
        it in the following discussion.  One other item to remember is that
        routing decisions are stateless
        <footnote>
          <para>
            The following discussion is actually a restatement of
            <ulink url="http://lists.netfilter.org/pipermail/netfilter/2001-May/011697.html">Wes
            Hodges' posting</ulink> on his solution to this problem.
          </para>
        </footnote>.
      </para>
      <para>
        We'll assume that the client IP is a fixed IP (64.70.12.210) and
        we'll discuss how this client IP would reach each of the services 
        published on &masq-gw;'s two public networks.  The IPs used for
        the services will be 67.17.28.10 and 205.254.211.17.
        Now, whether you are using NAT with &iproute2; or
        with iptables, you'll run across the problem here outlined.  Here
        is the flow of the packet through &masq-gw; to the server and back
        to the client.
      </para>
      <anchor id="ol-adv-multi-internet-inbound"/>
      <orderedlist>
        <title>Inbound NAT to the same server via two public IPs in two
          different networks</title>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            inbound packet from 64.70.12.210 to 67.17.28.10 arrives on eth4
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            packet is accepted, rewritten, and routed; from 64.70.12.210 to
            192.168.100.17;  if <command>iptables</command> DNAT,
            packet is rewritten in PREROUTING chain of nat table, then
            routed;  if &iproute2;, packet is routed and
            rewritten simultaneously
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            rewritten packet is transmitted out eth0
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            &isolde; receives packet, accepts, responds
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            inbound packet from 192.168.100.17 to 64.70.12.210
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            routing decision is made; default route (via 205.254.211.254) is
            selected; if &iproute2; is used, packet is
            also rewritten from 67.17.28.10 to 64.70.12.210
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            if <command>iptables</command> DNAT is used, connection tracking
            will take care of rewriting this packet from 67.17.28.10 to
            64.70.12.210
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            packet is transmitted out eth1
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        This is the problem!  The packet may have the correct source
        address, but it is leaving via the wrong interface.  Many ISPs
        filter traffic entering their network and will block traffic from
        your network with source IPs outside your allocated range.  To an
        ISP this looks like spoofed traffic.
      </para>
      <para>
        The solution is marvelously elegant and simple.  Select one IP on
        the internal server which will be reachable via one provider and one
        IP which will be reachable via the other provider.  By using two IP
        addresses on the internal machine, we can use <command>ip
        rule</command> on &masq-gw; to select a routing table with a
        different default route based upon the source IP of the response
        packets to clients.  Below, we'll assume the same routing tables as
        in the previous section (cf.
        <xref linkend="adv-multi-internet-outbound"/>).
      </para>
      <para>
        Here we have a server &isolde; which needs to be accessible via two
        different public IP addresses.  We'll add an IP address to &isolde;
        so that it is reachable on 192.168.100.10 as well as 192.168.100.17.
        Then, the following rules on &masq-gw; will ensure that packets are
        rewritten and routed in order to avoid the problem pointed out
        <link linkend="ol-adv-multi-internet-inbound">above</link>.
      </para>
      <example id="ex-adv-multi-internet-inbound">
        <title>Multiple Internet links, inbound traffic; using
          &iproute2; only
          <footnote>
            <para>
              This example makes no reference to packet filtering.  If you are
              reading this, I assume you are competent at determining the
              packet filtering issues.  If you have doubts about what rules to
              add, see <xref linkend="nat-stateless-pf-interaction"/>.
            </para>
          </footnote>
        </title>
        <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add nat 67.17.28.10 via 192.168.100.10</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add nat 67.17.28.10 from 192.168.100.10 table 4</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add nat 205.254.211.17 via 192.168.100.17</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add nat 205.254.211.17 from 192.168.100.17</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32765:  from 192.168.100.17 lookup main map-to 205.254.211.17
32765:  from 192.168.100.10 lookup 4 map-to 67.17.28.10
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table local | grep ^nat</userinput>
<computeroutput>nat 205.254.211.17 via 192.168.100.17  scope host 
nat 67.17.28.10 via 192.168.100.10  scope host</computeroutput>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="adv-multi-internet-bidirectional">
      <title>Using Multiple Connections to the Internet for Inbound and
        Outbound Connections</title>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
