<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ch-pat">
  <title>Port Address Translation</title>
  <para>
    Port address translation (PAT) is a logical extension of the concept of 
    network address translation (NAT).  PAT is occasionally known as network
    address and port translation (NAPT).  At the cost of some complexity, PAT
    allows for the use of a single IP address to present multiple services on
    different internal IPs to an exterior network.
  </para>
  <section id="pat-overview">
    <title>PAT Overview and Rationale</title>
    <para>
      Port address translation (hereafter PAT) provides a similar
      functionality to NAT, but is a more specific tool.  PAT forwards
      requests for a particular IP and port pair to another IP port pair.
      This feature is commonly used on publicly connected hosts to make an
      internal service available to a larger network.
    </para>
    <para>
      PAT will break in strange and wonderful ways if there is an alternate
      route between the two hosts connected by the port address translation.
    </para>
    <para>
      PAT address translation has one important benefit over NAT (with the
      &iproute2; tools).  Let's assume that you have only
      five public IP addresses for which you have paid dearly.  Additionally,
      let's assume that you want to run services on standard ports.  You had
      hoped to connect four SMTP servers, two SSH servers and five HTTP servers.
      If you had wanted to accomplish this with NAT, you'd need more IP space.
    </para>
    <para>
      With PAT, however,  you can define a separate destination address and port
      for each translation.  This means that you could do something like this
      to squeeze the most out of your public IP space:
    </para>
    <table pgwide="1" id="pat-table">
      <title>Port Address Translation</title>
      <tgroup cols="4" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Public IP</entry>
            <entry>Port</entry>
            <entry>Translated IP</entry>
            <entry>Port</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.81</entry>
            <entry>tcp/22 (ssh)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.31</entry>
            <entry>tcp/22 (ssh)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.82</entry>
            <entry>tcp/22 (ssh)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.39</entry>
            <entry>tcp/22 (ssh)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.81</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.24</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.82</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.7</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.83</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.57</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.84</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.44</entry>
            <entry>tcp/25 (smtp)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.81</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.95</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.82</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.74</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.83</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.101</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.84</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.39</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>205.254.211.85</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
            <entry>192.168.100.5</entry>
            <entry>tcp/80 (http)</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      This can be a convincing argument for the use of PAT where IP space is
      at a premium.  Let's examine the different methods of PAT under linux.
    </para>
    <para>
      The support for PAT under kernel 2.4 via netfilter is accomplished with
      the nat table and the DNAT target.  Because netfilter allows the
      arbitrary selection of packets, the translation can be made for a packet
      matching a very specific set of criteria.
    </para>
    <para>
      The userspace options for providing PAT are varied, but can be used with
      both kernel 2.2 and kernel 2.4.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="pat-userland">
    <title>PAT in User Space</title>
    <para>
      There are many tools which can accomplish PAT for you.  <link
      linkend="tools-redir"><command>redir</command></link> is a mature
      TCP port redirector.  There are a large
      number of similar projects which have varying maturity, reliability and
      configurability.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are some general issues which can affect the choice of a user
      space port redirection utility.  First, because the kernel is not
      performing the task, your CPU utilization will be higher simply because
      the a process is not as efficient as the kernel would be.  For port
      redirection utilities which work under a connection server (for
      example
      <link linkend="tools-tcpserver"><command>tcpserver</command></link>,
      <link linkend="tools-inetd"><command>inetd</command></link>, or
      <link linkend="tools-xinetd"><command>xinetd</command></link>)
      there will be additional process forking and memory consumption overhead.
    </para>
    <para>
      In practice, the above issues tend to be far less important than the
      following concerns:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Will the internal server receive a TCP connection initiated from
          the device on which the port redirector is running, or will the
          session appear to come from the real client?
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Is the number of connections going to overload the port redirector?
          (Hint: if you are expecting hundreds of connections an hour, you
          should probably be looking at DNAT or NAT instead of PAT.)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Can the port redirector perform rate limiting?
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      One of the first questions you will need to answer as you are deciding
      what PAT tool to use is the first question above.  If the source IP
      is important to the server, the port redirector will need to provide
      support for <link linkend="adv-nonlocal-bind">binding to non-local
      sockets</link>.  To my knowledge this is not an option compiled into
      most stock kernels, so may require a kernel compilation.
    </para>
    <para>
      <link linkend="tools-redir"><command>redir</command></link> supports
      port redirection running either under a connection server or binding
      directly to sockets itself.  If allowed to bind to sockets directly,
      <command>redir</command> can operate in what it terms transparent proxy
      mode.  This means that it binds to a non-local socket (the client's IP)
      on the routing device and connects to the server from that socket.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the IP of the client is an unimportant matter for the port
      redirector, there are many port redirection tools available.
      <link linkend="tools-xinetd"><command>xinetd</command></link> provides
      support for redirection out of the box.  A casual search of the net
      reveals that a large number of other port redirectors.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are looking for a UDP port redirector, you'll need to seek out
      the tool <command>uredir</command> which appears to function exactly as
      the TCP port redirectors.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="pat-userspace">
    <title>PAT with Userspace Tools</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="pat-transparent-userspace">
    <title>Transparent PAT with Userspace Tools</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="pat-transparent-netfilter">
    <title>Transparent PAT with Netfilter (DNAT)</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
