<!-- $Id$ -->

<appendix id="tools-ip-routing">
    <title>IP Route Management</title>
    <para>
      Routing and understanding routing in an IP network is one of the
      fundamentals you will need to grasp the flexibility of IP networking,
      and services which run on IP networks.  It is not enough to address the
      machines and mix yourself a dirty martini.  You'll need to verify that
      the machine has a route to any network with which it needs to exchange
      IP packets.
    </para>
    <para>
      One key element to remember when designing networks, viewing routing
      tables, debugging networking problems, and viewing network traffic on
      the wire is that IP routing is stateless
      <footnote>
        <para>
          For those who have some doubt, netfilter provides a connection
          tracking mechanism for packets passing through a linux router.  This
          connection tracking, however, is independent of routing.  It is
          important to not conflate the packet filtering connection tracking
          statefulness with the statelessness of IP routing.  For an example
          of a complex networking setup where netfilter's statefulness and the
          statelessness of IP routing collide, see
          <xref linkend="adv-multi-internet"/>.
        </para>
      </footnote>.
      This means that every time a new packet hits the routing stage, the
      router makes an independent decision about where to send this
      packet.
    </para>
    <para>
      In this section, we'll look at the tools available to manipulate and
      view the routing table(s).  We'll start with the well known <link
      linkend="tools-route"><command>route</command></link> command, and move
      on to the increasingly used <link linkend="tools-ip-route"><command>ip
      route</command></link> and <link linkend="tools-ip-rule"><command>ip
      rule</command></link> tools which are part of the
      &iproute2; package.
    </para>
    <section id="tools-route">
      <title><command>route</command></title>
      <para>
        In the same way that
        <link linkend="tools-ifconfig"><command>ifconfig</command></link> is
        the venerable utility for IP address management,
        <command>route</command> is a tremendously useful command for
        manipulating and displaying IP routing tables.
      </para>
      <para>
        Here we'll look at several tasks you can perform with
        <command>route</command>.  You can <link
        linkend="tools-route-show">display routes</link>, <link
        linkend="tools-route-add">add routes</link> (most importantly, the
        <link linkend="tools-route-add-default">default route</link>),
        <link linkend="tools-route-del">remove routes</link>, and <link
        linkend="tools-route-show-cache">examine the routing cache</link>.
        I will switch between traditional and CIDR notation for network
        addressing in this (and subsequent) sections, so the reader unaware of
        these notations is encouraged to refer liberally to the links provided
        in <xref linkend="links-general-ip"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        When using <command>route</command> and <command>ip route</command> on
        the same machine, it is important to understand that not all routing
        table entries can be shown with <command>route</command>.  The key
        distinction is that <command>route</command> only displays
        information in the main routing table.  NAT routes, and routes in
        tables other than the main routing table must be managed and viewed
        separately with the <link linkend="tools-ip-route"><command>ip
        route</command></link> tool.
      </para>
      <section id="tools-route-show">
        <title>Displaying the routing table with <command>route</command></title>
        <para>
          By far the simplest and most common task one performs with
          <command>route</command> is 
          viewing the routing table.  On a single-homed desktop like
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem>, the routing
          table will be very simple, probably comprised of only a few routes.
          Compare this to a complex routing table on a host with multiple
          interfaces and static routes to internal networks, such as
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem>.  It is by using
          the <command>route</command> command that you can determine where a
          packet goes when it leaves your machine.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-show-simple">
          <title>Viewing a simple routing table with <command>route</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
192.168.99.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo
0.0.0.0         192.168.99.254  0.0.0.0         UG    0      0        0 eth0</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          In the simplest routing tables, as in
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem>'s case, you'll
          see three separate routes.  The route which is customarily present
          on all machines (and which I'll not remark on after this) is the
          route to the loopback interface.  The loopback interface is an IP
          interface completely local to the host itself.  Most commonly,
          loopback is configured as a single IP address in a class A-sized
          network.  This entire network has been set aside for use on loopback
          devices.  The address used is usually 127.0.0.1/8, and the device
          name under all default installations of linux I have seen is
          <command>lo</command>.  It is not at all unheard of for people to
          host services on loopback which are intended only for consumption on
          that machine, e.g., SMTP on tcp/25.
        </para>
        <para>
          The remaining two lines define how 
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> should reach any
          other IP address anywhere on the Internet.  These two routing table
          entries divide the world into two different categories: a locally
          reachable network (192.168.99.0/24) and everything else.  If an
          address falls within the 192.168.99.0/24 range, 
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> knows it can
          reach the IP range directly on the wire, so any packets bound for
          this range will be pushed out onto the local media.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the packet falls in any other range
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> will consult its
          routing table and find no single route that matches.  In this case,
          the default route functions as a terminal choice.  If no other route
          matches, the packet will be forwarded to this destination address,
          which is usually a router to another set of networks and routers
          (which eventually lead to the Internet).
        </para>
        <para>
          Viewing a complex routing table is no more difficult than viewing a
          simple routing table, although it can be a bit more diffiult to
          read, interpret, and sometimes even find the route you wish to
          examine.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-show-complex">
          <title>Viewing a complex routing table with <command>route</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
192.168.100.0   0.0.0.0         255.255.255.252 U     0      0        0 eth3
205.254.211.0   0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth1
192.168.100.0   0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
192.168.99.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth2
192.168.98.0    192.168.99.1    255.255.255.0   UG    0      0        0 eth2
10.38.0.0       192.168.100.1   255.255.0.0     UG    0      0        0 eth3
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo
0.0.0.0         205.254.211.254 0.0.0.0         UG    0      0        0 eth1</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          The above routing table shows a more complex set of static routes
          than one finds on a single-homed host.  By comparing the network
          mask of the routes above, we can see that the network mask is listed
          from the most specific to the least specific.  Refer to
          <xref linkend="routing-selection"/> for more discussion.
        </para>
        <para>
          A quick glance down this routing table also provides us with a good
          deal of knowledge about the topology of the network.  Immediately we
          can identify four separate Ethernet interfaces, 3 locally connected
          class C sized networks, and one tiny subnet (192.168.100.0/30).  We
          can also determine that there are two networks reachable via static
          routes behind internal routers.
        </para>
        <para>
          Now that we have taken a quick glance at the output from the route
          command, let's examine a bit more systematically what it's reporting
          to us.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-route-output">
        <title>Reading <command>route</command>'s output</title>
        <para>
          For this discussion refer to the network map in the appendix, and
          also to <xref linkend="ex-tools-route-show-complex"/>.
          <command>route</command> is a venerable command, one which can
          manipulate routing tables for protocols other than IP.  If you wish
          to know what other protocols are supported, try <userinput>route
          --help</userinput> at your leisure.  Fortunately,
          <command>route</command> defaults to inet (IPv4) routes if no other
          address family is specified.
        </para>
        <para>
          By combining the values in columns one and three you can determine
          the destination network or host address.  The first line in 
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem>'s routing table
          shows 192.168.100.0/255.255.255.252, which is more conveniently
          written in CIDR notation as 192.168.100.0/30.  This is the smallest
          possible network according to <ulink
          url="http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc1878.txt">RFC 1878</ulink>.  The
          only two useable addresses are 192.168.100.1 
          (<systemitem class="systemname">service-router</systemitem>)
          and 192.168.100.2
          (<systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem>).
        </para>
        <para>
          The second column holds the IP address of the gateway to the
          destination if the destination is not a locally connected network.
          If there is a value other than 0.0.0.0 in this field, the kernel
          will address the outbound packet for this device (a router of some
          kind) rather than directly for the destination.  The column after
          the netmask column (Flags) should always contain a
          <command>G</command> for destination not locally connected to the
          linux machine.
        </para>
        <para>
          The fields Metric, Ref and Use are not generally used in simple or
          even moderately complex routing tables, however, we will discuss the
          Use column further in <xref linkend="tools-route-show-cache"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The final field in the <command>route</command> output contains the
          name of the interface through which the destination is reachable.
          This can be any interface known to the kernel which has an IP
          address.  In <xref linkend="ex-tools-route-show-complex"/> we can
          learn immediately that 192.168.98.0/24 is reachable through
          interface <constant>eth2</constant>.
        </para>
        <para>
          After this brief examination of the commonest of output from
          <command>route</command>, let's look at some of the other things we
          can learn from <command>route</command> and also how we can change
          the routing table.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-route-show-cache">
        <title>Using <command>route</command> to display the routing cache</title>
        <para>
          The routing cache is used by the kernel as a lookup table analogous
          to a quick reference card.  It's faster for the kernel to refer to
          the cache (internally implemented as a hash table) for a recently
          used route than to lookup the destination address again.  Routes
          existing in the route cache are periodically expired.  If you need
          to clean out the routing cache entirely, you'll want to become
          familiar with <link linkend="tools-ip-route-flush"><command>ip
          route flush cache</command></link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          At first, it might surprise you to learn that there are no entries
          for locally connected networks in a routing cache.  After a bit of
          reflection, you come to realize that there is on need to cache an IP
          route for a locally connected network because the machine is
          connected to the same Ethernet.  So, any given destination has an
          entry in either the arp table or in the routing cache.  For a
          clearer picture of the differences between each of the cached
          routse, I'd suggest adding a <option>-e</option> switch.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-show-cache">
          <title>Viewing the routing cache with <command>route</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route -Cen</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing cache
Source          Destination     Gateway         Flags   MSS Window  irtt Iface
194.52.197.133  192.168.99.35   192.168.99.35     l      40 0          0 lo
192.168.99.35   194.52.197.133  192.168.99.254         1500 0         29 eth0
192.168.99.35   192.168.99.254  192.168.99.254         1500 0          0 eth0
192.168.99.254  192.168.99.35   192.168.99.35     il     40 0          0 lo
192.168.99.35   192.168.99.35   192.168.99.35     l   16436 0          0 lo
192.168.99.35   194.52.197.133  192.168.99.254         1500 0          0 eth0
192.168.99.35   192.168.99.254  192.168.99.254         1500 0          0 eth0</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          FIXME!  I don't really know why there are three entries in the routing
          cache for each destination.  Here, for example, we see three entries
          in the routing cache for 194.52.197.133 (a Swedish destination).
        </para>
        <para>
          The MSS column tells us what the path MTU discovery has determined
          for a maximum segment size for the route to this destination.  By
          discovering the proper segment size for a route and caching this
          information, we can make most efficient use of bandwidth to the
          destination, without incurring the overhead of packet fragmentation
          enroute.  See <xref linkend="routing-icmp-mtu"/> for a more complete
          discussion of MSS and MTU.
        </para>
        <para>
          FIXME!  There has to be more we can say about the routing cache
          here.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-route-add">
        <title>Creating a static route with <command>route add</command></title>
        <para>
          Static routes are explicit routes to non-local destinations through
          routers or gateways which are not the default gateway.  The case of
          the routing table on 
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> is a classic
          example of the need for a static route.  There are two routers in
          the same network, 
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem> and
          <systemitem class="systemname">isdn-router</systemitem>.  If 
          <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> has packets for
          the 192.168.98.0/24 network, they should be routed to 192.168.99.1
          (<systemitem class="systemname">isdn-router</systemitem>).  Refer
          also to <xref linkend="basic-changing-static"/> for this example.
        </para>
        <para>
          As with <link
          linkend="tools-ifconfig"><command>ifconfig</command></link>,
          <command>route</command> has a syntax unlike most standard unix
          command line utilities, mixing options and arguments with less
          regularity.  Note the mandatory <option>-net</option> or
          <option>-host</option> options when adding or removing any route
          other than the default route.
        </para>
        <para>
          In order to add a static route to the routing table, you'll need to
          gather several pieces of information about the remote network.
        </para>
        <para>
          In our example network, 
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem> can only reach
          10.38.0.0/16 through 
          <systemitem class="systemname">service-router</systemitem>.  Let's
          add a static route to the masquerading firewall to ensure that
          10.38.0.0/16 is reachable.  Our intended routing table will look
          like the routing table in
          <xref linkend="ex-tools-route-show-complex"/>.
          Let's also view the output
          if we mistype the IP address of the default gateway and specify an
          address which is not a locally reachable address.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-add-net">
          <title>Adding a static route to a network <command>route add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>route add -net 10.38.0.0 netmask 255.255.0.0 gw 192.168.109.1</userinput>
<computeroutput>SIOCADDRT: Network is unreachable</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>route add -net 10.38.0.0 netmask 255.255.0.0 gw 192.168.100.1</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          It should be clear now that the gateway address must be reachable on
          a locally connected network for a static route to be useable (or
          even make sense).  In the first line, where we mistyped, the route
          could not be added to the routing table because the gateway address
          was not a reachable address.
        </para>
        <para>
          Now, instead of sending packets with a destination of 10.38.0.0/16
          to the default gateway, 
          <systemitem class="systemname">wan-gw</systemitem>,
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem> will send this
          traffic to 
          <systemitem class="systemname">service-router</systemitem> at IP
          address 192.168.100.1.
        </para>
        <para>
          The above is a simple example of routing a network to a separate
          gateway, a gateway other than the default gateway.  This is a common
          need on networks central to an operation, and less common in branch
          offices and remote networks.
        </para>
        <para>
          Occasionally, however, you'll have a single machine with an IP
          address in a different range on the same Ethernet as some other
          machines.  Or you might have a single machine which is reachable
          via a router.  Let's look at these two scenarios to see how we can
          create static routes to solve this routing need.
        </para>
        <para>
          Occasionally, you may have a desire to restrict communication from
          one network to another by not including routes to the network.
          In our sample network, &tristan; may be a
          workstation of an employee who doesn't need to reach any machines in
          the branch office.  Perhaps this employee needs to periodically
          access some data or service supplied on 192.168.98.101.  We'll need
          to add a static route to allow this machine to access this single
          host IP in the branch office network
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Though &tristan; does not
              have a direct route to the 192.168.98.0/24 network, it does have
              a default route which knows about this destination network.
              Therefore, for the purposes of this illustrative example, we'll
              assume that &masq-gw; is
              configured to drop or reject all traffic to 192.168.98.0/24 from
              192.168.99.0/24 and vice versa.  Effectively this means that the
              only path to reach the branch office from the main office is via 
              &isdn-router;.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Here's a summary of the <link linkend="basic-changing-static">required
          data</link> for our static route.  The destination is
          192.168.98.101/32 and the gateway is 192.168.99.1.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-add-host">
          <title>Adding a static route to a host with <command>route add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route add -host 192.168.98.101 gw 192.168.99.1</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
192.168.98.101  192.168.99.1    255.255.255.255 UG    0      0        0 eth0
192.168.99.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo
0.0.0.0         192.168.99.254  0.0.0.0         UG    0      0        0 eth0</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Now, we have successfully altered the routing table to include a
          host route for the single machine we want our employee to be able to
          reach.
        </para>
        <para>
          Even rarer, you may encounter a situation where a single Ethernet
          network is used to host multiple IP networks.  There are reasons
          people might do this, although I regard this is bad form.  If
          possible, it is cleaner, more secure, and easier to troubleshoot if
          you do not share IP networks on the same media segment.  With that
          said, you can still convince your linux box to be a part of each
          network
          <footnote>
            <para>
              There can potentially be routing problems with multiple IP
              networks on the same media segment, but if you can remember that
              IP routing is essentially stateless, you can plan around these
              routing problems and solve these problems.  For a fuller
              discussion of these issues, see <xref linkend="adv-multi-ips"/>
              and <xref linkend="adv-media-share"/>.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Let's assume for the sake of this example that NAT is not an option
          for us, and we need to move the machine 205.254.211.184 into another
          network.  Though it violates the concept of security partitioning,
          we have decided to put the server into the same network as
          <systemitem class="systemname">service-router</systemitem>.
          Naturally, we'll need to modify the routing table on 
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Be sure to refer to <xref linkend="adv-proxy-arp"/> for a
          complete discussion of this unusual networking scenario.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-add-host-dev">
          <title>Adding a static route to a host on the same media with <command>route add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>route add -host 205.254.211.184 dev eth3</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          I'll leave as an exercise to the reader's imagination the question
          of how to send all traffic to a locally connected network to an
          interface.  In light of the host route above, it should be a logical
          step for the reader to make.
        </para>
        <para>
          The above are common examples of the usage of the
          <command>route</command> command.
        </para>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-route-add-default">
        <title>Creating a default route with <command>route add default</command></title>
        <para>
          The default route is a special case of a static route.  Any machine
          which is connected to the Internet has a default route.  For the
          majority of smaller networks which are not running dynamic routing
          protocols, each machine on an internal network uses a router or
          firewall as its default gateway, forwarding all traffic to that
          destination.  Typically, this router or firewall forwards the
          traffic to the next router or device via a static route until the
          traffic reaches the ISP's service access router.  Many ISPs use
          dynamic routing internally to determine the best path out of their
          networks to remote destinations.
        </para>
        <para>
          But we are only interested in adding a default route and
          understanding that packets are reaching the default gateway.  Once
          the packets have reached the default gateway, we assume that the
          administrator of that device is monitoring its correct operation.
        </para>
        <para>
          With this bit of background about the default route, it is easy to
          see why a default route is a key part of any networking device's
          configuration.  If the machine is to reach machines other than the
          machines on the local network, it must know the address of the
          default gateway.
        </para>
        <para>
          Because the default gateway is so important, there is particular
          support for adding a default route included in the
          <command>route</command> command.  Refer to
          <xref linkend="ex-basic-set-default"/> for a simple
          example of adding a
          default route.  The syntax of the command is as follows:
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-add-default">
          <title>Setting the default route with <command>route</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route add default gw 192.168.99.254</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          This is the commonest method used for setting a default route,
          although the route can also be specified by the following command.
          I find the alternate method more explicit than the common method for
          setting default gateway, because the destination address and network
          mask are treated exactly like any other network address and netmask.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-add-default-alt">
          <title>An alternate method of setting the default route with <command>route</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route add -net 0.0.0.0 netmask 0.0.0.0 gw 192.168.99.254</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          The alternate method of setting a default route specifies a network
          and netmask of 0, which is shorthand for all destinations.  I'll
          reiterate that the kernel sees these two methods of setting the
          default route as identical.  The resulting routing table is exactly
          the same.  You may select whichever of these
          <command>route</command> invocations you find more comfortable.
        </para>
        <para>
          Now that we have covered adding static routes and the special static
          route, the default route, let's try our hand at removing existing
          routes from routing tables.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-route-del">
        <title>Removing routes with <command>route del</command></title>
        <para>
          Any route can be removed from the routing table as easily as it can
          be added.  The syntax of the command is exactly the same as the
          syntax of the <command>route add</command> command.
        </para>
        <para>
          After we went to all of the trouble above to put our machine
          205.254.211.184 into the network with
          <systemitem class="systemname">service-router</systemitem>, we
          probably realize that from a security partitioning standpoint, it is
          not only stupid, but also foolhardy!  So now, we conclude that we
          need to return 205.254.211.184 to its former network (the DMZ
          proper).  We'll now remove the special host route for its IP, so the
          network route for 205.254.211.0/24 will now be used for reaching
          this host.  (If you have questions about why, read
          <xref linkend="routing-selection"/>.)
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-del-host-dev">
          <title>Removing a static host route with <command>route del</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
205.254.211.184 0.0.0.0         255.255.255.255 U     0      0        0 eth3
192.168.100.0   0.0.0.0         255.255.255.252 U     0      0        0 eth3
205.254.211.0   0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth1
192.168.100.0   0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
192.168.99.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth2
192.168.98.0    192.168.99.1    255.255.255.0   UG    0      0        0 eth2
10.38.0.0       192.168.100.1   255.255.0.0     UG    0      0        0 eth3
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo
0.0.0.0         205.254.211.254 0.0.0.0         UG    0      0        0 eth1</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>route del -host 205.254.211.184 dev eth3</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Another possible example might be the prohibition of Internet
          traffic to a particular user.  If a machine does not have a default
          route, but instead has a routing table populated only with routes to
          internal networks, then that machine can only reach IP addresses in
          networks to which it has a routing table entry.  Let's say that you
          have a user who routinely spends work hours browsing the Internet,
          fetching mail from a POP account outside your network, and in short
          wastes time on the Internet.  You can easily prevent this user from
          reaching anything except your internal networks.  Naturally, this
          sort of a problem employee should probably face some sort of
          administrative sanction to address the real problem, but as a
          technical component of the strategy to prevent this user from
          wasting time on the Internet, you could remove access to the
          Internet from this employee's machine.
        </para>
        <para>
          In the below example, we'll use the <command>route</command> command
          a number of times for different operations, all of which you should
          be familiar with by now.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-route-del-default">
          <title>Removing the default route with <command>route del</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@morgan]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
192.168.98.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo
0.0.0.0         192.168.98.254  0.0.0.0         UG    0      0        0 eth0</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@morgan]# </prompt><userinput>route del default gw 192.168.98.254</userinput>
<prompt>[root@morgan]# </prompt><userinput>route add -net 192.168.99.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 gw 192.168.98.254</userinput>
<prompt>[root@morgan]# </prompt><userinput>route add -net 192.168.100.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 gw 192.168.98.254</userinput>
<prompt>[root@morgan]# </prompt><userinput>route add -net 205.254.211.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 gw 192.168.98.254</userinput>
<prompt>[root@morgan]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
205.254.211.0   192.168.98.254  255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
192.168.100.0   192.168.98.254  255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
192.168.99.0    192.168.98.254  255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
192.168.98.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Now, the user on <systemitem class="systemname">morgan</systemitem>
          can only reach the specified networks.  The networks we have entered
          here are all of our corporate networks.  If the user tries to
          generate a packet to any other destination, the kernel is not going
          to know where to send it, so will return in error code to the
          application trying to make the network connection.
        </para>
        <para>
          While this can be a very effective way to restrict access to an
          individual machine, it is an ineffective method of systems
          administration, since it requires that the user log in to the
          affected machine and make changes to the routing table on demand.  A
          better solution would be to use <link linkend="pf-network">packet
          filter rules</link>.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="tools-ip-route">
      <title><command>ip route</command></title>
      <para>
        Another part of the &iproute2; suite of tools for IP
        management, <command>ip route</command> provides management tools for
        manipulating any of the routing tables.  Operations
        include
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-show">displaying routes</link> or the
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-show-cache">routing cache</link>,
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-add">adding routes</link>,
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-del">deleting routes</link>,
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-change">modifying existing routes</link>, and
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-get">fetching a route</link> and
        <link linkend="tools-ip-route-flush">clearing an entire routing table or
        the routing cache</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        One thing to keep in mind when using the <command>ip route</command>
        is that you can operate on any of the 255 routing tables with this
        command.  Where the <link
        linkend="tools-route"><command>route</command></link>
        command operated only on the main routing table (table 254), the
        <command>ip route</command> command operates by default on the main
        routing table, but can be easily coaxed into using other tables with
        the <option>table</option> parameter.
      </para>
      <para>
        Fortunately, as mentioned earlier, the &iproute2;
        suite of tools does not rely on DNS for any operation so, the
        ubiquitous <option>-n</option> switch in previous examples will not be
        required in any example here.
      </para>
      <para>
        All operations with the <command>ip route</command> command are
        atomic, so each command will return either <computeroutput>RTNETLINK
        answers: No such process</computeroutput> in the case of an error, or
        nothing in the face of success.  The <option>-s</option> switch which
        provides additional statistical information when reporting link layer
        information will only provide additional information when reporting on
        the state of the <link linkend="tools-ip-route-show-cache">routing
        cache</link> or <link linkend="tools-ip-route-get">fetching a specific
        route</link>..
      </para>
      <para>
        The <command>ip route</command> utility when used in conjunction with
        the <link linkend="tools-ip-rule"><command>ip rule</command></link>
        utility can create stateless NAT tables.  It can even manipulate the
        local routing table, a routing table used for traffic bound for
        broadcast addresses and IP addresses hosted on the machine itself.
      </para>
      <para>
        In order to understand the context in which this tool runs, you need
        to understand some of the basics of IP routing, so if you have read
        the above introduction to the <command>ip route</command> tool, and
        are confused, you may want to read <xref linkend="ch-routing"/> and 
        grasp some of the concepts of IP routing (with linux) before
        continuing here. 
      </para>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-show">
        <title>Displaying a routing table with <command>ip route
          show</command></title>
        <para>
          In its simplest form, <command>ip route</command> can be used to
          display the main routing table output.  The output of this command
          is significantly different from the output of the <link
          linkend="tools-route-show"><command>route</command></link>.  For
          comparison, let's look at the output of both <command>route
          -n</command> and <command>ip route show</command>.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-show-main">
          <title>Viewing the main routing table with <command>ip route
            show</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>route -n</userinput>
<computeroutput>Kernel IP routing table
Destination     Gateway         Genmask         Flags Metric Ref    Use Iface
192.168.99.0    0.0.0.0         255.255.255.0   U     0      0        0 eth0
127.0.0.0       0.0.0.0         255.0.0.0       U     0      0        0 lo
0.0.0.0         192.168.99.254  0.0.0.0         UG    0      0        0 eth0</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.99.0/24 dev eth0  scope link 
127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  scope link 
default via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          If you are accustomed to the <command>route</command> output format,
          the <command>ip route</command> output can seem terse.  The
          same basic information is displayed, however.  As with our former
          example, let's ignore the 127.0.0.0/8 loopback route for the moment.
          This is a required route for any IPs hosted on the loopback
          interface.  We are far more interested in the other two routes.
        </para>
        <para>
          The network 192.168.99.0/24 is available on eth0 with a scope of
          link, which means that the network is valid and reachable through
          this device (eth0).  Refer to <xref linkend="tb-tools-ip-addr-scope"/>
          for definitions of possible scopes.  As long as link remains good on
          that device, we should be able to reach any IP address inside of
          192.168.99.0/24 through the eth0 interface.
        </para>
        <para>
          Finally, our all-important default route is expressed in the routing
          table with the word default.  Note that any destination which is
          reachable through a gateway appears in the routing table output with
          the keyword <option>via</option>.  This final line matches
          semantically with the final line of output from <command>route
          -n</command> above.
        </para>
        <para>
          Now, let's have a look at the local routing table, which we can't
          see with <command>route</command>.  To be fair, it is usually
          completely unnecessary to view and/or manipulate the local routing
          table, which is why <command>route</command> provides no way to
          access this information.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-show-local">
          <title>Viewing the local routing table with <command>ip route show
            table local</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table local</userinput>
<computeroutput>local 192.168.99.35 dev eth0  proto kernel  scope host  src 192.168.99.35 
broadcast 127.255.255.255 dev lo  proto kernel  scope link  src 127.0.0.1 
broadcast 192.168.99.255 dev eth0  proto kernel  scope link  src 192.168.99.35 
broadcast 127.0.0.0 dev lo  proto kernel  scope link  src 127.0.0.1 
local 127.0.0.1 dev lo  proto kernel  scope host  src 127.0.0.1 
local 127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  proto kernel  scope host  src 127.0.0.1</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          This gives us a good deal of information about the IP networks to
          which the machine is directly connected, and an inside look into the 
          way that the routing tables treat special addresses like broadcast
          addresses and locally configured addresses.
        </para>
        <para>
          The first field in this output tells us whether the route is for a
          broadcast address or an IP address or range locally hosted on this
          machine.  Subsequent fields inform us through which device the
          destination is reachable, and notably (in this table) that the
          kernel has added these routes as part of bringing up the IP layer
          interfaces.
        </para>
        <para>
          For each IP hosted on the machine, it makes sense that the machine
          should restrict accessiblity to that IP or IP range to itself only.
          This explains why, in <xref linkend="ex-tools-ip-route-show-local"/>,
          192.168.99.35 has a host scope.  Because <systemitem
          class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> hosts this IP, there's no
          reason for the packet to be routed off the box.  Similarly, a
          destination of localhost (127.0.0.1) does not need to be forwarded
          off this machine.  In each of these cases, the scope has been set to
          host.
        </para>
        <para>
          For broadcast addresses, which are intended for any listeners who
          happen to share the IP network, the destination only makes sense as
          for a scope of devices connected to the same link layer
          <footnote>
            <para>
              I'm going to specifically neglect a discussion of bridging and
              broadcast addresses for now.  Let's assume a simple Ethernet
              where the entire IP network is on one hub or switch.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The final characteristic available to us in each line of the local
          routing table output is the <option>src</option> keyword.  This is
          treated as a hint to the kernel about what IP address to select for
          a source address on outgoing packets on this interface.  Naturally,
          this is most commonly used (and abused) on multi-homed hosts,
          although almost every machine out there uses this hint for
          connections to localhost
          <footnote>
            <para>
              When a user initiates a connection to localhost (let's say
              localhost:25, where a private SMTP server is listening), the
              connection could, of course, come from the IP assigned to any of
              the Ethernet interfaces. It makes the most sense, however, for the
              source IP to be set to 127.0.0.1, since the connection is
              actually initiated from on the local machine.  Some services
              running on a local machine rely on the loopback interface and
              will restrict incoming connections to source addresses of
              127.0.0.1.  Frankly, I find this quite sensible for services
              which are not intended for public use.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Now that we have inspected the main routing table and the local
          routing table, let's see how easy it is to look at any one of the
          other routing tables.  This is as simple as specifying the table by
          its name in <filename>/etc/iproute2/rt_tables</filename> or by
          number.  There are a few reserved table identifiers in this file,
          but the other table numbers between 1 and 252 are available for the
          user.  Please note that this example is for demonstration only and
          has no intrinsic value other than showing the use of the
          <option>table</option> parameter.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-show-table">
          <title>Viewing a routing table with <command>ip route
            show table</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table special</userinput>
<computeroutput>Error: argument "special" is wrong: table id value is invalid
</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>echo 7 special >> /etc/iproute2/rt_tables</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table special</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add table special default via 192.168.99.254</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table special</userinput>
<computeroutput>default via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          In the above example you get a first glance at how to add a route to
          a table other than the main routing table, but what we are really
          interested in is the final command and output.  In
          <xref linkend="ex-tools-ip-route-show-table"/>, we have identified table 7
          by the name "special" and have added a route to this table.  The
          command <userinput>ip route show table special</userinput> shows us
          routing table number 7 from the kernel.
        </para>
        <para>
          <command>ip route</command> consults
          <filename>/etc/iproute2/rt_tables</filename> for a table identifier.
          If it finds no identifier, it complains that it cannot find a
          reference to such a table.  If a table identifier is found, then the
          corresponding routing table is displayed.
        </para>
        <para>
          The use of multiple routing tables can make a router very complex,
          very quickly.  Using names instead of numbers for these tables can
          assist in the management of this complexity.  For further discussion
          on managing multiple routing tables and some issues of handling
          them see <xref linkend="adv-rpdb"/>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-show-cache">
        <title>Displaying the routing cache with <command>ip route
          show cache</command></title>
        <para>
          The routing cache is used by the kernel as a lookup table analogous
          to a quick reference card.  It's faster for the kernel to refer to
          the cache (internally implemented as a hash table) for a recently
          used route than to lookup the destination address again.  Routes
          existing in the route cache are periodically expired.
        </para>
        <para>
          The routing cache can be displayed in all its glory with <command>ip
          route show cache</command>, which provides a detailed view of recent
          destination IP addresses and salient characteristics about those
          destinations.  On routers, masquerading boxen and firewalls, the
          routing cache can become very large.  Instead of viewing the entire
          routing cache even on a workstation, we'll select a particular
          destination from the routing cache to examine.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-show-cache">
          <title>Displaying the routing cache with <command>ip route
            show cache</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show cache 192.168.100.17</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.100.17 from 192.168.99.35 via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0 
    cache  mtu 1500 rtt 18ms rttvar 15ms cwnd 15 advmss 1460
192.168.100.17 via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0  src 192.168.99.35 
    cache  mtu 1500 advmss 1460</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          FIXME!  I don't know how to explain rtt, rttvar, and cwnd, even
          after reading Alexey's comments in the iproute2 documentation!
          Not only that, I'm not sure why there are two entries!
        </para>
        <para>
          The output in <xref linkend="ex-tools-ip-route-show-cache"/>
          summarizes the reachability of the destination 192.168.100.17 from
          192.168.99.35.  The first line of each entry provides some important
          information for us:  the destination IP, the source IP, the gateway
          through which the destination is reachable, and the interface
          through which packets were routed.  Together, these data
          identify a route entry in the cache.
        </para>
        <para>
          Characteristics of that route
          are summarized in the second line of each entry.  For the route
          between <systemitem class="systemname">tristan</systemitem> and
          <systemitem class="systemname">isolde</systemitem>, we see that Path
          MTU discovery has identified 1500 bytes as the maximum packet size
          from end to end.  The maximum segment size (MSS) of data is 1460
          bytes.  Although this is not usually of any but the most casual of
          interest, it can be helpful diagnostic information.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you are a die-hard fan of statistics, and can't get enough
          information about the routing on your machine, you can always
          throw the <option>-s</option> switch.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-show-cache-stats">
          <title>Displaying statistics from the routing cache with
            <command>ip -s route show cache</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip -s route show cache 192.168.100.17</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.100.17 from 192.168.99.35 via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0 
    cache  users 1 used 326 age 12sec mtu 1500 rtt 72ms rttvar 22ms cwnd 2 advmss 1460
192.168.100.17 via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0  src 192.168.99.35 
    cache  users 1 used 326 age 12sec mtu 1500 advmss 1460</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          With this output, you'll get just a bit more information about the
          routes.  The most interesting datum is usually the "used" field,
          which indicates the number of times this route has been accessed in
          the routing cache.  This can give you a very good idea of how many
          times a particular route has been used.  The age field is used by
          the kernel to decide when to expire a cache entry.  The age is reset
          every time the route is accessed
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Be wary of using
              <link linkend="tools-ip-route-get"><command>ip route
              get</command></link> and <command>ip route show cache</command>
              because <command>ip route get</command>
              implicitly causes a route lookup to be performed, thus
              increasing the used counter on the route, and resetting the age.
              This will alter the statistics reported by <command>ip -s route
              show cache</command>.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          In sum, you can use the routing cache to learn a good deal about
          remote IP destinations and some of the characteristics of the
          network path to those destinations.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-add">
        <title>Using <command>ip route add</command> to populate a routing
          table</title>
        <para>
          <command>ip route add</command> is a used to populate a
          routing table.  Although you can use <link
          linkend="tools-route-add"><command>route add</command></link> to do
          the same thing, <command>ip route add</command> offers a large
          number of options that are not possible with the venerable
          <command>route</command> command.
          After we have looked at some simple examples, we'll discuss more
          complex routes with <command>ip route</command>.
        </para>
        <para>
          In <xref linkend="tools-route"/>, we used two classic examples of
          adding a network route (to our service provider's network from )
          and a host route.  Let's look at the
          difference in syntax with the <command>ip route</command> command.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-add-net">
          <title>Adding a static route to a network with <command>route
            add</command>, cf. <xref linkend="ex-tools-route-add-net"/></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add 10.38.0.0/16 via 192.168.100.1</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          This is one of the simplest examples of the syntax of the
          <command>ip route</command>.  As you may recall, you can only add a
          route to a destination network through a gateway that is itself
          already reachable.  In this case,
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem> already knows a
          route to 192.168.100.1
          (<systemitem class="systemname">service-router</systemitem>).  Now
          any packets bound for 10.38.0.0/16 will be forwarded to
          192.168.100.1.
        </para>
        <para>
          Other interesting examples of this command involve the use of
          <option>prohibit</option> and <option>from</option>.  Use of the
          <option>prohibit</option> will cause the router to report that the
          requested destination is unreachable.  If you know a netblock that
          hosts a service you are not interested in allowing your users to
          access, this is an effective way to block the outbound connection
          attempts.
        </para>
        <para>
          Let's look at an example of <link
          linkend="tools-tcpdump"><command>tcpdump</command></link> output
          which shows the <option>prohibit</option> route in action.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-add-prohibit">
          <title>Adding a <option>prohibit</option> route with <command>route
            add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add prohibit 209.10.26.51</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ssh 209.10.26.51</userinput>
<computeroutput>ssh: connect to address 209.10.26.51 port 22: No route to host</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>tcpdump -nnq -i eth2</userinput>
<computeroutput>tcpdump: listening on eth2
22:13:13.740406 192.168.99.35.51973 &gt; 209.10.26.51.22: tcp 0 (DF)
22:13:13.740714 192.168.99.254 &gt; 192.168.99.35: icmp: host 209.10.26.51 unreachable - admin prohibited filter [tos 0xc0]</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Compare the ICMP packet returned to the sender in this case with the
          <link linkend="ex-pf-iptables-reject">ICMP packet returned</link> if
          you used <command>iptables</command> and the <option>REJECT</option>
          target
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Please note that I in the cross-referenced example I have used
              <command>iptables</command>.  The same behaviour should be
              expected with <command>ipchains</command>. (Anybody have any
              proof?)
            </para>
          </footnote>.
          Although the net effect is identical (the user is unable
          to reach the intended destinatioan), the user gets two different
          error messages.  With an <command>iptables</command>
          <option>REJECT</option>, the user sees <computeroutput>Connection
          refused</computeroutput>, where the user sees <computeroutput>No
          route to host</computeroutput> with the use of
          <option>prohibit</option>.  These are but two of the options for
          controlling outbound access from your network.
        </para>
        <para>
          Supposing you don't want to block access to this particular host for
          all of your users, the <option>from</option> option comes to your
          aid.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-add-from">
          <title>Using <option>from</option> in a routing command with
            <command>route add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add prohibit 209.10.26.51 from 192.168.99.35</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Now, you have effectively blocked the source IP 192.168.99.35 from
          reaching 209.10.26.51.  Any packets matching this source and
          destination address will match this route.  In this case,
          <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem> will generate an
          ICMP error message indicating that the destination is
          administratively unreachable.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you are still following along here, you can see that the options
          for identifying particular routes are many and multi-faceted.  The
          <option>src</option> option provides a hint to the kernel for source
          address selection.  When you are working with multiple routing
          tables and different classes of traffic, you can ease your
          administrative burden, by hosting several
          different IPs on your linux machine and setting the source address
          differently, depending on the type of traffic.
        </para>
        <para>
          In the example below, let's assume that our masquerading host also
          runs a DNS resolver for the internal network and we have selected
          all of the outbound DNS packets to be routed according to table 7
          <footnote>
            <para>
              If you wonder how this kind of magic is accomplished, you'll
              want to read <xref linkend="adv-routing-fwmark"/>.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
          Now, any packet which originates on this box (or is masqueraded
          through this table) will have its source IP set to 205.254.211.198.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-add-src">
          <title>Using <option>src</option> in a routing command with
            <command>route add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add default via 205.254.211.254 src 205.254.211.198 table 7</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          FIXME!!  I have nothing to say about <option>nexthop</option> yet,
          because I have never used it, this goes for
          <option>equalize</option> and <option>onlink</option> as well.  If
          anybody has some examples s/he would like to contribute, I'd love to
          hear.
        </para>
        <para>
          There are other options to the <command>ip route add</command>
          documented in Alexey's thorough &iproute2;
          documentation.  For further research, I'd suggested acquiring and
          reading this manual.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-add-default">
        <title>Adding a default route with <command>ip route add
          default</command></title>
        <para>
          Naturally, one of the most important routes on a machine is its
          default route.  Adding a default route is one of the simplest
          operations with <command>ip route</command>.
        </para>
        <para>
          We need exactly one piece of information in order to set the default
          route on a machine.  This is the IP address of the gateway.  The
          syntax of the command is extremely simple and aside from the use of
          the <option>via</option> instead of <option>gw</option>, it is
          almost the same command as the equivalent <command>route
          -n</command>.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-add-default">
          <title>Setting the default route with <command>ip route add default</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add default via 192.168.99.254</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-add-nat">
        <title>Setting up NAT with <command>ip route add nat</command></title>
        <para>
          Be sure to see <xref linkend="ch-nat"/> for a full treatment of the
          issues involved in network address translation (NAT).  If you are
          here to learn a bit more about how to set up NAT in your network,
          then you should know that the <command>ip route add nat</command> is
          only half of the solution.  You must understand that performing NAT
          with &iproute2; involves one component to rewrite
          the inbound packet (<command>ip route add nat</command>), and
          another command to rewrite the outbound packet (<link
          linkend="tools-ip-rule-add-nat"><command>ip rule add
          nat</command></link>).  If you only get half of the system in place,
          your NAT will only work halfway--or not at all, depending on how you
          define "work".
        </para>
        <para>
          Alexey documents clearly in the appendix to the
          &iproute2; manual that the NAT provided by the
          &iproute2; suite is stateless.  This is distinctly
          unlike NAT with netfilter.  Refer to <xref linkend="nat-dnat"/> and
          <xref linkend="state-conntrack"/>
          for a better look at the connection tracking and network address
          translation support available under netfilter.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <command>ip route add nat</command> command is used to rewrite
          the destination address of a packet from one IP or range to another
          IP or range.  The &iproute2; tools can only operate
          on the entire IP packet.  There is no provision directly within the
          &iproute2; suite to support conditional rewriting
          based on the destination port of a UDP datagram or TCP segment.
          It's the whole packet, every packet, and nothing but the packet
          <footnote>
            <para>
              This should not lead you into believing it cannot be done.  This
              is linux after all!  By routing via fwmark, and using the
              <option>--mark</option> option to <command>ipchains</command> or
              the MARK target and <option>--set-mark</option> option in
              <command>iptables</command>, you can perform conditional routing
              based on characteristics and contents of the packet.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-nat-simple">
          <title>Creating a NAT route for a single IP with <command>ip route add
            nat</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add nat 205.254.211.17 via 192.168.100.17</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table local | grep ^nat</userinput>
<computeroutput>nat 205.254.211.17 via 192.168.100.17  scope host</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          The route entry we have just made tells the kernel to rewrite any
          inbound packet bound for 205.254.211.17 to 192.168.100.17.  The
          actual rewriting of the packet occurs at the routing stage of the
          packets trip through the kernel.  This is an important detail,
          illuminated more fully in
          <xref linkend="nat-stateless-pf-interaction"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Not only can &iproute2; support network address
          translation for single IPs, but also for entire network ranges.  The
          syntax is substantially similar to the syntax above, but uses a
          CIDR network address instead of a single IP.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-nat-network">
          <title>Creating a NAT route for an entire network with <command>ip
            route add nat</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add nat 205.254.211.32/29 via 192.168.100.32</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show table local | grep ^nat</userinput>
<computeroutput>nat 205.254.211.32/29 via 192.168.100.32  scope host</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          In this example, we are adding a route for an entire network.  Any
          IP packets which come to us destined for any address between
          205.254.211.32 and 205.254.211.39 will be rewritten to the
          corresponding address in the range 192.168.100.32 through
          192.168.100.39.  This is a shorthand way to specify multiple
          translations with CIDR notation.
        </para>
        <para>
          Again, this is only one half of the story for NAT with
          &iproute2;.  Please be certain to read 
          the section below for usage information on <link
          linkend="tools-ip-rule-add-nat"><command>ip rule add
          nat</command></link>, in addition to <xref linkend="ch-nat"/> which
          will provide fuller documentation for NAT support under linux.
          Don't forget to use <link
          linkend="tools-ip-route-flush-cache"><command>ip route flush
          cache</command></link> after you add NAT routes and
          the corresponding NAT rules
          <footnote>
            <para>
              You can always use my
              <link linkend="ex-sc-nat">SysV initialization script</link>
              and
              <link linkend="ex-sc-static-nat">configuration file</link>
              instead of entering your own commands, however, it is
              always important to understand the tool you are using.
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-del">
        <title>Removing routes with <command>ip route del</command></title>
        <para>
          The <command>ip route del</command> takes exactly the same syntax as
          the <link linkend="tools-ip-route-add"><command>ip route
          add</command></link> command, so if you have familiarized yourself
          with the syntax, this should be a snap.
        </para>
        <para>
          It is, in fact, almost trivial to delete routes on the command line
          with <command>ip route del</command>.  You can simply identify the
          route you wish to remove with <link 
          linkend="tools-ip-route-show"><command>ip route show</command></link>
          command and append the output line verbatim to <command>ip route
          del</command>.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-del">
          <title>Removing routes with <command>ip route del</command>
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Please note that this is the same routing table as is shown in
              the <xref linkend="ex-tools-route-show-complex"/>, which
              displays the output from <command>route -n</command> on
              <systemitem class="systemname">masq-gw</systemitem>.
            </para>
          </footnote>
          </title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.100.0/30 dev eth3  scope link
205.254.211.0/24 dev eth1  scope link
192.168.100.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.99.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.98.0/24 via 192.168.99.1 dev eth0
10.38.0.0/16 via 192.168.100.1 dev eth3
127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  scope link 
default via 205.254.211.254 dev eth1</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route del 10.38.0.0/16 via 192.168.100.1 dev eth3</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          We identified the network route to 10.38.0.0/16 as the route we
          wished to remove, and simply appended the description of the route
          to our <command>ip route del</command> command.
        </para>
        <para>
          This command can be used to remove routes such as broadcast routes
          and routes to locally hosted IPs in addition to manipulation of
          any of the other routing tables.  This means that you can cause some
          very strange problems on your machine by inadvertently removing
          routes, especially routes to locally hosted IP addresses.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-change">
        <title>Altering existing routes with <command>ip route
          change</command></title>
        <para>
          Occasionally, you'll want to remove a route and replace it with
          another one.  Fortunately, this can be done atomically with
          <command>ip route change</command>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Let's change the default route on tristan with this command.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-change">
          <title>Altering existing routes with <command>ip route
            change</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route change default via 192.168.99.113 dev eth0</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.99.0/24 dev eth0  scope link 
127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  scope link 
default via 192.168.99.113 dev eth0</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          If you do use the <command>ip route change</command> command, you
          should be aware that it does not communicate a routing table state
          change to the routing cache, so here is another good place to get in
          the habit of using <link
          linkend="tools-ip-route-flush-cache"><command>ip route flush
          cache</command></link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          There's not much more to say about the use of this command.  If you
          don't want to use an <link 
          linkend="tools-ip-route-del"><command>ip route del</command></link>
          immediately followed by an <link
          linkend="tools-ip-route-add"><command>ip route add</command></link>
          you can use <command>ip route change</command>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-get">
        <title>Programmatically fetching route information with <command>ip
          route get</command></title>
        <para>
          When configuring routing tables, it is not always sufficient to
          search for the destination manually.  Especially with large routing
          tables, this can become a rather boring and time-consuming endeavor.
          Fortunately, <command>ip route get</command> elegantly solves the
          problem.  By simulating a request for the specified destination,
          <command>ip route get</command> causes the routing selection
          algorithm to be run.  When this is complete, it prints out the
          resulting path to the destination.  In one sense, this is almost
          equivalent to sending an ICMP echo request packet and then using
          <link linkend="tools-ip-route-show-cache"><command>ip route show
          cache</command></link>.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-get">
          <title>Testing routing tables with <command>ip route
            get</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip -s route get 127.0.0.1/32</userinput>
<computeroutput>ip -s route get 127.0.0.1/32
local 127.0.0.1 dev lo  src 127.0.0.1 
    cache &lt;local&gt;  users 1 used 1 mtu 16436 advmss 16396</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip -s route get 127.0.0.1/32</userinput>
<computeroutput>local 127.0.0.1 dev lo  src 127.0.0.1 
    cache &lt;local&gt;  users 1 used 2 mtu 16436 advmss 16396</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          For casual use, <command>ip route get</command> is an invaluable
          tool.  An obvious side effect of using <command>ip route
          get</command> the increase in the usage count of every touched entry
          in the routing cache.  While this is no problem, it will alter the
          count of packets which have used that particular route.  If you are
          using <command>ip</command> to count outbound packets (people have
          done it!) you should be cautious with this command.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-flush">
        <title>Clearing routing tables with <command>ip route
          flush</command></title>
        <para>
          The <option>flush</option> option, when used with <command>ip
          route</command> empties a routing table or removes the route for a
          particular destination.  In <xref linkend="ex-tools-ip-route-flush"/>,
          we'll first remove a route for a destination network using
          <command>ip route flush</command>, and then we'll remove all of the
          routes in the main routing table with one command.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you do not wish to delete routes by hand, you can quickly
          empty all of the routes in a table by specifying a table identifier
          to the <command>ip route flush</command> command.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-flush">
          <title>Removing a specific route and emptying a routing table with
            <command>ip route flush</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush</userinput>
<computeroutput>"ip route flush" requires arguments</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush 10.38</userinput>
<computeroutput>Nothing to flush.</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush 10.38.0.0/16</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.100.0/30 dev eth3  scope link
205.254.211.0/24 dev eth1  scope link
192.168.100.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.99.0/24 dev eth0  scope link
192.168.98.0/24 via 192.168.99.1 dev eth0
127.0.0.0/8 dev lo  scope link 
default via 205.254.211.254 dev eth1</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush table main</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Note that you should exercise caution when using <command>ip route
          flush table</command> because you can easily destroy your own route
          to the machine by specifying the main routing table or a routing
          table that is used to send packets to your workstation.  Naturally,
          this is not a problem if you are connected to the machine via a
          serial, modem, console, or other out of band connection.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-flush-cache">
        <title><command>ip route flush cache</command></title>
        <para>
          Above, in <xref linkend="tools-ip-route-show-cache"/>, we looked at
          the contents of the routing cache, a hash table in the kernel which
          contains recently used routes.  To quote John S. Denker, you
          should not forget to use <command>ip route flush cache</command>
          after you have changed the routing tables; "otherwise changes will
          take effect only after some maddeningly irreproducible delay."
          <footnote>
            <para>
              See this remark in his
              <ulink url="http://www.quintillion.com/moat/ipsec+routing/iproute2.html">documentation</ulink>
              of a workaround with FreeS/WAN and iproute2 to approximate more
              RFC-like SPD behaviour for a linux IPSec tunnel.
            </para>
          </footnote>
        </para>
        <para>
          Since the kernel refers to the routing cache before fetching a new
          route from the routing tables, <command>ip route flush
          cache</command> empties the cache of any data.  Now when the kernel
          goes to the routing cache to locate the best route to a destination,
          it finds the cache empty.  Next, it traverses the routing policy
          database and routing tables.  When the kernel finds the route, it
          will enter the newly fetched destination into the routing cache.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-route-flush-cache">
          <title>Emptying the routing cache with <command>ip route flush
            cache</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show cache</userinput>
<computeroutput>local 127.0.0.1 from 127.0.0.1 tos 0x10 dev lo 
    cache &lt;local&gt;  mtu 16436 advmss 16396
local 127.0.0.1 from 127.0.0.1 dev lo 
    cache &lt;local&gt;  mtu 16436 advmss 16396
192.168.100.17 from 192.168.99.35 via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0 
    cache  mtu 1500 rtt 18ms rttvar 15ms cwnd 15 advmss 1460
192.168.100.17 via 192.168.99.254 dev eth0  src 192.168.99.35 
    cache  mtu 1500 advmss 1460</computeroutput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush cache</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show cache</userinput>
<prompt>[root@tristan]# </prompt><userinput>ip route show cache</userinput>
<computeroutput>local 127.0.0.1 from 127.0.0.1 tos 0x10 dev lo 
    cache &lt;local&gt;  mtu 16436 advmss 16396
local 127.0.0.1 from 127.0.0.1 dev lo 
    cache &lt;local&gt;  mtu 16436 advmss 16396</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          When making routing changes to a linux box, you can save yourself
          some troubleshooting time (and confusion) by getting in the habit of
          finishing your routing commands with <command>ip route flush
          cache</command>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-route-summary">
        <title>Summary of the use of <command>ip route</command></title>
        <para>
          With this overview of the use of the <command>ip route</command>
          utility, you should be ready to step into some advanced territory to
          harness multiple routing tables, take advantage of special types of
          routes, use network address translation, and gather detailed
          statistics on the usage of your routing tables.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="tools-ip-rule">
      <title><command>ip rule</command></title>
      <para>
        Another part of the &iproute2; software package,
        <command>ip rule</command> is the single tool for manipulating the
        routing policy database under linux (RPDB).  For a fuller discussion
        of the RPDB, see <xref linkend="adv-rpdb"/>.  The RPDB can be <link
        linkend="tools-ip-rule-show">displayed with <command>ip rule
        show</command></link>.  Particular rules can be added and removed with
        (predictably, if you have been reading the sections on the other
        &iproute2; tools) <link
        linkend="tools-ip-rule-add"><command>ip rule add</command></link>
        command and the <link
        linkend="tools-ip-rule-add"><command>ip rule del</command></link>
        command.  We'll make a particular example of the <link
        linkend="tools-ip-rule-add-nat"><command>ip rule add
        nat</command></link>.
      </para>
      <section id="tools-ip-rule-intro">
        <title><command>ip rule show</command></title>
        <para>
          Briefly, the RPDB mediates access to the routing tables.  In the
          overwhelming majority of installations (most workstations, servers,
          and even routers),
          there is no need to take advantage of the RPDB.  A single IP routing
          table is all that is required for basic connectivity.  In more complex
          networking configurations, however, the RPDB allows the administrator
          to programmatically select a routing table based on characteristics of
          a packet.
        </para>
        <para>
          Along with this freedom and flexibility comes the power to break
          networking in strange and unexpected ways.  I will reiterate:
          <emphasis>IP routing is stateless</emphasis>.  Because IP routing is
          stateless, the network architect, planner or administrator needs to be
          aware of the issues involved with using multiple routing tables.
        </para>
        <para>
          For a fuller discussion of some of these issues, be sure to read
          <xref linkend="adv-rpdb"/>.  Now, let's look at some of the ways to use
          <command>ip rule</command>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-rule-show">
        <title>Displaying the RPDB with <command>ip rule show</command></title>
        <para>
          To display the RPDB, use the command <command>ip route show</command>.
          The output of the command is a list of rules in the RPDB sorted by
          order of priority.  The rules with the highest priority will be
          displayed at the top of the output.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-rule-show">
          <title>Displaying the RPDB with <command>ip rule
            show</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@isolde]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          There are some interesting items to observe here.  First, these are
          the three default rules in the RPDB which will be available on any
          machine with an RPDB.  The first rule specifies that any packet from
          any where should first be matched against routes in the local
          routing table.  Remember that the local routing table is for
          broadcast addresses on link layers, network address translation, and
          locally hosted IP addresses.
        </para>
        <para>
          If a packet is not bound for any of these three destinations, the
          kernel will check the next entry in the RPDB.  In the simple case
          above, on <systemitem class="systemname">isolde</systemitem>, a
          packet bound for 205.254.211.182 would first pass through the local
          routing table without matching any of the local destinations.  The
          next entry in the RPDB recommends using the main routing table to
          select a destination route.
        </para>
        <para>
          In <systemitem class="systemname">isolde</systemitem>'s main routing
          table, it is likely that there is no host nor network match for this
          destination, thus the packet will match the default route in the
          main routing table.
        </para>
        <para>
          FIXME!!  Can anybody (somebody?) explain to me why there is a rule
          priority 32767 which refers to table 253?  I'm still confused about
          this.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-rule-add">
        <title>Adding a rule to the RPDB with <command>ip rule
          add</command></title>
        <para>
          Adding a rule to the routing policy database is simple.  The syntax
          of the <command>ip rule add</command> command should be familiar to
          those who have read <xref linkend="tools-ip-route"/> or have used the
          <command>ip route</command> to populate routing tables.
        </para>
        <para>
          A simple rule selects a packet on the packet's characteristics.
          Some characteristics available as selection criteria  are the
          source address, the destination, the type of service (ToS), the
          interface on which the packet arrived, and an fwmark.
        </para>
        <para>
          One great way to take advantage of the RPDB is to split different
          types of traffic to different providers based on packet
          characteristics.  Let's assume two network connections on
          &masq-gw;, one that is a
          highly reliable high cost connection, and a much lower cost less
          reliable connection.  Let's also assume that we are using Type of
          Service flags on IP packets on the internal network.
        </para>
        <para>
          We might want to prefer a low-latency, highly reliable link
          for one type of packet.  By using <option>tos</option> as a
          selection criterion with <command>ip rule</command> we can
          effectively route these packets via our faster and more reliable
          internet connection.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-rule-add-simple">
          <title>Creating a simple entry in the RPDB with <command>ip rule
            add</command>
            <footnote>
              <para>
                Please note that this is an incomplete example.  Simply put,
                I'm not dealing with the issues of inbound packets or packets
                destined for locally connected networks in this example.  Keep
                in mind the instructional nature of this example, and plan
                your own network accordingly.  For a fuller discussion of the
                issues involved with handling multiple Internet links, see
                <xref linkend="adv-multi-internet"/>.  Note also, that there is
                no corresponding network connection in the example network for
                this network connection.
              </para>
            </footnote>
          </title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route add default via 205.254.211.254 table 8</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add tos 0x08 table 8</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip route flush cache</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32765:  from all tos 0x08 lookup 8 
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Note that the rule we inserted was added to the next available
          higher priority in the RPDB because we did not specify a priority.
          If we wished to specify a priority, we could use
          <option>prio</option>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Now any packet with an IP ToS field matching 0x08 will be routed
          according to the instructions in table 8.  If no route in table 8
          applies to the matched packet (not possible, since we added a
          default route), the packet would be routed according to the
          instructions in table "main".
        </para>
        <para>
          The selection criteria for matching a packet can be grouped.  Let's
          look at a more complex example of <command>ip rule</command> where
          we use multiple selection criteria.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-rule-add-complex">
          <title>Creating a complex entry in the RPDB with <command>ip rule
            add</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add from 192.168.100.17 tos 0x08 fwmark 4 table 7</userinput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Frankly, that's a very complex rule!  I do not know if I could
          describe a scenario where this particular rule would be required.
          The point, though, is that you can have arbitrarily complex
          selection criteria, and multiple rules which lookup routes in as
          many of the 253 routing tables as you wish.
        </para>
        <para>
          <command>ip rule add</command>, while a powerful tool, can quickly
          make a routing table or router too complex to easily understand.
          It's important to try to design and implement the simplest
          configuration to maintain on your router.  If you cannot avoid using
          multiple routing tables and the RPDB, at least be systematic about
          it.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-rule-add-nat">
        <title><command>ip rule add nat</command></title>
        <para>
          As discussed more thoroughly in <xref linkend="ch-nat"/>, this is the
          other half of &iproute2; supported network address
          translation.  The two components are <link
          linkend="tools-ip-route-add-nat"><command>ip route add
          nat</command></link> and <command>ip rule add nat</command>.
        </para>
        <para>
          <command>ip rule add nat</command> is used to rewrite the source IP
          on packets during the routing stage.  Each packet from the real IP
          is translated to the NAT IP without altering the destination address
          of the packet.
        </para>
        <para>
          NAT is commonly used to publish a service in an internal network on
          a public IP.  Thus packets returning to the public network need to
          be readdressed to appear with a source address of the publicly
          accessibly IP.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-rule-add-nat-simple">
          <title>Creating a NAT rule with <command>ip rule add
            nat</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add nat 205.254.211.17 from 192.168.100.17</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32765:  from 192.168.100.17 lookup main map-to 205.254.211.17
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          In more complex situations, entire subnets can be translated to
          provide NAT for a range of IPs.  The example below shows how to
          specify the <command>ip rule add nat</command> to complete the NAT
          mapping in <xref linkend="ex-tools-ip-route-nat-network"/>.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-rule-add-nat-network">
          <title>Creating a NAT rule for an entire network with <command>ip
            rule add nat</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule add nat 205.254.211.32 from 192.168.100.32/29</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32765:  from 192.168.100.32/29 lookup main map-to 205.254.211.32
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          Notice the <command>ip rule</command> synonym for the
          <option>nat</option> option.  It is valid to substitute
          <option>map-to</option> for <option>nat</option>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="tools-ip-rule-del">
        <title><command>ip rule del</command></title>
        <para>
          Naturally, no &iproute2; tool would be complete
          without the ability to undo what has been done.  With <command>ip
          rule del</command>, individual rules can be removed from the RPDB.
        </para>
        <para>
          It is at first quite confusing that the word <option>all</option> in
          the <command>ip rule show</command> output needs to be replaced with
          the network address 0/0.  I do not know why <option>all</option> is
          not acceptable as a synonym for 0/0, but you'll save yourself some
          headache by getting in the habit of replacing <option>all</option>
          with 0/0.
        </para>
        <para>
          By replacing the verb <option>add</option> in any of the command
          lines above with the verb <option>del</option>, you can remove the
          specified entry from the RPDB.
        </para>
        <example id="ex-tools-ip-rule-del-nat-network">
          <title>Removing a NAT rule for an entire network with <command>ip
            rule del nat</command></title>
          <programlisting>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule del nat 205.254.211.32 from 192.168.100.32/29</userinput>
<prompt>[root@masq-gw]# </prompt><userinput>ip rule show</userinput>
<computeroutput>0:      from all lookup local 
32766:  from all lookup main 
32767:  from all lookup 253</computeroutput>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
          The <command>ip rule</command> utility can be a great boon in the
          manipulation and maintenance of complex routers.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
</appendix>
