<!-- start of file -->

<!-- This .xml file is part of the Traffic-Control-HOWTO document -->

<!-- $Id$ -->

<!--

   The article was authored by Martin A. Brown <martin@linux-ip.net>
   for the linux community, and has been released under the GNU Free
   Documentation License (GFDL) through The Linux Documentation
   Project (TLDP).

   This HOWTO is likely available at the following address:

     http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Traffic-Control-HOWTO/
     
  -->

<!-- conventions used in this documentation....

   - each section is a separate file

  -->

<section id="links">

  <title>Annotated Traffic Control Links</title>
  <para>
    This section identifies a number of links to documentation
    about traffic control and Linux traffic control software.  Each link will
    be listed with a brief description of the content at that site.
  </para>


  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://luxik.cdi.cz/~devik/qos/htb/">HTB
          site</ulink>,
        &url-qdisc-htb-userguide; and
        &url-qdisc-htb-theory;
        (<emphasis>Martin <quote>devik</quote> Devera</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        Hierarchical Token Bucket, &link-sch_htb;, is a classful queuing
        discipline.  Widely used and supported it is also fairly well
        documented in the user guide and at
        <ulink url="http://www.docum.org/docum.org/">Stef Coene's site</ulink>
        (see below).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://opalsoft.net/qos/">General Quality of
        Service docs</ulink> (<emphasis>Leonardo Balliache</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        There is a good deal of understandable and introductory documentation
        on his site, and in particular has some excellent overview material.
        See in particular, the detailed
        <ulink url="http://opalsoft.net/qos/DS.htm">Linux QoS</ulink> document
        among others.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
         <ulink url="http://tcng.sourceforge.net/">&tcng; (Traffic Control
           Next Generation)</ulink> and
        <ulink url="http://linux-ip.net/gl/tcng/">&tcng; manual</ulink>
          (<emphasis>Werner Almesberger</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        The &tcng; software includes a language and a set of tools for
        creating and testing traffic control structures.  In addition to
        generating &tc; commands as output, it is also capable of providing
        output for non-Linux applications.  A key piece of the &tcng; suite
        which is ignored in this documentation is the <command>tcsim</command>
        traffic control simulator.
      </para>
      <para>
        The user manual provided with the &tcng; software has been converted
        to HTML with <command>latex2html</command>.  The distribution comes
        with the TeX documentation.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="ftp://ftp.inr.ac.ru/ip-routing/">&iproute2;</ulink> and
        <ulink url="http://linux-ip.net/gl/ip-cref/">&iproute2; manual</ulink>
        (<emphasis>Alexey Kuznetsov</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        This is a the source code for the &iproute2; suite, which includes the
        essential &tc; binary.  Note, that as of
        iproute2-2.4.7-now-ss020116-try.tar.gz, the package did not support
        &sch_htb;, so a patch available from the &url-qdisc-htb; site will be
        required.
      </para>
      <para>
        The manual documents the entire suite of tools, although the &tc;
        utility is not adequately documented here.  The ambitious reader is
        recommended to the LARTC HOWTO after consuming this introduction.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.docum.org/">Documentation, graphs, scripts and
        guidelines to traffic control under Linux</ulink>
        (<emphasis>Stef Coene</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        Stef Coene has been gathering statistics and test results, scripts and
        tips for the use of QoS under Linux.  There are some particularly
        useful graphs and guidelines available for implementing traffic
        control at Stef's site.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://lartc.org/howto/">LARTC HOWTO</ulink>
        (<emphasis>bert hubert, et. al.</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        The Linux Advanced Routing and Traffic Control HOWTO is one of the key
        sources of data about the sophisticated techniques which are available
        for use under Linux.  The Traffic Control Introduction HOWTO should
        provide the reader with enough background in the language and concepts
        of traffic control.  The LARTC HOWTO is the next place the reader
        should look for general traffic control information.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://linux-ip.net/">Guide to IP Networking with
        Linux</ulink> (<emphasis>Martin A. Brown</emphasis>)
      </para>
      <para>
        Not directly related to traffic control, this site includes articles
        and general documentation on the behaviour of the Linux IP layer.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.almesberger.net/cv/papers.html">Werner
        Almesberger's Papers</ulink>
      </para>
      <para>
        Werner Almesberger is one of the main developers and champions of
        traffic control under Linux (he's also the author of &tcng;, above).
        One of the key documents describing the entire traffic control
        architecture of the Linux kernel is his Linux Traffic Control -
        Implementation Overview which is available in
        <ulink url="http://www.almesberger.net/cv/papers/tcio8.pdf">PDF</ulink>
        or
        <ulink url="http://www.almesberger.net/cv/papers/tcio8.ps.gz">PS</ulink>
        format.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://diffserv.sourceforge.net/">Linux DiffServ
        project</ulink>
      </para>
      <para>
        Mercilessly snipped from the main page of the DiffServ site...
      </para>
      <blockquote>
         <para>
         Differentiated Services (short: Diffserv) is an architecture for
         providing different types or levels of service for network traffic.
         One key characteristic of Diffserv is that flows are aggregated in
         the network, so that core routers only need to distinguish a
         comparably small number of aggregated flows, even if those flows
         contain thousands or millions of individual flows.
         </para>
      </blockquote>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</section>

<!-- end of file -->
