<!-- start of file -->

<!-- This .xml file is part of the Traffic-Control-HOWTO document -->

<!-- $Id$ -->

<!--

   The article was authored by Martin A. Brown <martin@linux-ip.net>
   for the linux community, and has been released under the GNU Free
   Documentation License (GFDL) through The Linux Documentation
   Project (TLDP).

   This was initially authored while Martin A. Brown worked for
   SecurePipe, Inc.
     
   This HOWTO is likely available at the following address:

     http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Traffic-Control-HOWTO/
     
  -->

<!-- conventions used in this documentation....

   - each section is a separate file

  -->

<section id="overview">

  <title>Overview of Concepts</title>
  <para>
    This section will
    <link linkend="o-what-is">introduce traffic control</link> and
    <link linkend="o-why-use">examine reasons for it</link>,
    identify a few
    <link linkend="o-advantages">advantages</link> and
    <link linkend="o-disadvantages">disadvantages</link> and 
    introduce key concepts used in traffic control.
  </para>

  <section id="o-what-is">
    <title>What is it?</title>
    <para>
      Traffic control is the name given to the sets of queuing systems and
      mechanisms by which packets are received and transmitted on a router.
      This includes deciding which (and whether) packets to accept at what
      rate on the input of an interface and determining which packets to
      transmit in what order at what rate on the output of an interface.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the overwhelming majority of situations, traffic control consists of
      a single queue which collects entering packets and dequeues them as
      quickly as the hardware (or underlying device) can accept them.  This
      sort of queue is a &sch_fifo;.
    </para>
    <note>
      The default qdisc under Linux is the &link-sch_pfifo_fast;, which is
      slightly more complex than the &link-sch_fifo;.
    </note>
    <para>
      There are examples of queues in all sorts of software.  The queue is a
      way of organizing the pending tasks or data (see also
      <xref linkend="o-queues"/>).  Because network links typically carry data
      in a serialized fashion, a queue is required to manage the outbound
      data packets.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the case of a desktop machine and an efficient webserver sharing the
      same uplink to the Internet, the following contention for bandwidth may
      occur.  The web server may be able to fill up the output queue on the
      router faster than the data can be transmitted across the link, at which
      point the router starts to drop packets (its buffer is full!).  Now, the
      desktop machine (with an interactive application user) may be faced with
      packet loss and high latency.  Note that high latency sometimes leads to
      screaming users!  By separating the internal queues used to service
      these two different classes of application, there can be better sharing
      of the network resource between the two applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Traffic control is the set of tools which allows the user to have
      granular control over these queues and the queuing mechanisms of a
      networked device.  The power to rearrange traffic flows and packets with
      these tools is tremendous and can be complicated, but is no substitute
      for adequate bandwidth.
    </para>
    <para>
      The term Quality of Service (QoS) is often used as a synonym for traffic
      control.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-why-use">
    <title>Why use it?</title>
    <para>
      Packet-switched networks differ from circuit based networks in one very
      important regard.  A packet-switched network itself is stateless.  A
      circuit-based network (such as a telephone network) must hold state
      within the network.  IP networks are stateless and packet-switched 
      networks by design; in fact, this statelessness is one of the
      fundamental strengths of IP.
    </para>
    <para>
      The weakness of this statelessness is the lack of differentiation
      between types of flows.  In simplest terms, traffic control allows an
      administrator to queue packets differently based on attributes of the
      packet.  It can even be used to simulate the behaviour of a
      circuit-based network.  This introduces statefulness into the stateless
      network.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are many practical reasons to consider traffic control, and many
      scenarios in which using traffic control makes sense.  Below are some
      examples of common problems which can be solved or at least ameliorated
      with these tools.
    </para>
    <para>
      The list below is not an exhaustive list of the sorts of solutions
      available to users of traffic control, but introduces the
      types of problems that can be solved by using traffic control to
      maximize the usability of a network connection.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Common traffic control solutions</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Limit total bandwidth to a known rate; &link-sch_tbf;,
          &link-sch_htb; with child class(es).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Limit the bandwidth of a particular user, service or client;
          &link-sch_htb; classes and &elements-classifying; with a
          &linux-filter;.  traffic.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Maximize TCP throughput on an asymmetric link; prioritize
          transmission of ACK packets, &link-wondershaper;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Reserve bandwidth for a particular application or user;
          &link-sch_htb; with children classes and &elements-classifying;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Prefer latency sensitive traffic; &link-sch_prio; inside an
          &link-sch_htb; class.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Managed oversubscribed bandwidth; &link-sch_htb; with borrowing.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Allow equitable distribution of unreserved bandwidth; &link-sch_htb;
          with borrowing.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Ensure that a particular type of traffic is dropped; &linux-policer;
          attached to a &linux-filter; with a &linux-drop; action.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Remember, too that sometimes, it is simply better to purchase more
      bandwidth.  Traffic control does not solve all problems!
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-advantages">
    <title>Advantages</title>
    <para>
      When properly employed, traffic control should lead to more predictable
      usage of network resources and less volatile contention for these
      resources.  The network then meets the goals of the traffic control
      configuration.  Bulk download traffic can be allocated a reasonable
      amount of bandwidth even as higher priority interactive traffic is
      simultaneously
      serviced.  Even low priority data transfer such as mail can
      be allocated bandwidth without tremendously affecting the other classes
      of traffic.
    </para>
    <para>
      In a larger picture, if the traffic control configuration represents
      policy which has been communicated to the users, then users (and,
      by extension, applications) know what to expect from the network.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-disadvantages">
    <title>Disdvantages</title>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
      Complexity is easily one of the most significant disadvantages of using
      traffic control.  There are ways to become familiar with traffic control
      tools which ease the learning curve about traffic control and its 
      mechanisms, but identifying a traffic control misconfiguration can be
      quite a challenge.
    </para>
    <para>
      Traffic control when used appropriately can lead to more equitable
      distribution of network resources.  It can just as easily be installed
      in an inappropriate manner leading to further and more divisive
      contention for resources.
    </para>
    <para>
      The computing resources required on a router to support a traffic
      control scenario need to be capable of handling the increased cost of
      maintaining the traffic control structures.  Fortunately, this is a
      small incremental cost, but can become more significant as the
      configuration grows in size and complexity.
    </para>
    <para>
      For personal use, there's no training cost associated with the use of
      traffic control, but a company may find that purchasing more bandwidth
      is a simpler solution than employing traffic control.  Training
      employees  and ensuring depth of knowledge may be more costly than
      investing in more bandwidth.
    </para>
    <para>
      Although
      traffic control on packet-switched networks covers a larger conceptual
      area, you can think of traffic control as a way to provide [some of] the
      statefulness of a circuit-based network to a packet-switched network.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-queues">
    <title>Queues</title>
    <para>
      Queues form the backdrop for all of traffic control and are the integral
      concept behind scheduling.  A queue is a location (or buffer) containing
      a finite number of items waiting for an action or service.  In
      networking, a queue is the place where packets (our units) wait to be
      transmitted by the hardware (the service).  In the simplest model,
      packets are transmitted in a first-come first-serve basis
      <footnote>
        <para>
          This queueing model has long been used in civilized countries to
          distribute scant food or provisions equitably.  William Faulkner is
          reputed to have walked to the front of the line for to fetch his
          share of ice, proving that not everybody likes the FIFO model, and
          providing us a model for considering priority queuing.
        </para>
      </footnote>.
      In the discipline of computer networking (and more generally
      computer science), this sort of a queue is known as a &sch_fifo;.
    </para>
    <para>
      Without any other mechanisms, a queue doesn't offer any promise for
      traffic control.  There are only two interesting actions in a queue.
      Anything entering a queue is enqueued into the queue.  To remove an item
      from a queue is to dequeue that item.
    </para>
    <para>
      A queue becomes much more interesting when coupled with other mechanisms
      which can delay packets, rearrange, drop and prioritize packets in 
      multiple queues.  A queue can also use subqueues, which allow for
      complexity of behaviour in a scheduling operation.
    </para>
    <para>
      From the perspective of the higher layer software, a packet is simply
      enqueued for transmission, and the manner and order in which the
      enqueued packets are transmitted is immaterial to the higher layer.  So,
      to the higher layer, the entire traffic control system may appear as a
      single queue
      <footnote>
        <para>
          Similarly, the entire traffic control system appears as a queue or
          scheduler to the higher layer which is enqueuing packets into this
          layer.
        </para>
      </footnote>.
      It is only by examining the internals of this layer that
      the traffic control structures become exposed and available.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-flows">
    <title>Flows</title>
    <para>
      A flow is a distinct connection or conversation between two hosts.  Any
      unique set of packets between two hosts can be regarded as a flow.
      Under TCP the concept of a connection with a source IP and port and
      destination IP and port represents a flow.  A UDP flow can be similarly
      defined.
    </para>
    <para>
      Traffic control mechanisms frequently separate traffic into classes of
      flows which can be aggregated and transmitted as an aggregated flow
      (consider DiffServ).  Alternate mechanisms may attempt to divide
      bandwidth equally based on the individual flows.
    </para>
    <para>
      Flows become important when attempting to divide bandwidth equally among
      a set of competing flows, especially when some applications deliberately
      build a large number of flows.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-tokens">
    <title>Tokens and buckets</title>
    <anchor id="o-buckets" xreflabel="Tokens and buckets"/>
    <para>
      Two of the key underpinnings of a &elements-shaping; mechanisms are
      the interrelated concepts of tokens and buckets.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to control the rate of dequeuing, an implementation can count
      the number of packets or bytes dequeued as each item is dequeued,
      although this requires complex usage of timers and measurements to limit
      accurately.  Instead of calculating the current usage and time, one
      method, used widely in traffic control, is to generate tokens at a
      desired rate, and only dequeue packets or bytes if a token is available.
    </para>
    <para>
      Consider the analogy of an amusement park ride with a queue of people
      waiting to experience the ride.  Let's imagine a track on which carts
      traverse a fixed track.  The carts arrive at the head of the queue at a
      fixed rate.  In order to enjoy the ride, each person must wait for an
      available cart.  The cart is analogous to a token and the person is
      analogous to a packet.  Again, this mechanism is a rate-limiting or
      &elements-shaping; mechanism.  Only a certain number of people can
      experience the ride in a particular period.
    </para>
    <para>
      To extend the analogy, imagine an empty line for the amusement park
      ride and a large number of carts sitting on the track ready to carry
      people.  If a large number of people entered the line together many
      (maybe all) of them could experience the ride because of the carts
      available and waiting.  The number of carts available is a concept
      analogous to the bucket.  A bucket contains a number of tokens and can
      use all of the tokens in bucket without regard for passage of time.
    </para>
    <para>
      And to complete the analogy, the carts on the amusement park ride (our
      tokens) arrive at a fixed rate and are only kept available up to the
      size of the bucket.  So, the bucket is filled with tokens according to
      the rate, and if the tokens are not used, the bucket can fill up.  If
      tokens are used the bucket will not fill up.  Buckets are a key concept
      in supporting bursty traffic such as HTTP.
    </para>
    <para>
      The &link-sch_tbf; qdisc is a classical example of a shaper (the section
      on &sch_tbf; includes a diagram which may help to visualize the token
      and bucket concepts).  The &sch_tbf; generates &param-rate; tokens and
      only transmits packets when a token is available.  Tokens are a generic
      shaping concept.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the case that a queue does not need tokens immediately, the tokens
      can be collected until they are needed.  To collect tokens indefinitely
      would negate any benefit of shaping so tokens are collected until a
      certain number of tokens has been reached.  Now, the queue has tokens
      available for a large number of packets or bytes which need to be
      dequeued.  These intangible tokens are stored in an intangible bucket,
      and the number of tokens that can be stored depends on the size of the
      bucket.
    </para>
    <para>
      This also means that a bucket full of tokens may be available at any
      instant.  Very predictable regular traffic can be handled by small
      buckets.  Larger buckets may be required for burstier traffic, unless
      one of the desired goals is to reduce the burstiness of the
      &concepts-flows;.
    </para>
    <para>
      In summary, tokens are generated at rate, and a maximum of a bucket's
      worth of tokens may be collected.  This allows bursty traffic to be
      handled, while smoothing and shaping the transmitted traffic.
    </para>
    <para>
      The concepts of tokens and buckets are closely interrelated and are used
      in both &link-sch_tbf; (one of the &classless-qdiscs;) and
      &link-sch_htb; (one of the &classful-qdiscs;).
      Within the &tcng; language, the use of two- and three-color meters is
      indubitably a token and bucket concept.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="o-packets">
    <title>Packets and frames</title>
    <anchor id="o-frames"/>
    <para>
      The terms for data sent across network changes depending on the layer
      the user is examining.  This document will rather impolitely (and
      incorrectly) gloss over the technical distinction between
      packets and frames although they are outlined here.
    </para>
    <para>
      The word frame is typically used to describe a layer 2 (data link) unit
      of data to be forwarded to the next recipient.  Ethernet interfaces, PPP
      interfaces, and T1 interfaces all name their layer 2 data unit a frame.
      The frame is actually the unit on which traffic control is performed.
    </para>
    <para>
      A packet, on the other hand, is a higher layer concept, representing
      layer 3 (network) units.  The term packet is preferred in this
      documentation, although it is slightly inaccurate.
    </para>
  </section>

</section>

<!-- end of file -->
