<!-- start of file -->

<!-- This .xml file is part of the Traffic-Control-HOWTO document -->

<!-- $Id$ -->

<!--

   The article was authored by Martin A. Brown <martin@linux-ip.net>
   for the linux community, and has been released under the GNU Free
   Documentation License (GFDL) through The Linux Documentation
   Project (TLDP).

   This was initially authored while Martin A. Brown worked for
   SecurePipe, Inc.
     
   This HOWTO is likely available at the following address:

     http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Traffic-Control-HOWTO/
     
  -->

<!-- conventions used in this documentation....

   - each section is a separate file

  -->

<section id="rules">

  <title>Rules, Guidelines and Approaches</title>
  <para>
  </para>

  <section id="r-general">
    <title>General Rules of Linux Traffic Control</title>
    <para>
      There are a few general rules which ease the study of Linux traffic
      control.
      Traffic control structures under Linux are the same whether the initial
      configuration has been done with &link-tcng; or with &link-tc;.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Any router performing a shaping function should be the bottleneck on
          the link, and should be shaping slightly below the maximum available
          link bandwidth.  This prevents queues from forming in other routers,
          affording maximum control of packet latency/deferral to the shaping
          device.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A device can only shape traffic it transmits
          <footnote>
            <para>
              In fact, the
              <link linkend="s-imq">Intermediate Queuing Device
              (IMQ)</link> simulates an output device onto which traffic
              control structures can be attached.  This clever solution allows
              a networking device to shape ingress traffic in the same fashion
              as egress traffic.  Despite the apparent contradiction of the
              rule, IMQ appears as a device to the kernel.  Thus, there has
              been no violation of the rule, but rather a sneaky
              reinterpretation of that rule.
            </para>
          </footnote>.  Because the traffic has already been received on an
          input interface, the traffic cannot be shaped.  A traditional
          solution to this problem is an ingress policer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every interface must have a &linux-qdisc;.  The default qdisc
          (the &link-sch_pfifo_fast; qdisc) is used when another qdisc is not
          explicitly attached to the interface.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          One of the &classful-qdiscs; added to an interface with no children
          classes typically only consumes CPU for no benefit.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Any newly created class contains a &link-sch_fifo;.
          This qdisc can be replaced explicitly with any other qdisc.  The
          &sch_fifo; qdisc will be removed implicitly if a child class is
          attached to this class.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Classes directly attached to the &root-qdisc; can be used to
          simulate virtual circuits.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A &linux-filter; can be attached to classes or one of the
          &classful-qdiscs;.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <!--
  <section id="r-classes">
    <title>Rules for Classes</title>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>
    -->

  <section id="r-known-bandwidth">
    <title>Handling a link with a known bandwidth</title>
    <para>
      &sch_htb; is an ideal &linux-qdisc; to use on a link with a known
      bandwidth, because the innermost (root-most) class can be set to the
      maximum bandwidth available on a given link.  Flows can be further
      subdivided into children classes, allowing either guaranteed bandwidth
      to particular classes of traffic or allowing preference to specific
      kinds of traffic.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="r-unknown-bandwidth">
    <title>Handling a link with a variable (or unknown) bandwidth</title>
    <para>
      In theory, the &sch_prio; scheduler is an ideal match for links with
      variable bandwidth, because it is a work-conserving &linux-qdisc; (which
      means that it provides no &elements-shaping;).  In the case of a link
      with an unknown or fluctuating bandwidth, the &sch_prio; scheduler
      simply prefers to dequeue any available packet in the highest priority
      band first, then falling to the lower priority queues.
    </para>
    <!--
    
         FIXME:

           it seems like a PRIO qdisc would always be dequeuing
           packets as quickly as it got them, so is really only useful
           inside a shaping class, since (in most situations), the
           hardware is ready to dequeue a packet before there is a
           backlog in the class.  Without a shaping class around this
           PRIO qdisc, I'd expect that packets would end up queuing in
           an upstream device (a modem or router).

      -->
    <para>
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="r-sharing-flows">
    <title>Sharing/splitting bandwidth based on flows</title>
    <para>
      Of the many types of contention for network bandwidth, this is one of
      the easier types of contention to address in general.  By using the
      &sch_sfq; qdisc, traffic in a particular queue can be separated into
      flows, each of which will be serviced fairly (inside that queue).
      Well-behaved applications (and users) will find that using &sch_sfq; and
      &sch_esfq; are sufficient for most sharing needs.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Achilles heel of these fair queuing algorithms is a misbehaving user
      or application which opens many connections simultaneously (e.g., eMule,
      eDonkey, Kazaa).  By creating a large number of individual flows, the
      application can dominate slots in the fair queuing algorithm.  Restated,
      the fair queuing algorithm has no idea that a single application is
      generating the majority of the flows, and cannot penalize the user.
      Other methods <!-- FIXME; link here --> are called for.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="r-sharing-ips">
    <title>Sharing/splitting bandwidth based on IP</title>
    <para>
      For many administrators this is the ideal method of dividing bandwidth
      amongst their users.  Unfortunately, there is no easy solution, and it
      becomes increasingly complex with the number of machine sharing a
      network link.
    </para>
    <para>
      To divide bandwidth equitably between <parameter>N</parameter> IP
      addresses, there must be <parameter>N</parameter> classes.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

</section>

<!-- end of file -->
