<sect1 id="ch05-introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="introduction.html" dir="chapter05"?>

<para>In the following chapters we will install all the software that belongs 
to a basic Linux system. After you're done with this and the next chapter,
you'll have a fully working Linux system. The remaining chapters deal 
with creating the boot scripts, making the LFS system bootable and
setting up basic networking.</para>

<para>The software in this chapter will be linked statically and will be 
reinstalled in the next chapter and linked dynamically. The
reason for the static version first is that there is a chance that our
normal Linux system and the LFS system aren't using the same C
Library versions. If the programs in the first part are linked against
an older C library version, those programs might not work well on the
LFS system. Another reason is to resolve circular dependencies. An
example of such a dependency is that you need a compiler to install a
compiler, and you're going to need a shell to install a shell and that
compiler.</para>

<para>The key to learning what makes Linux tick is to know exactly what packages
are used for and why a user or the system needs them. Descriptions
of the package content are provided after the Installation subsection of each
package and in Appendix A as well.</para>

<para>During the installation of various packages, you will more than likely see
all kinds of compiler warnings scrolling by on the screen. These are 
normal and can be safely ignored. They are just that, warnings (mostly 
about improper use of the C or C++ syntax, but not illegal use. It's just 
that, often, C standards changed and packages still use the old standard 
which is not a problem).</para>

<para>Before we start, make sure the LFS environment variable is setup
properly if you decided to make use of it. Run the following:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>echo $LFS</userinput></screen></para>

<para>Check to make sure the output contains the correct directory to the LFS
partition's mount point (/mnt/lfs for example).</para>

</sect1>

