<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="H">
<title>H</title>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
h2ph
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
convert .h C header files to .ph Perl header files From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
h2xs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
convert .h C header files to Perl extensions From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
H4P
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Parallel Processing Project (ICI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HA Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Motorola Computer Group&apos;s Advanced High Availability Software for Linux. Runs on Motorola platforms, naturally. A &apos;special purpose/mini&apos; distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hack
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[very common] 1. n. Originally, a quick job that produces what is needed, but not well. 2. n. An incredibly good, and perhaps very time-consuming, piece of work that produces exactly what is needed. 3. vt. To bear emotionally or physically. &quot;I can&apos;t hack this heat!&quot; 4. vt. To work on something (typically a program). In an immediate sense: &quot;What are you doing?&quot; &quot;I&apos;m hacking TECO.&quot; In a general (time-extended) sense: &quot;What do you do around here?&quot; &quot;I hack TECO.&quot; More generally, &quot;I hack `foo&apos;&quot; is roughly equivalent to &quot;`foo&apos; is my major interest (or project)&quot;. &quot;I hack solid-state physics.&quot; See Hacking X for Y. 5. vt. To pull a prank on. See sense 2 and hacker (sense 5). 6. vi. To interact with a computer in a playful and exploratory rather than goal-directed way. &quot;Whatcha up to?&quot; &quot;Oh, just hacking.&quot; 7. n. Short for hacker. 8. See nethack. 9. [MIT] v. To explore the basements, roof ledges, and steam tunnels of a large, institutional building, to the dismay of Physical Plant workers and (since this is usually performed at educational institutions) the Campus Police. This activity has been found to be eerily similar to playing adventure games such as Dungeons and Dragons and Zork. See also vadding. Constructions on this term abound. They include `happy hacking&apos; (a farewell), `how&apos;s hacking?&apos; (a friendly greeting among hackers) and `hack, hack&apos; (a fairly content-free but friendly comment, often used as a temporary farewell). For more on this totipotent term see &quot;The Meaning of Hack&quot;. See also neat hack, real hack. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hacker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A computer user who uses clever or unorthodox techniques to solve technical problems or challenges. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hacker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An individual who is interested in exploring technology, computers, and data/communication networks. The opposite of a hacker is a cracker, whose interests in technology are for malicious or destructive aims. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hacker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [originally, someone who makes furniture with an axe] 1. A person who enjoys exploring the details of programmable systems and how to stretch their capabilities, as opposed to most users, who prefer to learn only the minimum necessary. 2. One who programs enthusiastically (even obsessively) or who enjoys programming rather than just theorizing about programming. 3. A person capable of appreciating hack value. 4. A person who is good at programming quickly. 5. An expert at a particular program, or one who frequently does work using it or on it; as in `a Unix hacker&apos;. (Definitions 1 through 5 are correlated, and people who fit them congregate.) 6. An expert or enthusiast of any kind. One might be an astronomy hacker, for example. 7. One who enjoys the intellectual challenge of creatively overcoming or circumventing limitations. 8. [deprecated] A malicious meddler who tries to discover sensitive information by poking around. Hence `password hacker&apos;, `network hacker&apos;. The correct term for this sense is cracker. The term `hacker&apos; also tends to connote membership in the global community defined by the net (see the network and Internet address). For discussion of some of the basics of this culture, see the How To Become A Hacker FAQ. It also implies that the person described is seen to subscribe to some version of the hacker ethic (see hacker ethic). It is better to be described as a hacker by others than to describe oneself that way. Hackers consider themselves something of an elite (a meritocracy based on ability), though one to which new members are gladly welcome. There is thus a certain ego satisfaction to be had in identifying yourself as a hacker (but if you claim to be one and are not, you&apos;ll quickly be labeled bogus). See also wannabee. This term seems to have been first adopted as a badge in the 1960s by the hacker culture surrounding TMRC and the MIT AI Lab. We have a report that it was used in a sense close to this entry&apos;s by teenage radio hams and electronics tinkerers in the mid-1950s.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hacker (hacking)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A hacker is someone who is able to manipulate the inner workings of computers, information, and technology. Consider Arthur C. Clark&apos;s Third Law: &quot;Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic&quot;. Since normal people have no clue as to how computers work, they often view hackers with suspicion and awe (as magicians, sorcerers, witches, and warlocks). This suspicion leads to the word &quot;hacker&quot; having the connotation of someone up to no good. History: The word &quot;hacker&quot; started out in the 14th century to mean somebody who was inexperienced or unskilled at a particular activity (such as a golf hacker). In the 1970s, the word &quot;hacker&quot; was used by computer enthusiasts to refer to themselves. This reflected the way enthusiasts approach computers: they eschew formal education and play around with the computer until they can get it to work. (In much the same way, a golf hacker keeps hacking at the golf ball until they get it in the hole). Furthermore, as &quot;experts&quot; learn about the technology, the more they realize how much they don&apos;t know (especially about the implications of technology). When experts refer to themselves as &quot;hackers&quot;, they are making a Socratic statement that they truly know nothing. For more information on this connotation, see ESR&apos;s computer enthusiast &quot;Jargon File&quot;. Key point: Today if you do a quick search of &quot;hacker&quot; in a search engine, you will still occasional uses of the word in senses used in the 1400s and 1970s, but the overwhelming usage in the 1990s describes people who break into computers using their sorcerous ways. Likewise, the vast majority of websites with the word &quot;hack&quot; in their title refer to illegitimate entry into computer systems, with notable exceptions like http://www.hacker.com/ (for golf). Controversy: The computer-enthusiast community does not like using &quot;hacker&quot; to describe malicious people; they prefer &quot;cracker&quot;. The security-community restricts the use of the word &quot;cracker&quot; to some who breaks encryption and copy-protection schemes. Consequently, a journalist who writes about cybercriminals cannot use either word without hate mail from the opposing community claiming they are using the word incorrectly. If a journalists writes about hackers breaking into computers, they will receive hate-mail claiming that not all hackers are malicious, and the that the correct word is &quot;cracker&quot;. Likewise, if they write about crackers breaking into computers, they will receive hate-mail claiming that crackers only break codes, but its hackers who break into systems. The best choice probably depends upon the audience; for example one should definitely talk about malicious crackers in a computer-enthusiast magazine like Linux Today. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hacker ethic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. The belief that information-sharing is a powerful positive good, and that it is an ethical duty of hackers to share their expertise by writing open-source and facilitating access to information and to computing resources wherever possible. 2. The belief that system-cracking for fun and exploration is ethically OK as long as the cracker commits no theft, vandalism, or breach of confidentiality. Both of these normative ethical principles are widely, but by no means universally, accepted among hackers. Most hackers subscribe to the hacker ethic in sense 1, and many act on it by writing and giving away open-source software. A few go further and assert that all information should be free and any proprietary control of it is bad; this is the philosophy behind the GNU project. Sense 2 is more controversial: some people consider the act of cracking itself to be unethical, like breaking and entering. But the belief that `ethical&apos; cracking excludes destruction at least moderates the behavior of people who see themselves as `benign&apos; crackers (see also samurai). On this view, it may be one of the highest forms of hackerly courtesy to (a) break into a system, and then (b) explain to the sysop, preferably by email from a superuser account, exactly how it was done and how the hole can be plugged -- acting as an unpaid (and unsolicited) tiger team. The most reliable manifestation of either version of the hacker ethic is that almost all hackers are actively willing to share technical tricks, software, and (where possible) computing resources with other hackers. Huge cooperative networks such as Usenet, FidoNet and Internet (see Internet address) can function without central control because of this trait; they both rely on and reinforce a sense of community that may be hackerdom&apos;s most valuable intangible asset.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HACL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Access Class Library (HOD, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HACMP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Availability Clustered Multi Processing (IBM, RS/6000, Bull), &quot;HA/CMP&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hard Array Logic From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Abstraction Layer (Windows NT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heuristically programmed ALgorithmic computer (2001) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hal91
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HAL91 -- minimalistic Linux distribution that fits on one floppy disk. The website is available in English, German and Italian. A small disk distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Half-duplex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An asynchrous communications protocol in which communications channel can handle only one signal at a time. The two stations alternate their tranmissions. Sysnonyous with local echo. See communications protocol, echoplex, and full duplex. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hall, Jon &quot;Maddog&quot;
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jon is famous for his vocal attendance of important Linux events. He is executive director of Linux International, formerly of DEC (Compaq). From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Halloween Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Halloween Linux is a German localized version of Red Hat.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HALPC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Houston Area League of PC-Users, &quot;HAL-PC&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
halt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
stop the system. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
halt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
To stop all running processes on a system cleanly. Once the system is halted, you may need to manually turn off your system to complete a system power off. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hamfax
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Receive/send radio facsimile transmissions with Soundcard/PTC-II With this package you can send or receive radio facsimile transmissions using either a Linux-supported soundcard or an SCS PTC-II data controller. Radio facsimile transmission are used most commonly by meteorological bureaus to provide weather maps to aircraft and shipping. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAMPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host AUTODIN Message Processing System (AUTODIN, mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hamsoft
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Reader for new hamradio linux software at radio.linux.org.au. Hamsoft is a reader for new hamradio linux software at radio.linux.org.au, the linux hamradio software database. When you select an entry in the list and click on read, the link will be opened in a mozilla window. Mozilla has to be running. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAND
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Have A Nice Day (slang, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Handler
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A driver, utility program, or subroutine that takes care of a task. The A20 handler, for example, is a routine that controls access to extended memory. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HANFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Highly Available Network File System From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hang
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A situation where a computer system has ceased interactivity due to resource limitation or software/hardware failure. A hung system usually requires user intervention such as stopping offending processes or physical system reboot. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hang
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
v. 1. [very common] To wait for an event that will never occur. &quot;The system is hanging because it can&apos;t read from the crashed drive&quot;. See wedged, hung. 2. To wait for some event to occur; to hang around until something happens. &quot;The program displays a menu and then hangs until you type a character.&quot; Compare block. 3. To attach a peripheral device, esp. in the construction `hang off&apos;: &quot;We&apos;re going to hang another tape drive off the file server.&quot; Implies a device attached with cables, rather than something that is strictly inside the machine&apos;s chassis.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hanterm-classic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Another X terminal emulator with Hangul support Hanterm is a replacement for xterm that supports Hangul input and output; It is a modified of the xterm program from XFree86.  Hanterm uses it own native input system and does not require an X input method server. This package contains `original hanterm&apos; made by Jake Song, and hanterm package contains hanterm-xf made by ChiDeok Hwang. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hanterm-xf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X terminal emulator with Hangul support Hanterm is a replacement for xterm that supports Hangul input and output; It is a modified of the xterm program from XFree86.  Hanterm uses it own native input system and does not require an X input method server. For hanterm to work properly, a Hangul-encoded font must be available; xfonts-bakemuk are all appropriate for this purpose. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hanzim
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Chinese character learning aid Hanzim is a program designed to help you memorize characters by helping you internalize their various systematicities.  It displays lists of characters with the same radicals, same remaining parts, and same pronunciations.  Along with the characters it displays pinyin pronunciations and lists of compounds. The program is also useful simply as a convenient dictionary.  You can look up characters and compounds by radical or pinyin. More information available at:         http://zakros.ucsd.edu/~arobert/hanzim.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Access Protocol (RFC 907/1221) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
happy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Parser generator for Haskell. This is the nth public release of our parser generator system for Haskell, called Happy (a dyslexic acronym for &apos;A Yacc-like Haskell Parser generator&apos;). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Happy Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Chinese Linux distribution.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hard boot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A boot initiated by hardware. This could be a computer power-up, a press of its reset button, or even a hardware glitch. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hard drive
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Shorthand for hard disk drive, a hard drive is a device that stores, retrieves, and executes computer data and software. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hard link
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
One of several directory entries which refer to the same Unix file. A hard link is created with the &quot;ln&quot; (link) command. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hard Links
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
UNIX allows the data of a file to have more than one name in separate places in the same file system. Such a file with more than one name for the same data is called a hard-linked file and is similar to a symbolic link. Try touch mydata; ln mydata mydataB; ls -al. The files mydata and mydataB are indistinguishable. They share the same data, and have a 2 in second column of the ls -al listing. This means that they are hard-linked twice (that there are two names for this file).  The reason why hard links are sometimes used in preference to symbolic links is that some programs are not fooled by a symbolic link: If you have, say, a script that uses cp to copy a file, it will copy the symbolic link instead of the file it points to. [ cp actually has an option to override this behavior.] A hard link, however, will always be seen as a real file. On the other hand, hard links cannot be made between files on different file systems nor can they be made between directories. From Rute-Users-Guide
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hard-link
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A directory entry, which maps a filename to an inode, number. A file may have multiple names or hard links. The link count gives the number of names by which a file is accessible. Hard links do not allow multiple names for directories and do not allow multiple names in different filesystems. From Linux Administrator&apos;s Guide
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hard-wired
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A processing function built in to the computer&apos;s electronic circuits instead of facilitated by program instructions. To improve computer performance, computer designers include circuits that perform specific functions, such as multiplication or division, at higher speeds. These functions are hard-wired. The term hard-wried also refers to the prorgam instructions contained in the computer&apos;s read-only memory (ROM) or firmware. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hardcoded
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
adj. 1. [common] Said of data inserted directly into a program, where it cannot be easily modified, as opposed to data in some profile, resource (see de-rezz sense 2), or environment variable that a user or hacker can easily modify. 2. In C, this is esp. applied to use of a literal instead of a #define macro (see magic number).  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
harddrake
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The harddrake service is a hardware probing tool run at system boot time to determine what hardware has been added or removed from the system.It then offer to run needed config tool to update the OS configuration. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
harddrake-ui
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This is the main configuration tool for hardware that calls all the other configuration tools. It offers a nice GUI that show the hardware configuration splitted by hardware classes. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
harden
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Makes your system hardened. This package is intended to help the administrator to improve the security of the system, or at least make the host less susceptible. NOTE! This package will not make your system uncrackable, and it is not intended to do so. Making your system secure involves a LOT more than just installing a package. You are recommended to read at least some documents in addition to installing this package. The documents can be found in the harden-doc package. This is of course just a start because there are LOT of information on how to make your system more secure. For more information on how to secure your system see: http://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/securing-debian-howto/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
harden
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The word &quot;harden&quot; implies putting a shell around a computer in order to protect it from intruders. In order to harden a system, you should consider the following techniques: Patch the OS with the latest security fixes. For example, when the &quot;ping-of-death&quot; DoS attack came out, many people needed to patch their TCP/IP stacks to defend against it. Patch the exposed services with the latest security fixes. For example, many third-party mail servers have been vulnerable to buffer overflow exploits. These are normally fixed a few weeks after being published in the hacker community. Therefore, you need to regularly check with the software vendor for the latest patch. Remove all defaults. In order to make their software easy-to-use, vendors include default accounts, default passwords, and samples. However, these can generally be exploited by hackers. You MUST read security guidelines for the particular OS or software package (especially web-server) and carefully remove these defaults/samples, or your box WILL be hacked. For example, most Microsoft IIS 4 web-servers can be compromised with either the .htr buffer overflow or RDO exploits, because webmasters forget (or don&apos;t know) to turn them off. Remove all unnecessary services. For example, most Sun Solaris based systems can be hacked through the RPC services. Install packet filtering software. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
harden-3rdflaws
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Avoid packages with security problems. Harden-3rdflaws is intended to help the administrator to avoid packages that are known to give 3rd parties (like connected web browsers or similar) problems in form of insecure code. If you want to avoid packages that remote users can use to compromise the system you should look at the harden-remoteflaws instead. If you want to avoid packages that local users can use to compromise the system you should look at the harden-localflaws instead. NOTE! This package will not make the 3rd party host uncrackable, and it is not inteded to do so. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
harden-environment
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardened system environment. Harden-environment provides a hardened system environment, or at least helps the administrator to configure such an environment. Right now this include packages for local intrusion detection. NOTE! This package will not make your system uncrackable, and it is not intended to do so. Making your system secure involves a LOT more than just installing a package. For more information on how to secure your system see: http://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/securing-debian-howto/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hardware compatibility
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The condition wherein a computer component or peripheral is capable of functioning with software or operating systems. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hardware error control
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Encoding an error-control protocol such as MNP4 or V.42, in the modem rather than in a comunications program. Hardware error control frees the central procssing unit (CPU) from the responsisbility of catching and correcting erros. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hardware reset
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Restarting the system by pushing the computeer&apos;s reset button or programmer&apos;s switch. A hardware reset might be necessary after a system crash so severe that you can&apos;t use the keyboard restart commnd (Ctrl+Alt+Del) to restart the computer. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hardwired
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
adj. 1. In software, syn. for hardcoded. 2. By extension, anything that is not modifiable, especially in the sense of customizable to one&apos;s particular needs or tastes.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Harrison, Geoff &quot;Mandrake&quot;
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a senior software engineer for VA Research. He&apos;s most commonly known as Mandrake, author of the mandrake.net &quot;Current News&quot; diary and the major contributor to the Enlightenment window manager. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Availability Subsystem (Bull) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hasciicam
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
ascii for the masses Hasciicam makes it possible to have live ASCII video on the web. It captures video from a tv card and renders it into ascii, formatting the output into an html page with a refresh tag or in a live ASCII window or in a simple text file as well, giving the possibility to anybody that has a bttv card. a linux box and a cheap modem line to show a live ASCII video feed that can be browsable without any need for plugin, java etc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hash (one-way hash, message digest, cryptographic checksum)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A crytographic operation where an entire message is run through some mathematical operations resulting in a fixed-length (e.g. 128-bit) string that is probably unique. This &quot;hash&quot; has two important properties: It is &quot;one-way&quot;; given a hash, somebody cannot figure out what input message generated the output hash. It is unique; there is more chance of an asteroid hitting the earth and wiping out all life than two messages accidentally hashing to the same value. No two messages should produce the same Example: Some common uses of hashes are: Creating an encryption key from a text password. Creating a unique &quot;fingerprint&quot; of a message that is then encrypted with a private key in order to sign a message. Create unique fingerprints of files in order to detect when they have changed. Example: The program &quot;tripwire&quot; detects intrusions by calculating a hash of all programs/binaries. On a regular basis, it recalculates the hash. If a file has changed, then the hash will also have changed. Tripwire then &quot;trips&quot; whenever the latest calculated hash of the file does not match the one stored in its database. Example: Some common hash algorithms are: SHA-1 If you need to choose a hash algorithm, this is probably the best one to choose (unless speed is the paramount concern). Of the most popular hash algorithms, this is currently (year 2001) considered to be the most secure. MD5 In the year 2001, more data is probably being hashed by MD5 than any other algorithm. However, a lot of people recommend moving to SHA-1 because of weaknesses discovered in MD5. RIPEMD MD4 A historically significant hash algorithm, but useless by today&apos;s standards. See also: integrity From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hashed Address Table From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hatman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Customizable high-resolution Pacman clone You have three lives, and you lose a life if you get eaten by a ghost. If you eat all the little dots on a level, you go onto the next level (if we&apos;ve bothered including any). At the edge of the screen there may be passageways apparently going nowhere - if you follow one you will wrap all the way around and appear at the other side of the screen, yes - really, as if by magic you have been transported from one side of the screen to the other, and the ghosts won&apos;t know what&apos;s hit &apos;em. Also, every now and then some fruit might appear at the edge of the screen. Being a healthy-eating sort of guy, hatman loves fruit, so you should go and eat it - it&apos;s extra points, you know. But the icing on the cake is the power-pellets. Eat one of these and the tables are turned. The ghosts turn gray (as one does, when one is scared) and now it&apos;s your turn to do some serious getting. Whilst the ghosts remain gray you can eat them - getting more points for each one you eat, once you eat them their eyes (hatman doesn&apos;t like the eyes - they give him indigestion) run back to the ghost&apos;s base and gets a new body. Don&apos;t worry about them turning back too suddenly - you will get a bit of a warning first. It&apos;s easy, and it&apos;s great fun. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HAVI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Home Audio Video Interoperability (org., Grundig, Hitachi, Matsushita, Philips, Sharp, Sony, Thomson, Toshiba) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Haydar Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This distribution will be available in Arabic, Dutch and English with more languages to follow. The Arabic support appears to be very comprehensive. The first beta release of Haydar was announced May 4, 2002. Beta 2 was released November 4, 2002.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hayes command set
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A standardised set of instructions used to control modems. Common Hayes commands include the following: AT (Attention, used to start all other commmands), ATDT (Attention, dial in tone mode), ATDP (Attention, dial in pulse mode), +++ (Enter the commnad mode during the commnication seesion), ATH (Attention, hangup). From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hayes compatible modem
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A modem that reconises the Hayes command set. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HBA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Bus Adapter (SCSI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HBCI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HomeBanking Computer Interface Internet, banking, Germany, HBCI From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HBT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hetero Bipolar Transistor (IBM, IC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Human Computer Interaction (BCS, conference) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Compatibility List (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Control Links From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCSDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Capacity Satellite Digital Service From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Capacity Storage System (Novell, Netware) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hamburger ComputerTage (fair) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High-speed CMOS [logic] with TTT-compatible [logic] levels (IC, MOS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HCTDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High-Capacity Terrestrial Digital Service From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Density From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Direct Access Method (DAM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hdate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Prints Hijra (Islamic lunar) dates, calendar, Islamic prayer times Generates Hijra date(s) and Hijra calendar for given AD date and computes daily, monthly, yearly Islamic prayer times for given location. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HoneyDanBer [standard] (Unix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDB3
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Density Bipolar 3 From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDBMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical DataBase Management System (DBMS, DB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hard Disk Controller From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDCD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Density Compact Disk (CD, Sony, Phillips) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hard Disk Drive (HDD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Highly Doped Drain (IC, MOSFET) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Data Format (NCSA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HDLC Distant Host From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HOOPS Device Interface (VAGI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDIT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Bandwidth Differential Interconnect Technology [bus] (VIA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Description Language (ASIC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDLC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High-level Data Link Control (ISO) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Device Module (I2O) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Handheld Device Markup Language (mobile-systems, HDTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hochgeschwindigkeits-DatenNetz From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heath Disk Operating System (OS, Heath) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hdparm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hdparm is a useful system utility for setting (E)IDE hard drive parameters. For example, hdparm can be used to tweak hard drive performance and to spin down hard drives for power conservation. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hdparm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tune hard disk parameters for high performance. get/set hard disk parameters for Linux IDE drives. Primary use is for enabling irq-unmasking and IDE multiplemode. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High availability Data Replication (Informix, DB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Dynamic Range From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDSL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High data / bit rate Digital Subscriber Line (BELLCORE, AT&amp;T, DSL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDSL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High-level Data Specification Language From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDTP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Handheld Device Transport Protocol (mobile-systems) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HDX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Half DupleX From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HoehenEinheit [1HE = 19&quot;] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hyundai Electronics of America (manufacturer) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
head
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
output the first part of files From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
head
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The mechanism that reads data from or writes data to a magnetic disk or tape. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Header
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Repeated text such as a page number and a short version of a document&apos;s title, that appears at the top of the pages in a document. Also the beginning of a Usenet of email message. The header contains important information about the sender&apos;s address the subject of the message, and other information. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heartbeat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. The signal emitted by a Level 2 Ethernet transceiver at the end of every packet to show that the collision-detection circuit is still connected. 2. A periodic synchronization signal used by software or hardware, such as a bus clock or a periodic interrupt. 3. The `natural&apos; oscillation frequency of a computer&apos;s clock crystal, before frequency division down to the machine&apos;s clock rate. 4. A signal emitted at regular intervals by software to demonstrate that it is still alive. Sometimes hardware is designed to reboot the machine if it stops hearing a heartbeat. See also breath-of-life packet. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heartbeat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Subsystem for High-Availability Linux heartbeat is a basic heartbeat subsystem for Linux-HA. It will run scripts at initialisation, and when machines go up or down. This version will also perform IP address takeover using gratuitous ARPs. It works correctly for a 2-node configuration, and is extensible to larger configurations. It implements the following kinds of heartbeats:   * Bidirectional Serial Rings (&quot;raw&quot; serial ports)   * UDP/IP broadcast (ethernet, etc) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Header Error Check From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Header Error Control (ATM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HECTOR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HEterogeneous Computer TOgetheR (IBM, Uni Karlsruhe, Germany) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heimdal
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heimdal is a free implementation of Kerberos 5, that aims to be compatible with MIT Kerberos. This package includes servers like telnetd and ftpd that have been compiled with Heimdal support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heimdal-kdc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDC for Heimdal Kerberos Heimdal is a free implementation of Kerberos 5, that aims to be compatible with MIT Kerberos. This package includes the KDC (key distribution centre) server, which is designed to run on a secure computer and keeps track of users passwords. This is done using the Kerberos protocol in such a way that the server computers do not need to know user&apos;s passwords. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heise-register
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
register of the magazines c&apos;t, iX, Elrad and Gateway This package installs an online register of the famous German computer and electronic magazines published by Heise:    * c&apos;t - magazin f|r computer technik  (12/1983 - 20/2001)    * iX  (11/1988 - 10/2001)    * Elrad  (1994 - 1997)    * Gateway  (1/1993 - 6/1997) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Emulation Layer From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Header Extension Length From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hello
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The classic greeting, and a good example The GNU hello program produces a familiar, friendly greeting.  It allows nonprogrammers to use a classic computer science tool which would otherwise be unavailable to them. Seriously, though: this is an example of how to do a Debian package. It is the Debian version of the GNU Project&apos;s `hello world&apos; program (which is itself an example for the GNU Project). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
help2man
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Automatic manpage generator Program to create simple man pages from the --help and --version output of other programs. Since most GNU documentation is now in info format, this provides a way to generate a placeholder man page pointing to that resource while still providing some useful information. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEMT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Electron Mobility Transistor From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HEPNET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Energy Physics NETwork (network) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
herbix
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Herbix is a Linux server that fits on a floppy. It supports ipchains and can serve FTP, HTTP, IRC, DHCP, SMTP, and IDENT. Version 1.0-25 was released April 1, 2002. Version 1.0-67 was released January 4, 2003. A floppy-based distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hercules
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
System/370, ESA/390 and z/Architecture Emulator Hercules is an open source software implementation of the mainframe System/370 and ESA/390 architectures, in addition to the new 64-bit z/Architecture. This means that your PC can emulate an IBM mainframe processor. The mainframe can range from a 360 to a z900 - running in &quot;System/370&quot; mode, &quot;ESA/390&quot; mode, or &quot;z/Architecture&quot; mode. Hercules executes S/370, ESA/390, and z/Architecture instructions and channel programs. It emulates mainframe I/O devices by using PC devices. For example, 3390 DASD devices are emulated by large files on your hard disk, and local 3270 screens are emulated by tn3270 sessions. Hercules implements only the raw S/370, ESA/390, and z/Architecture instruction set; it does not provide any operating system facilities. This means that you need to provide an operating system or standalone program which Hercules can load from an emulated disk or tape device. You will have to use a free software operating system such as Linux, write the operating system or standalone program yourself, obtain a license from IBM to run one of their operating systems on your PC, or use IBM programs and operating systems which have been placed in the public domain. Virtual networking can be accomplished using the TUN/TAP driver in 2.2 and 2.4 kernels.  For older kernels, try the vmnet package. Hercules was created by Roger Bowler and is maintained by Jay Maynard. Jan Jaeger designed and implemented many of the advanced features of Hercules. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HERMES
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heuristic Emergency Response Management Expert System (XPS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hermes1
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Hermes pixel-format library Hermes is a library that does the dirty work of a graphics library or application that nobody else wants to do, and it does it fast because the effort is concentrated on just that. The thing nobody wants to do is conversion between pixel formats - between all pixel formats that is, not between any two. There are handwritten assembler routines in Hermes that should make anything look fast. An application or library that uses Hermes will for example be able to render into one buffer and convert it to whatever pixel format is available on the target platform at the time. Other services provided by Hermes include palette handling including caching of lookup tables, and surface clearing to a specific colour value. See http://www.clanlib.org/ for more info From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HERODE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Handling the Electronic Representation of mixed text - image Office Documents based on ECMA standard 101 (ESPRIT, SNI, TITN, ECMA, ODA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heroes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Collect powerups and avoid your opponents&apos; trails Heroes is similar to the &quot;Tron&quot; and &quot;Nibbles&quot; games of yore, but includes many graphical improvements and new game features.  In it, you must maneuver a small vehicle around a world and collect powerups while avoiding obstacles, your opponents&apos; trails, and even your own trail. Several styles of play are available, including &quot;get-all-the-bonuses&quot;, deathmatch, and &quot;squish-the-pedestrians&quot;.  All game styles can be played in both single-player and two-player (split-screen) modes. You should install the heroes-sound-effects package if you want sound effects, and the heroes-sound-tracks package if you want background music in the game. These packages are quite large (especially heroes-sound-tracks), so you might want to try the game out before installing them. This package contains a small number of common files for the GGI and SDL versions of heroes. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HES
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Home Electronic System (SNI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HES
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Honeywell Executive System (OS, Honeywell 800) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hesiod
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hesiod is a system which uses existing DNS functionality to provide access to databases of information that changes infrequently. It is often used to distribute information kept in the /etc/passwd, /etc/group, and /etc/printcapfiles, among others. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hesiod
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Name service for network authentication and access. Replaces local authentication files such as /etc/passwd and /etc/group. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hesiod
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Utilities for Project Athena&apos;s service name resolution protocol Hesiod is a name service library that can provide general name service for a variety of applications.  It is derived from BIND, the Berkeley Internet Name Daemon, and leverages the existing DNS infrastructure of a network.  It is used on a number of university networks, including MIT and Iowa State University. If you will not be using this system on a network that already uses Hesiod, you probably do not need this package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hevea
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A fast and powerful LaTeX to HTML translator HeVeA is a LaTeX to HTML translator. Its remarkable features are  - It produces good output. By default (can be turned off) it uses the    symbol face for math symbols. Either way it usually avoids generating    zillions of picture files.  - It is highly configurable through (La)TeX macros. Though aimed at    LaTeX input it understands a fair subset of TeX&apos; macro language.  - It runs fast. This version of HeVeA is patched to generate by default PNG picture files instead of GIF. See also http://para.inria.fr/~maranget/hevea/index.html. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
hexadecimal dumping tool for Japanese hexdump program that distinguish Japanese 2bytes code character. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hex (hexadecimal)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In computer science, the word hexadecimal means base-16 numbers. These are numbers that use digits in the range: 0123456789ABCDEF. In the C programming language (as well as Java, JavaScript, C++, and other places), hexadecimal numbers are prefixed by a 0x. In this manner, one can tell that the number 0x80 is equivalent to 128 decimal, not 80 decimal. Key point: Hex is so important because 4-bits have 16-possible combinations. Therefore, a 4-bit value can be represented by a single hex digit. In this manner, every byte (8-bits) can be represented by two hex digits. Key point: Script kiddies tend to dismiss hexadecimal as one of those &quot;unnecessary details&quot;. In reality, you must be able to comfortably do hex math in your head, and freely convert with binary. You should also be able to interpret hexdumps, where a block of data is dumped out into columns of hex numbers. A tutorial for this is at http://www.robertgraham.com/pubs/sniffing-faq.html#hexadecimal. Key point: My mother, an otherwise avowed computerphobe, calculates her age in hex. She is in her early 0x30s. (For those who cannot do the math as well as my mom, 0x30 == 3*16 == 48). From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hexadecimal
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. Base 16. Coined in the early 1960s to replace earlier `sexadecimal&apos;, which was too racy and amusing for stuffy IBM, and later adopted by the rest of the industry. Actually, neither term is etymologically pure. If we take `binary&apos; to be paradigmatic, the most etymologically correct term for base 10, for example, is `denary&apos;, which comes from `deni&apos; (ten at a time, ten each), a Latin `distributive&apos; number; the corresponding term for base-16 would be something like `sendenary&apos;. &quot;Decimal&quot; comes from the combining root of `decem&apos;, Latin for 10. If wish to create a truly analogous word for base 16, we should start with `sedecim&apos;, Latin for 16. Ergo, `sedecimal&apos; is the word that would have been created by a Latin scholar. The `sexa-&apos; prefix is Latin but incorrect in this context, and `hexa-&apos; is Greek. The word `octal&apos; is similarly incorrect; a correct form would be `octaval&apos; (to go with decimal), or `octonary&apos; (to go with binary). If anyone ever implements a base-3 computer, computer scientists will be faced with the unprecedented dilemma of a choice between two correct forms; both `ternary&apos; and `trinary&apos; have a claim to this throne.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hexcurse
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A ncurses-based hex editor with many features HexCurse is a versatile ncurses-based hex editor written in C that provides the user with many features. It currently supports searching, hex, and decimal address output, jumping  to specified locations in a file, and quick keyboard shortcuts to commands. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hexdump
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
ASCII, decimal, hexadecimal, octal dump From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hexedit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
view and edit files in hexadecimal or in ASCII. hexedit shows a file both in ASCII and in hexadecimal. The file can be a device as the file is not whole read. You can modify the file and search through it. You have also copy&amp;paste and save to file functions. Truncating or appending to the file. Modifications are shown in bold. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hextype
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hexdump according to DOS Debug output format The output consists of 3 columns. Each row contains up to 16 characters.  The first column contains the address of the row (in 16-byte words).  In the second column each byte is represented by its hexadecimal value (00 to FF), and in the third are the bytes as printable characters. Unlike od -c, hextype does not print unprintable chars with a two-character escape sequence.  They are replaced by a dot. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hexxagon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hexagonal Ataxx clone for GTK The goal of the game is to conquer as much of the board as possible. This is done by capturing the opponent&apos;s pieces or by cloning your own. The board is a hexagon built from smaller hexagons. Hexxagon is just like Ataxx apart from the board design. The Ataxx board is square and the Hexxagon board is hexagonal. This is the GTK xivVersion From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
heyu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
heyu - 2 way x10 communications for the CM11A heyu&apos; is similar to the package &apos;x10&apos;, differing mainly in the controller supported (this package supports CM11A, &apos;x10&apos; supports the CP290) X-10 modules are devices that plug into an electrical outlet and allow you to remotely control the power to a lamp or an appliance that is plugged into them. There are also X-10 modules that install in place of wall switches to control lights, fans, and many other appliances. This package supports the CM11A Interface (from Radio Shack), which supports two-way communication.  This allows for devices such as motion detectors to trigger scripts on your system, turning lights on, updating web pages, or send you e-mail. See: http://heyu.tanj.com/  For more information From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Have Fun (slang, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HFC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hybrid Fiber Coax [network] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HFD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hauptanschluss fuer Direktruf / Datenleitung (Telekom), &quot;HfD&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HFDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Highly Functional Distributed System (MTRON) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierachical File System (Apple, CD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hfsplus
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
tools to access HFS+ formatted volumes HFS+ is a modernized version of Apple Computer&apos;s HFS Filesystem. Nowadays, it is widely used with more recent versions of MacOS. Unfortunately, it is not yet supported by the Linux kernel.  hfsplus consists of a library and set of tools that allow access to HFS+ volumes. This package contains the tools themselves. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hfsutils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tools for reading and writing Macintosh volumes. HFS is the native Macintosh filesystem format. This package contains several command-line utilities for reading and writing Macintosh HFS-formatted media such as floppy disks, CD-ROMs, and hard disks. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HFT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Function Terminal (AIX, IBM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HGA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hercules Graphics Adapter From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HGC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hercules Graphics Card From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HHI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heinrich Hertz Institut Org., Germany From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hochschulverband Informationswissenschaften (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Human Interaction Component From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hybrid Integrated Circuit From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HID
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Human Interface Device (MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIDAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Indexed Direct Access Method (DAM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hidden file
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A file with a name that begins with a period (.) on UNIX and Linux systems. They are called hidden because they are not shown by default during a directory listing or in a file manager. For example, user configuration files are often hidden to prevent accidental deletion or modification. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hidden flag
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [scientific computation] An extra option added to a routine without changing the calling sequence. For example, instead of adding an explicit input variable to instruct a routine to give extra diagnostic output, the programmer might just add a test for some otherwise meaningless feature of the existing inputs, such as a negative mass. The use of hidden flags can make a program very hard to debug and understand, but is all too common wherever programs are hacked on in a hurry. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIFD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HIgh capacity Floppy Disk (Sony, Fuji), &quot;HiFD&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIFI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hypertext Interface For Information (ESPRIT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIFIVE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HIgh Fidelity Interactive Visual Environment (DEC), &quot;Hi-FIVE&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIFT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Implemented Fault Tolerance (SIFT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIGGENS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Human Interface Graphical GENeration System (Uni Colorado) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
high bit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [from `high-order bit&apos;] 1. The most significant bit in a byte. 2. [common] By extension, the most significant part of something other than a data byte: &quot;Spare me the whole saga, just give me the high bit.&quot; See also meta bit, hobbit, dread high-bit disease, and compare the mainstream slang `bottom line&apos;. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
High Siera
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An obsolete standard for encoding data onto CD-ROMs. Although similar to High Sierra, the widely used ISO 9660 standard is incompatible. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
high-level language
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
computer language that can be used on many different computer systems. By contrast, a low-level language refers to specific hardware locations and is inseparable from a specific hardware architecture. Another name for low-level language is assembly language. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hindent
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Reformats HTML code This utility reformats HTML code to be properly indented/nested for improved readability.  You can indent the existing lines as-is, or totally reformat the code to have one tag per line.  Hindent is useful in deciphering software-generated HTML code when it&apos;s all just one huge line, or help you find find that last missing end-tag, or deal with code victimized by creeping featurism. Written in Perl for Unix.  Understands all HTML 3.2 nestable tags. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HINT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical INTegration [benchmark] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIPERLAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HIgh PErformance Radio Local Area Network (LAN, ETSI, EN 300 652) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIPPI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HIgh Performance Parallel Interface From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIPPI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Peripheral Interface From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HIRD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HURD of Interface Representing Depth (GNU, HURD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HISAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Indexed Sequential Acess Method (SAM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HISP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HIgh SPeed channel connector (Cray, I/O) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HispaFuentes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HispaFuentes is a Red Hat compatible distribution. Version 8.0 contains Ximian 1.4, KDE 2.1, CUPS and much more. Spanish distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
histchars
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The two or three characters which control history expansion and tokenization (see HISTORY EXPANSION below). The first character is the history expansion character, that is, the character which signals the start of a history expansion, normally `!&apos;. The second character is the quick substitution character, which is used as shorthand for re-running the previous command entered, substituting one string for another in the command. The default is `^&apos;. The optional third character is the character which signifies that the remainder of the line is a comment, when found as the first character of a word, normally `#&apos;. The history comment character causes history substitution to be skipped for the remaining words on the line. It does not necessarily cause the shell parser to treat the rest of the line as a comment. From Rute-Users-Guide
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
history
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In the C shell and the Korn shell, a list of command lines (or events) previously executed by a user. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
As used in reference to the World Wide Web, ?hit? means a single request from a web browser for a single item from a web server; thus in order for a web browser to display a page that contains 3 graphics, 4 ?hits? would occur at the server: 1 for the HTML page, and one for each of the 3 graphics. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hitop
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A high-level website description language Hitop is an HTML preprocessor and website design tool. It helps you to produce consistent, accessible, attractive, navigable and maintainable websites. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hlatex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
LaTeX Korean support HLaTeX is a LaTeX package use Hangul with LaTeX. With this package, you can run latex on KS X 1001 based Korean LaTeX file to produce a professionally looking Korean documents. You can typeset all Korean characters defined in KS X 1001, including Korean Symbol, Hangul and Hanja. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hlfl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Level Firewall Language HLFL translates your high level language firewalling rules into usable rules for ipfw, IPFilter, ipfwadm, IPChains, Netfilter, and Cisco. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hlins
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Insert URLs into html documents Hlins is a tool to insert hypertext links into HTML documents, using a database with entries of the form &quot;name = url&quot;. It is designed for inserting URLs of real persons: it knows about abbreviations of first and middle names and tolerates dropping the second part of a composite last name. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HLL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Level Language From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HLLAPI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Level Language Application Programming Interface (IBM, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HLPI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Higher Layer Protocol Identifier From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HLR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Home Location Register (LR, GSM, GPRS, mobile-systems) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HLS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hue, Luminance, Saturation (color system, DTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Memory Area From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMAC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
keyed-Hashing for Message AuthentiCation (cryptography, RFC 2104) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Highspeed Memory Controller (Apple) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Head Mounted Display (VR) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Human-Machine Interface From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hmmer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
models protein or nucleic acid sequences. Hmmer is a suite of programs which use profile hidden Markov models (profile HMMs) to model the primary structure consensus of a family of protein or nucleic acid sequences. Homepage:  http://hmmer.wustl.edu/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMMP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperMedia Management Protocol (MS, Intel, Cisco, WWW, HMMS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperMedia Management Schema (MS, Intel, Cisco, WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High performance Metal Oxide Semiconductor (IC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Monitoring Protocol (RFC 869) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HMUX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hybrid MUltipleXer (FDDI), &quot;H-MUX&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hnb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical notebook Hnb is an ncurses program to organize many kinds of data in one place, for example addresses, todo lists, ideas, book reviews or to store snippets of brainstorming, to make a structured packing list or just to take random notes. It can export ascii, html and xml, supports todo checkboxes, checkbox trees with percentages, priorities, preferences, searching and more. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HNF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heinz Nixdorf Museumsforum (org., Paderborn, Germany) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HNI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Heinz Nixdorf Institut (org., ZIT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hns2-cgi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hyper Nikki System (CGI) HNS(Hyper Nikki System, Nikki means &quot;Diary&quot; in Japanese) is a set of CGI scripts which can generate HTML-based web diary a la Slashdot/Advogato from its own very simple meta files (hnf).  HNS takes care of complicated, diary-specific operations such as date handling, URL anchor, etc. so keeping your diary with HNS is much easier than writing HTML by hand. This package provides main cgi scripts. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hns2-tools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hyper Nikki System tools for editing diary. HNS(Hyper Nikki System, Nikki means &quot;Diary&quot; in Japanese) is a set of CGI scripts which can generate HTML-based web diary a la Slashdot/Advogato from its own very simple meta files (hnf).  HNS takes care of complicated, diary-specific operations such as date handling, URL anchor, etc. so keeping your diary with HNS is much easier than writing HTML by hand. This package provides tools for editing diary.   todayhns, edit the diary of today wrapper script.   hnf-mode, major mode for emacsen to edit hnf file. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host On Demand (IBM, HOD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hodie
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
prints the date in latin hodie has the same functionality as the date (1) program, only it prints it in grammatically correct latin From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Head Of Line From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOLAP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hybrid OnLine Analytical Processing (OLAP, DB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hole
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. A region in an otherwise flat entity which is not actually present. For example, some Unix filesystems can store large files with holes so that unused regions of the file are never actually stored on disk. (In techspeak, these are referred to as `sparse&apos; files.) As another example, the region of memory in IBM PCs reserved for memory-mapped I/O devices which may not actually be present is called `the I/O hole&apos;, since memory-management systems must skip over this area when filling user requests for memory.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOLON Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HOLON Linux is aimed at mass consumers. It is developed by HOLON Inc. (in Japan). They did a TV commercial, which was (and is) an unprecedented promotion in Japan. Their server version received a &quot;Good Design Award&quot; by the Ministry of International Trade and Industry in Japan. Their desktop version product includes 2.8GB of commercial and multimedia applications.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Home
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A directory or WWW page that is &apos;owned&apos; by a user is often referred to as their &apos;home directory&apos; or &apos;home page&apos;. From KADOWKEV
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Home Directory
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The directory the user is placed in after logging on. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
home directory
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the directory you are placed in immediately after you log in to the system. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Home Page (or Homepage)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Several meanings. Originally, the web page that your browser is set to use when it starts up. The more common meaning refers to the main web page for a business, organization, person or simply the main page out of a collection of web pages, e.g. &quot;Check out so-and-so&apos;s new Home Page.&quot; From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Home Page or Homepage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the top level hypertext document in a collection of pages or web site. Often uses index.html as file name. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOMERF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Home Radio Frequency (WLAN), &quot;HomeRF&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hook
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A feature included in a software or hardware product to enable hobbyists and programmers to add their own custom features. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hook
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. A software or hardware feature included in order to simplify later additions or changes by a user. For example, a simple program that prints numbers might always print them in base 10, but a more flexible version would let a variable determine what base to use; setting the variable to 5 would make the program print numbers in base 5. The variable is a simple hook. An even more flexible program might examine the variable and treat a value of 16 or less as the base to use, but treat any other number as the address of a user-supplied routine for printing a number. This is a hairy but powerful hook; one can then write a routine to print numbers as Roman numerals, say, or as Hebrew characters, and plug it into the program through the hook. Often the difference between a good program and a superb one is that the latter has useful hooks in judiciously chosen places. Both may do the original job about equally well, but the one with the hooks is much more flexible for future expansion of capabilities (EMACS, for example, is all hooks). The term `user exit&apos; is synonymous but much more formal and less hackish.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hook
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The technique of inserting code into a system call in order to alter it. The typical hook works by replacing the function pointer to the call with its own, then once it is done doing its processing, it will then call the original function pointer. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOOPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Object Orientated Picture System (Ithaca, Autodesk, OOP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Homecast Open Protocol (WLAN, Alation Systems) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
horde
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Core elements for the Horde Web Application Suite A set of PHP3 scripts that implement an web based application suite. This package is required to run other programs such as IMP which is a web based IMAP client.  Other applications will follow as soon as they are functional. PLEASE NOTE, you must have either a database setup locally or remotely prior to installing this package otherwise the install could fail. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
host
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A computer system that is connected to a network and communicates with other systems. Hosts are usually assigned unique addresses or names to distinguish one host from another. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
host
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A physical or virtual device with a &quot;host&quot; internet address, like 123.2.3.4. That is, not a network address like 123.2.0.0 . Typically, the device is a network interface device like an Ethernet card or a PPP controlled serial interface. Often, a computer is connected via only one such device, and it is thus natural to speak of &quot;host&quot; and &quot;computer&quot; synonymously and it is often done. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Host
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Any computer on a network that is a repository for services available to other computers on the network. It is quite common to have one host machine provide several services, such as SMTP (email) and HTTP (web). From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
host
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
DNS lookup utility From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Host
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In the Internet, any computer that can function as the beginning and end porint of data transfers. An Internet host has a unique Internet address (called an IP address) and a unique domain name. In networks and telecommunications generaly, the coputer that performs centralised functions such as making program or data files available to other computers. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
host
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Utility for Querying DNS Servers &apos;host&apos; is a utility, similar to &apos;nslookup&apos; (deprecated) or &apos;dig&apos;, used to query DNS servers for domain names and zones. This package provides the original version of &apos;host&apos;, originally in the package &apos;dnsutils&apos;. BIND9 provides a similar utility, in &apos;bind9-host&apos;. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hostid
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
print the numeric identifier for the current host From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hostname
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A name assigned or configured to a host on a network. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hostname
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A utility to set/show the host name or domain name The hostname command can be used to either set or display the current host or domain name of the system. This name is used by many of the networking programs to identify the machine. The domain name is also used by NIS/YP. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hostname
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
show or set the system&apos;s host name From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hotkeys
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A hotkeys daemon for your Internet/multimedia keyboard in X This program sits at the back and listens for the &quot;special&quot; hotkeys that you won&apos;t normally use on your Internet/Multimedia keyboards. The buttons perform their intended behaviors, such as volume up and down, mute the speaker, launch applications, etc. It has On-screen display (OSD) to show the volume, program that&apos;s being started, etc. It features an XML-based keycode configuration file format, which makes it possible to define the hotkeys to launch any programs you want. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hotplug
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux Hotplug Scripts This package contains the scripts necessary for hotplug Linux support, and lets you plug in new devices and use them immediately. Initially, it includes support for USB and PCI (Cardbus) devices, and can automatically configure network interfaces. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hotplug
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The term &quot;hotplugging&quot; refers to the dynamic reconfiguration performed after a device has been attached to a running system. This package contains the application which is called by the kernel when a USB device is added; hotplug then loads the required modules for that device. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hotplug
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This package contains the scripts necessary for hotplug Linux support, and lets you plug in new devices and use them immediately. Initially, it includes support for USB and PCI (Cardbus) devices, and can automatically configure network interfaces. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hotplug-utils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux Hotplug utility programs This package contains some utilities for hotplug Linux support, fxload hotplug demon. This program is conveniently able to download firmware into FX and FX2 ez-usb devices. It is intended to be invoked by hotplug scripts when the unprogrammed device appears on the bus. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hover
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
To place the mouse cursor over the panel or desktop object. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HOWTO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A freely distributable document that describes in detail how to set up or configure a Linux component. It is often the best starting point for a beginner. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
howto-html-en
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux HOWTOs are detailed documents which describe a specific aspect ofconfiguring or using Linux.  Linux HOWTOs are a great source of practical information about your system.  The latest versions of these documents are located at http://www.linuxdoc.org/docs.html#howto From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
howto-utils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux HOWTOs are parts of the  Linux Documentation Project. They are detailed documents which describe a specific aspect of configuring or using Linux.  Linux HOWTOs are a great source of practical information about your system.  The latest versions of these documents are located at http://www.linuxdoc.org/docs.html#howto Currently, available tools are :- makehowtoindex is an index generator for html formatted HOWTO documents- mirror_howtos mirror howtos and mini-howtos- untar_howtos process a howto mirror (obtained by mirror_howtos) From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard (manufacturer) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hp-ppd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HP Postscript Printer Definition (PPD) files Because PostScript is a device independent page description language, there is a need to provide a mechanism for a print spooler to customize the PostScript Job to the actual device. PPD, PostScript Printer Definitions, specify the device specific PostScript commands to access device specific features. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hp2xx
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A HPGL converter into some vector- and raster formats HP2XX reads HPGL ASCII source files, interprets them, and converts them into either another vector-oriented format or one of several rasterfile formats. Currently, its HPGL parser recognizes a subset of the HP 7550A command set. Some high-level functions are missing. Also, only some of the fixed space vector fonts and none of the variable space arc fonts are supported. Beside these limitations, hp2xx has proven to work with many HP-GL sources without any trouble. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hp48cc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
C-like compiler which produces HP48 RPN `hp48cc&apos; is a C-like compiler that translates the input code into the HP48 RPN language.  The language recognized by the compiler is only a small subset of the C language, with some non-standard extensions, but powerful enough to write complex programs simply. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Architecture (HP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPBIDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard Broadband Internet Delivery System (HP, Internet), &quot;HP BIDS&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Handheld Personal Computer (PC), &quot;H/PC&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Computing From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPCC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Computing and Communication From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPCS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Communication Server (Tobit, NLM, Netware) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance FORTRAN (FORTRAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance FileSystem (OS/2) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPGL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard Graphics Language (CAD, CAM, HP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPIB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard Interface Bus (GPIB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hpijs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HP Inkjet Server - Ghostscript driver for HP inkjets This package contains the hpijs binary which provides Ghostscript with a driver for most inkjet manufactured by Hewlett Packard using the ijs interface. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hpijs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
hpijs is a collection of optimized drivers for HP printers. hpijs supports the DeskJet 350C, 600C, 600C Photo, 630C, Apollo 2000,Apollo 2100, Apollo 2560, DeskJet 800C, DeskJet 825, DeskJet 900,PhotoSmart, DeskJet 990C, and PhotoSmart 100 series. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hping2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Active Network Smashing Tool hping2 is a network tool able to send custom ICMP/UDP/TCP packets and to display target replies like ping does with ICMP replies. It handles fragmentation and arbitrary packet body and size, and can be used to transfer files under supported protocols. Using hping2, you can:         Test firewall rules,         Perform [spoofed] port scanning,         Test net performance using different protocols,         Packet size,         TOS (type of service), and         Fragmentation,         Do path MTU discovery,         Transfer files (even between really Fascist firewall rules),         Perform traceroute-like actions under different protocols,         Fingerprint remote OSs,         Audit a TCP/IP stack, etc. hping2 is a good tool for learning TCP/IP. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hyper Page Mode From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPMI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? [Schnittstelle] (CAD), &quot;HP-MI&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPNA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPOFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Optical File System (IBM, OS/2, MOD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hpoj
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HP OfficeJet Linux driver (hpoj) This software provides Linux support for most &quot;multi-function&quot; (or &quot;all-in-one&quot;) peripherals from Hewlett-Packard, including OfficeJet, LaserJet, and Printer/Scanner/Copier (&quot;PSC&quot;) products. It consists of:  - Low-level drivers and libraries to communicate with the device. Depending on  your hardware and operating system configuration, you may connect devices  directly to your workstation with a parallel port or USB (Universal Serial  Bus), or to a LAN (Local Area Network) using certain models of HP JetDirect  print servers.  - An application programming interface (API) known as &quot;PTAL&quot; (Peripheral  Transport Abstraction Library) that hides the differences in accessing  devices connected via parallel, USB, or JetDirect.  - Printing support, largely powered by ghostscript, the HP inkjet driver  (for selected models), and one of various print spoolers (Berkeley lpd,  gnulpr, LPRng, CUPS, PDQ, etc.) that may already be installed on your  computer.  - Scanning support, powered either by Scanner Access Now Easy (SANE) or  by &quot;ptal-hp scan&quot;, a command-line application provided with the hpoj package.  - Graphical and command-line applications to access various features of the  peripheral, such as displaying status of the device and setting the clock. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPPA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard Precision Architecture (HP, RISC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPPCL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard Printer Control Language From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Routing From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Priority Request (VUMA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hpscanpbm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HP ScanJet scanning utility This program controls Hewlett-Packard ScanJet series scanners. It captures the image based on command-line parameters, and provides it as a thresholded, dithered, grayscale, or full-color Portable Pixmap. This is not a device driver; your ScanJet should be connected to a SCSI adapter that is supported by Linux (which does not include the card that came with the ScanJet).  This program uses the generic SCSI interface, so this feature must be available in the kernel. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hpsockd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HP SOCKS server. Provides a SOCKS v5 server, with v4 support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPTS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Performance Transaction Systems From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPUX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard / UniX (Unix), &quot;HP/UX&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPVEE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett-Packard Visual Engineering Environment (HP, GUI), &quot;HP VEE&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HPVUE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hewlett Packard - Visual User Environment (HP, GUI), &quot;HP-VUE&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HQX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A popular program for the Macintosh used to convert binary files so they can be sent as text, similar to (but incompatible with) uuencode. From KADOWKEV
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Rate (IEEE 802.11) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HRC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hybrid Ring Control (FDDI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HRFWG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Home Radio Frequency Working Group (WLAN, HOMERF) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed (MODEM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Access From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hue Saturation Brightness (DTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Storage Controller From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HTML Sucks Completely (HTML, Amiga) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSCDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Cable Data Services From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSCSD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Circuit Switched Data (GSM, mobile-systems) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSDRAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? Random Access Memory (RAM, DRAM, IC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Sierra File System From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hsftp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
FTP emulator which uses ssh as end-to-end transport hsftp is an ftp emulator that provides the look-and-feel of an ftp session, but uses ssh to transport commands and data. No dedicated daemon (apart from sshd) is required. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Interface From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hue, Saturation, Intensity (DTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? High Speed Interface / SNA, &quot;HSI/S&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSLAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Local Area Network, &quot;HS-LAN&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSLFX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? [hardware description language] (HDL, NTT, LSI), &quot;HSL-FX&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSLN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Local Network From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hardware Specific Module (ODI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchical Storage Management From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchisches SpeicherManagement From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSMD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Mobile Data HSCSD, Germany, E-Plus From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Signal Processing (DFUe, WinModem) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[UUNet] HighSpeed Peering From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSRP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hot Standby Router Protocol (Cisco, IOS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSSDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High-Speed Switched Digital Service From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSSI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Serial Interface From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HSSN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HighSpeed Switching Network (Cray, ATM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hawaiian Standard Time [-1030] (TZ) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Soft Tech (manufacturer, ISDN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Speed Technology (US Robotics) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Horizontal Tab From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ht
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Viewer/editor/analyser (mostly) for executables This is HT, including HT-analyser; please note that this is a BETA version of the program. Therefore HT is incomplete and sometimes buggy. For more info (e.g. keybindings) see the README file! 1. Supported file formats      - common object file format (COFF)      - executable and linkable format (ELF)      - linear executables (LE)      - standard DO$ executables (MZ)      - new executables (NE)      - portable executables (PE) 2. Code &amp; Data Analyser      - finds branch sources and destinations recursively      - finds procedure entries      - creates labels based on this information      - creates xref information      - allows to interactively analyse unexplored code      - allows to create/rename/delete labels 3. Target systems      - GNU/Linux      - FreeBSD      - DJGPP      - Win32 From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htag
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A tagline adder for email, news and FidoNet messages. htag is a tagline adder but it has now been so over engineered that it will also do anything you want it to[0], do lots of stuff I want it to, and do stuff it wants to. [0] Or at least it will if you write the appropriate plugin. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htcheck
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Utility for checking web site for dead/external links ht://Check is more than a link checker.  It&apos;s a console application written for Linux systems in C++ and derived from the best search engine available on the Internet for free (GNU GPL): ht://Dig. It can retrieve information through HTTP/1.1 and store them in a MySQL database, and it&apos;s particularly suitable for small Internet domains or Intranet. Its purpose is to help a webmaster managing one or more related sites: after a &quot;crawl&quot;, ht://Check gives back very useful summaries and reports, including broken links, anchors not found, content-types and HTTP status codes summaries, etc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htdig
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The ht://Dig system is a Web search and indexing system for a small domain or intranet. This system is not meant to replace the need for powerful Internet-wide search systems; instead it is meant to cover the search needs for a single company, campus, or even a particular subsection of a website. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htdig
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WWW search system for an intranet or small internet The ht://Dig system is a complete world wide web indexing and searching system for a small domain or intranet. This system is not meant to replace the need for powerful internet-wide search systems like Lycos, Infoseek, Webcrawler and AltaVista. Instead it is meant to cover the search needs for a single company, campus, or even a particular sub section of a web site. As opposed to some WAIS-based or web-server based search engines, ht://Dig can span several web servers at a site. The type of these different web servers doesn&apos;t matter as long as they understand the HTTP 1.0 protocol. Features:    * Intranet searching    * It is free    * Robot exclusion is supported    * Boolean expression searching    * Configurable search results    * Fuzzy searching    * Searching of HTML and text files    * Keywords can be added to HTML documents    * Email notification of expired documents    * A Protected server can be indexed    * Searches on subsections of the database    * Full source code included    * The depth of the search can be limited    * Full support for the ISO-Latin-1 character set From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTDM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hybrid Time Division Multiplexing [protocol] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hyper-g Text Format (Hyper-G) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a file grabber that will get files from HTTP servers HTGET is a file grabber that will get files from HTTP servers. The aim behind this program is to create a downloader that you can leave running in the background - one that&apos;s totally reliable and can cope with just about any problem, and won&apos;t stop downloading unless it&apos;s forced to. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hope This Helps (slang) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperText Markup Language (Internet, WWW, SGML, RFC 1866/1942, HTML) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
See hypertext markup language (HTML). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTML (Hypertext Markup Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A set of conventions for marking the portions of a document so that, when accessed by a program called a parser, each portion appears with a distinctive format. HTML is the markup language behind the appearance of documents on the WWW (World Wide Web), and the parser programs for accessing thes documents are called Webbrowsers. A subset of the SGML (Standard Generalised Markup Language), HTML includes capabilities that enable authors to insert hyperlinks, which when clicked display another HTML document. The process of composing HTML text is called authoring. You can author HTML text by editing a plain-text document with a stand alone HTML editor, such as HTML assistant. In adddition, add-on programs are available that provide HTML editing capaibilities such as Bluefish. Unlike a word processing program&apos;s formatting codes, HTML codes - called tags - do not specify just how the tagged text is a certain portion of a document, such as a title, heading, or body text. The parser decides how to format the text. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
html2ps
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HTML to PostScript converter This program converts HTML directly to PostScript.  The HTML code can be retrieved from one or more URLs or local files, specified as parameters on the command line.  A comprehensive level of HTML is supported, including inline images, CSS1, and some features of HTML 4.0. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
html2text
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An advanced HTML to text converter. html2text was written because the author wasn&apos;t happy with the output of &quot;lynx -dump&quot; and so he wrote something better. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
html2wml
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
converts HTML pages to WML (WAP) pages Html2Wml converts HTML pages to WML pages, suitable for being viewed on a Wap device. The conversion can be done either on the command line to create static WML pages or on-the-fly by calling this program as a CGI. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htmldoc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HTML processor that generates indexed HTML, PS, and PDF. HTMLDOC is a program for writing documentation in HTML and producing indexed HTML, PostScript, or PDF output (with tables of contents). It supports most HTML 3.2 and some HTML 4.0 syntax, as well as GIF, JPEG, and PNG images. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htmlgen
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Generation of HTML documents with Python scripts. HTMLgen is a class library for the generation of HTML documents with Python scripts. It&apos;s used when you want to create HTML pages containing information which changes from time to time. For example you might want to have a page which provides an overall system summary of data collected nightly. Or maybe you have a catalog of data and images that you would like formed into a spiffy set of web pages for the world to browse. Python is a great scripting language for these tasks and with HTMLgen it&apos;s very straightforward to construct objects which are rendered into consistently structured web pages. Of course, CGI scripts written in Python can take advantage of these classes as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htmlheadline
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
script that automatically fetches news headlines, and browses on Browser HtmlHeadLine.sh is a script that automatically fetches news headlines.   Basic features:      One shell only.      Title, Link, Description, HP, ChangeLog, DL of headline on netscape.      &apos;Desc_&apos; means Description show/hide on mouse.      It is easy to modify if you know awk. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htmltoc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
add table of contents to HTML document From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htmlview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The htmlview utility uses an installed and preferred HTML viewer to display a local HTML page. It is used by several configuration tools to display their help pages. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
htp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An HTML pre-processor htp is an HTML pre-processor. It is designed to be a flexible authoring tool that can easily be integrated into the HTML design process. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Temperature PolySilicon From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTSI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Host Transport Service Interface (ICC, CT-API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperText Transfer Protocol (WWW, RFC 2068) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
See hypertext transfer protocol (http). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTP (Hypertext Transfer Protocol)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Internet standard that supports the exchange of information on the World Wide Web (WWW). By defining Universal Resource Locators (URLs) and how they can be used to retrieve resources (including not only Web documents but also File Transport Protocol (FTP)-accessible files, Usenet newsgroups, and Gopher menus) anywhere on the Internet, HTTP enables Web authors to embed hyperlinks in Web documents. When clicked, a hyperlink initiates a data transfer process that accesses and retrieves document, without any further intervention from the use (or, indeed, without any knowledge of where the document is coming from or how it was accessed). In short, HTTP lays the foundation for transparent access to the Internet. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTP (Hypertext Transfer Protocol)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The protocol used to provide hypertext links between pages. It is the standard way of transfering HTML documents between Web servers and browsers. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
http://www.madeinlinux.com/ From LWN Distribution List
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>

<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
httpd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Apache is a powerful, full-featured, efficient, and freely-available Web server. Apache is also the most popular Web server on the Internet. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTPD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperText Transfer Protocol DAEMON (WWW, HTTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Httpd (Hypertext Transer Protocol Deamon)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A web server originally developed at the Swiss Center for Particle Research (CERN) and originally called CERN htpd. Subsequently, httpd was developed independently at the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA) for UNIX systems. An important innovation in the history of Web servers, NASA httpd introduced forms, clickable imagemaps, authenticationm and key word searches. Most of these features are now taken for granted in other Web servers. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
httperf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An HTTP server performance tester. httperf is a tool to measure web server  performance. It speaks the HTTP protocol both in its HTTP/1.0 and HTTP/1.1 flavors and offers a variety of workload generators. While running, it keeps track of a number of performance metrics that are summarized in the form  of  statistics  that  are printed  at the end of a test run. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTPNG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperText Transfer Protocol - Next Generation (WWW), &quot;HTTP-NG&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HTTPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HyperText Transfer Protocol [SSL] Secured (HTTP, SSL, WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
httptunnel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tunnels a data stream in HTTP requests. Creates a bidirectional virtual data stream tunnelled in HTTP requests. The requests can be sent via a HTTP proxy if so desired. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hub
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Central connectivity device for resources on a network. Computer systems, servers, network storage, printers, and more connect to hubs to communicate with each other. A switch and a router are two types of hubs. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hubcot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
USB Hub muscot - utility &quot;Hubcot&quot; is the USB Hub with cute muscot(Toro and Hello Kitty). The muscot moves his arm and head by receiving a signal from USB. This package contains the utility for hubcot. &quot;Hubcot&quot; is trademarked by Dreams come true co.,Ltd. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hubcot-source
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
USB Hub muscot - source of module &quot;Hubcot&quot; is the USB Hub with cute muscot(Toro and Hello Kitty). The muscot moves his arm and head by receiving a signal from USB. This package contains the source code for hubcot module.  Please note that the kernel sources must be installed to compile this module. &quot;Hubcot&quot; is trademarked by Dreams come true co.,Ltd. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HUGO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Holland User Group for OS/2 (org., user group, OS/2, Netherlands) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hugs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Haskell 98 interpreter Hugs is an interpreter for the non-strict, purely functional programming language Haskell.  This version of Hugs, Hugs 98, supports nearly all of the new Haskell 98 specification. Documentation is available in the hugs-doc package.  The Haskell language is described by documents in the haskell-doc package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hung
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
adj. [from `hung up&apos;; common] Equivalent to wedged, but more common at Unix/C sites. Not generally used of people. Syn. with locked up, wedged; compare hosed. See also hang. A hung state is distinguished from crashed or down, where the program or system is also unusable but because it is not running rather than because it is waiting for something. However, the recovery from both situations is often the same. It is also distinguished from the similar but more drastic state wedged - hung software can be woken up with easy things like interrupt keys, but wedged will need a kill -9 or even reboot.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hung system
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A computer that has experienced a system failure and is no longer processing data, even though cursor might still be blinking on-screen. The only option in most cases is to restart the system, which means losing any unsaved work. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hunglish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A consistent English-Hungarian keyboard layout Hunglish provides an English-Hungarian dual keyboard layout. The layout is the same both on the linux console and under X. The package provides full support for all Hungarian letters on all common keyboards, including US 101-key layouts. In Hunglish, you can switch modes by pressing the Print Screen key.  The Windows keys work as mode shift. Please read /usr/share/doc/hunglish/README for more information. (All documentation is in Hungarian.) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hunt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Advanced packet sniffer and connection intrusion. Hunt is a program for intruding into a connection, watching it and resetting it. Note that hunt is operating on Ethernet and is best used for connections which can be watched through it. However, it is possible to do something even for hosts on another segments or hosts that are on switched ports. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
huntd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
hunt daemon, back-end for hunt game From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HURD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HIRD of Unix-Replacing DAEMONs (GNU, HIRD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hurd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Hurd will be the foundation of the whole GNU system. It is built on top of the Mach 3.0 kernel, a free message-passing kernel developed by CMU. Mach&apos;s virtual memory management and message-passing facilities are extensively used by the Hurd. The GNU C Library will provide the Unix system call interface, and will call the Hurd for needed services it can&apos;t provide itself. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hwbrowser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical browser for your current hardware configuration. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hwclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
query and set the hardware clock (RTC) From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hwdata
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
hardware identification / configuration data This package contains various hardware identification and configuration data, such as the pci.ids database, or the XFree86 Cards database. Its needed for the kudzu hardware detection. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hwtools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Collection of tools for low-level hardware management This package is a collection of tools useful for hardware troubleshooting and optimization (for ix86 machines):  irqtune: adjusts priority of interrupts (improves serial performance),  scanport: scans for hardware not already handled by Linux drivers,  memmxtest: a real mode memory test, with MMX support.  You may want to look at package memtest86 as well. Be aware that these tools require some knowledge of what are they doing to be used properly, not causing damage to your system. Some programs that were previously part of this package have been moved to their own packages (hdparm, scsitools, memtest86) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hx
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Unix client for Hotline Hx is the Unix client for Hotline. Hotline is kind of like IRC, kind of like an FTP server, all put together. It let&apos;s people chat on a server, and upload and download files. It works on the concept of servers, using trackers to keep track of which servers are available. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HYCH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hope You Can Help (slang, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hylafax-client
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Flexible client/server fax software - client utilities The HylaFAX client software communicates with a HylaFAX server via TCP/IP. HylaFAX support the sending and receiving of facsimiles, the polled retrieval of facsimiles and the send of alphanumeric pages. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hylafax-server
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Flexible client/server fax software - server daemons This package support the sending and receiving of facsimiles, the polled retrieval of facsimiles and the send of alphanumeric pages. The host running the server must have either a Class 1, Class 2, or a Class 2.0 fax modem attached to one of its serial ports. End-user applications to manage the transmission of documents via facsimile are provided separately by the hylafax-client package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hyperlatex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Creating HTML using LaTeX documents. Hyperlatex allows you to use a LaTeX-like language to prepare documents in HTML (the hypertext markup language used by the world wide web), and, at the same time, to produce a fine printed document from your input. You can use all of LaTeX&apos;s power for the printed output, and you don&apos;t have to learn a new language for creating hypertext documents. Note that Hyperlatex is not meant to translate arbitrary Latex files into HTML. Rather, it provides an authoring environment for writing printed documents and HTML documents at the same time, using an extended subset of Latex (excluding concepts that have no HTML counterpart and adding commands for new HTML concepts such as hyperlinks or included images). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hypermail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Create HTML archives of mailing lists Creates crosslinked and threaded HTML archives of mailboxes or mailing lists.  Can be configured to automagically update the archives when new messages arrive. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hyperspec
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Common Lisp ANSI-standard Hyperspec This is a installer package for the html-ed version of the ANSI standard for Common Lisp. Note that these pages are only FYI and are not valid as a reference. But for all intents and purposes this is a good enough reference for daily work. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hypertext
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A document which has been marked up to allow a user to select words or pictures within the document, click on them, and connect to further information. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Hypertext
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Generally, any text that contains links to other documents - words or phrases in the document that can be chosen by a reader and which cause another document to be retrieved and displayed. See also: HTML, HTTP From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hypertext markup language (HTML)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A standardized language for the formatting of interactive text on the World Wide Web. HTML uses tags and scripting and is typically rendered on Web browsers. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hypertext transfer protocol (http)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The protocol used to transfer information from Web servers to web browsers. Website addresses begin with http:// and is rendered on browsers using hypertext markup language (HTML). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hyphen-show
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Show hyphenations in DVI-files hyphen_show scans a DVI-file, tries to find all hyhenations and writes them to stdout. It is useful to check whether TeX&apos;s hyphenation algorithm really did the good job it is supposed to do. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HYTEA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
HYperText Environment for Authoring (ESPRIT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
HYTIME
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hypermedia/Time-based structuring language (SGML, ISO, IEC, IS 10744), &quot;HyTime&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
hztty
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Translates GB, Big5, zW/HZ Chinese encodings in a tty session This program turns a tty session from one Chinese encoding to another. For example, running hztty on cxterm can allow you to read/write Chinese in HZ format, which was not supported by cxterm. If you have many applications in different encodings but your favor terminal program only supports one, hztty can make life easy. For example, hztty can your GB cxterm into a HZ terminal, a Unicode (16bit, or UTF8, or UTF7) terminal, or a Big5 terminal.  Author: Yongguang Zhang &lt;ygz@cs.purdue.edu&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossary>
