<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="J">
<title>J</title>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
J-LINUX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An Italian distribution based on Mandrake. Full support of the Italian language both at the operating system and at a documentation and installation level, with an English language version of the web site. This site was last updated May 30, 2001 and appears to have disappeared [July 22, 2002].  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
J2EE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java 2 Enterprise Edition (Java, Sun) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
J2ME
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java 2 Micro Edition (Java, Sun) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
J2SE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java 2 Standard Edition (Java, Sun) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ja-trans
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese gettext message files Japanese message files from japo@flatout.org and ja@li.org. This package includes:  - net-tools 1.51: incomplete  - textutils 2.0: Bug#43846 Done: man-db, wget, gettext (Bug#43844), fileutils(Bug#43843), tar, grep,       sh-utils, glibc 2.1.94, texinfo Sponsored by Fumitoshi UKAI &lt;ukai@debian.or.jp&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JAAS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Authentication and Authorization Service (Java, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jabber
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Daemon for the jabber.org Open Source Instant Messenger Jabber is a Free Instant Messaging System In this Package you will find jabberd, a message transport server based on a XML Message Routing Infrastructure. All this high-tech is simply used to provide you with your own IM Server. See http://www.jabber.org/ for more details. Jabber supports connecting to AIM, ICQ, IRC, MSM and a lot of others, so you can use all available IM systems from one client. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jablicator
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Share a set of package choices Allows others to easily replicate your package choices via Debian&apos;s apt-get utility. Generating an apt-gettable, custom debian package, with the appropriate dependencies. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jack
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Rip and encode CDs with one command Jack has been developed with one main goal: making MP3s or OGGs without having to worry. There is nearly no way that an incomplete rip goes unnoticed, e.g. jack compares WAV and OGG file sizes when continuing from a previous run. Jack also checks your HD space before doing anything (even keeps some MB free). Jack is different from other such tools in a number of ways:  - it supports different rippers and encoders  - it is very configurable  - it doesn&apos;t need X  - it can &quot;rip&quot; virtual CD images like the ones created by cdrdao  - when using cdparanoia, cdparanoia&apos;s status information is displayed    for all tracks, so you can see if something went wrong  - it uses sophisticated disk space management, i.e. it schedules it&apos;s    ripping/encoding processes depending on available space.  - freedb query, file renaming and id3 tagging  - it can resume work after it has been interrupted. If all tracks have    been ripped, it doesn&apos;t even need the CD anymore, even if you want    to do a freedb query.  - it can do a freedb query based on OGGs alone, like if you don&apos;t    remember from which CD those OGGs came from.  - freedb submissions From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JACM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Journal of the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JAD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Application Development From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jade
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
James Clark&apos;s DSSSL Engine Jade is an implementation of the DSSSL style language. The jade engine is a useful tool (in conjunction with a DSSSL style sheet) for translating SGML documents into other formats.  Jade can currently generate SGML, RTF, and TeX.  In conjunction with the &quot;jadetex&quot; TeX style, it can generate quite nice output.  Author:   James Clark &lt;jjc@jclark.com&gt;  Homepage: http://www.jclark.com/jade/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JADE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jasmine Application Development Environment (Jasmine, DB, CA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jadetex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JadeTeX contains the additional LaTeX macros necessary for taking JadeTeX output files and processing them as TeX files (to obtain DVI,PostScript, or PDF files, for example). From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jadetex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
LaTeX macros for SGML to DVI/PS/PDF conversion with Jade JadeTeX provides a set of LaTeX macros to process the TeX files generated by Jade or OpenJade. Using Jade and JadeTeX you can print every SGML document for which you have or make a DSSSL description. Homepage: http://jadetex.sourceforge.net/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jadetex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
processing tex files produced by the backend of Jade. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jags
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Just Another GTK+ Samba Client Jags is a Gtk+ based &quot;windows network neighbourhood browser&quot;. The program parses the output from smbclient (part of the samba-package) and use this to display a graphic view of the network. This program does the parsing with help from shell- scripts. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Just Another ICMP Logger Jail (Just Another ICMP Logger) is a small program which runs in the background, and can be configured to log at different syslog levels the reception of various ICMP packets. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Jailbait
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JAILBAIT&apos;s Another Interesting Linux But Also Intimidating Too: A fully-functional Linux distribution that fits into 16 MB. Many modern net-appliance-type products such as the Netpliance iOpener have an internal SanDisk device that is 16 MB in size.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jam
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A replacement for make This is the Jam/MR program as published by Perforce.  For a version with additionnal features see the `ftjam&apos; package. A powerful and highly customizable utility to build programs and other things, that can run on Un*x, Nt, VMS, OS/2 and Macintosh MPW, using portable Jamfiles.  It can build large projects spread across many directories in one pass. It takes some time to fully apprehend, as there&apos;s no tutorial available yet, especially when one&apos;s already accustomed to make(1), but there&apos;s no comparison in power when comparing these 2 tools. Standard rules:  - can automatically extract header dependencies for C/C++ (you can customize for you own language)  - provide for automatic &quot;clean&quot;, &quot;install&quot;, &quot;uninstall&quot; rules, so that an automake-like tool is not needed From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JANET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Academic NETwork (network, UK) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JAP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Anon Proxy (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JAR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Archive (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jargon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The definitive compendium of hacker slang. This is the Jargon File, a comprehensive compendium of hacker slang illuminating many aspects of hackish tradition, folklore, and humor. The file is in info format, but includes an HTML page with links to the home site. Note that this package is now out-of-date, because the upstream author is no longer maintaining an info version of the file. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JARS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Applet Rating Service (Java, WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JASS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Javascript-Accessable Style Sheets (HTML, WWW, JavaScript) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Java
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Computer language developed by SUN which allows you to write software which works on a wide range of computers . JAVA is currently the programming language of choice on the Internet and it allows tiny programs to be created and sent over the network. More information is available at http://java.sun.com/ From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Java
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A programming language based on C developed in 1996 by Sun Microsystems. It was developed for network computing because it allows for mini-applications, called &quot;applets&quot; to be distributed to different computer clients connected to the network. An applet will run identically on any existing computer environment. Browsers like Netscape &amp; Internet Explorer make use of Java. From Faculty-of-Education
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Java
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An object-oriented language originally developed at Sun by James Gosling (and known by the name &quot;Oak&quot;) with the intention of being the successor to C++ (the project was however originally sold to Sun as an embedded language for use in set-top boxes). After the great Internet explosion of 1993-1994, Java was hacked into a byte-interpreted language and became the focus of a relentless hype campaign by Sun, which touted it as the new language of choice for distributed applications. Java is indeed a stronger and cleaner design than C++ and has been embraced by many in the hacker community - but it has been a considerable source of frustration to many others, for reasons ranging from uneven support on different Web browser platforms, performance issues, and some notorious deficiencies of some of the standard toolkits (AWT in particular). Microsoft&apos;s determined attempts to corrupt the language (which it rightly sees as a threat to its OS monopoly) have not helped. As of 1999, these issues are still in the process of being resolved. Despite many attractive features and a good design, it is difficult to find people willing to praise Java who have tried to implement a complex, real-world system with it (but to be fair it is early days yet, and no other language has ever been forced to spend its childhood under the limelight the way Java has). On the other hand, Java has already been a big win in academic circles, where it has taken the place of Pascal as the preferred tool for teaching the basics of good programming to the next generation of hackers.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Java
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An object-oriented programming language developed by Sun Microsystems. to be operating system independent. Java is often used on Web servers. Java applications and applets are sometimes offered as downloads to run on users&apos; systems. Java programming can produce applications, or smaller Java applets. Java is a somewhat simplified version of the C++ language, and is normally interpreted rather than compiled. (Also, see JIT Compiler.) From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Java
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java is a network-friendly programming language invented by Sun Microsystems. Java is often used to build large, complex systems that involve several different computers interacting across networks, for example transaction processing systems. Java is also becoming popular for creating programs that run in small electronic devicws, such as mobile telephones. A very common use of Java is to create programs that can be safely downloaded to your computer through the Internet and immediately run without fear of viruses or other harm to your computer or files. Using small Java programs (called &quot;Applets&quot;), Web pages can include functions such as animations,calculators, and other fancy tricks. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Java Applets
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Small Java programs that are embedded in a Web page and run within a browser, not as a stand-alone application. Applets cannot access some resources on the local computer, such as files and serial devices (modems, printers, etc.), and generally cannot communicate with other computers across a network. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
java-common
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Base of all Java packages This package must be installed in the system if a Java environment is desired. It covers useful information for Java users in Debian GNU/Linux, including:   - The Java policy document which describes the layout of Java support in     Debian and how Java packages should behave.   - The Debian-Java-FAQ which provides information on the status of     Java support in Debian, available compilers, virtual machines, Java     programs and libraries as well as on legal issues. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
java2html
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Highlight Java and C++ sources for WWW presentation java2html can highlight your source for presentation in the WWW. It can also be used as a CGI script and can detect whether the client browser supports compressed data to save bandwidth. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JavaBeans
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A component architecture for the Java programming language, developed initially by Sun, but now available from several other vendors. JavaBeans components are called &quot;beans&quot;. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JAVAOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Operating System (Java), &quot;JavaOS&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JavaScript
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JavaScript is a programming language that is mostly used in web pages, usually to add features that make the web page more interactive. When JavaScript is included in an HTML file it relies upon the browser to interpret the JavaScript. When JavaScript is combined with Cascading Style Sheets(CSS), and later versions of HTML (4.0 and later) the result is often called DHTML. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JavaScript
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Misconception: JavaScript is completely different than Java. Netscape renamed their &quot;LiveScript&quot; in order to take advantage of all the marketing hype surrounding Java. Both Java and JavaScript inherit similar syntax from their C/C++ parents, but they were designed completely independently. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JavaScript
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Netscape&apos;s simple, cross-platform, World-Wide Web scripting language, only very vaguely related to Java. JavaScript is intimately tied to the World-Wide Web, and currently runs in only three environments - as a server-side scripting language, as an embedded language in server-parsed HTML, and as an embedded language run in browsers. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jaxml
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Python module for generating XML documents jaxml is a python module that defines a class XML_document, which allows easy and trouble-free generation of XML documents. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JAXP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java API for XML Processing (Java, API, XML) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jbibtex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
make a bibliography for ASCII p(La)TeX / NTT j(La)TeX This is JBibTeX, a Japanized BibTeX based on the original BibTeX 0.99c. JBibTeX can handle Kanji characters (EUC-JP). This package contains library files for JBibTeX.  You need to install jbibtex-bin to use JBibTeX. This is a part of ASCII pTeX distribution,  but you can use this program not only with ASCII p(La)TeX but also with NTT j(La)TeX. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JBIG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Bi-level Image expert Group (org., JTC1) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JBLinux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A distribution for workstations and servers. JBLinux was at version 2.2 as of August 10, 2001.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jbofihe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A parser for the lojban language jbofihe is a command-line driven program with the following functions:  * Checking grammatical correctness of Lojban text  * Displaying successfully analysed text with nesting of grammatical    constructs shown (either inline or as a tree)  * Displaying approximate word-for-word English translations of the Lojban    words, with some limited &apos;part-of-speech&apos; adjustment of the English forms.  * Showing which sumti fill each of the places of each selbri From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCALS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Computer-Aided Logistics System (CAL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job Control Block (BS2000) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCDW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Callable Data Wrapper (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Cryptographic Extension (Java, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JESSI Common Framework From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/J-C-L/ n. 1. IBM&apos;s supremely rude Job Control Language. JCL is the script language used to control the execution of programs in IBM&apos;s batch systems. JCL has a very fascist syntax, and some versions will, for example, barf if two spaces appear where it expects one. Most programmers confronted with JCL simply copy a working file (or card deck), changing the file names. Someone who actually understands and generates unique JCL is regarded with the mixed respect one gives to someone who memorizes the phone book. It is reported that hackers at IBM itself sometimes sing &quot;Who&apos;s the breeder of the crud that mangles you and me? I-B-M, J-C-L, M-o-u-s-e&quot; to the tune of the &quot;Mickey Mouse Club&quot; theme to express their opinion of the beast. 2. A comparative for any very rude software that a hacker is expected to use. &quot;That&apos;s as bad as JCL.&quot; As with COBOL, JCL is often used as an archetype of ugliness even by those who haven&apos;t experienced it. See also IBM, fear and loathing. A (poorly documented, naturally) shell simulating JCL syntax is available at the Retrocomputing Museum http://www.ccil.org/retro.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job Control Language (IBM, OS/360) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCL (Job Control Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In mainframe computing, a progamming language that allows progammer to spcify batch processing instructions, which the computer then carries out. The abbreviation JCL refers to the job control language used in IBM mainframes. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JCW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Callable Wrapper (MS, Java, VM, COM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JDBC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java standard DataBase Connectivity (DB, Java, Sun, Borland, ODBC, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jde
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Development Environment for Emacs or XEmacs. The Java Development Environment (JDE) is an Emacs Lisp package that interfaces Emacs to third-party Java application development tools, such as those provided by JavaSoft&apos;s Java Development Kit (JDK). The result is an integrated development environment (IDE) comparable in power to many commercial Java IDEs. Features include:  - source code editing with syntax highlighting and auto indentation  - compilation with automatic jump from error messages to responsible line    in the source code.  - run Java application in an interactive (comint) Emacs buffer  - integrated debugging with interactive debug command buffer and automatic    display of current source file/line when stepping through code  - browse JDK doc, using the browser of your choice  - browse your source code, using the Emacs etags facility or a    tree-structured speedbar.  - easily and infinitely customizable From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JDK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Development Kit (Sun, Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JDK (Java Development Kit)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A free software development package from Sun Microsystems that implements the basic set of tools needed to write, test and debug Java applications and applets. From Matisse Versions are also available from IBM and open source groups for a variety of platforms including Linux. From Binh
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jdresolve
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
fast alternative to apache logresolve The jdresolve application resolves IP addresses into hostnames. To reduce the time necessary to resolve large batches of addresses, jdresolve opens many concurrent connections to the DNS servers, and keeps a large number of text lines in memory. These lines can have any content, as long as the IP addresses are the first field to the left. This is usually the case with most formats of HTTP and FTP log files. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jed
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Editor for programmers. (textmode version) Jed offers: Extensible in a language resembling C. Completely customizable. Capable of read GNU info files from within JED&apos;s info browser. A variety of programming modes (with syntax highlighting) are available including Pascal, Java, Perl, C, C++, FORTRAN, TeX, HTML, SH, IDL, DCL, NROFF, PostScript, Basic. Folding support. Edit TeX files with AUC-TeX style editing (BiBTeX support too). Rectangular cut/paste; regular expressions; incremental searches; search replace across multiple files; multiple windows; multiple buffers; shell modes; directory editor (dired); mail; rmail; ispell; and much more. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JEDEC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Electronic Devices Engineering Council (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jedstate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Extended mind for John E. Davis&apos; text editor jed Jedstate is some sort of an extended mind for John E. Davis&apos; splendid text editor jed. Using jedstate and jed&apos;s startup and exit hooks as a glue jed &quot;remembers&quot; the position of the cursor for all visited files and will automagically jump to that position whenever the file is revisited.  The database is purgeable based on a time-since-last-view criterion. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JEIDA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japan Electronics Industry Development Association (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jered
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simple full screen text editor with colored C/C++ syntax JERED is a full page text editor for Unix. It is based on the text editor E from IBM. The old name was JE, which meant Jerome&apos;s Editor. Now it is called JERED, which means JErome&apos;s Renamed EDitor. This editor features: automatic color enhancement of C and C++ syntax, recording &amp; playback of macros, multi-file sessions, automatic screen size recognition, block movements, shell escapes, custom user configuration, small run size (about 45K with a shared ncurses library, and about 170K with a static ncurses lib, very fast loading, and straightforward design. Lightweight &amp; cool. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JES
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job Entry Subsystem (IBM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jesred
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A redirector for Squid Jesred is a very fast and highly configurable redirector for the Squid Internet Object Cache. It was derived from Chris Foote&apos;s and Wayne Piekarski&apos;s Squirm 1.0 betaB and some code from Squid itself, but is about 2-3x faster than the original version and has some additional features. Jesred has the following features:   * uses only a very small amount of memory (a little bit more than     squirm 1.0 betaB, but still less than perl ;-))   * able to rewrite GET and optionally ICP_QUERY requests as well   * one global configuration file   * one IP access control file which supports CIDR notation only     (i.e. subnet/mask). Thus only URL requests from the specified   * subnets/clients are rewritten, if necessary.   * one rewrite rules configuration file (regular expression matching     and replacement)   * optionally logging of common and error messages to a file   * optionally logging of URL rewrites to a separate log file,     incl. the number of the rule, which has been used to rewrite the     URL   * able to re-read all its configuration files on the fly by sending     a HUP signal to the process. That&apos;s why there is no need to     restart Squid, if you want to:       1.change the used log file name[s] (useful for log file rotation)       2.enable/disable logging       3.enable/disable debug mode if compiled with DEBUG option       4.enable/disable URL rewriting of ICP_QUERY (sibling) requests       5.change the IP access patterns       6.change the redirect rules   * If you mess up configuration file[s], Jesred runs in Echo Mode     (always echos back a newline - i.e. no URL replacement) and squid     keeps working. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JESS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Expert System Shell (Java, Shell) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jester
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-based board game similar to Othello It can be played head-to-head on the console or by a single player against the computer.  Jester allows you to waste valuable time that could otherwise be spent playing Solitaire. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jfbterm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanized framebuffer terminal with Multilingual Enhancement. Jfbterm/me is a Japanized framebuffer terminal with Multilingual Enhancement. It can display ISO-8859-1, ISO-8859-2, ISO-2022-JP, EUC-JP, ISO-2022-CN, CN-GB, ISO-2022-KR, EUC-KR and Wansung. BIG5 is planned to support. It supprts 8 bpp PACKED-PIXELS PSEUDOCOLOR and (15|16|24|32) bpp PACKED-PIXELS TRUECOLOR framebuffers (vga16fb is supported). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JFC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Foundation Classes (Java, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JFET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Junction Field Effect Transistor (IC, FET) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JFIF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JPEG File Interchange Format (JPEG) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jflex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
lexical analyzer generator for Java JFlex is a lexical analyzer generator for Java written in Java. It is also a rewrite of the very useful tool JLex which was developed by Elliot Berk at Princeton University. As Vern Paxon states for his C/C++ tool flex :  They do not share any code though. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Journaled File System (LVM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JFS (Journaled/Journaling File System)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A file system that includes built-in backup/recovery capabilities. Changes to the index are written to a log file before the changes take effect so that if the index is corrupted (by a power failure during the index write, for example), the index can be rebuilt from the log, including the changes. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jfsutils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The jfsutils package contains a number of utilities for creating, checking, modifying, and correcting any inconsistencies in JFS filesystems.  The following utilities are available: fsck.jfs - initiate replay of the JFS transaction log, and check and repair a JFS formatted device; logdump - dump a JFS formatted device&apos;s journal log; logredo -&quot;replay&quot; a JFS formatted device&apos;s journal log;  mkfs.jfs - create a JFS formatted partition; xchkdmp - dump the contents of a JFS fsck log file created with xchklog; xchklog - extract a log from the JFS fsck workspace into a file;  xpeek - shell-type JFS file system editor. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jfsutils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Utilities for managing the JFS filesystem Utilities for managing IBM&apos;s Journaled File System (JFS) under Linux. IBM&apos;s journaled file system technology, currently used in IBM enterprise servers, is designed for high-throughput server environments, key to running intranet and other high-performance e-business file servers. The following utilities are available: fsck.jfs - initiate replay of the JFS transaction log, and check and repair a JFS formatted device. logdump - dump a JFS formatted device&apos;s journal log. logredo - &quot;replay&quot; a JFS formatted device&apos;s journal log. mkfs.jfs - create a JFS formatted partition. xchkdmp - dump the contents of a JFS fsck log file created with xchklog. xchklog - extract a log from the JFS fsck workspace into a file. xpeek - shell-type JFS file system editor. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JFT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job File Table (DOS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jftpgw
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joe&apos;s FTP Proxy/Gateway. FTP proxy program with the following features:  * Active as well as passive FTP transfers.  * Logging of connection attempts.  * Access control features  * If run as root, it drops the privileges as often as possible.  * You can pretend to run a real ftp server.  * User specific forward features.  * Specify how many users are allowed to log in from which IP ranges.  * The throughput rate can be throttled.  * Various login strings are possible.  * Regular users can run the proxy server on unprivileged ports as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jgraph
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jim Plank&apos;s program for producing PostScript graphs Jgraph takes a description of a graph or graphs and produces a postscript file on the standard output. Jgraph is ideal for plotting any mixture of scatter point graphs, line graphs, and/or bar graphs, and embedding the output into LaTeX, or any other text processing system which can read postscript. The graph description language is simple enough to get nice looking graphs with a minimum of effort, yet powerful enough to give the user the flexibility to tailor the appearance of the graph to his or her individual preferences.  This includes plotting multiple graphs and laying them out separately on the page (or pages). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jhcore
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jay&apos;s House Core, an enhanced core database for lambdamoo Jay&apos;s House Core, a lambdacore based db with significant enhancements. It features:  * Hypertext help system  * Administration groups  * Enhanced english presentation tools  * Added objects (furniture, doors, windows, etc)  * A tutorial From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jhead
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Manipulate the non-image part of EXIF compliant JPEG files Jhead is a command line driven utility for extracting digital camera settings from the Exif format files used by many digital cameras. It handles the various confusing ways these can be expressed, and displays them as F-stop, shutter speed, etc. It is also able to reduce the size of digital camera JPEGs without loss of information, by deleting integral thumbnails that digital cameras put into the Exif header. Upstream is: http://www.sentex.net/~mwandel/jhead/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JICST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japan Information Center of Science and Technology (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIEO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Interoperability Engineering Organization (org., DISA, mil., USA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JPEG Interchange Format (JPEG) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jiffy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Visualization for nec-based antenna designs It is never been easier to design antennas!  Most hams enjoy ``fiddling&apos;&apos; with antennas, but comparatively few of us are really interested in doing one-handed chin-ups at fifty feet above the cold frozen earth on a snowy and windy night in January. Jiffy will make life a lot easier for you. It can make a drawing from the antenna design that you made and it can display elevation and azimuth patterns from the nec output. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jiffy-perl-tk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Visualization for nec-based antenna designs using perl-tk Another version of jiffy, which uses perl-tk. Compared to the original jiffy, a program called necview is added, which can view your antenna design from different angles. A major advantage of this version of jiffy as compared to the tcl/tk/blt based version: it&apos;s a lot faster. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jigdo-file
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Download Debian CD images from any Debian mirror Using the jigdo-lite script contained in this package, you can use your nearest &quot;regular&quot; Debian mirror to download Debian CD images, instead of having to use one of the few, slow, overloaded mirrors that offer the images as direct HTTP or FTP downloads. See &lt;http://www.debian.org/CD/jigdo-cd/&gt; for details. Jigsaw Download, or short jigdo, is a scheme developed primarily to make it easy to distribute huge filesystem images (e.g. CD (ISO9660) or DVD (UDF) images) over the internet, but it could also be used for other data which is awkward to handle due to its size, like audio/video files or large software packages. jigdo tries to ensure that the large file is downloaded in small parts which can be stored on different servers. People who want to download the image do so by telling the jigdo download tool to process one &quot;.jigdo&quot; file; using it, jigdo downloads the parts and reassembles the image. jigdo-file is used to prepare the files for download. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jikes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fast Java compiler adhering to language and VM specifications Jikes is a Java compiler that translates Java source files as defined in The Java Language Specification (Addison-Wesley, 1996) into the bytecoded instruction set and binary format defined in The Java Virtual Machine Specification (Addison-Wesley, 1996). Unlike other compilers, Jikes accepts the Java language only as specified: not as a subset, variant, or superset. In addition to strictly adhering to specifications, Jikes is faster than most compilers and can compute the complete dependency relations in program files. This allows for the generation of dependency makefiles suitable for use with make. Jikes can also be run in incremental mode: after the initial compilation, Jikes waits until prompted, determines which files have been changed, and then does the minimal amount of work needed to bring the class files into a complete and consistent state. This cycle can be repeated until the q command is entered to end the compilation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jikespg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jikes Parser Generator Jikes Parser Generator is a parser generator that accepts as input an annotated  description for a language grammar and produces text files suitable for inclusion in a parser for that language. It is similar in function and use to the widely-available parser generators Yacc and Bison. It also provides support for automatic diagnosis and recovery from syntactic errors. It is the parser generator used by the Jikes Compiler. Jikes Parser Generator can generate parsers for LALR(k) grammars and produce output suitable for use with parsers written in Java, C, or C++. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Jini
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Pronounced &quot;Genie&quot;. Software from Sun that works somewhat like &quot;plug-and-play&quot;, in that it allows a hardware device to announce itself to the operating system (and provide details about the device) when the hardware is attached, without requiring a system reboot. It also announces itself to the network the system is connected to, providing easy network sharing of the device. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIPDEC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japan Information Processing DEvelopment Center (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JANET Internet Protocol Service (JANET) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese Institute of Standards (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JISC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese Industrial Standards Committee (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Just In Time [compiler] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JIT (Just-In-Time) Compiler
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A compiler for the Java language that allows interpreted Java programs to be automatically compiled into native machine language on the fly, for faster performance of the program. Some JVMs include a JIT compiler. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JITC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Interoperability Technology Center (org., DISA, mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jitterbug
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A cgi-bin tool for problem reporting and tracking JitterBug is a cgi-bin tool for problem reporting and tracking developed by Andrew Tridgell for the Samba Team. It is highly customizable to your own project&apos;s needs. It has both a web interface and an e-mail based one for submitting bug reports. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Just Kidding (DFUe, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jless
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A file pager program, similar to more(1) supporting ISO2022 Jless is a program similar to more (1), but which allows backward movement in the file as well as forward movement.  Also, jless does not have to read the entire input file before starting, so with large input files it starts up faster than text editors like vi (1).  Jless uses terminfo, so it can run on a variety of terminals.  There is even limited support for hardcopy terminals. Jless supporting ISO 2022 code extension techniques and Japanese codes. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jlex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Lex-style lexical analyser generator for Java The JLex utility is a lexical analyser generator, modelled after the popular UNIX &quot;lex&quot; utility. JLex takes a specification file similar to that accepted by Lex, then creates a Java source file for the corresponding lexical analyzer. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JMI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Metadata Interface (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jmk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A cross-platform make tool written in Java jmk is an application which is used to ensure that a set of files is in a consistent state. If jmk detects an inconsistency, it executes commands that correct the inconsistency. The rules used to detect and correct inconsistencies are given in a makefile. jmk is designed to support the task of writing platform independent makefiles. File names and path lists are written in a canonical form, and translated by jmk into native form. The rules given in a jmk makefile can invoke programs as separate processes. To produce a machine independent makefile, a makefile should only invoke programs that use the same command line argument syntax across platforms. Examples of such programs include Sun&apos;s Java compiler (javac) and their Java Archive Tool (jar). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jmon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
distributed resource monitor Resource monitoring for large networks. The jMon system allows for the real time monitoring of CPU, memory and swap usage. The system makes use of a small daemon running on each of the machines that are to be monitored. The client makes a TCP/IP connection with each of the servers specified in the configuration file. The statistics of all the host machines are displayed in an ncurses window on the console. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jmpost
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanized MetaPost, a system for drawing pictures This is jMetaPost, a Japanized MetaPost based on the original MetaPost 0.641. jMetaPost can handle Kanji characters (EUC-JP). MetaPost interprets the MetaPost language and produces PostScript pictures.  The MetaPost language is similar to Knuth&apos;s Metafont with additional features for including tex(1) or troff(1) commands and accessing features of PostScript not found in Metafont. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JMSC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese MIDI Standard Committee (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JMSWG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Multi-TADIL Standards Working Group (org., mil., TADIL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JNDI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Naming and Directory Interface (JavaSoft, API, Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jnethack
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The dungeon exploration game JNetHack (nethack with Japanese l10n) JNetHack is Japanese localized version of NetHack. NetHack is D&amp;D (Dungeons and Dragons) style adventure game. Special features of JNetHack version are following:  * Japanese message  * New character &apos;Fighter&apos; (She wears &apos;sailor blouse&apos;)  * High score server  * GTK+ mode  * And so on... From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JNI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Native method Interface (Java, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JNSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JNT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Network Technology (Java, Informatec) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Job
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A task for a computer. The word derives from the days when people had to take their programs to a computing department to be run on a mainframe, and thereby assign a job to the copmuting department. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Job control
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Refers to the ability to selectively stop (suspend) the execution of processes and continue (resume) their execution at a later point. A user typically employs this facility via an interactive interface supplied jointly by the system&apos;s terminal driver and bash. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Job queue
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A series of tasks automatically executed, one after the other, by the computer. In mainframe data processing during the 1950s and 1960s, the job queue was literallly a queue, or line of people waiting to have their programs run. With interactive, multi-user computing and personal computing, you usually don&apos;t need to line up to get your work done (although jobs can still back up at a busy printer). The term is still used in WordPerfect, for example, where you can assign a job number to several files you want to print, and the program prints the files in the order you assign. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JODS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jasmine Object Database Server (Jasmine, DB, CA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
joe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
user friendly full screen text editor Joe, the Joe&apos;s Own Editor, has the feel of most PC text editors: the key sequences are reminiscent of WordStar and Turbo C editors, but the feature set is much larger than of those.  Joe has all of the features a Unix user should expect: full use of termcap/terminfo, complete VI-style Unix integration, a powerful configuration file, and regular expression search system.  It also has six help reference cards which are always available, and an intuitive, simple, and well thought-out user interface. Joe has a great screen update optimization algorithm, multiple windows (through/between which you can scroll) and lacks the confusing notion of named buffers.  It has command history, TAB expansion in file selection menus, undo and redo functions, (un)indenting and paragraph formatting, filtering highlighted blocks through any external Unix command, editing a pipe into or out of a command, and block move, copy, delete or filter. Through simple QEdit-style configuration files, Joe can be set up to emulate editors such as Pico and Emacs, along with a complete immitation of WordStar, and a restricted mode version (lets you edit only the files specified on the command line).  Joe also has a deferred screen update to handle typeahead, and it ensures that deferral is not bypassed by tty buffering.  It&apos;s usable even at 2400 baud, and it will work on any kind of sane terminal. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
john
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An active password cracking tool john, normally called john the ripper, is a tool to find weak passwords of your users, and even mail them automatically if you want. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOHNNIAC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JOHN von Neumann Integrator and Automatic Computer From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
join
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
join lines of two files on a common field From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Journal of Online Law (WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOLT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java OnLine Transactions (Java, Bea, OLTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOOP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Journal of Object Orientated Programming (OOP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JOHNNIAC Open Shop System (OS, JOHNNIAC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Object Services Submission From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOTS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Operational Tactical System (mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Journaling
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Same as &quot;logging&quot;. Writing information to a journal (log) file as a method of tracking changes. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JOVE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jonathan&apos;s Own Version of EMACS (EMACS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jove
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jonathan&apos;s Own Version of Emacs - a compact, powerful editor. Jove is a compact, powerful Emacs-style text-editor. It provides the common emacs keyboard bindings, together with a reasonable assortment of the most popular advanced features (e.g. interactive shell windows, compile-it, language specific modes) while weighing in with CPU, memory, and disk requirements comparable to vi(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
joystick
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Testing and calibration tools jstest (1)      - joystick test program jscal (1)       - joystick calibration program inputattach (1) - attach a serial line to a joystick device joystick-device-check(8) - fixes the major numbers depending                            on the running kernel From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
joystick
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Linux Joystick Driver provides support for a variety of joysticks and similar devices. This package includes several utilities for setting up, calibrating, and testing your joystick. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JPEG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Photographics Expert Group (org., JTC1, RFC 1521, JPEG) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JPEG (Joint Photographic Experts Group)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JPEG is most commonly mentioned as a format for image files. JPEG format is preferred to the GIF format for photographic images as opposed to line art or simple logo art. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jpeginfo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Prints information and tests integrity of JPEG/JFIF files. jpeginfo can be used to generate informative listings of jpeg files, and also to check jpeg files for errors. It can also detect broken jpeg and delete them automatically. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jpilot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A GTK app to modify the contents of your Palm Pilots DB&apos;s This is an impressive near-full-featured Palm Pilot desktop similar to the one that comes with the Pilot for Windows platforms. You have access to the following applications: o Datebook o Address book o ToDo list o Memos Plug-ins are available in the jpilot-plugins package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jpilot-plugins
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Plugins for jpilot (Palm Pilot desktop) This package includes two plugins for jpilot: o Expenses o SyncTime o KeyRing From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JPLDIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jet Propulsion Laboratory Display Information System From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JPM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Package Manager (MS, Java, VM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Print Service (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JRE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Runtime Environment (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JRMP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Remote Method Protocol (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese Standards Association (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jscalibrator
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GTK Joystick Calibrator With jscalibrator you can calibrate your joystick for Linux games. More information can be found at the jscalibrator web site http://wolfpack.twu.net/libjsw/ . From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jackson System Development (JSP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSDK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Servlet Development Kit (Java, Sun) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jserv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Servlet 2.0 engine with an optional Apache module Apache JServ is a 100% pure Java servlet engine fully compliant with the JavaSoft Java Servlet APIs 2.0 specification.  It works on any 1.1-compliant JVM, and contains a dynamically-loadable module (mod_jserv) to activate support in Apache 1.3. Servlet 2.0 classes (servlet-2.0.jar) are included from a free (LGPL) implementation found at http://www.euronet.nl/~pauls/java/servlet/. For more information, see the servlet engine project homepage at http://java.apache.org/. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jslaunch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joystick button shell command execution/shutdown tool jslaunch is a very small daemon/program that will start a specified shell command when a combination of joystick buttons is pressed. One of its uses is as a backup way to make a clean shutdown if your console has been messed up by X11 or SVGAlib and you don&apos;t have a terminal sitting on your desk to log in and shut down from, but you can use it for example as a remote control to do just about anything (including starting a measurement on an experimental setup connected to your computer). You will not need any joystick drivers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSME
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jackson Structured Programming (JSD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Server Pages (Java, Sun, JSP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSPE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japan Society for System Audits (org., JIPDEC, Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JSSE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Secure Socket Extension (Java, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japan Standard Time [+0900] (TZ) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jswat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
JPDA java debugger JSwat is an extensible, standalone, graphical Java debugger front-end, written to use the Java Platform Debugger Architecture (JPDA) package provided by JavaSoft. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Time [+0730] (TZ) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Technical Architecture (JIEO, mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTAG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Test Action Group (org., Philips, IC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jump Trace Buffer (CPU) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTBP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job To Be Processed [block] (BS2000) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTBPX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job To Be Processed [block] eXtension (BS2000) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTC1
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Technical Committee 1 (ISO, IEC, IT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jtex-base
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
basic jTeX library files. jTeX is a TeX for Japanese language. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jtex-bin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese TeX (NTT version) and other japanese tex staffs. JTeX is TeX for Japanese text based on the original Knuth&apos;s TeX. Include: jtex, jlatex, amsjtex (amsjtex depends on tetex-extra package) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Job Transfer and Manipulation (ISO 8831/32) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Justification based Truth Maintenance System (AI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JTSSG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Telecommunications Standards Steering Group (mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JUGHEAD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jonzy&apos;s Universal Gopher Hierarchy Excavation And Display From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
juice
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
playlist editor / player frontend Juice is a frontend for mpg123 and other players. It provides a nifty dialog-based playlist editor. It basically allows you to browse through your files in a &quot;Midnight Commander&quot;-like fashion. The MP3&apos;s you select are treated as a playlist which can be shuffled, rearranged, saved, etc. In order to play audio files, two player interfaces are provided. The mpg123-specific interface uses the remote protocol of mpg123 (This feature was introduced in version 0.59r in order to accommodate generic frontends.) The other player frontend is generic and allows for any player to be used. This is useful if you do not want to limit the functionality of juice to MP3&apos;s. Please note that this generic frontend is still in early beta phase and is pretty buggy. Of course juice comes with all the bells &amp; whistles you&apos;d expect from a quality application and has (among others) full integrated help functionality as well as full dialog based configuration file editor. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
juke
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A curse based jukebox program. Juke is a simple curses/ ncurses based juke box program for Unix computers. It uses command line based players to play all kinds of music format. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JUMBO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Universal Molecular Browser for Objects (XML) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JUNET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japan Unix NETwork (network, Unix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
junit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Automated testing framework for Java JUnit is a simple framework for writing and running automated tests. As a political gesture, it celebrates programmers testing their own software. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
junit-freenet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
basic reimplementation of the JUnit unit testing framework This is a basic reimplementation of the JUnit unit testing framework, it was just an afternoons hack, so for real testing you  may still wish to use JUnit, but developing against this should avoid any  questions regarding licensing. This code is written without the authorization or knowledge of the original JUnit authors, and bears no relation to their code short of containing the same class, method, and field names. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
junkbuster
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Internet Junkbuster! Junkbuster is an instrumentable proxy that filters the HTTP stream between web servers and browsers.  It can prevent ads and other unwanted junk from appearing in your web browser. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
junkfilter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A junk-email filtering program for procmail This package uses procmail filtering algorithms to detect junk email. This results in internal procmail variables being assigned to indicate the reason why the email has been classified as junk. The user can then use those variables within their .procmailrc file to deal with the junk in any way they see fit. There are a number of filters available in the package, and can be selected from a simple config file on a per-user basis. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
justification
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The positioning of text along the document margins in a word processing application. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JVC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
J++ Visual Compiler (MS, Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JVIDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Visually Integrated Display System (mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jvim-canna
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanized VIM (Canna version) JVIM 3.0 is Japanized VIM (VI clone editor) by K.Tsuchida &lt;ken_t@st.rim.or.jp&gt; on May 5, 2001 (patch version 2.1a). This editor can utilize the canna-server in &quot;canna&quot; package directly without other extra libraries (i.e. libonew) in order to enter &quot;Kanji&quot; from kon (Kanji linux cONsole) in kon2 package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JVM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Java Virtual Machine (Java) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JVM (Java Virtual Machine)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Java runtime environment, required for the running of Java programs, which includes a Java interpreter. A different JVM is required for each unique operating system (Linux, OS/2, Windows 98, etc.), but any JVM can run the same version of a Java program. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jw
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
(Jade Wrapper) converts SGML files to other formats From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jwhois
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Improved Caching Whois client GNU jwhois is an Internet Whois client that queries hosts for information according to RFC 954 - NICNAME/WHOIS. JWHOIS is configured via a configuration file that contains information about all known Whois servers. Upon execution, the host to query is selected based on the information in the configuration file. The configuration file is highly customizable and makes heavy use of regular expressions. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
JWICS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Joint Worldwide Intelligence Communications System (mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jython
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Python seamlessly integrated with Java Jython is an implementation of the high-level, dynamic, object-oriented language Python seamlessly integrated with the Java platform.  The predecessor to Jython, JPython, is certified as 100% Pure Java. Jython is complementary to Java and allows the two languages to be freely mixed.  It is especially suited for embedded scripting, interactive experimentation and rapid application development, and it can interact with Java packages or with running Java applications. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
jzip
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Text mode interpreter for Z-Code adventures, etc. This package provides the jzip Z-Code interpreter required to run Infocom or Inform-generated text adventures, although the format can be used for more than games. It is based on the zip interpreter sources and adapted by John D. Holder &lt;jholder@frii.com&gt;. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossary>
