<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="K">
<title>K</title>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
K Desktop Environment (KDE)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical desktop interface designed with free software tools and libraries for the free software community. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
K12LTSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K12LTSP is a terminal server appliance distribution of Red Hat Linux. It&apos;s easy to install and configure.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
k3b
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K3b is CD-writing software which intends to be feature-rich and provide an easily usable interface. Features include burning audio CDs from .WAV and .MP3 audio files, configuring external programs and configuring devices. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
k6fftwgel2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Library for computing Fast Fourier Transforms on AMD K6-2 This library computes Fast Fourier Transforms (FFT) in one or more dimensions. It is extremely fast. This package contains the documentation and the shared version of the libraries. To get the static library and the header files you need to install k6fftwgel-dev. This library uses the same interface as fftw so should be a drop-in replacement, but is currently limited to single precision only. The code is tuned for AMD k6-2 processors and can be as much as three times as fast as vanilla fftw. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
k7fftwgel2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Library for computing Fast Fourier Transforms on AMD K7 This library computes Fast Fourier Transforms (FFT) in one or more dimensions. It is extremely fast. This package contains the documentation and the shared version of the libraries. To get the static library and the header files you need to install k7fftwgel-dev. This library uses the same interface as fftw so should be a drop-in replacement, but is currently limited to single precision only. The code is tuned for AMD k7 processors and can be as much as three times as fast as vanilla fftw. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kab
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An addressbook for KDE This is the KDE Addressbook From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kabalone
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Abalone board game for KDE Abalone is a simple board strategy game that is played by two players. There are red and yellow pieces for each player. Beginning from a start position where each player has 14 pieces, moves are drawn until one player has pushed 6 pieces of his opponent out of the board From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kaffe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A JVM to run Java bytecode This is Kaffe, a virtual machine designed to execute Java bytecode. It performs &quot;just-in-time&quot; code conversion from the abstract code to the host machine&apos;s native code.  This will ultimately allow execution of Java code at the same speed as standard compiled code but while maintaining the advantages and flexibility of code independence. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kakasi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KAnji KAna Simple Inverter KAKASI is the language processing filter to convert Kanji characters to Hiragana, Katakana or Romaji(1) and may be helpful to read Japanese documents. The name &quot;KAKASI&quot; is the abbreviation of &quot;kanji kana simple inverter&quot; and the inverse of SKK &quot;simple kana kanji converter&quot; which is developed by Masahiko Sato at Tohoku University. The most entries of the kakasi dictionary is derived form the SKK dictionaries. If you have some interests in the naming of &quot;KAKASI&quot;, please consult to Japanese-English dictionary. :-) (1) &quot;Romaji&quot; is alphabetical description of Japanese pronunciation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kakasi-dic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KAKASI dictionary files This package provides KAKASI dictionary files. You have to install this package if you use KAKASI. KAKASI is the language processing filter to convert Kanji characters to Hiragana, Katakana or Romaji(1) and may be helpful to read Japanese documents. (1) &quot;Romaji&quot; is alphabetical description of Japanese pronunciation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kaladix Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The aim of Kaladix Linux is to become a ultra-secure Linux distribution that satisfied all your needs as a Linux for your server environment. Current release is pre-0.4. A &apos;secured&apos; distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kallsyms
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Extract all kernel symbols for debugging From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kamera
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
digital camera io_slave for Konqueror This is a digital camera io_slave for KDE which uses gphoto2 and libgpio to allow access to your camera&apos;s pictures with the URL kamera:/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kamera
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kamera adds support for digital cameras to KDE. After installing kamera, you can access your digital camera just like a filesystem from KDE applications. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KriminalAktenNachweis (INPOL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kanadic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Katakana and hiragana drill files for KDrill Those files let you pratice your basics katakana and hiragana with kdrill. It includes both the basic version and the extended versions. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kandy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Mobile phone utility for KDE At the moment Kandy is more or less a terminal program with some special features to store commands and their parameters, but is also has a simple GUI to access the phone book of a mobile phone and it is able to save this phone book to the KDE address book. Kandy is aimed at mobile phones with integrated (GSM) modems. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kannel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WAP and SMS gateway Kannel is a gateway for connecting WAP (Wireless Application Protocol) phones to the Internet. It also works as an SMS gateway, for providing SMS based services for GSM phones. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kapptemplate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
creates a framework to develop a KDE application KAppTemplate is a shell script that will create the necessary framework to develop various KDE applications.  It takes care of the autoconf/automake code as well as providing a skeleton and example of what the code typically looks like. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kaptain
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical front-end for command line programs (KDE version) Kaptain is a universal graphical front-end (KDE) based on context-free grammars. The program kaptain reads a file containing grammatical rules for generating text. It builds a dialog from the grammar and generates the text according to the user&apos;s settings. There&apos;s also Qt version of this package (captain) if you don&apos;t want to install KDE libraries. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KARL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? [hardware description language] (HDL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
karm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A time tracker for KDE KArm is a time tracker for busy people who need to keep track of the amount of time they spend on various tasks. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
karpski
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
ethernet analyzer and sniffer This is a GTK based packet analyzer.  Its abilities as a sniffer or scanner are limited, but this sniffer is much easier to use than other popular sniffers such as tcpdump.  In addition,  there is a protocol definition file in which other protocols can be added. Karpski may also be used to launch programs against addresses on your local network and as a local network intrusion tool. For more information: http://mojo.calyx.net/~btx/karpski.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kascade
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Client for Kascade, a distributed Open directory search-engine Kascade is a novel type of search-engine, based on the Open directory principle. This means that anyone can structure a small part of the information on the internet, corresponding to their personal interests or expertise. The resulting parts are placed in a large categorical structure that others can browse to search for information. Examples of Open Directory initiatives are Dmoz and Infomarker. In contrast with other Open Directory initiatives, though, the parts that people maintain now reside on their own server. What results is a distributed Open Directory! As with Gnutella, though, there are no fixed central servers. This implies that anyone can start a new structure. Actually any piece can be easily replaced, hopefully leading to competitive improvement. The distributed nature and lack of central control facilities make for a system immune to company or government control, much like Gnutella and the Internet itself. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kasteroids
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Asteroids for KDE You know this game.  It is based on Warwick Allison&apos;s QwSpriteField widget. The objective of kasteroids is to destroy all the asteroids on the screen to advance to the next level. Your ship is destroyed if it makes contact with an asteroid. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
text editor for KDE Kate is a fast text editor for the KDE desktop with an Emacs-style document interface. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kate-plugins
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
plugins for Kate, the KDE text editor This package contains a variety of useful plugins for Kate, the Emacs-styled text editor for KDE.  The plugins can be loaded through the plugin manager in Kate settings. Highlights include HTML tag insertion, insertion of shell command output, opening of include files, a project manager and a text filter. This package is part of the KDE addons module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
katomic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Atomic Entertainment Handbook This is a puzzle game, in which the object is to assemble a molecule from its atoms on a Sokoban-like board.  On each move, an atom goes as far as it can in a specified direction before being stopped by a wall or another atom. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KiloByte From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
See kilobit (Kb). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
See kilobyte (KB). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbabel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a PO-file editor for KDE KBabel is a gettext message (PO file) editor for KDE. It is designed to make editing and managing PO files easy. It includes full navigational and editing capabilities, syntax checking and statistics. A catalog manager is also included, which allows you to keep track of many PO files at once. KBabel is designed to help you to translate fast and consistently. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbackgammon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Backgammon game for KDE KBackgammon is a backgammon program for KDE2. It is based on the code, ideas and concepts of KFibs (which is a FIBS client for KDE1). For a short time, KBackgammon was called bacKgammon (if you know somebody who is still using bacKgammon, please force them to upgrade :-)). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbackup
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A console single host backup solution for various media From the Documentation: It is one of the most powerful backup packages around, supporting a wide range of devices and options. For reasons of portability and reliability it uses the well-established afio and tar programs for writing archives. It greatly extends the capabilities of these archive handlers, providing all the features you might expect from a full-fledged backup system. It can be easily and extensively configured and operated with a user friendly menu interface and can also run automatically for doing scheduled backups without user interaction. Among the features are: compressed archives, encrypted archives, double buffering, automatic handling of multi-volume archives, tape archives, floppy archives, hard disk archives, file archives, incremental backups, scheduled backups, extensive manual. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbackup-multibuf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Multibuf extends kbackup for multiple volumes multibuf is a tape archive manager which provides the capability of extending a single logical archive over multiple physical media volumes. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbattleship
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Battleship game for KDE This is an implementation of the Battleship game.  Each player tries to be the first to sink all the opponent&apos;s ships by firing &quot;blindly&quot; at them.  The game has options to play over a network connection or against the computer. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux console font and keytable utilities. This package allows you to set up the Linux console, change the font, resize text mode virtual consoles and remap the keyboard. It now contains the `openvt&apos; program, formerly known as `open&apos;. It now contains the `kbdrate&apos; program, formerly part of the `util-linux&apos; package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The kbd package contains tools for managing a Linux system&apos;s console&apos;s behavior, including the keyboard, the screenfonts, the virtual terminals and font files. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbd-compat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wrappers around console-tools for backward compatibility with `kbd&apos;. This package provides the following wrapper scripts, for compatibility with old `kbd&apos; package, for programs which depends on the former&apos;s command-line interfaces:  setfont, loadunimap, saveunimap, mapscrn. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbdconfig
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The kbdconfig utility is a terminal mode program which provides a simple interface for setting the keyboard map for your system. You need keyboard maps to use any keyboard other than the US default keyboard. Kbdconfig will load the selected keymap before exiting and configure your machine to use that keymap automatically after rebooting. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbdrate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
reset the keyboard repeat rate and delay time From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbd_mode
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
report or set the keyboard mode From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbear
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical ftp client for KDE KBear is a graphical ftp client with ability to connect to multiple hosts simultaneously. You can copy/move files or directories between the hosts by drag and drop or cut and paste. It also has a dynamic site database. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kbedic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K Bulgarian/English Dictionary KBE Dictionary is an electronic dictionary with graphical user interface.  It can translate words from English to Bulgarian and from Bulgarian to English.  You can use it to learn English too -- it can examine you. The dictionary databases are not included in this package.  You have to download bedic-data.tar.gz from http://kbedic.sourceforge.net/download.php.  Install the files buleng.dat and engbul.dat in /usr/local/share/bedic. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kblackbox
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A simple logical game for the KDE project KBlackBox is a game of hide and seek played on an grid of boxes. Your opponent (Random number generator, in this case) has hidden several balls within this box. By shooting rays into the box and observing where they emerge it is possible to deduce the positions of the hidden balls. The fewer rays you use to find the balls, the lower your score. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KBPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KiloBits Per Second From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kbps
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
One Thousand bps, actual number is 1024 bps. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KBS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge-Based System From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcalc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE pocket calculator. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kanji code filter kcc can converts various Japanese encodings such as EUC-JP, 7bitJIS, 8bitJIS and ShiftJIS with Half-width Kana supports. kcc can detect these encoding automatically as much as possible. Sponsored by Fumitoshi UKAI &lt;ukai@debian.or.jp&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KCC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge Consistency Checker (AD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a CD player applet for KDE Kicker Kcd provides a docklet for the KDE Kicker which has some controls (previous, play, pause, stop, next, eject) and displays elapsed/remaining play-time. It also features CDDB support. This is an early development version for testing purposes. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KCGI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kyocera ??? (Kyocera) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KCGL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KyoCera Graphic Language (Kyocera) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcharselect
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE Character Selector - allows you to enter characters not found on your keyboard. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcharselect
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE character selector. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kchart
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a chart drawing program for the KDE Office Suite From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kchart
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a chart drawing program for the KDE Office Suite KChart is a chart drawing application. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcmlinuz
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE Frontend for the Linux kernel configuration kcmlinuz is a KDE based frontend to Linux kernel configuration. It runs out of the KDE Control Center. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcolorchooser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Colour chooser for KDE. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcoloredit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An editor for palette files This is a color palette editor for KDE. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcoloredit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Colour editor for KDE. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcpuload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a CPU meter for Kicker A simple CPU meter for the KDE Kicker which displays percent usage, with support for SMP and separate user/system loads. It will show the CPU usage in form of one or two configurable diagrams. There are settings for colors and some different styles. Note that it isn&apos;t the real system load that&apos;s shown, but the percent used of the total CPU power, which is calculated from the number of CPU ticks. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcron
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Crontab editor for KDE Crontab editor for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kcron
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Views and sets cron daemon configuration. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdbg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical debugger interface KDbg is a graphical user interface to gdb, the GNU debugger. It provides an intuitive interface for setting breakpoints, inspecting variables, and stepping through code. KDbg requires KDE but you can of course debug any program. Features:  * Inspection of variable values in a tree structure.  * Direct member: For certain compound data types the most important    member values are displayed next to the variable name, so that it is    not necessary to expand the subtree of that variable in order to see    the member value. KDbg can also display Qt 2&apos;s QString values, which    are Unicode strings.  * Debugger at your finger tips: The basic debugger functions (step,    next, run, finish, until, set/clear/enable/disable breakpoint) are    bound to function keys F5 through F10. Quick and easy.  * View source code, search text, set program arguments and environment    variables, display arbitrary expressions.  * Debugging of core dumps, attaching to running processes is possible.  * Conditional breakpoints. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdbg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDbg is a graphical user interface to gdb, the GNU debugger. It provides an intuitive interface for setting breakpoints, inspecting variables, and stepping through code. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Key Distribution Center, Verschluesselung From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
see key distribution center (KDC). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kokusai Denshin Denwa (org., Japan) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K Destop Environment (Linux, KDE) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kde
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The K Desktop Environment A metapackage containing dependencies for the core suite of KDE including kdelibs, kdebase, kdeadmin, kdegraphics, kdemultimedia, kdenetwork, kdepim, koffice, and kdeutils.  Provides Suggests and Recommends for all other KDE based packages. Does not contain depends for Toys, Games, or Development packages. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDE (K Desktop Environment)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
One of several user interfaces (window managers) for Linux, built with Qt. For more on KDE, go to www.kde.org. (Also, see AfterStep, Enlightenment, GNOME and X Window System.) From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDE Desktop Environment
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a completely new desktop, incorporating a large suite of applications for Unix workstations. While KDE includes a window manager, file manager, panel, control center and many other components that one would expect to be part of a contemporary desktop environment, the true strength of this exceptional environment lies in the interoperability of its components. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kde-designer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Qt GUI Designer (With KDE Widget support) This package contains Qt Designer.  Qt Designer is a tool that makes designing and implementing user interfaces a lot easier.  With Qt Designer, you will learn how to create your own dialogs and how to arrange the user interface elements in the dialogs so that the dialogs look both nice and natural and can accommodate various environments, like different languages and user settings. This package contains KDE widget support From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kde-devel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The K Desktop Environment (development files) A metapackage containing dependencies for the core development suite of KDE including libqt-dev, kdelibs-dev and all other core KDE development packages. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kde-extras
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The K Desktop Environment (extras) A metapackage containing dependencies for the non-core KDE packages including those packages which may not be suitable for all users.  This may also include packages which could potentially open up security risks or depend on packages which may.  This would include packages such as klisa, kwuftpd, ktalkd, and lilo-config. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdeaddons-kicker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Plugins and additional applets for Kicker (the KDE panel) From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdeaddons-knewsticker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Scripts extending the functionality of KNewsTicker From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdeaddons-konqueror
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Plugins extending the functionality of Konqueror. kdeaddons-konqueror contains, among other things, plugins for translating webpages, checking web pages for valid HTML code, and viewing the DOM tree of web pages. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdeadmin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The kdeadmin package contains packages that usually only a system administrator might need:
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdeartwork
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Additional artwork (themes, sound themes, ...) for KDE From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdebase
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Core applications for the K Desktop Environment.  Included are: kdm(replacement for xdm), kwin (window manager), konqueror (filemanager, web browser, ftp client, ...), konsole (xterm replacement), kpanel (application starter and desktop pager), kaudio (audio server), kdehelp (viewer for kde help files, info and man pages), kthememgr (system for managing alternate theme packages) plus other KDEcomponents (kcheckpass, kikbd, kscreensaver, kcontrol, kfind, kfontmanager, kmenuedit). From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdebase
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Core applications for the K Desktop Environment. Here is an overview of the directories:
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdebase-crypto
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE crypto control module This package contains the crypto control module for KDE which allows for configuration of SSL settings. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdebase-libs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE libraries and modules for kdebase This package contains the different interface modules and libraries provided by the kdebase package.  These includes interfaces to pop3, nntp and others. This package also contains kdesu. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdecarddecks
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Card decks for KDE games Several different collections of card images for use by KDE games. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdegames
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Games and gaming libraries for the K Desktop Environment. Included with this package are: kenolaba, kasteroids, kblackbox, kmahjongg, kmines, konquest, kpat, kpoker, kreversi, ksame, kshisen, ksokoban, ksmiletris, ksnake, ksirtet, katomic, kjumpingcube, ktuberling. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdegraphics
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical tools for the K Desktop Environment. kdegraphics is a collection of graphic oriented applications:
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdelibs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Libraries for the K Desktop Environment. KDE Libraries include: kdecore (KDE core library), kdeui (userinterface), kfm (file manager), khtmlw (HTML widget), kio (Input/Output, networking), kspell (spelling checker), jscript (javascript), kab (addressbook), kimgio (image manipulation). From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdemultimedia
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Multimedia tools for the K Desktop Environment.
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdenetwork
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Networking applications for the K Desktop Environment. - kdict: graphical client for the DICT protocol. - kit: AOL instant messenger client, using the TOC protocol - kmail: universal mail client - kmailcvt: converst addressbooks to kmail format - knewsticker: RDF newsticker applet - knode: online newsreader - korn: new mail notification tool - kpf: public fileserver applet - ksirc: IRC client - ktalkd: talk daemon - kxmlrpc: KDE XmlRpc Daemon - lanbrowsing: lan browsing kio slave - krfb: Desktop Sharing server, allow others to access your desktop via VNC - krdc: a client for Desktop Sharing and other VNC servers From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdepalettes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
palettes that match the KDE standard colour palette KDEPalettes provides palettes for both the Gimp and Xpaint that match the KDE standard color palette.  They may be useful for designing themes and icons. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdepasswd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Password changer frontend for KDE This is a simple app for users to change their system passwords with. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdepasswd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE frontend to changing your password and other user data. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdepim
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A PIM (Personal Information Manager) for KDE. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdepim
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Information Management applications for the K Desktop Environment.
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdesdk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE Software Development Kit This is a collection of applications and tools used by KDE developers. It also has example code for use in learning KDE programming or starting a new KDE application. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdessh
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Frontend to ssh for KDE This is a frontend to ssh designed for use with KDE.  This program is designed for the purpose of executing commands on a remote system using ssh. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdestudio
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a powerful development environment for KDE KDE Studio is an integrated development environment for the KDE. It delivers a full-fledged IDE for the development of sophisticated C++ KDE applications - including the high utility features you expect from a modern development environment, such as code completion, dynamic syntax highlighting and popup function parameter lookup. Debugging is simplified by tight integration with kdbg in the IDE. KDE Studio supports complex projects, composed of multiple executables, static or shared libraries, all in one centralized workspace, including support for multiple targets from a single project. You can explore the structure of your classes with an intuitive tree view. Functions and data members are exposed for a quick understanding of library structures. The class tree is updated on the fly while you type your code. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdetoys
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Toys for the K Desktop Environment. Software included in this package are:
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdeutils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Utilities for the K Desktop Environment.
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdevelop
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An IDE for Unix/X11 KDevelop is an easy to use Integrated Development Environment for developing C/C++ applications under X11. It features project management, an advanced editor, a class browser and an integrated debugger. The application wizard can generate fully functional projects for terminal programs and GUI programs using Qt, KDE or GNOME. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdevelop
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The KDevelop Integrated Development Environment provides many features that developers need as well as providing a unified interface to programs like gdb,the C/C++ compiler, and make. KDevelop manages or provides:   * All development tools needed for C++ programming like Compiler, Linker,     automake and autoconf   * KAppWizard, which generates complete, ready-to-go sample applications   * Classgenerator, for creating new classes and integrating them into the     current project   * File management for sources, headers, documentation etc. to be included in     the project   * The creation of User-Handbooks written with SGML and the automatic     generation of HTML-output with the KDE look and feel   * Automatic HTML-based API-documentation for your project&apos;s classes with     cross-references to the used libraries; Internationalization support for     your application, allowing translators to easily add their target language     to a project   * WYSIWYG (What you see is what you get) creation of user interfaces with a     built-in dialog editor   * Debugging your application by integrating KDbg   * Editing of project-specific pixmaps with KIconEdit   * The inclusion of any other program you need for development by adding it to     the &quot;Tools&quot; menu according to your individual needs. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdewallpapers
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Some wallpapers for KDE The wallpapers that come with KDE, but can be used everywhere else as well From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Disk space GUI for KDE This program shows the disk usage of the mounted devices. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
kdeutils-kdf contains the kdf, kwikdisk and kcmdf tools for monitoring available diskspace. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdict
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
dict client based on KDE/Qt kdict is an advanced kde graphical client for the DICT Protocol, with full unicode support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K Display Manager (KDE) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The K Desktop Manager The K Desktop Manager kdm manages a collection of X servers, which may be on the local host or remote machines.  It provides services similar to those provided by init, getty, and login on character-based terminals: prompting for login name and password, authenticating the user, and running a session.  kdm supports XDMCP (X Display Manager Control Protocol) and can also be used to run a chooser process which presents the user with a menu of possible hosts that offer XDMCP display management. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdoc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
C++ and IDL Source Documentation System KDOC creates cross-referenced documentation for C++ and CORBA IDL libraries directly from the source. Documentation can be embedded in special documents in the source. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdrill
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Kanji drill and dictionary program Offers lot of options like guessing kanji, guessing meaning, by grade or even from a selected kanji list. You can even practice your kana. A kanjidic is essential to run this program although you can specify your own dictionary on the command line. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KDT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keyboard Display Terminal From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kdvi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A DVI (TeX output) file viewer for KDE. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kedit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A simple text editor for KDE A simple text editor for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kedit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An easy to use text editor From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Keeper Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keeper Linux fits on two floppy disks. It is designed for use in specific application areas, such as dedicated network gateways, firewalls and the administration of remote systems. Release 1.1a came out March 14, 2002. Version KLX-2.01, released April 23, 2002, boots directly from CDROM with its root filing system in ramdisk (no hard disk required). A &apos;special purpose/mini&apos; distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kerberos
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An authentication standard. History: Developed at MIT in the 1980s as part of its project Athena (the netpc product that also spawned X Windows and other technologies). Kerberos has long been available as an add-on to virtually all UNIX systems. Version 4 was discovered to be insecure, and was followed by version 5. Microsoft implemented a variant of version 5 in Win2k. Key point: Microsoft&apos;s implementation in Win2k is not quite standard in much the same way that its implementations of PPP, PPTP, IPsec, etc. all make use of proprietary extensions. Kerberos: DES From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kerberos
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Network authentication system developed by the Massachusets Institute of Technology to control access to services and applications. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kerberos
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The authentication system of MIT&apos;s Project Athena. It is based on symmetric key cryptography. Adopted by OSF as the basis of security for DME. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kermit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A terminal program and file transfer protocol, kermit can be used to download files from a remote system to your home computer. Kermit is distinguished by it&apos;s ability to transfer files over telnet and other connections that would corrupt a binary transfer. It is often available as a Unix command. From KADOWKEV
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kermit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An asynchronous communications protocol that makes the error-free transmission of program files via the telephone system easier. Developed by Columbia University and placed in the public domain, Kermit is used by academic institutions because, unlike XMODEM, Kermit can be implemented on mainframe systems that transmit 7 bits per byte. See communications protocol. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KERMIT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kl-10 Error-free Reciprocal Micro Interconnect over Tty lines From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In an operating system, the core portions of the program that reside in memory and perform the most essential operating ystem tasks, such as handling disk input output operations and managing the internal memory. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Part of an operating system that implements the interaction with hardware and the sharing of resources.
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The core of the operating system, upon which all other components rely. The kernel manages such tasks as low-level hardware interaction and the sharing of resources, including memory allocation, input/output, security, and user access. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The core of the operating system. The kernel has complete control over everything that happens. When your computer crashes, it means the kernel has crashed. If only a single program crashes but the rest of the system remains running, then the kernel itself hasn&apos;t crashed. The kernel is designed to coordinate among the different components of the operating system, such as disk drive, networking, keyboard, and running programs. Key point: The kernel is responsible for security, preventing one program from one user from breaking into other programs running on the same system. All systems except the older Mac and Windows do not provide this level of security. Key point: The kernel itself does not interact with the user. For example, the word &quot;Linux&quot; really means just the kernel. What we see in Linux distributions is actually the kernel plus a whole bunch of UNIX-like applications built on top of it. Contrast: There are two modes your software might be running in. Kernel mode is running within the context of the kernel itself, and describes not only the kernel but also device drivers. User mode is the context the rest of the software runs in. The key point is that when you are running in kernel mode, you&apos;ve got access to the entire system and nobody can stop you. However, when you are running in user mode (especially when not logged in as root), then the kernel imposes security on your activity. This means that if you break into a normal HTTP server, you may not actually be able to break into the entire machine. However, newer versions of the Linux kernel are putting things like HTTP servers into the kernel itself (for performance reasons). An exploitable flaw in such services will allow the entire machine to be compromised. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The critical piece of an operating system; performs the basic functions that more advanced functions depend on. Linux is based on the kernel developed by Linus Torvalds and a group of core developers. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the fundamental part of the operating system that handles resource management, process control, and Input/Output (I/O) support. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The kernel package contains the Linux kernel (vmlinuz), the core of the Red Hat Linux operating system. The kernel handles the basic functions of the operating system: memory allocation, processallocation, device input and output, etc. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kernel headers
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The header files define structures and constants that are needed for building most standard programs. The header files are also needed for rebuilding the kernel. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernel-source
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The kernel-source package contains the source code files for the Linux kernel. These source files are needed to build most C programs, since they depend on the constants defined in the source code. The source files can also be used to build a custom kernel that is better tuned to your particular hardware. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernellab
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Manage kernel configs for many machines easily Kernellab allows you to manage kernel configurations for a large number of heterogenous machines relatively easily. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kernelversion
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
program to report major version of kernel From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KES
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Key Escrow System (cryptography) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ketm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An old-school 2d-scrolling shooter A hicolor/hiresolution classical game that has similarities with Raptor, Tyrian and Galaga. You are a spacepilot controlling your secret prototype ship. At regular interval&apos;s you get attacked by the bad guys. You have a mission to clean this sector from them (ie. Kill Everything That Moves). Be sure to pick up some weapon and ship upgrades on the way. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kexample
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a simple KDE demo application for programmers This package provides KLess, a simple KDE demo application with heavily documented source code.  KLess is a basic text viewer. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
key
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In cryptography, the value needed to encrypt and/or decrypt something. It is usually a number or a short string less than 20 characters long. Contrast: People are confused as to the difference between a key and a password. A key is a large number whereas a password is simply a series of letters (and possibly digits and punctuation). Since cryptography only uses keys, the password is generally converted to a number through the use of an appropriate mathematical function, like a hash. Public/private keys present a special difficulty in that they contain extremely large, unwieldy numbers that are protected by a separate password. Contrast: There are two types of keys: symmetric keys use the same key for both encryption and decryption asymmetric (aka. public/private key) are produced in pairs, where one key encrypts, but a mirror key must be used to decrypt the message, and somebody with one key cannot figure out the other key. Contrast: A common question deals with the difference between 40-bit and 128-bit encryption in web browsers like Netscape. The answer is that the most obvious way to break the encryption and read the plain text is to simply try all possible keys. A 40-bit key has roughly one trillion (1,000,000,000,000) combinations. It could take your computer several weeks to try all these combinations. The implication: the average person only needs a few weeks to decrypt any message you send across the wire with a 40-bit browser, should they manage to sniff it from the wire. Every extra bit of key length means the key will take twice as long to crack. Therefore, if a system takes one week to crack a 40-bit key, it will take two weeks to crack a 41-bit key. Therefore, a 128-bit key will take 2^(128-40) times longer to crack than a 40-bit key (i.e. 309,485,009,821,345,068,724,781,056 times longer). Example: The following table shows the relative difficulty in cracking keys (circa year 2000). Bits Difficulty 8 paper and pencil (puzzle appears in Sunday paper) 16 tiny computer 32 your desktop computer 40 a few computers and a fair amount of time 56 custom hardware 64 distributed.net (a hundred thousand machine cranking away for a couple of years) 80 government agencies (NSA, CIA) 128 not crackable at the current time 256 quantum computers Key point: Moore&apos;s Law breaks all cryptosystems, eventually. This, and only this, is why DES has become obsolete. Note: 40-bit and 128-bit keys mean the RC4 algorithm used within web-browsers to talk to web servers via SSL. The U.S. restricts export of all software whose keys are greater than 40-bits in order to be able to spy on foreigners (ostensibly only in a military engagement). Key point: You can classify keys according to their lifetimes: In PKI, &quot;session keys&quot; are randomly generated and last only the lifetime of the connection. The public/private keys are used to exchange them so that people eavesdropping on the wire cannot figure out what they are. Longer term keys are often based upon a hash of a password and are explicitly generated by the user. An example would be a user who encrypts a file with a key. Key point: The Kerckhoff principle states that cryptography should be based upon the assumption that the enemy will discover all the details of your system. Therefore, all the security of the system should be held within the key. Not only that, the idea is that the details of the system should be actively published and publicized in the hopes that people will analyze the system, discover them, and publish the weaknesses before the enemy gets a chance to. All the best cryptosystems have been well published and analyzed in public forums. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
key
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Unique identifier used to encrypt or decrypt secure data. Encrypted data must have a key to be decrypted. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
key distribution center (KDC)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
System that distributes and manages shared and private keys for authentication of network sessions and access to applications. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keybled
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE keyboard LED applet KeybLED is a Panel applet which displays a keyboard&apos;s LED status. It is particulary useful for keyboards which lack their own LED status indicators (e.g. cordless keyboards), or just for the fun! It utilizes the XTest X-server extension of keyboard indicator state changes. Features:  * Configurable LED size, shape, look, colour, LED orientation (vertical/    horizontal), label size and label location (left/right, top/bottom, hidden);  * Ability to select which LEDs are displayed;  * Ability to turn on or off LEDs on startup;  * An LED&apos;s status can be toggled with the mouse;  * Clicking on the applet pops up an indicator showing which LEDs are    activated. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keyboard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Computer system peripheral that users operate by tapping buttons to display characters on a monitor or other output. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keyboard-properties
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
allows you to configure your keyboard. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keychain
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An OpenSSH key manager Keychain is an OpenSSH key manager, typically run from ~/.bash_profile.  When run, it will make sure ssh-agent is running; if not, it will start ssh-agent. It will redirect ssh-agent&apos;s output to ~/.ssh-agent, so that cron jobs that need to use ssh-agent keys can simply source this file and make the necessary passwordless ssh connections.  In addition, when keychain runs, it will check with ssh-agent and make sure that the ssh RSA/DSA keys that you specified on the keychain command line have actually been added to ssh-agent.  If not, you are prompted for the appropriate passphrases so that they can be added by keychain. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keylaunch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A small utility for binding commands to a hot key. KeyLaunch is a small utility for binding commands to a hot key. It reads a configuration file in .keylaunchrc. KeyLaunch uses Ctrl, Alt and Shift as modifier keys, the hotkey is up to the user. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keylookup
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A tool to fetch keys from keyservers A nice console tool written in perl to fetch public keys from keyservers. You give it a keyserver and something to search for and it allows you to select one or several or the resulting keys. It has two user interfaces, plain and dialog. The dialog (which is nicer) it the default one. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keynote
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Decentralized Trust-Management system The KeyNote architecture and language are useful as building blocks for the trust management aspects of a variety of Internet protocols and services. This package contains the keynote binary used to generate and verify KeyNote assertions. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keystroke
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Equivalent to one tap of a keyboard or keypad. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keystroke logger (keylogger)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program that runs in the background that records all the keystrokes. Key point: Once keystrokes are logged, they are shipped raw to the hacker. The hacker then peruses them carefully in the hopes of either finding passwords, or possibly other useful information that could be used to compromise the system or be used in a social engineering attack. For example, a key logger will reveal the contents of all e-mail composed by the user. Key point: Keylog programs are commonly included in rootkits and remote administration trojans. Key point: You can also purchase hardware devices that plug-in between the keyboard and the main system (for PCs). These are OS independent, they simply start recording, then the hacker can retrieve the device and instruct it to simply spit out all the characters back again on the hackers system. History: In November of 2001, the FBI revealed it has developed a keylogger Trojan as part of its Carnivore surveillance technologies. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
keytab-lilo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
compile keytables files for use with LILO From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfax
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Views faxes within the KDE environment. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfile-png
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The PNG KFile plugin allows all applications using KFile (for example, Konqueror) to view information on PNG files. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfind
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE based file finder A KDE based file finder From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfloppy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A floppy disk formatter frontend KFloppy formats disks and puts a DOS or ext2fs filesystem on them From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KFM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K File Manager (KDE) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfocus
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Lightweight project management program for KDE Personal project management program with support for task lists and log books Supports:  - Categorizing tasks into projects  - Viewing how much time you have left to complete a task  - Creating logs of completed tasks  - Scheduling followup tasks when a task is completed  - Scheduling tasks to start in the future From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kformula
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a formula editor for the KDE Office Suite From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kformula
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a formula editor for the KDE Office Suite KFormula is a formula editor that provides the basic input facilities and the support functionality expected of a KOffice application. Features include easy Greek letter insertion, intelligent cursor movement, advanced syntax highlighting, multi-level undo support and LaTeX export. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kforth
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Small Forth Interpreter Written in C++ Implements a subset of ANS Forth, plus some extensions. kForth can serve as a standalone computing environment, or its object code may be interfaced to another program to serve as a customizable programming language for that application. See http://ccreweb.org/software/kforth/kforth.html for more information. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfract
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
fractal generator for KDE Kfract is a generator for fractals. Well, at this early stage it&apos;s only capable of Mandelbrot sets and Julia sets. Nothing fancy like Xfractint. And it&apos;s way far from being as fast as Xfractint. But it&apos;s much easier to use. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kfract
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Generates fractal images. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kftgt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
ticket forwarder for Kerberos 4 The client half of a client/server pair that allows Kerberos 4 tickets to be forwarded to another network host and used to authenticate further services on the network.  This package includes kftgt, for forwarding tickets, and klogin, a script to forward a ticket with kftgt and invoke krlogin in one step.  For the corresponding ticket forwarding server for Kerberos 4, see the kftgtd package. kftgt and kftgtd do not provide ticket forwarding for Kerberos 5, which has built-in ticket forwarding. For now, this package depends on kerberos4kth-clients, because the Debian packages for Kerberos 5 do not properly authenticate to MIT Kerberos 4 servers.  There is hope that this problem will be fixed soon.  When it is, krb5-user will be allowed as an alternative to kerberos4kth-clients. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kftgtd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
ticket forwarder for Kerberos 4 The server half of a client/server pair that allows Kerberos 4 tickets to be forwarded from another network host and used to authenticate further services on the network.  This package contains kftgtd, to receive forwarded tickets.  For the corresponding ticket forward client for Kerberos 4, see the kftgt package. kftgt and kftgtd do not provide ticket forwarding for Kerberos 5, which has built-in ticket forwarding. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kgeo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an interactive geometry program for KDE With this program you can do geometry on a computer just like you would on a blackboard in a classroom.  However, the computer allows you to go beyond that, since KGeo is designed to do interactive geometry. For example, the program allows you to move and change geometrical drawings, so that you can see all the changes.  Imagine a triangle that can be altered into any shape you want, just by moving its corners around.  At the same time you can see that the angles change, but that they always add up to 180 degrees. KGeo was formerly called KEuklid. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kghostview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PostScript viewer for KDE. KGhostview is the PostScript viewer for the K Desktop Environment. It is a port of Tim Theisen&apos;s Ghostview program which is used to view documents prepared in Adobe&apos;s PostScript page description language. PostScript is the major page description language for printing on UNIX systems and this application is used to preview material intended for printing or for reading documents online. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kghostview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Viewer for PostScript and PDF files. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KGRZ
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kommunales GebietsRechenzentrum Giessen (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
khexedit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE hex editor. It allows you to edit binary files. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KHG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel Hacking Guide (Linux) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kuenstliche Intelligenz From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kicker-applets
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
applets for Kicker, the KDE panel This package contains a variety of applets for Kicker, the KDE panel. The applets will appear in the panel&apos;s Add--Applet menu. Included are a system monitor and a colour picker. This package is part of the KDE addons module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kickstart
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A method for automatic Red Hat Linux installations based on settings pre-configured in a special kickstart file. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kiconedit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An icon editor for creating KDE icons KIconedit is an icon editor for creating KDE and other icons From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KIF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Konferenz der Informatik Fachschaften (conference) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kill
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
report process status From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kill
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
send signal to a process From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kill
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
To stop an onging process. In the better UseNet newsreaders, to delete an article containig a certain word, name, or origin site so that articles containing this information do not appear subsequently in the article selector. See article selector, global kill file, and kill file. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
killall
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
kill processes by name From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
killall5
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
send a signal to all processes. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kilobit (Kb)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
1024 bits of data. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kilobyte
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A thousand bytes. Actually, usually 1024 (210) bytes. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kilobyte (KB)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
1024 characters (or bytes) of data. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kimberlite
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
High Availability Clustering Package Kimberlite is a complete framework providing high availability for application services on Linux.  The key features of the architecture include the following:  - A complete high-availability service infrastructure prevents you    from having to assemble an infrastructure from disparate    components.  - An extensible service-configuration framework enables you to    easily integrate a wide variety of applications.  - An exceptional data integrity guarantee differentiates the    software from other contemporary offerings from the Linux    community.  Because of this guarantee, a Kimberlite cluster    provides a solid foundation for highly-available data services,    such as network-exported databases and NFS file systems, and is    ideal as the data tier for dynamic web content.  - Services fail over automatically when problems occur, without    requiring manual intervention by system administrators.  - A command line user interface and a web-based graphical user    interface enable you to monitor and manage the cluster.  - A cluster utilizes commodity hardware and storage options, such as    SCSI and FibreChannel. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kimwitu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Compiler development tool, complementary to lex and yacc. Kimwitu (pronounced kee&apos;mweetoo) is a system that supports the construction of programs that use trees or terms as their main data structure. It is a `meta-tool&apos; in the development process of tools. It can easily be interfaced with Yacc and Lex - the idea is that yacc and lex are used to do the parsing, and Kimwitu routines are used to built and manipulate the parse tree. There is also Kimwitu++ (also packaged for Debian) which interfaces with C++ instead of C. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kimwitu++
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A (syntax-)tree-handling tool (term processor) Kimwitu++ is a system that supports the construction of programs that use trees or terms as their main data structure.  It allows you to define, store and operate on trees with typed nodes. Each type of node has a specific number of sons, and expects these sons to have specific types.  The most popular example of such trees are syntax trees. The nodes are defined in a Yacc-like fashion.  The tree can be unparsed (ie. treewalk) and rewritten (ie. term substitution). Kimwitu++ gives you powerful pattern matching for specifying unparse and rewrite rules. Kimwitu++ is an extension to C++. It introduces Yacc-like node definitions, the unparse and rewrite rules, and extensions for pattern matching within functions. It will translate its input files into pure C++. To build the tree you might use a parser generated with Bison, but you are free to use other tools.  There also exists Kimwitu (also packaged for Debian) which interfaces with C instead of C++ which can also be used in C++ projects, but Kimwitu++ has some extensions one might consider useful. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kinkatta
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
AOL Instant Messenger client for KDE Kinkatta is an instant messenger for AOL. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kino
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Non-linear editor for Digital Video data Kino allows you to record, create, edit, and play movies recorded with DV camcorders. Unlike other editors, this program uses many keyboard commands for fast navigating and editing inside the movie. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kio-fish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
ssh kioslave for konqueror kio_fish is a kioslave for KDE 2.0 that lets you view and manipulate your remote files using just a simple shell account and some standard unix commands on the remote machine. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KIPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kilo Instructions Per Second From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KIR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kyocera Image Refinement (Kyocera) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Kirch, Olaf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
author of the Linux Network Administrator&apos;s Guide. Olaf also moderates the Linux Security Mailing Lists, developing the Linux NFS daemon and a kernel-based nfsd. NFS file locking is also being worked on. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kismet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless 802.11b monitoring tool Kismet is a 802.11b wireless network sniffer.  It is capable of sniffing using almost any wireless card supported in Linux, which currently divide into cards handled by libpcap and the Linux-Wireless extensions (such as Cisco Aironet), and cards supported by the Wlan-NG project which use the Prism/2 chipset (such as Linksys, Dlink, and Zoom). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kiss
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Karel&apos;s Interactive Simple Shell Kiss is basically a simple shell interpreter, like Bash or Tcsh, except that it lacks a good deal of the sophistication of a good shell. On the other hand it is small and well suited for rescue disks. It comes with the following BUILTINS: !, alias, cat, cd, chgrp, chmod, chown, cp, exec, exit, grep, help, history kill, ln, ls, mkdir, mknod, more, mv, printenv, pwd, read, rm, rmdir, setenv, sleep, source, touch, umount, unsetenv, ver, wc, where kiss comes with a bare version, a getline version and a full featured readline version. bkiss, gkiss and rkiss are dynamically linked. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KISS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keep It Simple, Stupid (DFUe, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kissme
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A free Java Virtual Machine kissme is a free Java Virtual Machine for Linux. It uses the GNU Classpath java class library. Currently it can only run console applications (there is no working AWT support in Classpath). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
AOL Instant Messenger frontend for KDE AOL Instant Messenger frontend for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KIT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel software for Intelligent Terminals (T-Online, Telekom, BTX) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kivio
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a flowcharting program for the KDE Office Suite Kivio is a flowcharting program that offers basic flowcharting abilities, but with a twist.  Objects are scriptable, and a backend plugin system offers the ability to make objects do just about anything. Feed it a directory of C++ header files, or even Java files, and let it generate a graphical class map for you.  Give it a network and let it explore and map out the network for you.  All this is possible through the scripting/plugin architecture Kivio possesses. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kjezz
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Jezzball clone for the K Desktop Environment. This is a clone of the popular Jezzball game originally created by Microsoft. Jezzball is one of the rare and simple games requiring skill, timing, and patience in order to be successful. A ball begins to bounce off of an area enclosed by four borders (like a square). You must move your pointer to certain areas within the square. Upon clicking, a new border is constructed at a relatively quick pace. You can change the direction of the borders by 90 degrees as well. Ultimately, you must force the ball to bounce around in a smaller, and smaller area as time goes by without the ball ever touching the borders as they are being constructed. If a ball touches a certain part of the border as it is being built, the game is over. After 75% of the original space has been blocked off from the moving ball, you advance one level, and one more ball is added to the mix in the following level. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kjots
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A small note taker program for KDE kjots is a small note taker program. Name and idea are taken from the jots program included in the tkgoodstuff package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kjots
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KJots is a virtual notepad - you can put notes on your desktop. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kjumpingcube
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tactical one or two player game KJumpingCube is a simple tactical game. You can play it against the computer or against a friend. The playing field consists of squares that contains points.  By clicking on the squares you can increase the points and if the points reach a maximum the points will jump to the squares neighbours and take them over. Winner is the one, who owns all squares. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Konnectivity Koordination (DE-NIC, DOMAIN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klaptopdaemon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
battery monitoring and management for laptops battery monitoring and management for laptops. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kleandisk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a file cleanup and backup tool for KDE Kleandisk searches your system and gives a list of files which can be deleted, backed up or archived.  Kleandisk itself can also be used as a backup and archiving tool. Files are selected for cleaning, backup and archiving according to user-defined file groups, making Kleandisk easy to extend and automate. Automatic scheduled operations are supported. Kleandisk can wrap /usr/bin/install to provide easy uninstallation of files installed using &quot;make install&quot;.  To use this feature, python will need to be present on your system. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KL1 to C compiler system The KLIC implementation compiles KL1 programs into C programs, then compiles them using C compilers of the host system, and then links the objects with runtime libraries (including libraries provided by UNIX). KLIC is an implementation of a concurrent logic programming language KL1.  KL1 is based on a flat version of the Guarded Horn Clauses (GHC) language.  GHC is a member of so-called commited-choice logic programming language family and has sibblings such as Concurrent Prolog, Parlog, Janus and Fleng. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KLICK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Karlsruher LIChtleiter-Kommunikationsnetz (Uni Karlsruhe, Germany) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klines
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Color lines for KDE KLines is a simple game. It is played by one player, so there is only one winner :-). You play for fun and against the high score. It was inspired by a well known game - &quot;Color lines&quot;, written for DOS by Olga Demina, Igor Demina, Igor Ivkin and Gennady Denisov back in 1992. The main rules of the game are as simple as possible: you move (using the mouse) marbles from cell to cell and build lines (horizontal, vertical or diagonal). When a line contains 5 or more marbles, they are removed and your score grows. After each turn the computer drops three more marbles. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KLIPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kilo Logical Inferences Per Second (AI, KI, XPS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klisa
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
LAN information service similar to &quot;Network Neighbourhood&quot; LISa is intended to provide a kind of &quot;Network Neighborhood&quot; but using only the TCP/IP protocol stack, without the SMB protocol. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kljettool
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE Configuration tool for HP LaserJet and compatible printers. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kljettool
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Laser Jet tools for KDE Laser Jet tools for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klogd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel Log Daemon From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klogd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel Logging Daemon The klogd daemon listens to kernel message sources and is responsible for prioritizing and processing operating system messages.  The klogd daemon can run as a client of syslogd or optionally as a standalone program.  Klogd can now be used to decode EIP addresses if it can determine a System.map file. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klpq
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE tool for managing your print spooler. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klpq
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE port of a program called xlpq Klpq is a frontend to lpq, lprm and lpc.  It allows for viewing, deleting, or adjusting print jobs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klprfax
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A LPD fax frontend using efax With this program you can fax by printing to an lpd device. It requires efax of Ed Casas, http://www.ecc.com. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
klprfax
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fax sending support for KDE.kdeutils-klprfax allows any KDE application to treat a fax modem just like a printer. Any KDE application that can print will be able to send faxes. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KLT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Karhunen Loeve Transformation From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KLT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel Latency Time From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge Management From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmago
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE download manager KMAGO stands for MAnager for Get Operations. It is a download manager with a nice GUI interface. KMAGO is built as a frontend for GNU wget currently. Features:  * drag and drop operations with applications (konqueror, netscape) and    between kmago widgets  * system tray icon with drag and drop capabilities  * transfer grouping  * multiple downloads control with priority and selectable priority    policy  * resume capability check  * full configurable  * enabled to manage many retriever commands  * stable and reliable downloading process based on GNU wget From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmahjongg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the classic mahjongg game for KDE project Your mission in this game is to remove all tiles from the game board. A matching pair of tiles can be removed, if they are &apos;free&apos;, which means that no other tiles block them on the left or right side. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A mail client for KDE. KMail supports local mail spools as well as all commonly used Internet mail protocols (POP3, IMAP, SMTP, ...) From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Mail Client based on Qt and KDE Mail Client based on Qt and KDE Supports pop3, pop3s, GPG/PGP From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmailcvt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Converts mailboxes to KMail format. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmerlin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Instant messaging (IM) client for the MSN messenger network KMerlin (f/k/a KMsn) is an IM (instant messaging) client for the MSN messenger network. Features include: A buddy list on which you can block users, multiple chat windows, and multiple users per chat (simply invite those you want in your chat session). Keep in touch with all your Windows friends! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmid
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
midi/karaoke player for KDE midi/karaoke player for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmidi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
midi-to-wav player/converter for KDE midi-to-wav player/converter for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmines
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Minesweeper for KDE KMines is the classic Minesweeper game. You must uncover all the empty cases without blowing on a mine. When you uncover a case, a number appears : it indicates how many mines surround this case. If there is no number the neighbour cases are automatically uncovered. In your process of uncovering secure cases, it is very useful to put a flag on the cases which contain a mine. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmix
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A sound mixer applet for KDE. kmix allows you to control the volumes of your sound card from a KDE panel applet. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmLinux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
kmLinux is developed by the [German] national education server Schleswig-Holstein in co-operation with the association free software and education. It&apos;s a complete Linux system for the personal computer, which can be installed easily. Web site in German.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmoon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
moon phase indicator for KDE Displays the current phase of the moon in the KDE system tray. This package is part of the official KDE toys module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KMOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel of a Multiprocess Operating System (OS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge Management Systeme From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kmtrace
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a KDE memory leak tracer KMtrace is a KDE tool to assist with malloc debugging using glibc&apos;s &quot;mtrace&quot; functionality. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knapster2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE2 Napster client Napster is a popular MP3 sound file download program.  This is a Napster client for KDE 2. It supports searching with criteria, hotlists, transfer management, chat, and a music library with an integral mp3 player. It should work fine with &quot;regular&quot; Napster and Opennap servers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knetfilter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A GUI for configuring the 2.4 kernel IP Tables Knetfilter is a GUI to configure your 2.4 kernel IP firewalling, masquerading and NAT rules. You must have a kernel compiled with iptables (netfilter) support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knetload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a network throughput meter for Kicker A small Network throughput meter for the KDE Kicker which works with just about any network device. It will show the speeds of a network device with two diagrams, one for outgoing and one for incoming data. KNETLoad can read almost any device that is listed in the /proc/net/dev file, which includes eth0, ppp0, ippp0 and many others, even non predefined devices can be typed into the program. The colors, style and speed of the diagrams can be configured. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knews
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical threaded news reader Knews is an X11 based thread-oriented news reader.  It is capable of representing threads as a graphical tree, represents quotations with different colors and much more. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knewsticker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A News ticker for KDE This is a News ticker for the KDE panel.  It can scroll news from your favorite news sites like /. and freshmeat. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knewsticker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KNewsticker is a KDE applet that will display current news from Internet sites of your choice. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knewsticker-scripts
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
scripts for KNewsTicker, the KDE news ticker This package contains a variety of scripts that provide additional news sources for KNewsTicker, the news ticker applet for the KDE panel.  See /usr/share/doc/knewsticker-scripts/README.Debian for usage details. Highlights include newsgroup handling and stock data retrieval. This package is part of the KDE addons module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knewstickerstub
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A stub for the KDE panel news ticker. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KNI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Katmai New Instructions (Intel, ISSE, predecessor) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Query/set kernel image parameters. Set the default root device, root filesystem flags, swap device, ram disk parameters, and video mode. Replaces the rdev, swapdev, rootflags, ramsize and vidmode programs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KNN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kuenstliche Neuronale Netze (neural nets) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knocker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a simple and easy to use TCP security port scanner Knocker is a new, simple, and easy to use TCP security port scanner written in C, using threads. It is able to analyze hosts and the network services which are running on them. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knode
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
News reader for KDE News reader for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KNOOM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KNowledge Orientated Office Model From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KNOPPIX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A German distribution. Take your KNOPPIX CD with you when you&apos;re on the road and run Linux anywhere. KNOPPIX is a complete GNU/Linux installation which runs from CD, with automatic hardware detection and configuration for many graphics and sound cards, SCSI devices, and peripherals. Version 1.5 (the initial Freshmeat announcement) was released May 29, 2002. Version 3.2-2003-06-06 was released June 9, 2003. A CD-based distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KnoppiXMAME
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KnoppiXMAME is a bootable arcade machine emulator with hardware detection and autoconfiguration. It works automatically on all modern and not-so-modern hardware, including gameports and joysticks. It is powered by Knoppix Debian GNU/Linux, X-MAME, and gxmame. Stable version 1.0 was released June 18, 2003. A CD-based distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
knotes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Sticky notes for KDE Sticky notes for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koalamud
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a distributed MUD server. The Koala mud server is designed to be a highly scalable, distributed multiuser roleplaying game.  The game world can be distributed across multiple machines in multiple different locations.  For the purposes of stability, multiple machines can be setup to run the same part of the world. Players can wander around the entirety of the world from any of the client servers that are attached to the network. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kodo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
mouse odometer for KDE KOdometer measures your desktop mileage. It tracks the movement of your mouse pointer across your desktop and renders it in inches/feet/miles!  It can do cm/metres/km too.  Its most exciting feature is the tripometer, and its utter uselessness. This package is part of the official KDE toys module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koffice
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE Office Suite KOffice is an integrated office suite for KDE, the K Desktop Environment.  It offers a word processor, spreadsheet, presentation program, graphics tools and more. This package provides all the components of KOffice. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koffice
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Office applications for the K Desktop Environment.KOffice contains:   * KWord: word processor   * KSpread: spreadsheet   * KPresenter: presentations   * KChart: diagram generator   * KOntour   * Krayon   * Kugar   * Kivio   * Some filters (Excel 97, Winword 97/2000, etc.) From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
komba2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE Samba browser Komba2 is a GUI machine and share browser for the SMB protocol. Komba2 allows you to scan any number of subnets for machines with SMB. The workgroups, machines and share are shown in a tree-view. For each machine you can then view the list of shares, and mount, unmount or browse them. You can also search a machine by  name or ip. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kon2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kanji ON Console. KON2 display KANJI on console. (KON Version2) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koncd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KOnCD is a graphical frontend for mastering and burning CD-ROMs. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konfont
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Public domain japanese fonts for KON2. This package is public domain japanese fonts. And customized for kon2 package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konq-plugins
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
plugins for Konqueror, the KDE file/web/doc browser This package contains a variety of useful plugins for Konqueror, the file manager, web browser and document viewer for KDE. The plugins will appear in Konqueror&apos;s Tools menu. Highlights for web browsing include web page translation, web page archiving, HTML structural analysis and fast access to common options.  Highlights for directory browsing include directory filters and image gallery creation. This package is part of the KDE addons module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konq-speaker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
text-to-speech plugins for Konqueror and Kate This package contains text-to-speech plugins for Konqueror (the KDE file manager and web browser) and Kate (a KDE text editor). Text-to-speech is provided by the festival speech system. These plugins can be accessed through Konqueror&apos;s Tools menu and the plugin manager in Kate settings. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konqueror
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE&apos;s advanced File Manager, Web Browser and Document Viewer KDE&apos;s advanced File Manager, Web Browser and Document Viewer From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konquest
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE based GNU-Lactic Konquest game This the KDE version of Gnu-Lactic Konquest, a multi-player strategy game. The goal of the game is to expand your interstellar empire across the galaxy and, of course, crush your rivals in the process. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konsole
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X terminal emulation for KDE Konsole is an X terminal emulation which provides a command-line interface (CLI) while using the graphical K Desktop Environment. Konsole helps to better organize user&apos;s desktop by containing multiple sessions in a single window (a less cluttered desktop). It&apos;s advanced features include a simple configuration and the ability to use multiple terminal shells in a single window Using Konsole, a user can open:  Linux console sessions  Midnight Commander file manager sessions  Shell sessions  Root consoles sessions From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kontour
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a vector graphics tool for the KDE Office Suite Kontour is a vector graphics application.  This application was formerly known as KIllustrator. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konverse
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a Jabber client for KDE Konverse is a Jabber client for the K Desktop Environment.  It offers instant messaging and can converse with other clients such as Jabber, AOL Instant Messenger, ICQ, MSN Instant Messenger or Yahoo! Messenger. Jabber is an XML-based, open-source system and protocol for real-time messaging and presence notification.  The first application of Jabber is an instant messaging (IM) system similar to AOL Instant Messenger, ICQ, MSN Instant Messenger, or Yahoo! Messenger.  However, Jabber is also being applied in the realms of wireless communications, embedded systems, and Internet infrastructure.  See www.jabber.org for further details. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
konwert
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Charset conversion for files or terminal I/O `konwert&apos; is yet another charset converter.  Some particular features are:  * one-to-many conversions  * context-dependent conversions  * approximations of some unavailable characters  * (as a result) ability to transcript eg. russian cyrillic into polish phonetic equivalent  * etc. `filterm&apos; applies filter conversion to a terminal&apos;s I/O, to get on-the-fly charset conversion, and customized input methods. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kooka
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Scanner program for KDE2 Kooka is a scanner program based on SANE and KScan library. ***WARNING*** Please read the WARNING file first in /usr/share/doc/kooka From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KORE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
??? From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
korganizer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A full Personal Information Manage (PIM). From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
korganizer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Personal organizer based on Qt and KDE A complete calendar and scheduling program. KOrganizer supports information interchange with other calendar applications through the industry standard vCalendar file format. KOrganizer aims to be a complete program for organizing your appointments, contacts, projects, etc.  It is in the same spirit as similar programs like the now ubiquitous Microsoft Outlook, Starfish Internet Sidekick, Time &amp; Chaos, etc. (all for the Microsoft Windows platform, of course.)  Best of all, It reads and writes the vCalendar file format NATIVELY (please see http://www.imc.org/pdi for more information), which is now an industry-wide personal data interchange format.  Because of this, you should be able to move from other modern PIMs to KOrganizer with relative ease.  Current users of the popular program ical should definitely take a look at KOrganizer and compare features. KOrganizer also offers full synchronization with your Palm Pilot, if you have kpilot installed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
korinoco
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Clone the &quot;Client Manager&quot; from Lucent Technologies, Inc. The KOrinoco application tries to clone the &quot;Client Manager&quot; from Lucent Technologies, Inc. It provides information about your access point, connection quality and other stuff. In theory, not only the original Orinoco card but as well other 802.11 compliant cards _should_ be supported. However, this is untested. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
korn
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Mail notifier for KDE Mail notifier for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Korn Shell
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An enhanced version of the Bourne Shell, including extensive scripting support and command line editing. It supports many scripts written for the Bourne Shell. (Also, see Bash.) From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
korn shell
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An enhanced version of the Bourne shell. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kent On-Line System (OS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koscript
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a script interpreter for the KDE Office Suite From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koshell
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the KDE Office Suite workspace From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koshell
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the KDE Office Suite workspace The KOffice workspace is a desktop with easy one-click launchers for KOffice applications. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koth
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
King of the Hill King of the Hill, KOTH, is an artillery game in the grand old tradition of little tanks with ridiculously powerful weapons trying to blow each other up while trying to avoid getting blown up themselves. KOTH is based on a client-server networking model.  Players can join and leave at any time, and because bandwidth use is quite modest you can even easily play over a modem - KOTH really is a strategy game, ping time is irrelevant. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
koules
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Space action game for X11. A somewhat abstract space action game for X11 with sound. Supports multiplayer deathmatch and cooperative play. Koules is a fast action  arcade-style game for UNIX and OS/2. This version  supports X window  system, SVGAlib  for Linux and OS/2. It works in fine (up to 900x620) resolution with cool 256 color graphics, multiplayer mode up to 5 players, full sound and, of course, network support. Koules is an original idea. First version of Koules was developed from scratch by Jan Hubicka in July 1995. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpackage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Installs, removes, and queries packages. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpackage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Software package tool for KDE This is a frontend to both .rpm and .deb package formats.  It allows you to view currently installed packages, browse available packages, and install/remove them. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpaint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A simple bitmap paint program for KDE. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpaint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Simple Paint Program for KDE KPaint is a very simple paint program for KDE. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpaint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Painting tool for KDE. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE solitaire patience game. KPatience is a collection of 14 card games. All the games are single player games. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KPCMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kodak Precision Color Management System (Kodak, DTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KPDL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kyocera Page Description Language (Kyocera) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KPF is an easy to use public file server controlled from the KDE panel. Simply drag a file or directory to the KPF button to share it. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KPI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernel Programming Interface (Unix, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpilot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Palm Pilot sync tool for KDE Palm Pilot sync tool for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE process manager. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KPM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kyocera PrintMonitor (Kyocera) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Process manager for KDE This is a process manager (top + ps and all) for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpmdocked
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE process manager. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpoker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE based Poker clone KPoker is a KDE compliant clone of those highly addictive pocket video poker games which are sometimes called &quot;Videopoker&quot; as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KPOP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kerberized Post Office Protocol (POP3) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kppp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PPP dialer for KDE This is a PPP GUI based on Qt and KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kppp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PPP Networking applications for the K Desktop Environment. Install kppp if you intend to use KDE on a machine using PPP networking. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpppload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KPPPLoad is a PPP connection load monitor which works with KDE&apos;ssession management. KPPPLoad resembles xload. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kprconverter.pl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
converts a KPresenter document from old to new format From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpresenter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a presentation program for the KDE Office Suite From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpresenter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a presentation program for the KDE Office Suite KPresenter is a fully-featured presentation program.  It is sufficiently developed that it is already being successfully used for giving talks and presentations. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kprof
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a KDE visual tool to help analyze profiling results KProf is a visual tool for developers that displays the execution profiling output generated by code profiling tools.  The output of gprof being usually difficult to read (beyond the flat profile information), KProf presents the information in list- or tree-views that make the execution profiling information very easy to understand. Currently supported profilers include GNU gprof, Function Check and Palm OS Emulator with profile option. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpsepath
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
script to make teTeX-style kpsetool, kpsexpand, and kpsepath available From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpsestat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
compute octal mode from mode of existing file From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpsetool
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
script to make teTeX-style kpsetool, kpsexpand, and kpsepath available From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpsewhich
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
standalone path lookup and and expansion for kpathsea From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kpsexpand
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
script to make teTeX-style kpsetool, kpsexpand, and kpsepath available From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KPT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kai&apos;s PowerTools (DTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KQML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge Query Manipulation Language (AI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge Representation (AI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[brian] Kernighan &amp; [dennis] Ritchie [c standard], &quot;K&amp;R&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KRA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Key Recovery Alliance (org., cryptography) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
krbafs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This package contains the krbafs shared library, which allows programs to obtain AFS network filesystem tokens using Kerberos IV credentials, without having to link with official AFS libraries which may not beavailable for a given platform. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kreatecd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE CD burner with an easy interface The description is a rip-off from http://www.kreatecd.de/intro.php KreateCD is a graphical user interface for the K Desktop Environment to copy and master own audio CDs (CDDA) or data CDs (CD-ROM). The idea to create such an application came to mind because there are only a few such applications for Linux and many people are not able to use the command line tools. Xcdroast is not bad at all but there are some features which are missing. I don&apos;t like TCL/TK very much so I decided to create a similar but more extended application for my favorite desktop environment : KDE. KreateCD itself uses some command line applications as base applications and provides a comfortable and very intuitive user interface which should be usable by people who don&apos;t have any experiences with Linux at all. The main features of KreateCD are:  o Intuitive user interface  o Supports mastering of ISO-9660 CD-ROM tracks  o Is able to read .WAV audio files  o Easy to use CD copy function  o Some useful features to edit audio tracks before you write it to CD.    (volume boosting, balance and range selection)  o Audio playback From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
krecord
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE sound recorder This is a sound recorder for KDE.  It can just record and playback wav-files, that&apos;s all. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kregexpeditor
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Regular Expressions Editor. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kreversi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Reversi for KDE Reversi is a simple strategy game that is played by two players. There is only one type of piece - one side of it is black, the other white. If a player captures a piece on the board, that piece is turned and belongs to that player. The winner is the person that has more pieces of his own color on the board and if there are no more moves possible. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
krootwarning
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This package contains a warning box displayed when you are using KDE with system administrator permissions. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
krozat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This package contains the default Mandrake Linux screensaver for KDE. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KRUD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kevin&apos;s Red Hat Uber Distribution. See LWN review.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kruler
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a screen ruler and color measurement tool for KDE Kruler is a screen ruler and color measurement tool for KDE. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kruler
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Screen ruler for KDE. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
krusader
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
File Manager for KDE Krusader is an &quot;old-school&quot; file manager. Its twin-panel look follows in the footsteps of the great file managers of old such as GNU&apos;s Midnight Commander(c) and the Norton Commander(c) for DOS. Krusader features an intuitive GUI, complete drag n&apos; drop capability, transparent handling of archives, MIME type support, and more. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kalman Saffran Associates (manufacturer) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KommunikationsStrukturAnalyse (OA, TUB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksame
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
SameGame for KDE KSame is a simple game. It&apos;s played by one player, so there is only one winner :-) You play for fun and against the high score. It has been inspired by SameGame, that is only famous on the Macintosh platform. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kscd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE based cd player This is a KDE based cd player From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kscore
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
sports ticker for KDE A sports ticker applet for the KDE panel. This package is part of the official KDE toys module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kscreensaver
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Screen savers for KDE This package contains all of the Screen Savers that are included in the kdebase distribution. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Key Sequenced Data Set (VSAM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kseg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Explore planar Euclidean geometry. KSEG allows you to interactively create a geometrical construction, similar to what you can do with a straight edge and compass.  Points may be inserted on the page with right mouse-button clicks, and then used to form segments, lines, circles, or other geometrical objects. At any time you can drag existing points around, and watch how the constructed objects respond. See http://www.mit.edu/~ibaran/kseg.html for more info. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksensors
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
lm-sensors frontend for KDE This is a lm-sensors frontend for KDE for monitoring a motherboard. It allows you to access information from temperature and fan speed sensors. You will need lm-sensors kernel modules to use this package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Key Strokes per Hour From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Korn SHell (Unix, Shell) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksh
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Public domain Korn shell From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kshisen
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Shisen-Sho for KDE KShisen-Sho is a single-player-game similar to Mahjongg and uses the same set of tiles as Mahjongg. The object of the game is to remove all tiles from the field. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSI-Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The web site is in Russian and does not appear to have been updated since 1999. Distribution development is not all that active. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSIG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Khronos Special Interest Group From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksimus
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE tool for simulating electrical circuits KSimus is an application for simulating networks with boolean and floating point data type. Some more data types are planned. Currently there exists only a few components, but because of the modular character of KSimus extensions are easy to develop. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksirc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
IRC Client based on Qt and KDE IRC Client based on Qt and KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksirtet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tetris and Puyo-Puyo games for KDE This program is a clone of the well known game Tetris. You must fit the falling pieces to form full lines. You can rotate and translate the falling piece. The game ends when no more piece can fall ie when your incomplete lines reach the top of the board. Every time you have destroyed 10 lines, you gain a level and the pieces fall quicker (exactly the piece falls from a line each 1/(1+level) second). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSLNRC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Knowledge Systems Laboratory of the National Research Council (org., Canada, AI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksmiletris
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tetris like game for KDE This is a game with falling blocks composed of different types of smilies. The object of the game is to &quot;crack a smile&quot; by guiding blocks so there are two or more of the same symbol vertically. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksmp3play
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Curses-based MP3 player. ksmp3play is a curses-based MP3 player with features such as song rating and volume settings for each song. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksnake
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Snake Race for KDE Snake Race is a game of speed and agility. You are a hungry snake and are trying to eat all the apples in the room before getting out! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksnapshot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE applet for taking screenshots. ksnapshot allows both capturing the whole desktop and capturing justthe active window. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksnapshot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Screenshot application for KDE KSnapshot is a simple applet for taking screenshots. It is capable of capturing images of either the whole desktop or just a single window. The images can then be saved in a variety of formats. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksokoban
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Sokoban game for KDE The first sokoban game was created in 1982 by Hiroyuki Imabayashi at the Japanese company Thinking Rabbit, Inc. &quot;Sokoban&quot; is japanese for &quot;warehouse keeper&quot;. The idea is that you are a warehouse keeper trying to push crates to their proper locations in a warehouse. The problem is that you cannot pull the crates or step over them. If you are not careful, some of the crates can get stuck in wrong places and/or block your way. It can be rather difficult just to solve a level. But if you want to make it even harder, you can try to minimise the number of moves and/or pushes you use to solve the level. To make the game more fun for small kids (below 10 years or so), some collections with easier levels are also included in KSokoban. These are marked (easy) in the level collection menu. Of course, these levels can be fun for adults too, for example if you don&apos;t want to expose yourself to too much mental strain. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kernelized Secure Operating System (OS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kspaceduel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Arcade two-player space game for KDE KSpaceduel is an space arcade game for two players. Each player controls a ship that flies around the sun and tries to shoot at the other ship. You can play KSpaceduel with another person, against the computer, or you can have the computer control both ships and play each other From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSPM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KeyStrokes Per Minute From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kspread
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a spreadsheet for the KDE Office Suite KSpread is a powerful spreadsheet application. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kspy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
examines the internal state of a Qt/KDE app KSpy is a tiny library which can be used to graphically display the QObjects in use by a Qt/KDE app.  In addition to the object tree, you can also view the properties, signals and slots of any QObject. Basically it provides much the same info as QObject::dumpObjectTree() and QObject::dumpObjectInfo(), but in a much more convenient form.  KSpy has minimal overhead for the application, because the kspy library is loaded dynamically using KLibLoader. See /usr/share/doc/kspy/README for usage instructions. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keyboard Send Receive From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kilo-Samples per Second From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kstars
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Desktop planetarium for KDE2 KStars displays an accurate representation of the night sky for any time and date, from any location on Earth. The display can be panned in altitude and azimuth, and can be zoomed in and out. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kstartperf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
startup time measurement for KDE apps KStartPerf measures startup time for KDE applications. This package is part of the KDE Software Development Kit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksticker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A KDE-based scrolling stock ticker. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksymoops
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux kernel oops and error message decoder The Linux kernel produces error messages that contain machine specific numbers which are meaningless for debugging.  ksymoops reads machine specific files and the error log and converts the addresses to meaningful symbols and offsets. This is a complete replacement for the version of ksymoops in the kernel.  Older versions of ksymoops were in scripts/ksymoops.cc, more recently there was a version in the scripts/ksymoops directory. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksymoops
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Linux kernel produces error messages that contain machine specific numbers that are meaningless for debugging. The ksymoops utility reads machine specific files and the error log and converts the addresses to meaningful symbols and offsets. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksysv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
SysV-style init configuration editor This program allows you to edit your start and stop scripts using a drag and drop GUI. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ksysv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Views and sets SysV init configuration. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktalkd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Talk daemon for KDE Talk daemon for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kteatime
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
tea cooker timer for KDE A tea cooker timer that sits in the KDE system tray. This package is part of the official KDE toys module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kterm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Multi-lingual terminal emulator for X. Kterm is an X11 terminal emulator that can handle multi-lingual text. This release is based on xterm of X11R6.1. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktexmaker2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
LaTeX source editor, TeX shell and Gnuplot front end for KDE Ktexmaker2 is a LaTeX source editor, TeX shell and Gnuplot front end for KDE. The source editor is a multi-document version of KWrite for .tex and .bib files.  Menus and wizards are provided to assist with tag insertion and code generation.  A structure view of the document assists with navigation within source files. The TeX shell assists with LaTeX and bibtex compilation as well as DVI and postscript document viewing.  It supports documents divided into several files. The Gnuplot front end is an adaptation of the Xgfe program. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktimer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a timer for KDE This is a timer application for KDE.  It allows you to execute commands after a certain amount of time.  It allows for looping commands as well as delaying the execution of a command. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktimetrace
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical tool to measure and graph data KTimeTrace is a graphical tool based on Qt that measures and displays data from data acquisition hardware.  It captures samples from a data acquisition device, saving it to disk while providing a real-time graphing display. KTimeTrace requires having a data acquisition device that is supported by Comedi in order to capture data.  See the libcomedi0 package or http://stm.lbl.gov/comedi for more information about Comedi. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktouch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program for learning touch typing. KTouch is a program for learning touch typing. KTouch is a way to learn to type on a keyboard quickly and correctly. Every finger has its place on the keyboard with associated keys to press. KTouch helps you learn to touch typing by providing you with something to write. KTouch can also help you to remember what fingers to use. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktron
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
tron-clone for the K Desktop Environment KTron is a simple tron-clone for the K Desktop Environment. Object of the game is to avoid running into walls, your own tail, and that of your opponent. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktuberling
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Potato Guy for KDE KTuberling is a game intended for small children. Of course, it may be suitable for adults who have remained young at heart. It is a potato editor. That means that you can drag and drop eyes, mouths, moustache, and other parts of face and goodies onto a potato-like guy. There is no winner for the game. The only purpose is to make the funniest faces you can. There is a museum (like a &quot;Madame Tusseau&quot; gallery) where you can find many funny examples of decorated potatoes. Of course, you can send your own creations to the programmer, Eric Bischoff, who will include them in the museum if he gets some spare time. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ktux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tux screensaver for KDE A neat Tux-in-a-spaceship screensaver for the K Desktop Environment (KDE). This package is part of the official KDE toys module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kudzu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Red Hat Linux hardware probing tool. This is a hardware probing tool run at system boot time to determine what hardware has been added or removed from the system. http://rhlinux.redhat.com/kudzu/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kugar
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a business report maker for the KDE Office Suite Kugar is a tool for generating business quality reports which can be viewed and printed.  It includes a standalone report viewer and a KPart report viewer.  The latter means that any KDE application can embed the report viewing functionality and that reports can be viewed using the Konqueror browser. This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kuickshow
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kuickshow is a picture viewer for KDE. It displays the directorystructure, displaying images as thumbnails. Clicking on an image shows the image in its normal size. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kuser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A user/group administration tool for KDE A user/group administration tool for KDE From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KUTGW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keep Up The Good Work (slang, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kuvert
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A wrapper that encrypts or signs outgoing mail. kuvert automatically signs and/or encrypts outgoing mail using the PGP/MIME standard (rfc2015), based on the availability of the recipient&apos;s key in your keyring. Other than similar wrappers, kuvert does not store the passphrases on disk but keeps them just in memory; if available, kuvert prefers to store the key passphrases with quintuple-agent. kuvert works as a wrapper around your MTA. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KV
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KabelVerzweiger From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KV
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Karnaugh Veitch diagram From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A simple image viewer/converter for KDE. KView is a simple image viewer/converter application. This package contains kview, kdvi and kfax. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KView is a KDE image viewer, supporting a wide range of graphics fileformats. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kviewshell
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KViewShell allows the kview image viewer to be embedded into other KDE applications. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kvirc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fully scriptable graphical IRC client with plugin support A highly configurable graphical IRC client with an MDI interface, built-in scripting language, support for DCC, drag &amp; drop, and much more. KVIrc uses the Qt widget set, has support for KDE, has more features than you can think of, can be extended using its own scripting language, supports custom plugins and is nearly a desktop environment on its own. If you are interested in extending the client and writing your own scripts, you probably want to also install the kvirc-doc package. If you&apos;re a developer and you want to write a custom plugin for KVIrc, you need to install the kvirc-dev package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KVM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Kilobyte Virtual Machine (Java, Sun, MIDP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kwave
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A sound editor for KDE2. &quot;Kwave&quot; is a simple sound editor for KDE2. Its features include:   * simple cut, copy and paste functions   * undo/redo   * simple filter design tools   * a small editor for additive synthesis   * labeling of signals   * some analysis functions such as Sonagram or Fourier Transformation   * internally uses 24 bit integer sample data   * free selectable sample rates   * support for editing of multi-channel files   * playback of multi-channel audio files (audio output will be mixed     down to mono or stereo)   * extendible through an easy-to-use plugin interface Documentation for this package is available in either English, French or German. Please choose your appropriate scribus-doc-XX documentation package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kweather
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a weather display applet for KDE Kicker KWeather is an applet for the KDE Kicker that will display your area&apos;s current weather.  Information shown includes the temperature, wind speed and air pressure.  By pressing a button a full weather report can be obtained. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kwikdisk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
KDE free disk space utility. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kwin4
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Connect Four clone for KDE Four wins is a game for two players. Each player is represented by a colour (yellow and red). The goal of the game is to get four connected pieces of your colour into a row, column or any diagonal. This is done by placing one of your pieces into any of the seven columns. A piece will begin to fill a column from the bottom, i.e. it will fall down until it reaches the ground level or another stone. After a move is done it is the turn of the other player. This is repeated until the game is over, i.e. one of the players has four pieces in a row, column or diagonal or no more moves are possible because the board is filled. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
KWM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
K Window Manager (KDE) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kword
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a word processor for the KDE Office Suite KWord is a frame-based word processor comparable to FrameMaker.  It can be used for desktop publishing, but also for &quot;normal&quot; word processing (like writing letters, reports and so on). This package is part of the KDE Office Suite. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kworldclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
earth watcher for KDE Displays where in the world it is light and dark depending on time, as well as offering the time in all of the major cities of the world. This can be run standalone or as an applet in the KDE panel. This package is part of the official KDE toys module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kwuftpd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
wu-ftpd configuration tool This program allows you to manipulate the configuration files for wu-ftpd. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
kxmleditor
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML Editor for KDE KXML Editor is simple program, that display and edit contents of XML file. Left side contain tree with XML document structure, right side contain list of attributes for selected XML element and its contents. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossary>
