<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY About-the-Author SYSTEM "About-the-Author.xml">
<!ENTITY Contributors SYSTEM "Contributors.xml">
<!ENTITY Disclaimer   SYSTEM "Disclaimer.xml">
<!ENTITY Donations SYSTEM "Donations.xml">
<!ENTITY Feedback     SYSTEM "Feedback.xml">
<!ENTITY References   SYSTEM "References.xml">
<!ENTITY GFDL         SYSTEM "fdl.xml">
<!ENTITY Punctuation SYSTEM "Punctuation.xml">
<!ENTITY A SYSTEM "A.xml">
<!ENTITY B SYSTEM "B.xml">
<!ENTITY C SYSTEM "C.xml">
<!ENTITY D SYSTEM "D.xml">
<!ENTITY E SYSTEM "E.xml">
<!ENTITY F SYSTEM "F.xml">
<!ENTITY G SYSTEM "G.xml">
<!ENTITY H SYSTEM "H.xml">
<!ENTITY I SYSTEM "I.xml">
<!ENTITY J SYSTEM "J.xml">
<!ENTITY K SYSTEM "K.xml">
<!ENTITY L SYSTEM "L.xml">
<!ENTITY M SYSTEM "M.xml">
<!ENTITY N SYSTEM "N.xml">
<!ENTITY O SYSTEM "O.xml">
<!ENTITY P SYSTEM "P.xml">
<!ENTITY Q SYSTEM "Q.xml">
<!ENTITY R SYSTEM "R.xml">
<!ENTITY S SYSTEM "S.xml">
<!ENTITY T SYSTEM "T.xml">
<!ENTITY U SYSTEM "U.xml">
<!ENTITY V SYSTEM "V.xml">
<!ENTITY W SYSTEM "W.xml">
<!ENTITY X SYSTEM "X.xml">
<!ENTITY Y SYSTEM "Y.xml">
<!ENTITY Z SYSTEM "Z.xml">
]>


<book>

<bookinfo>
<title>Linux Dictionary</title>
<subtitle>Version 0.16</subtitle>
<pubdate>2004-08-16</pubdate>

<author>
<firstname>Author: Binh</firstname>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<affiliation>
<address>
<email>linuxfilesystem(at)yahoo(dot)com(dot)au</email>
</address>
</affiliation>
</author>

<abstract>
<para>
This document is designed to be a resource for those Linux users wishing
to seek clarification on Linux/UNIX/POSIX related terms and jargon. At
approximately 24000 definitions and two thousand pages it is one of the largest
Linux related dictionaries currently available. Due to the rapid rate at which 
new terms are being created it has been decided that this will be an active 
project. We welcome input into the content of this document. At this moment
in time half yearly updates are being envisaged.
</para>

<para>
Please note that if you wish to find a 'Computer Dictionary' then
see the 'Computer Dictionary Project' at 
<ulink url="http://computerdictionary.tsf.org.za/">
http://computerdictionary.tsf.org.za/</ulink>
</para>

<para>Searchable databases exist at locations such as:</para> 

<para><ulink url="http://www.swpearl.com/eng/scripts/dictionary/">
http://www.swpearl.com/eng/scripts/dictionary/</ulink></para> 
<para>(SWP) Sun Wah-PearL Linux Training and Development Centre
is a centre of the Hong Kong Polytechnic University, established
in 2000. Presently SWP is delivering professional grade Linux
and related Open Source Software (OSS) technology training and
consultant service in Hong Kong. SWP has an ambitious aim to promote
the use of Linux and related Open Source Software (OSS) and Standards. 
The vendor independent positioning of SWP has been very well perceived
by the market. Throughout the last couple of years, SWP becomes the Top
Leading OSS training and service provider in Hong Kong.</para>

<para><ulink url="http://www.geona.com/dictionary?b=">
http://www.geona.com/dictionary?b=</ulink></para>
<para>Geona, operated by Gold Vision Communications, is a new 
powerful search engine and internet directory, delivering quick
and relevant results on almost any topic or subject you can imagine.
The term "Geona" is an Italian and Hebrew name, meaning wisdom,
exaltation, pride or majesty. We use our own database of spidered 
web sites and the Open Directory database, the same database which
powers the core directory services for the Web's largest and most
popular search engines and portals. Geona is spidering all domains
listed in the non-adult part of the Open Directory and millions of
additional sites of general interest to maintain a fulltext index
of highly relevant web sites.</para>

<para><ulink url="http://www.linuxdig.com/documents/dictionary.php">
http://www.linuxdig.com/documents/dictionary.php</ulink></para>
<para>LINUXDIG.COM, "Yours News and Resource Site",
LinuxDig.com was started in May 2001 as a hobby site with the
original intention of getting the RFC's online and becoming an
Open Source software link/download site. But since that time the site
has evolved to become a RFC distribution site, linux news site 
and a locally written technology news site (with bad grammer :))
with focus on Linux while also containing articles about anything 
and everything we find interesting in the computer world. LinuxDig.Com 
contains about 20,000 documents and this number is growing everyday!
</para>

<para><ulink url="http://linux.about.com/library/glossary/blglossary.htm">
http://linux.about.com/library/glossary/blglossary.htm</ulink></para>
<para>Each month more than 20 million people visit About.com.
Whether it be home repair and decorating ideas, recipes, movie
trailers, or car buying tips, our Guides offer practical advice
and solutions for every day life. Wherever you land on the new
About.com, you'll find other content that is relevant to your
interests. If you're looking for "How To" advice on planning
to re-finish your deck, we'll also show you the tools you need
to get the job done. If you've been to About before, we'll show
you the latest updates, so you don't see the same thing twice.
No matter where you are on About.com, or how you got here,
you'll always find content that is relevant to your needs.
</para>

<!--

<para>
<ulink url="http://startext.demon.co.uk/Linux-Dictionary/">
http://startext.demon.co.uk/Linux-Dictionary/<ulink>
</para>	

<para>
<ulink url="http://www.lifeindevelopment.com/linux-dictionary/">
http://www.lifeindevelopment.com/linux-dictionary/</ulink>
Life in Development - Blog for Geeks, For those who develop while being developed,
Designerz, is a team of professionals-web
designers and architects, graphic artists, content
editors, search engine optimizers, and quality control
managers-who work together to give you a cohesive web-based product.
Designerz, is one provider for all your needs. Our integrated approach to your project saves you money and time. We strive for your satisfaction with the process as well as the product.
We rate our work on the quality, not the quantity, of projects we develop. Team members receive quality-based assessments by customers and company management.
We monitor every team member’s role in developing a project to assure that our clients' needs are completely met. 
</para>

<para>
<ulink url="www.trainingbyroi.com">
	www.trainingbyroi.com</ulink>
ROITraining - Maximise Your Training Investment, 

ROI measures success through one simple abbreviated formula:

LE + WE = ROI

The Learning Experience + Work Environment = Business Results = ROI.

Every part of the equation needs to be in place to maximize your training investment and produce measurable results. 
</para>

<para>
<ulink url="http://www.indialinux.org/">
	http://www.indialinux.org/</ulink>	
IndiaLinux.org - For an India with Open Source and Open Minds
</para>

-->

<para>Should you wish to possess your own localised searcheable
version please make use of the available "dict",
<ulink url="http://www.dict.org">http://www.dict.org/</ulink>
version at the Linux Documentation Project home page, <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/">http://www.tldp.org/</ulink>
The author has decided to leave it up to readers to determine
how to install and run it on their specific systems.
</para>

<para>An alternative form of the dictionary is available at:</para> 

<para><ulink url="http://elibrary.fultus.com/covers/technical/linux/guides/Linux-Dictionary/cover.html">
http://elibrary.fultus.com/covers/technical/linux/guides/Linux-Dictionary/cover.html</ulink></para>
<para>Fultus Corporation helps writers and companies to publish, promote,
market, and sell books and eBooks. Fultus combines traditional self-publishing
practices with modern technology to produce paperback and hardcover
print-on-demand (POD) books and electronic books (eBooks).
Fultus publishes works (fiction, non-fiction, science fiction, mystery,
...) by both published and unpublished authors. We enable you to
self-publish easily and cost-effectively, creating your book as
a print-ready paperback or hardcover POD book or as an electronic
book (eBook) in multiple eBook's formats. You retain all rights
to your work. We provide distribution to bookstores worldwide. And all
at a fraction of the cost of traditional publishing.
We also offer corporate publishing solutions that enable businesses to
produce and deliver manuals and documentation more efficiently and
economically. Our use of electronic delivery and print-on-demand technologies
reduces printed inventory and saves time.</para>

<para>Please inform the author as to whether you would like to create a
database or an alternative form of the dictionary so that he can include 
you in this list. Also note that the author considers breaches 
of copyright to be extremely serious. He will pursue all claims 
to the fullest extent of the law.</para>

</abstract>

<legalnotice>
<para>Copyright 2003 Binh Nguyen</para>
<para>Trademarks are owned by their owners.</para>
<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
Version 1.2; with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts,
and with no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in
the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
</legalnotice>
</bookinfo>

<preface><title>Source and pre-formatted versions available</title>
<para>
The source code and other machine readable formats
of this book can be found on the Internet at the
Linux Documentation Project home page <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/">http://www.tldp.org/</ulink>
The latest version of this document can be found at
<ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/Linux-Dictionary/">
http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/Linux-Dictionary/</ulink>
</para>
</preface>

<chapter>
<title>Linux Dictionary</title>

&Punctuation;
&A;
&B;
&C;
&D;
&E;
&F;
&G;
&H;
&I;
&J;
&K;
&L;
&M;
&N;
&O;
&P;
&Q;
&R;
&S;
&T;
&U;
&V;
&W;
&X;
&Y;
&Z;

<para></para>
</chapter>

&About-the-Author;
&Contributors;
&Disclaimer;
&Donations;
&Feedback;
&References;
&GFDL;

</book>
