<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="W">
<title>W</title>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Show who is logged on and what they are doing. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w-bassman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an alternative &quot;w&quot; command This is a version of the &quot;w&quot; command that might be familiar to old Slackware users. It formats the output differently, in a way some consider clearer and easier to read. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w.procps
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Show who is logged on and what they are doing. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
W2K
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows 2000 (Windows, MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3-el-e20
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web browser for GNU Emacs 20 A full-featured web browser, written entirely in Emacs-Lisp, that supports all the bells and whistles in use on the web today: frames, tables, stylesheets, and much more. Supports asynchronous connections, allowing users to browse numerous sites concurrently, while others continue to download.  Tight integration with the standard Emacs mail and news reading packages allows easy sharing of information.  Since Emacs is first and foremost the most powerful editor around, the information you uncover on the web can immediately be put to work. Yet another reason to never leave Emacs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3-el-e21
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web browser for GNU Emacs 21 A full-featured web browser, written entirely in Emacs-Lisp, that supports all the bells and whistles in use on the web today: frames, tables, stylesheets, and much more. Supports asynchronous connections, allowing users to browse numerous sites concurrently, while others continue to download.  Tight integration with the standard Emacs mail and news reading packages allows easy sharing of information.  Since Emacs is first and foremost the most powerful editor around, the information you uncover on the web can immediately be put to work. Yet another reason to never leave Emacs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
W3C
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Acronym for the World Wide Web Consortium, an independent peak body founded in 1994 to develop common protocols and standards for the evolution of the World Wide Web. It is jointly hosted by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Laboratory for Computer Science in the USA, the Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique [INRIA] in Europe, and the Keio University Shonan Fujisawa Campus in Asia. The Consortium is led by Tim Berners-Lee, the primary inventor of the World Wide Web. More information can be found at: http://www.W3C.org/ From Faculty-of-Education
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
W3C
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide Web Consortium (WWW, org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3cam
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a simple CGI to retrieve images from video4linux device. w3cam is a simple CGI to retrieve images from video4linux device. In other words this program will only run on Linux machines which support a video4linux-device. w3cam supports a plain mode and a gui mode. In the gui mode a html with a form is supplied to change some parameters with the mouse .. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3m
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WWW browsable pager with excellent tables/frames support w3m is a text-based World Wide Web browser with IPv6 support. It features excellent support for tables and frames. It can be used as a standalone file pager, too.  * You can follow links and/or view images in HTML.  * Internet message preview mode, you can browse HTML mail.  * You can follow links in plain text if it includes URL forms.  * With w3m-img, you can view image inline. For more information, see http://sourceforge.net/projects/w3m From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3m-el
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a simple Emacs interface of w3m This package contains a interface program of w3m, which is a pager with WWW capability.  It can be used as lightweight WWW browser on emacsen. This is also known as emacs-w3m. http://emacs-w3m.namazu.org/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3m-img
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
inline image extension support utilities for w3m w3m-img provides some utilities to support inline images for w3m on terminal emulator in X Window System environments. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3m-ssl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WWW browsable pager with SSL support w3m is a text-based World Wide Web browser with IPv6 support. It features excellent support for tables and frames. It can be used as a standalone file pager, too.  * You can follow links and/or view images in HTML.  * Internet message preview mode, you can browse HTML mail.  * You can follow links in plain text if it includes URL forms.  * With w3m-img, you can view image inline. This package is built with SSL support. For more information, see http://sourceforge.net/projects/w3m From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3mir
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
w3mir is an all purpose HTTP copying and mirroring tool. w3mir can create and maintain a browsable copy of one, or several WWW sites. It can preserve link integrety within the mirrored documents as well as the integrey of links outside the mirror. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3mmee
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WWW browsable pager with excellent tables/frames, MB extension w3mmee is w3m with multibyte encoding extension. For more information, see http://w3m.sourceforge.net/ and http://pub.ks-and-ks.ne.jp/prog/w3mmee/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3mmee-img
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
inline image extension support utilities for w3mmee w3mmee-img provides some utilities to support inline images for w3mmee on terminal emulator in X Window System environments. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w3mmee-ssl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WWW browsable pager with SSL support, MB extension w3mmee is w3m with multibyte encoding extension. This package is built with SSL support. For more information, see http://w3m.sourceforge.net/ and http://pub.ks-and-ks.ne.jp/prog/w3mmee/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
w9wm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Enhanced window manager based on 9wm w9wm is a quick and dirty hack based on 9wm. It provides support for virtual screens as well as for keyboard bindings. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
waba
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
light weight virtual machine similar to Java Waba is a small, efficient and reliable Java Virtual Machine (VM) aimed at portable devices (but also runnable on desktop computers), wribtten by Rick Wild of Wabasoft. The Waba VM is an open source project. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WABI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Application Binary Interface (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Accessibility Initiative (WWW, W3C, WAI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Application Interface (WWW, Netscape) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Area Information Servers - A commercial software package that allows the indexing of huge quantities of information, and then making those indices searchable across networks such as the Internet . A prominent feature of WAIS is that the search results are ranked (&quot;scored&quot;) according to how relevant the &quot;hits&quot; are, and that subsequent searches can find &quot;more stuff like that last batch&quot; and thus refine the search process. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Area Information Service (Internet) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAIS (Wide Area Information Server). From Faculty-of-Education
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>

<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAIS (Wide Area Information Servers)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A commercial software package that allows the indexing of huge quantities of information, and then making those indices searchable across networks such as the Internet. A prominent feature of WAIS is that the search results are ranked (scored) accordingto how relevant the hits are, and that subsequent searches can find more stuff like that last batch and thus refine the search process. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAIS (Wide Area Information Servers)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
These servers allow users to conduct full-text keyword searches in documents, databases, and libraries connected to the Internet. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wait state
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A microprocessor clock cycle in which nothing at all occurs. A wait state is programmed into a computer system to allow other components, such as random-access memory (RAM), to catch up with the central processing unit (CPU). The number of wait states depends on the speed of the processor in relation to the speed of memory. Wait states can be eliminated-resulting in a zero wait states machine by using fast (but expensive) cache memory, interfaced memory, page-mode , or static chips. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAITS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Westcoast Alternative to ITS From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wajig
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simplified Debian package management front end Wajig is a single commandline wrapper around apt, apt-cache, dpkg, /etc/init.d scripts and more, intended to be easy to use and providing extensive documentation for all of its functions. With a suitable sudo(1) configuration, most if not all package installation (as well as creation) tasks can be done from a user shell. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wall
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
write a message to users From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wall time
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. (also `wall clock time&apos;) 1. `Real world&apos; time (what the clock on the wall shows), as opposed to the system clock&apos;s idea of time. 2. The real running time of a program, as opposed to the number of ticks required to execute it (on a timesharing system these always differ, as no one program gets all the ticks, and on multiprocessor systems with good thread support one may get more processor time than real time).  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wall wart
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. A small power-supply brick with integral male plug, designed to plug directly into a wall outlet; called a `wart&apos; because when installed on a power strip it tends to block up at least one more socket than it uses.. These are frequently associated with modems and other small electronic devices which would become unacceptably bulky or hot if they had power supplies on board (there are other reasons as well having to do with the cost of UL certification). From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wallp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GTK+ and Imlib based app for periodically updating root of X WallP uses Imlib for its image rendering, so any image format readable by Imlib will work with WallP.  The user controls the period between changes, in minutes. GTK+ is used as the toolkit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wallpaper
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. A file containing a listing (e.g., assembly listing) or a transcript, esp. a file containing a transcript of all or part of a login session. (The idea was that the paper for such listings was essentially good only for wallpaper, as evidenced at Stanford, where it was used to cover windows.) Now rare, esp. since other systems have developed other terms for it (e.g., PHOTO on TWENEX). However, the Unix world doesn&apos;t have an equivalent term, so perhaps wallpaper will take hold there. The term probably originated on ITS, where the commands to begin and end transcript files were :WALBEG and :WALEND, with default file WALL PAPER (the space was a path delimiter). 2. The background pattern used on graphical workstations (this is techspeak under the `Windows&apos; graphical user interface to MS-DOS). 3. `wallpaper file&apos; n. The file that contains the wallpaper information before it is actually printed on paper. (Even if you don&apos;t intend ever to produce a real paper copy of the file, it is still called a wallpaper file.)  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Warren Abstract Machine (PROLOG) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Application Manager (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAMIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless, Adaptive and Mobile Information Systems (ESTO) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Acronym for Wide Area Network, which is generally a network connecting several physically distant locations, as opposed to a LAN. The Internet is an example of a worldwide WAN. From KADOWKEV
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
see wide-area network (WAN). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Area Network From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Area Network, which is generally a network connecting several physically distant locations, as opposed to a LAN. The Internet is an example of a worldwide WAN. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAN (Wide Area Network)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Any internet or network that covers an area larger than a single building or campus. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAND
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Area Network Distribution (WAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wanpipe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Configuration utilities for Sangoma S508/S514 WAN cards This package installs configuration tools and firmware modules for the Sangoma S508 and S514 router cards.  You may use this software to build a stable and flexible WAN router for frame-relay, PPP, or Cisco HDLC leased-line links based on these cards. This package is compiled against kernel 2.2.13.  This upstream version does not have support for X.25. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Application Protocol (mobile-systems, WLAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wissenschaftliche ArbeitsPlatzrechner From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Warewulf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Warewulf is a unique Linux distribution for cluster nodes. It facilitates a central administration model for all nodes and includes tools needed to build configuration files, monitor, and control the nodes. It is totally customizable and can be adapted to just about any type of cluster. The node distributions are built from a virtual node filesystem residing on the master, transfered to the nodes either by Etherboot or CDROM images, and run from RAM. Administration is scalable and easy. It was originally designed for Beowulf, but can be used in other environments as well. The initial version, 0.3, was released March 11, 2002. Version 1.11 was released May 15, 2003. A &apos;special purpose/mini&apos; distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
warm boot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A system restart performed after the system has been powered and operating. A warm boot is performed by using a special key combination or by pressing a reset button, while a cold boot involves actually turning the big red switch off and on. A warm boot is preferable to a cold start because a warm boot places less strain on your system&apos;s electrical and electronic components. See programmer&apos;s switch. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
warm boot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. See boot. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WASP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web stAndardS Project (WWW, W3C) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WAT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
West Africa Time [-0100] (TZ) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
watanabe-vf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This package contains the Watanabe font in SYOTAI CLUB format. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
watanabe-vfont
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Japanese Mincho font in Zeit&apos;s Syotai Club format. Vector fonts made from labosystem123 32dots font. This package replaces zeitfonts package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
watch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
call Tcl procedures before and after each command From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
watch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
execute a program periodically, showing output fullscreen From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
watchdog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A software watchdog The watchdog program writes to /dev/watchdog every ten seconds. If the device is open but not written to within a minute the machine will reboot -- a feature available when &quot;software watchdog&quot; support is compiled into the kernel. The ability to reboot will depend on the state of the machine and interrupts.  To use this software, linux 1.3.52 or later is needed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WATS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Area Telephone Service From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wav2cdr
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Converts wav files into CD-ROM audio file format. This program converts wav sound files into a format suitable for CD-ROMs, and can perform some editing functions like cutting or volume change. It is rather rudimentary, the wav file must have the same sampling parameters as CD audio. Runs on big and little endian machines. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Wave table synthesis
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A method, far superior to FM synthesis, of generating and reproducing music in a sound board Wave table synthesis uses a pre-recorded sample of dozens of orchestral instruments to determine how particular notes played on those instruments should sound. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wavemon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Device Monitoring Application Wavemon allows you to watch signal and noise levels, packet statistics, device configuration and network parameters of your wireless network hardware.  It has currently only been tested with the Lucent Orinoco series of cards, although it *should* work (though with varying features) with all devices supported by the wireless kernel extensions by Jean Tourrilhes. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wavtools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WAV play, record, and compression wavtools is a set of programs to play, record, and manage the compression of sound. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wayv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Experimental hand writing/gesture recognition program Enables human computer interaction, especially using gestures inputed via the mouse. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WorkBench (Amiga, Commodore) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WBC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide Band Channel (FDDI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wbd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Multicast White Board This is a free clone of wb, a multicast white board application. It allows you to share a virtual white board with other people running wbd over the Mbone (multicast backbone of the Internet). You can paint, write and import text and graphics. You will need a multicast router and a connection to the Mbone if you want to share your white board with people outside of your local subnet. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WBEM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Based Enterprise Management [protocol] (DMTF, BMC, Cisco, Compaq, Intel, MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WBI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Browser Intelligence (WWW, IBM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wbritish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
English dictionary words for /usr/share/dict This package provides the file /usr/share/dict/british-english containing a list of English words with British spellings, extracted from the ispell british dictionary. This list can be used by spelling checkers, and by programs such as look(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WBS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WissensBasierte Systeme (KI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
print the number of bytes, words, and lines in files From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WildCard multicast route entry (PIM, Multicast) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Word Count (Unix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WCAG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WAI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wcatalan
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Catalan dictionary words for /usr/share/dict This package contains an alphabetic list of Catalan words as put together by Ignasi Labastida i Juan &lt;nasi@optica.fao.ub.es&gt; from a list of words by Joan Dolg. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WCB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Write Combining Buffer (CPU) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WCCE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Conference on Computers in Education (IFIP, conference) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WCGA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Computer Graphics Association (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WCMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Content Management Software / System (CMS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WCS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Writable Control Store (VAX, DEC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Western Digital [corporation] (manufacturer) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Working Draft From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wdanish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Danish dictionary / wordlist This is a flat list of Danish words and names. This can be used by spellcheckers or any other purpose needing a lot of words. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wdg-html-reference
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WDGs&apos; HTML 3.2, HTML 4, and CSS references Attractive, well laid-out guides to the HTML 3.2, HTML 4, and Cascading Style Sheets specifications in HTML format. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wdg-html-validator
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WDG HTML Validator This is a CGI script which lets you enter the URL of a web page which will be then checked against a validating SGML parser for conformance to official HTML standards.  Pages can also be uploaded and HTML can be directly entered. A command-line version is also included in the package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wdiff
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The GNU wdiff utility. Compares two files word by word. `wdiff&apos; is a front-end to GNU `diff&apos;.  It compares two files, finding which words have been deleted or added to the first in order to create the second.  It has many output formats and interacts well with terminals and pagers (notably with `less&apos;).  `wdiff&apos; is particularly useful when two texts differ only by a few words and paragraphs have been refilled. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Word Developers Kit (MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Driver Library (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Definition Language From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wavelength Division Multiplexing [protocol] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows / Win32 Driver Model (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wdm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WINGs Display Manager - an xdm replacement with a WindowMaker look This is an xdm replacement based on the WINGs widget set.  WINGs is the NeXT-like widget set used by WindowMaker and some other programs.  wdm provides a nice and versatile login panel along with xdm functionality. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDMCSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Driver Model Connection and Streaming Architecture (MS, Windows, WDM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WatchDog Process From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WatchDog Server From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Watch Dog Timer From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WDT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Western  [european] Daylight Time [+0100] (TZ, WET) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wdutch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
List of Dutch words in new (August 1996) spelling. This package contains an alphabetic list of 229365 Dutch words. See the idutch package for the same wordlist in a format suitable for the spelling checker ispell. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
weave
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
translate WEB to TeX From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Web
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In the World Wide Web or any hypertext systems a set of related documents that together make up a hypertext presentation. The documents do not have to be stored on the same computer system, but they are explicitly interlinked, generally by providing internal navigation buttons. A web generally induces a welcome page that serves as the top-level document (home page) of the web. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Web
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
see World Wide Web (WWW). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Web browser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program that runs on an Internet-connected computer and provides access to the riches of the World Wide Web (WWW). Web browsers are of two kinds; text-only browsers and graphical Web browsers such as NCSA Mosaic and Netscape Navigator. Graphical browsers are preferable because you can see in-line images, fonts, and document layouts. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Web browser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An application that accesses and displays hypertext markup language (HTML) webpages and other resources available on the World Wide Web (WWW). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Web page
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A document designed for viewing in a web browser. Typically written in HTML. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webalizer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web server log analysis program The Webalizer is a web server log analysis program. It is designed to scan web server log files in various formats and produce usage statistics in HTML format for viewing through a browser. The Webalizer produces yearly, monthly, daily and hourly statistics. In the monthly reports, various statistics may be produced to show overall usage, usage by day and hour, usage by visiting sites, URLs, user agents (browsers), referrers and country. The Webalizer is highly configurable by use of either command line options or a configuration file, allowing the program to be tailored to individual needs easily. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webbase
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A crawler/indexer for the Internet webbase is a crawler for the Internet. It has two main functions : crawl the WEB to get documents and build a full text database with this documents. The crawler part visit the documents and store intersting information about them localy. It visits the document on a regular basis to make sure that it is still there and updates it if it changes. The full text database uses the localy copies of the document to build a searchable index. The full text indexing functions are not included in webbase. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webcam
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
capture and upload images webcam captures images from a video4linux device like bttv, annotates them and and uploads them to a webserver using ftp in a endless loop. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WEBDAV
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WWW), &quot;webDAV&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Webfish Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Webfish Linux is a small, stripped down Linux distribution based on GNU source packages. Webfish is built with the more experienced user in mind and is aimed at small, fast, secure server and workstation systems with a minimum of installed packages. The initial release of Webfish Linux, version 0.9b, was released June 20, 2002. Version 1.0pre1 was released on March 25, 2003. The Webfish Linux Firewall-1 branch released its initial verion, 1.1, on July 24, 2002. Fishwall 1.2 was released August 27, 2002.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webfs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
lightweight http server for static content This is a simple http server for purely static content.  You can use it to serve the content of a ftp server via http for example.  It is also nice to export some files the quick way by starting a http server in a few seconds, without editing some config file first. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
weblint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a syntax and minimal style checker for HTML This is perl script which picks fluff off html pages, much in the same way traditional lint picks fluff off C programs. The script is pretty much a a wrapper around the Weblint module.  It currently supports HTML 4.0 (and only HTML 4.0).  It allows the various syntax and stylistic checks to be enabled or disabled by the user or in a system-wide configuration file. NOTE: This is a beta release of Weblint 2.0 that provides a subset of of the final functionality.  There are one or two features from 1.020 that aren&apos;t currently available.  But this implements just about all the warnings from 1.020 and uses current HTML standards. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webmagick
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
create gallery thumbnails for website WebMagick provides a means of easily putting image collections on the Web. It recurses through directory trees, building HTML pages and imagemap (GIF or JPEG) files to allow the user to navigate through collections of thumbnail images (somewhat similar to &apos;xv&apos;) and select the images to view with a mouse click. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webmin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A web-based administration interface for Unix systems. Using Webmin youcan configure DNS, Samba, NFS, local/remote filesystems, Apache, Sendmail/Postfix, and more using your web browser. After installation, enter the URL https://localhost:10000/ into your browser and login as root with your root password. Please consider logging in and modify your password for security issue. PLEASE NOTE THAT THIS VERSION NOW USES SECURE WEB TRANSACTIONS: YOU HAVE TO LOGIN TO &quot;https://localhost:10000/&quot; AND NOT &quot;http://localhost:10000/&quot;. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webmin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web-based administration toolkit Webmin is a web-based interface for system administration for Unix. Using any browser that supports tables and forms (and Java for the File Manager module), you can setup user accounts, Apache, DNS, file sharing and so on. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webpage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A page that contains text, images, and multimedia presentations and is viewable in a Web browser. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
webrick
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simple HTTP Server Toolkit for Ruby WEBrick is a Ruby library program to build HTTP servers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
websec
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Secretary Web Secretary is a web page monitoring software. However, it goes beyond the normal functionalities offered by such software. Not only does it detect changes based on content analysis (instead of date/time stamp or simple textual comparison), it will email the changed page to you WITH THE NEW CONTENT HIGHLIGHTED! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
website
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A collection of webpages, files, and other resources published or aggregated by one source. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WECA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Ethernet Compatibility Alliance (org., WLAN, LAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WEEB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Western Europe EDIFACT Board (org., EDIFACT), &quot;WE/EB&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
weex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A non-interactive FTP client for updating web pages Weex is an utility designed to automate the task of remotely maintaining a web page or other FTP archive. With weex, the maintainer of a web site or archive that must be administered through FTP interaction can largely ignore that process. The archive administrator simply creates a local directory that serves as an exact model for the off-site data. All modifications and direct interaction is done locally to this directory structure. When the administrator wishes to coordinate the data on the remote site with that of the local model directory, simply executing weex accomplishes this in the most bandwidth-efficient fashion by only transferring files that need updating. The program will create or remove (!) files or directories as necessary to accurately establish the local model on the remote server. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WEFT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Embedding Font Tool (MS, WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
welcome2l
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Linux ANSI boot logo. This is a little program that may run at login time to produce nice ANSI login logo. Welcome2L intends to produce  the best looking ANSI screens by making full usage of PC graphic characters. Therefore an architecture able to display those characters (i386, Alpha with TGA adapter,... ) is required to use it.  And, even if it will work on larger screens, it will only produce 80 column ANSI screens. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WELL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Whole Earth &apos;Lectronic Net (network) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
well-behaved
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
adj. 1. [primarily MS-DOS] Said of software conforming to system interface guidelines and standards. Well-behaved software uses the operating system to do chores such as keyboard input, allocating memory and drawing graphics. Oppose ill-behaved. 2. Software that does its job quietly and without counterintuitive effects. Esp. said of software having an interface spec sufficiently simple and well-defined that it can be used as a tool by other software. See cat. 3. Said of an algorithm that doesn&apos;t crash or blow up, even when given pathological input. Implies that the stability of the algorithm is intrinsic, which makes this somewhat different from bulletproof.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wemi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Branch of SEMI kernel package using widget. WEMI is a branch of the SEMI package using widgets.  It is a library adding MIME features to Emacs, based on SEMI, which also available as a Debian package.  It is a replacement of SEMI, containing all of SEMI&apos;s features. WEMI does not support anything older than Emacs 19.28 or XEmacs 19.14.  WEMI also does not support Emacs 19.29 to 19.34, XEmacs 19.15 or XEmacs 20.2 without mule, but WEMI may work with them. ==== SEMI is a library adding MIME features to Emacs. MIME is a proposed internet standard allowing the use of other character sets than (ASCII) plain text in the contents and headers of messages. ==== From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wenglish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
English dictionary words for /usr/share/dict This package provides the file /usr/share/dict/american-english containing a list of English words with American spellings. This list can be used by spelling checkers, and by programs such as look(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WEP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wired Equivalent Privacy (WLAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WESTNET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WESTern regional NETwork (network, USA), &quot;Westnet&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Western European Time [+0000] (TZ, WDT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wfaroese
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Faroese dictionary / wordlist This is a flat list of Faroese words and names. This can be used by spellcheckers or any other purpose needing a lot of words. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wait for Caller (BBS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Foundation Classes (MS, Java, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wfinnish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A small Finnish dictionary for /usr/share/dict. This is a list of Finnish words and names in various inflected forms, containing roughly 0.7 million items, to be used for whatever purpose you may think of. Larger lists (roughly two or over six million items) can be manually generated from the medium-size and large Finnish Ispell dictionaries in packages ifinnish and ifinnish-large.  Please find instructions in /usr/share/doc/wfinnish/README.Debian after installing this package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wired For Management (Intel), &quot;WfM&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Works For Me (slang, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFMC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WorkFlow Management Coalition (org.), &quot;WfMC&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFQ
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Weighted Fair Queueing (VOIP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wfrench
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
French dictionary words for /usr/share/dict This package provides the file /usr/share/dict/french containing a list of French words.  This list can be used by spelling checkers, and by programs such as look(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WFW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows For Workgroups (MS), &quot;WfW&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Working Group (SC, ISO, IEC, ETSI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wgerman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The German dictionary for /usr/share/dict. This is the German dictionary as put together by heinz.knutzen@web.de. This dictionary refers to the old German orthography.  For the new orthography see wngerman. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GNU Wget is a file retrieval utility which can use either the HTTP or FTP protocols. Wget features include the ability to work in the background while you are logged out, recursive retrieval of directories, file name wildcard matching, remote file time stamp storage and comparison, use of Rest with FTP servers and Range with HTTP servers to retrieve files over slow or unstable connections,support for Proxy servers, and configurability. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
retrieves files from the web Wget is a network utility to retrieve files from the Web using http and ftp, the two most widely used Internet protocols. It works non-interactively, so it will work in the background, after having logged off. The program supports recursive retrieval of web-authoring pages as well as ftp sites -- you can use wget to make mirrors of archives and home pages or to travel the Web like a WWW robot. Wget works particularly well with slow or unstable connections by continuing to retrieve a document until the document is fully downloaded. Re-getting files from where it left off works on servers (both http and ftp) that support it. Both http and ftp retrievals can be time stamped, so wget can see if the remote file has changed since the last retrieval and automatically retrieve the new version if it has. Wget supports proxy servers; this can lighten the network load, speed up retrieval, and provide access behind firewalls. http://www.gnu.org/software/wget/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
what you see is what you get (wysiwyg)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Concept that is commonly utilized by complex document formatting applications for ease of use and accurate rendering. As a user creates a document, it is rendered on a display as it appears when it is saved, printed, or sent to another party. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whatis
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display manual page descriptions From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WHCA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
White House Communications Agency (DISA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wheel bit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. A privilege bit that allows the possessor to perform some restricted operation on a timesharing system, such as read or write any file on the system regardless of protections, change or look at any address in the running monitor, crash or reload the system, and kill or create jobs and user accounts. The term was invented on the TENEX operating system, and carried over to TOPS-20, XEROX-IFS, and others. The state of being in a privileged logon is sometimes called `wheel mode&apos;. This term entered the Unix culture from TWENEX in the mid-1980s and has been gaining popularity there (esp. at university sites). See also root.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wheel of reincarnation
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[coined in a paper by T. H. Myer and I.E. Sutherland &quot;On the Design of Display Processors&quot;, Comm. ACM, Vol. 11, no. 6, June 1968)] Term used to refer to a well-known effect whereby function in a computing system family is migrated out to special-purpose peripheral hardware for speed, then the peripheral evolves toward more computing power as it does its job, then somebody notices that it is inefficient to support two asymmetrical processors in the architecture and folds the function back into the main CPU, at which point the cycle begins again. Several iterations of this cycle have been observed in graphics-processor design, and at least one or two in communications and floating-point processors. Also known as `the Wheel of Life&apos;, `the Wheel of Samsara&apos;, and other variations of the basic Hindu/Buddhist theological idea. See also blitter, bit bang.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whereami
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Automatically reconfigure your (laptop) system for a new location whereami is a set of useful scripts and a coordinating system for automatically re-locating your computer within the current (network) environment. Typically, you would use whereami to automatically detect and re-configure your laptop when you move between a variety of diverse networks and/or docking environments. Although whereami will work best if all of your networks assign addresses through dhcp, this is not a pre-requisite and the system allows any technique to be used to ascertain the new location with as little ongoing user intervention as possible. Having ascertained the correct location, whereami will run appropriate (user-configured) scripts to adjust the laptop operation to suit the current environment. See http://debiana.net/whereami/ for more information.  You may also get useful assistance from the debian-laptop mailing list, which is frequented by several of the contributors. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whereis
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
locate the binary, source, and manual page files for a command From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
which
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The which command shows the full pathname of a specified program, if the specified program is in your PATH. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whichman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fault tolerant search utilities: whichman, ftff, ftwhich. whichman uses a fault tolerant approximate matching algorithm to search for man-pages that match approximately the specified name. The fault tolerant matching is very useful in cases where you remember only roughly the name of a command.    Example: whichman netwhat    This finds netstat.8: /usr/share/man/man8/netstat.8 ftff searches the directory tree. This is a case in-sensitive and fault tolerant way of &apos;find . -name xxxx -print&apos;. ftwhich finds files which are in one of the directories in your PATH and uses a fault tolerant search algorithm. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WHIIG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Hardware Instrumentation Implementation Guidelines (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whiptail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays user-friendly dialog boxes from shell scripts. whiptail is a &quot;dialog&quot; replacement using newt instead of ncurses. It provides a method of displaying several different types of dialog boxes from shell scripts. This allows a developer of a script to interact with the user in a much friendlier manner. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whiptail-utf8
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays user-friendly dialog boxes from shell scripts. whiptail is a &quot;dialog&quot; replacement using newt instead of ncurses. It provides a method of displaying several different types of dialog boxes from shell scripts. This allows a developer of a script to interact with the user in a much friendlier manner. This version of whiptail is compiled and linked against utf8 version of the libraries. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whisker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
CGI scanner to audit web servers Whisker is a state-of-the-art CGI scanner that can:   - detect the running web server and perform only tests specific     to that server and version   - apply intrusion detection evasion methods   - do brute force on accounts using HTTP-AUTH   - use virtual hosts   - run in multi-thread mode It can output the information in different formats including HTML and nmap. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
White Book
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. Syn. K&amp;R. 2. Adobe&apos;s fourth book in the PostScript series, describing the previously-secret format of Type 1 fonts; &quot;Adobe Type 1 Font Format, version 1.1&quot;, (Addison-Wesley, 1990, ISBN 0-201-57044-0). See also Red Book, Green Book, Blue Book. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
White Dwarf Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
White Dwarf Linux is named for a White Dwarf Star. White Dwarf Stars are small but extremely dense stars. White Dwarf Linux is small enough to load in 16MB of Flash, but dense enough to contain the features that embedded applications demand. Version 1.2.0 was released July 28, 2002.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
white-hat hackers (ethical-hacking)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
So-called &quot;ethical&quot; hackers who work with clients in order to help them secure their systems. White-hats can be: members of tiger teams system hardening specialists researchers looking for vulnerabilities (with the goal of finding them and removing them before the black-hats). Contrast: Whereas a &quot;white-hate&quot; is considered a &quot;good guy&quot;, a &quot;black-hat&quot; describes the &quot;bad&quot; hackers. See also: penetration testing From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whitelist
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. The opposite of a blacklist. That is, instead of being an explicit list of people who are banned, it&apos;s an explicit list of people who are to be admitted. Hackers use this especially of lists of email addresses that are explicitly enabled to get past strict anti-spam filters. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whizzytex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a WYSIWIG environment for LaTeX WhizzyTeX is an emacs minor mode for incrementally (TeXing and) previewing a LaTeX file that you are editing. It works with ghostview-based and xdvi-based previewers, but best visual effect and more options will be available if you use the advi previewer. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
who
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
show who is logged on From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
who
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Shows who is logged on. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whoami
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
print effective userid From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whois
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A whois client that accepts both traditional and finger-style queries. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whois
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
client for the whois directory service From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whois
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The GNU whois client This is a new whois (RFC 954) client rewritten from scratch by me. It is derived from and compatible with the usual BSD and RIPE whois(1) programs. It is intelligent and can automatically select the appropriate whois server for most queries. The package also contains mkpasswd, a simple front end to crypt(3). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WHOLIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Health Organization Library Information System (org., UNO) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WHOSIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Health Organization Statistical Information System (org., UNO) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
whowatch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Real-time user logins monitoring tool. whowatch is a ncurses who-like utility that displays information about the users currently logged on to the machine, in real-time.  Besides standard information (login name, tty, host, user&apos;s process), the type of the connection (ie. telnet or ssh) is shown. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WHQL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Hardware Quality Lab (MS, Windows, PC97) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Image Aquisition (MS, Windows, API, DDI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIDD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web InformationsDienst Deutschland (WWW, Neuss, Germany) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wide-area network (WAN)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A network of computers connected to each other over a long distance, for example on the Internet. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Widget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical user interface programming object (button, scrollbar, radio button, etc.) for the X Window System. (Also, see X Window System.) From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
widget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A standardized on-screen representation of a control that may be manipulated by the user. Scroll bars, buttons, and text boxes are all examples of widgets. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
widget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a user interface object in X graphical user interfaces. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
widget
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. A meta-thing. Used to stand for a real object in didactic examples (especially database tutorials). Legend has it that the original widgets were holders for buggy whips. &quot;But suppose the parts list for a widget has 52 entries....&quot; 2. [poss. evoking `window gadget&apos;] A user interface object in X graphical user interfaces. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Interface Facility (WWW, MVS, OS/390) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Wiki
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wiki is a piece of server software that allows users to freely create and edit Web page content using any Web browser. Wiki supports hyperlinks and has a simple text syntax for creating new pages and crosslinks between internal pages on the fly. Wiki is unusual among group communication mechanisms in that it allows the organization of contributions to be edited in addition to the content itself. Like many simple concepts, "open editing" has some profound and subtle effects on Wiki usage. Allowing everyday users to create and edit any page in a Web site is exciting in that it encourages democratic use of the Web and promotes content composition by nontechnical users. Historical Note. The first ever wiki site was created for the Portland Pattern Repository in 1995. That site now hosts tens of thousands of pages. From Wiki
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wild
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A phrase that implies that the technique is currently being used, as opposed to be purely theoretical. For example, while tens of thousands of viruses are known to exist, only a few hundred can be found in the wild. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wild card
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
character, used to search for text, that may represent any character (or any character in a set). A wild-card character is like a wild card in a card game, which may represent any other card in the deck. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wily
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A work-alike of the Acme programming environment for Plan 9 Wily&apos;s basic functions are to edit and search for text and to run commands. It is intended to eventually be an integrated working environment for all tasks involving text. It uses the mouse heavily. It emphasises speed for experienced users, but is probably simple to learn as it has very few concepts. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIMAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WIreless Metropolitan Area Network From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIMP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window, Icon, Menu, Pointing device From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIMP environment
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [acronym: `Window, Icon, Menu, Pointing device (or Pull-down menu)&apos;] A graphical-user-interface environment such as X or the Macintosh interface, esp. as described by a hacker who prefers command-line interfaces for their superior flexibility and extensibility. However, it is also used without negative connotations; one must pay attention to voice tone and other signals to interpret correctly. See menuitis, user-obsequious.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WIssenschaftsNetz (network, DFN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
winbind
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Service to resolve user and group information from Windows NT servers This package provides the winbindd daemon, which provides a service for the Name Service Switch capability that is present in most modern C libraries (like the GNU C Library - glibc.) The service provided by winbindd is called `winbind&apos; and can be used to resolve user and group information from a Windows NT server. The service can also provide authentication services via an associated PAM module. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
window
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical representation of a program displayed on the screen. Each running program has a separate window displaying the contents of the program. Some programs have more than one window displayed, usually to separate functions logically and facilitate use of the program. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
window manager
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program that controls the display and positioning of graphical windows on a screen; accounts for such variables as screen resolution and user manipulation (for example, a user repositioning or resizing a window). From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Window Manager
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The graphical user interface (GUI) that runs on top of X Window to provide the user with windows, icons, taskbars and other desktop objects. (Also, see Desktop.) From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
window manager
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the main interface between the X Window system and the user. It rovides such functionality as window borders, menus, icons, virtual desktops, button bars, tool bars, and allows the user to customize it at will, often adding to its functionality in the process. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WindowMaker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window Maker is an X11 window manager which emulates the look and feel of the NeXTSTEP (TM) graphical user interface. It is relatively fast, feature rich and easy to configure and use. Window Maker is part of the official GNU project, which means that Window Maker can interoperate with other GNU projects, such as GNOME. Window Maker allows users to switch themes &apos;on the fly,&apos; to place favorite applications on either an application dock, similar to AfterStep&apos;s Wharf or on a workspace dock, a &apos;clip&apos; which extends the application dock&apos;s usefulness. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
windows-el
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window manager for GNU Emacs You can divide  the screen of GNU Emacs  as many as you  like. Since efficiency of implementation or so  depends  much  on  the style  of  window division,  you  may have  your  own  style  of partitioning.   But  if you  switch the  mode to  e-mail mode or NetNews mode, they break your favorite style. Windows.el  enables  you  to  have  multiple  favorite  window configurations at the  same time, and switch them.  Furthermore, it can save all window  configurations into a  file and  restore them correctly. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wine
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
run Windows programs on Unix From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wine
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Emulator (Binary Emulator). the MS-Windows emulator.  This is still a developers release and many applications may still not work. This package consists of the emulator program for running windows executables. Wine is often updated. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
winesetuptk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Emulator (Configuration and Setup Tool) This is an easy-to-use Wine setup tool provided by CodeWeavers, Inc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wing
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a galaga knock-off, arcade game WING is a galaga knock-off, arcade game. It features high quality prerendered graphics, dynamically generated stars in background, single player game against computer controlled opponents, 6 levels of play, digital sound effects, digital music streams, and a high score list. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WINHEC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WINdows Hardware Engineering Conference (MS, Windows, conference), &quot;WinHEC&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WINLAB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Information Network LABoratory (org., STC, USA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WinLinux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WinLinux 2001 was designed and built to be the easiest to use Linux system. Its installation and configuration tasks are performed directly from Windows using graphical tools. WinLinux 2003 is currently available.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WINS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Internet Naming Service (MS, Windows NT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WinSlack
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WinSlack is a basic Linux install with KDE and Star Office. It requires no logon, and gives you a desktop environment similar to that other leading PC GUI, it also has supermount compiled into the kernel so that CD-ROM&apos;s and floppies are automatically mounted and unmounted. You can also format floppies from the desktop. Upon exiting the X session, the machine will shutdown. It is based primarily on Slackware 7.1 with some modifications.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Wintel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. Microsoft Windows plus Intel - the tacit alliance that dominated desktop computing in the 1990s. Now (1999) possibly on the verge of breaking up under pressure from Linux; see Lintel. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wipe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Erased data can frequently be retrieved through forensics on the magnetic material of a hard-disk drive or backup tape. So-called &quot;magnetoresistive microscopes&quot; have been developed that painstakingly scour magnetic media, and are able to reconstruct the magnetic image of a disk surface. This will show the faint residue of overwritten data. A common security measure is to &quot;wipe&quot; all traces of the data from a machine. Wiping usually involves: Clearing caches and logfiles. Example include browser caches, cookie files, history logs, and recently used document lists. Note that passwords are often stored in cookies and history URLs. Hard-disks &quot;erase&quot; files by simply removing their entries from the directory. The files still exist on the hard-disk. The first step of wiping is to actually erase them by overwriting that area of the disk. Overwriting erased areas of the hard-disk at least 7-times with different bytes (DoD spec) in order to remove all magnetic traces. Forensics specialists can usually read data from a disk that has been overwritten only once. Wiping the pagefile. Most programs do this by repeated allocating all possible memory in the system then freeing it, multiple times. Contrast: Wiping data from the disk is the electronic equivalent of shredding. It is not as strong as degaussing the disk. Misconception: Many crypto programs also contain a feature for wiping free-space. However, deleted files may be overwritten by some other file between wiping passes. This deleted file won&apos;t be wiped, and may be recoverable. Key point: In a court case in 2001, the FBI was able to successful retrieve overwritten files from a defendant&apos;s hard-drive. History: Microsoft&apos;s Windows XP, shipped in October of 2001, contains an automatic wipe feature for permanently deleting files. This has made some forensics investigators worried that they will no longer be able to successfully retrieve deleted files from dumb-criminal&apos;s machines. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wipe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Secure file deletion Recovery of supposedly erased data from magnetic media is easier than what many people would like to believe. A technique called Magnetic Force Microscopy (MFM) allows any moderately funded opponent to recover the last two or three layers of data written to disk. Wipe repeatedly writes special patterns to the files to be destroyed, using the fsync() call and/or the O_SYNC bit to force disk access. Homepage: http://gsu.linux.org.tr/wipe/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIPO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Intellectual Property Organization (org.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wireless
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The condition of functioning without a wire or cable attached. For example, a wireless network uses radio frequencies travelling in the air instead of a physical wire to transmit data. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Wireless Fidelity (Wi-Fi)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
see 802.11 From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wireless-tools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tools for manipulating Linux Wireless Extensions This package contains the Wireless tools, used to manipulate the Linux Wireless Extensions. The Wireless Extension is an interface allowing you to set Wireless LAN specific parameters and get the specific stats. The tools in this package only work with kernel versions 2.2.14 and above, and 2.3.24 and above. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WISC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wisconsin Integrally Synchronized Computer From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WISE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World-wide Information System for r&amp;d Efforts (WWW, IGD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simple windowing shell From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wish list
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. A list of desired features or bug fixes that probably won&apos;t get done for a long time, usually because the person responsible for the code is too busy or can&apos;t think of a clean way to do it. &quot;OK, I&apos;ll add automatic filename completion to the wish list for the new interface.&quot; Compare tick-list features. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wish8.3
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simple windowing shell From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WISIA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wissenschaftliches InformationsSystem fuer den Internationalen Artenschutz (WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
witalian
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Italian dictionary words for /usr/share/dict/. This package contains an alphabetic list of Italian words. You may wish to use it in conjunction with a program like spell(1) to spell-check an Italian text, or with a program like look(1) for word completion. It may even be used by the sysadmin to look for weak user passwords. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WITT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Workstation Interactive Test Tool (IBM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wizard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. Transitively, a person who knows how a complex piece of software or hardware works (that is, who groks it); esp. someone who can find and fix bugs quickly in an emergency. Someone is a hacker if he or she has general hacking ability, but is a wizard with respect to something only if he or she has specific detailed knowledge of that thing. A good hacker could become a wizard for something given the time to study it. 2. The term `wizard&apos; is also used intransitively of someone who has extremely high-level hacking or problem-solving ability. 3. A person who is permitted to do things forbidden to ordinary people; one who has wheel privileges on a system. 4. A Unix expert, esp. a Unix systems programmer. This usage is well enough established that `Unix Wizard&apos; is a recognized job title at some corporations and to most headhunters. See guru, lord high fixer. See also deep magic, heavy wizardry, incantation, magic, mutter, rain dance, voodoo programming, wave a dead chicken. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wizard mode
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [from rogue] A special access mode of a program or system, usually passworded, that permits some users godlike privileges. Generally not used for operating systems themselves (`root mode&apos; or `wheel mode&apos; would be used instead). This term is often used with respect to games that have editable state. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WIZOP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WIzard sysOP, &quot;WizOp&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WKS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Well Known Services (DNS, Internet) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Message Interface On Emacsen. Wanderlust is IMAP4, POP and NNTP client on Emacsen. Wanderlust has many powerful features.  - Coding with only Elisp.  - MIME support (SEMI or tm)  - 3 frames mode(folder, summary, message)  - Thread view  - Virtual Folder Support  - Archived Folder Support  - MH local Folder Support  - and so on. Wanderlust is needs MULE support with emacsen. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLAN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Local Area Network (LAN, WLAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLANA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Local Area Network Alliance (org., WLAN, LAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLBS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Load Balancing Service (MS, Windows NT) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLIF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless LAN Interoperability Forum (org., WLAN, LAN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Local Loop From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Library Objects From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wafer Level Packaging From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WLS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
White Line Skip (Fax) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wm2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Small, unconfigurable window manager wm2 is a window manager for X.  It provides an unusual style of window decoration and as little functionality as Chris Cannam feels comfortable with in a window manager.  wm2 is not configurable, except by editing the source and recompiling the code, and is really intended for people who don&apos;t particularly want their window manager to be too friendly. The &quot;debian menus&quot; functionality has been removed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WMA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Media Audio [CODEC] (MS, Windows, audio, CODEC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmacpi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An ACPI battery monitor for WindowMaker (alpha) This is a battery monitor that uses ACPI to query the battery status. As the interface to ACPI changes rather often, this program usually only works with a very specific kernel version. This package is for kernel version 2.4.2 or greater, ACPI subsystem version 20010313 or greater. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmaker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
NeXTSTEP-like window manager for X Written by Alfredo Kojima (http://www.inf.ufrgs.br/~kojima) almost from scratch, resembles the NeXTStep look very closely, and it&apos;s now an official GNU project.  Window Maker is not overloaded with features, and it&apos;s easier to configure than most other window managers.  Its final goal is to produce a window manager that doesn&apos;t require editing of configuration files.  Window Maker is fast and doesn&apos;t require tons of memory to run. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmakerconf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GTK+ based configuration tool for Window Maker Interactive graphical configuration utility for Window Maker. It offers to configure Window Maker using a mouse driven point and click interface avoiding direct manual editing of its configuration files. There&apos;s not much point in installing this program without Window Maker on the system, but I guess there are some circumstances where that&apos;s desirable, for example, self-compiled wmaker versions. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmanager
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Select a window manager at X startup wmanager is a small X11 application for selecting a window manager at X startup. wmanager looks for a file named &apos;.wmmanagerrc&apos; in the user&apos;s home directory which contains a list of window managers; you can create such a file with wmanagerrc-update. You can also use wmanager-loop that runs window managers chosen by the user until told to exit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmapm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An APM display program designed for WindowMaker Displays the Advanced Power Management (APM) status of your computer in a small icon. This includes battery or AC operation, battery life remaining (both in percentage and graph), time left until battery-depletion, charging status, and battery status. There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it require WindowMaker, except maybe the look. To use this program you need to enable APM support for your kernel during configuration; the corresponding questions are in the &apos;Character devices&apos; section. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmavgload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
small NeXTStep-like system load average monitor wmavgload provides CPU load averages integrated over 5 (main window), 30 and 60 seconds. Also, it takes very little space (64x64 square). There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it *require* WindowMaker, i.e. it works great with other window managers. But if you are looking for seamless integration on your desktop, wmavgload may suit your needs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmbattery
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Display laptop battery info, dockable in WindowMaker Wmbattery displays the status of your laptop&apos;s battery in a small icon. This includes if it is plugged in, if the battery is charging, how many minutes of battery life remain, battery life remaining (with both a percentage and a graph), and battery status (high - green, low - yellow, or critical - red). There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it require WindowMaker, except maybe the look. It can be docked in WindowMaker or AfterStep&apos;s dock. To use this program you need to enable APM support for your kernel during configuration; the corresponding questions are in the &apos;Character devices&apos; section. It will only work on laptops with an APM BIOS. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmbiff
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A dockable app that displays information about mailboxes WMBiff is an WindowMaker docking utility, that displays the number of read and unread messages in up to five mailboxes. You can also define actions to execute on new mail arrival (for example, play a sound file), [auto]fetchmail from a remote server or to execute your mail reader with a mouse click. WMBiff also supports notification of incoming Licq messages, so you can put Licq in the background. At this moment, wmbiff supports unix-style, maildir, pop3, APOP, IMAP and IMAPS mailboxes, as well as Licq and GnomeICU history files. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmbubble
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A system-load meter for Window Maker that features a duck A Window Maker dockapp (though it does not specifically require the Window Maker window manager) that indicates the system load. The more profuse the bubbles, the higher the CPU usage. The higher the water, the more memory being used. It can also start up to two programs depending upon which mouse button is pressed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmbutton
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockapp displaying nine configurable buttons Wmbutton displays nine buttons which can be configured through a config file. Each button can be assigned up to three commands (one per mouse button). It is intended as a dockapp for X window managers such as Window Maker, AfterStep, BlackBox, and Enlightenment. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcalc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockable calculator application Wmcalc is a small calculator meant for the WindowMaker dock or Afterstep Wharf. It is a simple calculator with basic functions and memory slots, and can launch any external application for more complex calculations. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcalclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A dock.app which simply tells time and date. wmCalclock is a dock app specifically written for Window Maker, but will work with other window managers.  Some features include antialiased text display, with the ability to choose between different fonts, and colors. 12 and 24 hour time, Greenwich time, Greenwich Mean Sidereal Time, and Local Sidereal Time. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockapp that displays the cut buffer content Wmcb is a WindowMaker dockapp that displays the current content of the cut buffers built into every Xserver. It allows the buffers to be manipulated with the mouse in a point and click manner. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcdplay
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A CD player based on ascd designed for WindowMaker There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it *require* WindowMaker, except maybe the look. It&apos;s extremely customizable, provides great control, and runs on a 64x64 window. You can get it too look almost like anything, provided of course you READ the documentation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
dockable clock applet for Window Maker Wmclock is a dockable applet which displays the date and time in a dockable tile.  Wmclock is specially designed for the Window Maker window manager, and features multiple language support,  am/pm time display, and can run a user-specified program on a mouse click. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcpu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window Maker docking app similar to xosview Displays a 64x64 box with:  * CPU  * Mem  * Swap  * Uptime From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcpuload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockapp that displays the current CPU usage WMCPULoad is a dockapp for X window managers such as WindowMaker, AfterStep, BlackBox and Enlightenment. It displays the current CPU usage as percentage value and chart with an LCD-like look. Its appearance can be configured from the commandline and it has a backlight mode which can be triggered manually or by an adjustable alarm percentage. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmcube
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Spinning 3D object that shows the current CPU load wmcube is a dockapp that displays a realtime rotating 3D object which indicates current CPU load. The higher the load, the faster the object spins. On SMP machines one instance can be run for each processor. Originally wmcube could spin only a cube, hence the name. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmdate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Calendar for window manager docking bars. wmdate produces a 64x64 pixel calendar for use in the docking bars of window managers.  It was written specificly for Window Maker and goes well with docking bars that have a &quot;clock-only&quot; clock app such as pclock. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Mail Folder This program converts emails to HTML and makes index files (by author, data, subject,thread). Of course there are other programs making the same, but here are some features which not all have:        - correct threading without level limitation        - quoted-printable text encoding        - home page hyperlink (X-URL)        - faces support        - breaking indexes in different pages to make them smaller          (don&apos;t break between threads)        - index time limitation (older mail disappears from the index)        - frame support From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmfire
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A very cool fiery way of showing your CPU usage! The display is a 64x64 window designed to Dock into Window Maker&apos;s Docking bar. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmfsm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WindowMaker dock app for monitoring filesystem usage Nice graphical &apos;df&apos;, showing you to what degree the mounted filesystems are used. Another X11 dockable application designed for WindowMaker. It works with other window managers as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmgrabimage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
maintains a small thumbnail image from the WWW wmGrabImage is a WindowMaker DockApp that maintains a small thumbnail copy of your favorite image from the WWW. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmgtemp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Temperature sensor dockapp for WindowMaker It displays the CPU and SYS temperatures (both in numerically and graphically) of motherboards with the VIA686A chipset primarily but also supports some other sensors, including W83781D, W83627HF and AS99127F. There is also intention of adding support for other chipsets in the future. You will need a kernel compiled with i2c capabilities to make this work, use the i2c-source package to make it for yourself. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WMI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Management Instrumentation / Interface (MS, Windows, WMI, CIM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmifs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WindowMaker dock app for monitoring network traffic wmifs is a dockable applet for X11 that can monitor all your network interfaces. It&apos;s designed for WindowMaker&apos;s Dock and AfterStep&apos;s Wharf, but it&apos;s not dependent on these window managers and should work with any other. WMiFS stands for &quot;Window Maker InterFace Statistics&quot;. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wminet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An inetd monitoring dockapp designed for WindowMaker WMiNET has some nice &amp; nifty features for monitoring, like:   * Monitors number of processes, users, http users, and NFS mounts   * LPD monitoring   * Monitors any tcp port you specify   * Selectable LED or LCD GUI   * Enable/disable monitoring using ~/.wminetrc   * Customs stats positioning using  ~/.wminetrc   * User-definable scripts/commands using ~/.wminetrc From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmitime
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
yet another clock dock app for Window Maker WMitime is yet another clock dock app (and quite overglorified at that! :) it shows standard time, date, as well as the new internet time. (see http://www.swatch.com/) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmix
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockapp mixer for OSS or ALSA Dockapp mixer for OSS or ALSA. Allows toggling record source, muting individual channels, adjusting volume and balance, all in a compact dockapp size, with TV-like on-screen-display for volume levels. Supports mousewheel to adjust current channelvolume and can be controlled remotely with SIGUSR1 / SIGUSR2 to adjust the volume. Keeps a simple configuration file for user-defined settings. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wml
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Website META Language by Ralf Engelschall WML is a free and extensible Webdesigner&apos;s off-line HTML generation toolkit for Unix.  WML consists of a control frontend driving up to nine backends in a sequential pass-oriented filtering scheme. Each backend provides one particular core language. For maximum power WML additionally ships with a well-suited set of include files which provide higher-level features build on top of the backends core languages. While not trivial and idiot proof WML provides most of the core features real hackers always wanted for HTML generation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Markup Language (mobile-systems, WAP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
system load monitor designed for Window Maker wmload displays a graphical representation of the kernel/system statistics on a 64x64 miniwindow. There are three shades in the window: the light one, which corresponds to user statistics, second is the nice time statistics, and the darkest one is system statistics. It works with other window managers, there isn&apos;t anything in the program to make it require Window Maker, except maybe the look. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A mail notification program designed for WindowMaker There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it require WindowMaker, except maybe the look. It&apos;s much like xbiff, and was derived from asmail 0.50. Now includes support for a variety of mailboxes, including mbox, MH, maildir, POP3 and IMAP.  A few pixmaps and sounds are included with the package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmand
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a dockable Mandelbrot fractal browser wmMand is a dockable Mandelbrot fractal browser or explorer. The window initially comes up with the whole Mandelbrot set in view. The mouse buttons can be used to zoom into or out of the set. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmatrix
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
View The Matrix in a Window Maker dock application wmMatrix displays The Matrix (from the film of the same name) in a Window Maker dock application. Based on the xscreensaver module created by Jamie Zawinski. Although it works best with Window Maker, wmMatrix also works fine with other window managers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmixer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A mixer application designed for WindowMaker There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it require WindowMaker, except maybe the NeXTStep look and the fact that it properly docks. It can be used with other window managers without problems From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Monitor CPU load and average system load WMMon monitors the realtime CPU load as well the average system load and gives you some nice additional features too... WMMon currently provides:   * Realtime CPU &apos;stress&apos; meter   * Average system load, like xload &amp; wmavgload   * Average system load graphic is auto-scaling   * Realtime Disk I/O &apos;stress&apos; meter   * Average Disk I/O load graphic (auto-scaling)   * Realtime total Mem &amp; Swap usage meters   * System uptime display   * Realtime cycling through all monitor modes   * Can launch 3 user definable commands through ~/.wmmonrc   * Can be started multiple times From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmoonclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays the phase of the moon wmMoonClock displays a small pixmap of the current phase of the moon. It is designed for use with the Window Maker dock, but will of course work elsewhere. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmmount
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
mount utility and free space monitoring tool, NeXTStep-like wmmount can be used to mount and unmount floppies, CD-ROM&apos;s, ZIP drives, and file systems in general. It also displays the amount of free space on the file system. It is very customizable and runs on a 64x64 window. There&apos;s nothing in the program that makes it *require* WindowMaker, i.e. it works great with other window managers. But if you are looking for seamless integration on your desktop, wmmount may very well suit your needs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmnd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockapp monitoring network interfaces Shows a graph of incoming/outgoing traffic, activity indicators for rx/tx and current/maximum rate for rx/tx in bytes or packets. Tailored for use with WindowMaker, it will as well work with any other window manager though. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmnet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
network monitor for WindowMaker using kernel IP accounting This little program polls /proc/net/ip_acct and does a few things with the data it gets. The speedometer keeps track of the current speed per second and shows it in a color corresponding to which of rx or tx that has the highest speed at the moment. You WILL need ip accounting in your kernel and at least two ip firewall rules. This version allows you to specify which accounting rule to watch for tx and rx and you will have to enter them in ipfwadm or use the debian package ipac. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmnetselect
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Enhanced Netscape launch button designed for Windowmaker This is a replacement for the Netscape/Mozilla launch button in your dock, that enhances the functionality of the button. You can use it just as you normally would to start Netscape. If you select an URL and paste it into the wmnetselect button, it will redirect netscape to that URL. Other features include quick Google.com searches and quick addition of URLs to your bookmarks. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmnut
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A wmaker dock app that displays UPS statistics from NUT&apos;s upsd WMNUT monitors UPS statistics through the NUT (Network UPS Tools, www.exploits.org/nut) framework on Linux and other systems.  This information, presented in a nice visual format, can be invaluable on stations using an UPS. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmpinboard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window Maker dock applet resembling a miniature pinboard Themable Window Maker dock applet resembling a miniature pinboard. Icon is titled TODO.  Includes alarm functions.  Think of it as very high-tech post-its for your dockbar. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmpload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Program to monitor network device statistics Wmpload is a Window Maker dock application to monitor ppp network device statistics and graphs information using Athena stripchart widgets. It  can monitor  any device that reports statistics to /proc/net/dev  including ethernet, plip, loopback etc. It shows totals and  current rates for a given ppp interface and is customizable to show using X resources. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmppp.app
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PPP dial control and network load monitor with NeXTStep look wmppp.app provides a PPP activator and network load monitor on a 64x64 mini window.  With wmppp you can monitor the total traffic as well as the outbound and inbound traffic.  It is designed to work with the WindowMaker dock, but will work great with other window managers as well. Now with experimental (untested) ippp device support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmppxp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PPxP console for Window Maker dock WMPPxP is a Window Maker dock app of PPxP console.  PPxP is yet another ppp program. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmpuzzle
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WindowMaker dock app 4x4 puzzle wmpuzzle provides a 4x4 puzzle on a 64x64 mini window. Currently you can puzzle an eagle, earth, the Debian logo or the Linux penguin. Other images will be included on request. wmpuzzle is designed to work with the WindowMaker dock, but will work with other window managers as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmrack
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Combined CD Player + Mixer designed for WindowMaker This dockapp combines a CD player and a mixer in one 48x48 window. Very efficient on screen real-estate.  Especially handy if you mainly want a mixer, and only rarely use a CD player, but want to have one around just in case. It&apos;s designed with WindowMaker in mind, but it works fine with any window manager, and can be swallowed by afterstep/fvwm/gnome panel/etc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WMRM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Media Rights Manager (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Warehouse Management System (DB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Workflow Management Systems From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmscope
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical representation of sound waves in a dockapp wmscope is a dockapp that displays sound waves graphically, reading from a variety of sources. It also has a standby sine wave interference pattern to display when there is no audio input. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmsensors
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WindowMaker dock applet for lmsensors wmsensors is a WindowMaker applet that shows bar graphs of the information available through the lm-sensors interface From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmsmpmon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A CPU monitoring dockapp for SMP systems wmSMPmon is a CPU monitoring applet for SMP systems running Window Maker. It features two graphs for each CPU. It can be run on a System with only one CPU too, but it seems that the graph will show wrong value ranges. It has three different looks. You can change between them by clicking on the graph. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmsun
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockable WindowMaker SunRise/SunSet App wmSun displays the current day&apos;s Sun Rise and Set Times. You must enter your Latitude and Longitude for it to work correctly. wmSun is designed to work with the WindowMaker dock, but will work with other window managers as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmsysmon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WindowMaker dock-app for monitoring your system. wmsysmon is a dockable application for WindowMaker (and possibly Afterstep). It monitors Memory, Swap, Disk IO, uptime and interrupts. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmtictactoe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockable Tic Tac Toe game wmTicTacToe is a dock application meant for WindowMaker. It allows you to play TicTacToe against another human or the computer. You can switch between a scoreboard and the gameboard, and it is great to relax and enjoy for a few minutes while working. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmtime
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays time and date WMTime displays the time and date and gives you some nice additional features too. It is intended for docking in WindowMaker. WMTime currently provides:   * Time and date;   * Realtime morphing UI (analog &lt;&gt; digital mode);   * Autoscaling and anti aliased hands;   * Locale, can display DAY and DATE in various languages;   * Can launch 3 user definable commands through ~/.wmtimerc;   * Can be run multiple times;   * Commandline options for help (-h), version (-v), digital     clock mode (-digital) and and display (-d) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmtop
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockapp that displays 3 top memory or CPU using processes wmtop maintains a view of the 3 top CPU (or memory) consuming processes displaying the amount of CPU used as a horizontal bar. Very useful for spotting those rogue Netscape processes! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmtv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockable video4linux TV player for WindowMaker A miniature size dockable TV appllication. It currently supports channel presets, PAL/SECAM/NTSC, fine tuning, scanning of TV stations, use of external TV application, and more. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmtz
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A wmaker dock app that displays the time in different zones. wmtz displays the time in different  time  zones  and  can also show Julian day numbers, sidereal time, internet time (swatch beats) and local time, date and weekday. wmtz  can also  convert between JD and Gregorian dates via a command line interface. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmusic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a remote-control DockApp for xmms wmusic is a dockapp that remote-controls xmms. Features include VCR-style controls, Time and Playlist display, supa stylee rotating arrow, hiding of the xmms windows and reactive interface. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WMV
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Media Video [CODEC] (MS, Windows, video, CODEC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmwave
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Monitor status of an 802.11 wireless ethernet link wmwave is dockapp for Window Maker to display statistical information about a current wirless ethernet connection.  While made for Window Maker, it works with other window managers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmweather
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WindowMaker dock app that shows your current weather wmWeather provides a monitor on a 64x64 mini window that displays the current weather. The weather reports are received from the same source that pilots use. wmWeather is designed to work with the WindowMaker dock, but will work with other window managers as well. xbase-clients are required for the left click to bring up the complete METAR record. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmwork
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keep track of time worked on projects wmwork provides a monitor on a 64x64 mini window that helps you keeping track of your time. The idea is based on the program Worklog written by Truxton King Fulton II. In contrast to Worklog wmwork is a graphical application designed to work with the WindowMaker dock, but will work with other window managers as well. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmx10
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Control X10 home automation modules via a firecracker CM-17A X10 serial dogle The program is a WindowMaker/AfterStep applet. It allows for turning off, turning on, dimming, and brightening of X10 modules via the firecracker CM-17A X10 serial dogle. wmx10 controls one &quot;house&quot; at a time, up to eight separate devices on each &quot;house&quot;. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmxmms
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a dockable XMMS control applet. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmxmms-spectrum
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XMMS spectrum analyser plugin for the Window Maker dock WMXMMS-Spectrum is an XMMS visualisation plugin that displays a spectrum analyser in a Window Maker dock application. Although it works best with Window Maker, it also works fine with other window managers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wmxres
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
dock application to select your display mode among those possible wmxres is a tiny dockable application that comes in handy when you want a specific X mode.  Modes can be scrolled through until the desired one is active. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wn
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Secure and efficient http server with advanced features. WN is a server for the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1).  Its primary design goals are security and functionality usually available only with complex CGI scripts without the necessity of writing or using these scripts.  This includes extensive security checks, full text searching and conditionally served text. Despite this extensive functionality the WN executable is substantially smaller than the CERN or NCSA servers.  Both a stand-alone daemon and a version intended for use under inetd are provided.  The inetd version is designed to minimize the use of system resources and it is appropriate for moderate or lightly loaded servers which cannot be totally dedicated to Web serving. WN&apos;s security model is based on the use of a small flat database in each directory with information about the files in that directory.  Fields associated with a file include its title, and may include keywords, expiration date and any user defined fields like author or document id.  Unlike other servers, the default action for WN is to deny access to a file.  A file can only be served if explicit permission to do so has been granted by entering it in this database. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wngerman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
New German orthography dictionary for /usr/share/dict This is a wordlist with the new German orthography. It is based on the famous hkgerman dictionary (using the old German orthography) which was put together by Heinz Knutzen and is available as the Debian package wgerman. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WNIM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wide area Network Interface Module From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wnn7egg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wnn-nana-tamago -- EGG Input Method with Wnn7 for Emacsen EGG for Wnn7, called `wnn-nana-tamago&apos; is Japanese Input Method for Emacsen. It is based on Tamago ver.3 (v3.09) and incorporated the communication library part of Tamago Ver.4 This only can use with Jserver of Wnn7. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wnorwegian
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Norwegian dictionary / wordlist This is a list of Norwegian names and words, to be used for whatever purpose you may think of. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WNPP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Work-Needing and Prospective Packages (Linux, Debian) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WON
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World-O-Networking (BeOS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
woody
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hierarchic text editor Woody is a hierarchical text editor/outliner. It allows you to group related bits of information together into a common meaningful category. It is similar to BrainForest for the Palm Pilot. The program is ideal for maintaining TODO files. The program stores the files in xml, but can export to plain text files. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
word processor
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An application that can be used to create documents with easily configured appearance and format settings. Graphical word processors have adopted the what you see is what you get (wysiwyg) method of document creation. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
word2x
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Translates Word files into ascii text or LaTeX Takes Word files and transforms them into ascii text or LaTeX From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WORDIA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WORD Internet Assistant (MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wordinspect
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GTK-based Dictionary Client This package provides a graphical frontend to dict, which is a client that queries the dictd server.  Since dict is TCP based, it can access servers on the local host, on a local network, or on the Internet. In addition to the dict client, this package requires access to a dictd server, either from dictd installed on the local machine or network, or over the Internet to one of the DICT Development Group&apos;s public servers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wordnet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Electronic lexical database of English language WordNet(.) is an on-line lexical reference system whose design is inspired by current psycholinguistic theories of human lexical memory. English nouns, verbs, adjectives and adverbs are organized into synonym sets, each representing one underlying lexical concept. Different relations link the synonym sets. WordNet was developed by the Cognitive Science Laboratory (http://www.cogsci.princeton.edu/) at Princeton University under the direction of Professor George A. Miller (Principal Investigator). WordNet is considered to be the most important resource available to researchers in computational linguistics, text analysis, and many related areas. Its design is inspired by current psycholinguistic and computational theories of human lexical memory. English nouns, verbs, adjectives, and adverbs are organized into synonym sets, each representing one underlying lexical concept. Different relations link the synonym sets. More Information on http://www.cogsci.princeton.edu/~wn/. Binary and manpages for this binaries as well as general manpagesurl: http://www.cogsci.princeton.edu/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wordplay
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
anagram generator Wordplay generates anagrams of words or phrases. For example, &quot;Debian/Gnu Linux&quot; = &quot;blade gun in unix&quot;, &quot;able nun dig unix&quot;, &quot;dual benign unix&quot;, or &quot;lad begun in unix&quot;. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
words
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The words file is a dictionary of English words for the/usr/share/dict directory. Programs like Ispell use this database of words to check spelling. Password checkers use it to look for bad passwords. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
workaround
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. A temporary kluge used to bypass, mask, or otherwise avoid a bug or misfeature in some system. Theoretically, workarounds are always replaced by fixes; in practice, customers often find themselves living with workarounds for long periods of time. &quot;The code died on NUL characters in the input, so I fixed it to interpret them as spaces.&quot; &quot;That&apos;s not a fix, that&apos;s a workaround!&quot; 2. A procedure to be employed by the user in order to do what some currently non-working feature should do. Hypothetical example: &quot;Using META-F7 crashes the 4.43 build of Weemax, but as a workaround you can type CTRL-R, then SHIFT-F5, and delete the remaining cruft by hand.&quot;  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
workbone
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A simple text-based CD player Workbone is a simple, curses-based CD player that is controled by the num-lock keys. The cdtool package can be used to determine the contents of a CD before playing it. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
worker
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A highly configurable two-paned file manager for X Worker is a file manager much like the Amiga&apos;s DirOpus.  It can be controlled with mouse or keyboard.  There is no restriction on the number or type of button functions.  Files are recognized by both extension and content, content by recognizing common bytes in the sample files you show it.  Drag &amp; Drop is supported. If xli is installed, it quickly previews pictures in the opposite pane.  If xbase-clients is installed, xmessage is used to display some informative messages. See http://www.boomerangsworld.de/worker From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
workgroup
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A collection of individual computer users that are logically connected, usually by a single project or by a department within an organization. Members of a workgroup share common data and collaborate with each other as they work with it. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Working Directory
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Another name for the current directory, or the directory in which the user is currently working. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
working directory
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The directory in which you are working; also known as the current directory. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
worklog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keep Track of Time worked on Projects From the author: Worklog is a program that helps you keep track of your time.  I wrote this program because I have several projects that require me to keep a timesheet.  I sometimes spend 5 minutes here and there doing miscellaneous administrative tasks.  Rather than invoke an editor on a timesheet file for every little segment of my time spent doing these tasks, I wanted to leave a clock running and indicate with one or two keystrokes the onset or change of any given task.  Worklog is a simple ncurses based program to do just that. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
workman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical tool for playing audio CDs on a CD-ROM drive. WorkMan can play and control audio CDs from a comfortable OpenLook interface. It can retrieve information about CDs from a CDDB server, store this information in a database, and extract it automatically when the CD is inserted later again. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Workspace
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Another name for the Root Window, or Desktop. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
workspace
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In the X Window System, the root window, or desktop, on which all other windows are overlaid. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Workstation
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Typically a more powerful computer than a personal computer (eg Mac or PC). Workstations are typified through features such as high resolution displays, very large memory capacities, and excellent multi task; abilities running on UNIX or a similar operating system. From Faculty-of-Education
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
World Wide Web (WWW)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An intercontinental network of connected computers that serve documents, files, and other resources over the Internet. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
World-Wide-Web
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A distributed hypertext information system that uses HTTP to retrieve text and graphics, often erroneously referred to by the name of one type of browser, Mosaic. From KADOWKEV
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
worm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program that propagates itself by attacking other machines and copying itself to them. Example: In the late 1980s, the Morris Worm shutdown the Internet for a couple of days. At the time, well-known bugs in the UNIX sendmail program could allow a hacker to break into machines. Robert T. Morris wrote a program that would san machines for these security holes, then break into the machine. After breaking in, the program would copy itself up to that machine, then launch it. In this manner, the worm spread from machine to machine, multiplying until it had broken into nearly every machine which contained these bugs. However, the worm itself had a bug where it couldn&apos;t detect that a machine had already been broken into. Therefore, it would repeatedly break into the same machine over and over, until it machine collapsed from running too many instances of the worm. Copycats of the Morris Worm pop up repeatedly as new security holes appear in popular systems (like Linux), but they never have the devastating effect of the Morris Worm. Example: In the late 1999, the Melissa Worm/Virus nearly disabled the Internet. The worm spread by e-mailing itself to the first 50 people in a user&apos;s e-mail address book. Victims would then receive an e-mail from somebody they knew and trusted, so they would open the attached document and run the macros. In this manner, Melissa spread from inbox to inbox. Melissa is sort of a cross between a virus and a worm: it had the ability to spread itself like a worm, but it still required user interaction. Example: Around 1998, the ADMworm traveled by exploiting a few well-known Linux vulnerabilities in Linux machines, breaking into the machine, installing itself, then hunting for more machines.  Example: Having failed to learn their lesson in 1999, the industry was pummeled by the ILOVEYOU worm in early 2000. It spread in much the same way, though this time it was a VBS script rather than an .exe. Contrast: There really is not difference between a worm and a virus. The dividing line is usually drawn along the amount of human interaction involved, and how it spreads from machine to machine. A worm spreads itself with zero human interaction, whereas a virus is spread by human contact: humans exchange files from machine to machine, and when a human runs the infected program, the virus only infects other files on the same machine. Some viruses do attack servers, but only because the user is connected to the server. The Melissa Virus/Worm crosses the line: it spreads from one machine to another like a worm, but it must be launched by the user like a virus. Example: The SirCam Worm of July 2001 didn&apos;t explode as fast as other viruses, but had a large effect on the net through its &quot;background&quot; operation on a machine and the technique of spidering the cached files in web-browsers looking for e-mail addresses. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Worm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A virus that&apos;s designed to find all data in memory or on disk and alter any data it encounters. The alteration may be to change certain chracters to numbers or to swap bytes of stored memory. A few programs may still run, but usually data is irretrievably corrupted. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Worm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A worm is a virus that does not infect other programs. It makes copies of itself, and infects additional computers (typically by making use of network connections) but does not attach itself to additional programs; however a worm might alter, install, or destroy files and programs. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
worm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [from `tapeworm&apos; in John Brunner&apos;s novel &quot;The Shockwave Rider&quot;, via XEROX PARC] A program that propagates itself over a network, reproducing itself as it goes. Compare virus. Nowadays the term has negative connotations, as it is assumed that only crackers write worms. Perhaps the best-known example was Robert T. Morris&apos;s Great Worm of 1988, a `benign&apos; one that got out of control and hogged hundreds of Suns and VAXen across the U.S. See also cracker, RTM, Trojan horse, ice. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WORM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Write Once Read Many (CD) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOSA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Open System Architecture (MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOSAXCEM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WOSA eXtensions for Control, Engineering and Manufacturing (WOSA, MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOSAXFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WOSA eXtensions for Financial Services (WOSA, MS), &quot;WOSA X FS&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOSAXRT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WOSA eXtensions for Real-Time market data (WOSA, MS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOSC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Organization of Systems and Cybernetics (org., France) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows On Windows From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WOWLinux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The site appears current. Korean distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Word Perfect From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wp2x
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WordPerfect 5.x to whatever converter This program converts simple WordPerfect 5.0 and 5.1 files into any other document processing languages that use plain text files, like TeX, LaTeX, troff, GML and HTML. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wpac-applet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wallpaper auto changer for GNOME wpac-applet is a GNOME applet which automatically changes the wallpaper. You need xloadimage because it called by wpac-applet internally. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wpolish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Polish dictionary words for /usr/dict This package provides the file /usr/share/dict/polish containing a list of Polish words.  This list can be used by spelling checkers, and by programs such as look(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wpp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Web Preprocessor - a Perl script to preprocess HTML files WPP is a small Perl script that allows preprocessing of HTML files. You can define variables, which are abbreviations for longer constructs, and include common HTML fragments. It&apos;s useful for giving an uniform layout to different HTML pages. It can be used into cgi-bin programs for automatic generation of pages. With less HTML code inside them you can make more flexible and readable scripts. WPP provides four separate facilities that you can use as you see fit: inclusion of text/HTML fragments, variables expansion, conditional generation, macros expansion. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wprint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Print any charset from web browsers and HtmlDoc WorldPrint is a filter for Mozilla (Galeon, etc.), Htmldoc, and Netscape PostScript output that uses TrueType fonts to allow the printing of pages written in Unicode, Big5, SJIS, KOI-8, ISO-8859* and others. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Printing System (MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Word Processing Software From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WorkPlace Shell (OS/2, IBM, Shell) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WQL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WMI Query Language (MS, Windows, WMI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WRAM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window Random Access Memory (RAM, IC, Samsung, Matrox) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wrap around
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
vi. (also n. `wraparound&apos; and v. shorthand `wrap&apos;) 1. [techspeak] The action of a counter that starts over at zero or at `minus infinity&apos; (see infinity) after its maximum value has been reached, and continues incrementing, either because it is programmed to do so or because of an overflow (as when a car&apos;s odometer starts over at 0). 2. To change phase gradually and continuously by maintaining a steady wake-sleep cycle somewhat longer than 24 hours, e.g., living six long (28-hour) days in a week (or, equivalently, sleeping at the rate of 10 microhertz). This sense is also called phase-wrapping. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Wrapper
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program used to start another program. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wrapper
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program used to start another program; usually a wrapper is SUID or SGID so it can bestow privileges onto another program that the other program would not normally have write. Allows you to communicate with other users, by copying lines from your terminal to theirs. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WRB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Request Broker (Oracle, WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
write
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
send a message to another user From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
write
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
write to a file descriptor From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
write-only code
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. [a play on `read-only memory&apos;] Code so arcane, complex, or ill-structured that it cannot be modified or even comprehended by anyone but its author, and possibly not even by him/her. A Bad Thing.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
write-only language
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. A language with syntax (or semantics) sufficiently dense and bizarre that any routine of significant size is automatically write-only code. A sobriquet applied occasionally to C and often to APL, though INTERCAL and TECO certainly deserve it more. See also Befunge. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
write-only memory
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. The obvious antonym to `read-only memory&apos;. Out of frustration with the long and seemingly useless chain of approvals required of component specifications, during which no actual checking seemed to occur, an engineer at Signetics once created a specification for a write-only memory and included it with a bunch of other specifications to be approved. This inclusion came to the attention of Signetics management only when regular customers started calling and asking for pricing information. Signetics published a corrected edition of the data book and requested the return of the `erroneous&apos; ones. Later, in 1972, Signetics bought a double-page spread in &quot;Electronics&quot; magazine&apos;s April issue and used the spec as an April Fools&apos; Day joke. Instead of the more conventional characteristic curves, the 25120 &quot;fully encoded, 9046 x N, Random Access, write-only-memory&quot; data sheet included diagrams of &quot;bit capacity vs. Temp.&quot;, &quot;Iff vs. Vff&quot;, &quot;Number of pins remaining vs. number of socket insertions&quot;, and &quot;AQL vs. selling price&quot;. The 25120 required a 6.3 VAC VFF supply, a +10V VCC, and VDD of 0V, +/- 2%.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WRT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Whitewater Resource Toolkit (Windows, TPW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WRT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
With Respect To (slang, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Server (Corel) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSEB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Warp Server E-Business (IBM, OS/2), &quot;WSeb&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Work Station Feature (IBM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Work Station Function (IN) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Scripting Host (MS, Windows, COM, WSH) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wsoundprefs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Preferences editor for the Window Maker sound server WSoundPrefs is a WPrefs look-alike.  It can be used to customize the sounds Window Maker uses for different events, as well as editing sound sets. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wsoundserver
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Window Maker Sound Server WSoundServer is a complete, from scratch, reimplementation of a sound server for Window Maker window manager, done by Pascal Hofstee. It supports WAVE (wav), AIFF, Sun/NeXT (au), and snd audio formats. This package contains the sound server, the wsound library and soundset utilities. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Session Protocol (WAP, mobile-systems) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Workstation Security Package From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wspanish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Spanish dictionary words for /usr/share/dict This package contains an alphabetic list of Spanish words From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WSS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Sound System (Windows, audio) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wswedish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Swedish dictionary. This is a list of 120,000 Swedish words and names, to be used for whatever purpose you may think of. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Windows Terminal Controller From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wterm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An rxvt based, color xterm replacement. Wterm is an rxvt based, 8-bit clean, color, xterm replacement. It contains features such as transparency, reverse transparency, background images, nice looking NeXT style scrollbars and is very customisable. Wterm is optimised for use under WindowMaker 0.50.x and up. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
What / Where / Who / Why The F*** (DFUe, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTH
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
What / Where / Who / Why The Hell (DFUe, Usenet, IRC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTLS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Transport Layer Security From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wtmp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
records all logins and logouts. Its format is exactly like utmp except that a null user name indicates a logout on the associated terminal. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wireless Transport Protocol (WAP, mobile-systems) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web Transaction Security (WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WTX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wokstation Technology eXtended [format] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wu-ftpd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
powerful and widely used FTP server This FTP daemon, originally from the Washington University of St. Louis, is a powerful, and widely used replacement FTP server for Unix systems. The FTP protocol is a method of transferring files between machines on a network and/or over the Internet. Besides fully supporting the FTP protocol defined in RFCs 959 and 1579 (and others), it adds the following features:     o  logging of transfers,     o  logging of commands,     o  on the fly compression and archiving,     o  classification of users on type and location,     o  per class limits,     o  per directory upload permissions,     o  restricted guest accounts,     o  system wide and per directory messages,     o  directory aliases,     o  cdpath,     o  filename filter,     o  virtual host support (similar to the Apache HTTP server). This release is maintained by the WU-FTPD Development Group as a public service to the Internet. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Convert and preview Microsoft Word documents. wv (previously known as mswordview) is a library which allows access to Microsoft Word files.  It can load and parse the Word 2000, 97, 95, and 6 file format.  (Work is underway to support reading earlier formats as well: Word 2 documents are converted to plain text.) Among the provided programs are:  * wvWare: Converts to HTML and LaTeX.  It&apos;s used by a small army of    helper scripts able to preview Word documents and convert them to    various other formats, like PostScript, PDF, DVI, etc.  * wvRTF: Converts to Microsoft&apos;s Rich Text Format.  * wvSummary: Displays the summary information stream of all OLE2    files, i.e. Excel, PowerPoint, Visio, Access, etc.  * wvVersion: Outputs the version of the Word format a document is    stored in. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wvdial
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PPP dialer with built-in intelligence. WvDial sacrifices some of the flexibility of programs like &quot;chat&quot; in order to make your dialup configuration easier.  When you install this package, your modem will be detected automatically and you need to specify just three parameters: the phone number, username, and password.  WvDial knows enough to dial with most modems and log in to most servers without any other help. In particular, you no longer need a &quot;chat script&quot; to handle the most common situations. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wvdial
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WvDial automatically locates and configures modems and can log into almost any ISP&apos;s server without special configuration. You need to input the username, password, and phone number, and then WvDial will negotiate the PPP connection using any mechanism needed. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WVNET
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
West Virginia Network for Educational Telecomputing (network, USA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WVSO
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WiederVerwendbare SoftwareObjekte From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWDC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide Developer Conference (Apple) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWIMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Worldwide Warning Indicator Monitoring System (mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wwl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Calculates distance and azimuth between two Maidenhead locators Given two Maidenhead locators, wwl calculates distance (qrb) and azimuth. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWMCCS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Worldwide Military Command and Control System (mil., predecessor, GCCS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWOLS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide On-Line System (mil.) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wwsympa
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Web interface for administrating Sympa WWSympa is a well integrated web interface for configuring Sympa. It comes with original features such as :  - Unique interface for users and admin, authentication  - Contextual internationalization (English, French and Spanish)  - Archives (MhOnArc) with access control and a Search Engine     (MarcSearch)  - Clean moderation  - Edition of service messages (templates) for owner and listmaster  - Semi-automatic bounces management  - HTTPS authentication  - Support for virtual hosting with respect to virtual domains From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide Web (Internet) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWW
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide Web--also known as WEB--this is the generic name given to all of the hypertext-based HTML documents on the Internet. A revolutionary Internet browsing system that allows point-and-click%navigation of the Internet. The WWW is a spiderweb-like interconnection of millions of pieces of information located on computers around the world. Web documents use hypertext, which incorporates text and graphical links to other documents and files on Internet-connected computers. From Glossary of Distance Education and Internet Terminology 
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WWW (World Wide Web)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide Web (or simply Web for short) is a term frequently used (incorrectly) when referring to &quot;The Internet&quot;, WWW has two major meanings: First, loosely used: the whole constellation of resources that can be accessed using Gopher, FTP, HTTP,telnet, USENET, WAIS and some other tools. Second, the universe of hypertext servers (HTTP servers), more commonly called &quot;web servers&quot;, which are the servers that serve web pages to web browsers. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
www-mysql
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a WWW interface for the TCX mySQL database www-mysql is a web interface for the mySQL database. SQL commands can be embedded into web pages; these are executed on the server by www-mysql and the resulting web page sent to the browser. All SQL commands and queries supported by mySQL can be used via www-mysql. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
www-pgsql
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a WWW interface for the PostgreSQL database www-pgsql is a web interface for the PostgreSQL database. SQL commands can be embedded into web pages; these are executed on the server by www-pgsql and the resulting web page sent to the browser. All SQL commands and queries supported by PostgreSQL can be used via www-pgsql. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wwwconfig-common
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Debian web auto configuration. A package to provide common setup scripts for some packages that need apache, php and a database. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wwwoffle
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
World Wide Web OFFline Explorer The wwwoffled program is a simple proxy server with special features for use with dial-up internet links.  This means that it is possible to browse web pages and read them without having to remain connected. While Online    - Caching of pages that are viewed for review later.    - Conditional fetching to only get pages that have changed.    - Modification of pages e.g. to remove the BLINK tag or popup windows. While Offline    - The ability to follow links and mark other pages for download.    - Browser or command line interface to select pages for downloading.    - Optional info on bottom of pages showing cached date and allowing refresh.    - Works with password protected pages and pages containing forms.    - Cached pages can be searched with the ht://dig search engine. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wxwin2.2-headers
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
wxWindows Cross-platform C++ GUI toolkit (header files) wxWindows is a class library for C++ providing GUI (Graphical User Interface) and other facilities on more than one platform.  Version 2.2 currently supports subsets of GTK+, Motif, and MS Windows. This package provides the common header files required to build applications using the wxWindows toolkit. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wyg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
(Where&apos;s Your Grammar?) command line parser generator WYG (Where&apos;s Your Grammar?) is a tool that automates the use of lex, yacc, and getopt_long to create a front-end for your projects that can be configured from files or via the command line. For more information, see http://www.larsshack.org/sw/wyg/. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WYSIAYG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/wiz&apos;ee-ayg/ adj. Describes a user interface under which &quot;What You See Is All You Get&quot;; an unhappy variant of WYSIWYG. Visual, `point-and-shoot&apos;-style interfaces tend to have easy initial learning curves, but also to lack depth; they often frustrate advanced users who would be better served by a command-style interface. When this happens, the frustrated user has a WYSIAYG problem. This term is most often used of editors, word processors, and document formatting programs. WYSIWYG `desktop publishing&apos; programs, for example, are a clear win for creating small documents with lots of fonts and graphics in them, especially things like newsletters and presentation slides. When typesetting book-length manuscripts, on the other hand, scale changes the nature of the task; one quickly runs into WYSIAYG limitations, and the increased power and flexibility of a command-driven formatter like TeX or Unix&apos;s troff becomes not just desirable but a necessity. Compare YAFIYGI. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WYSIWIS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
What You See Is What I See From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WYSIWYG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
&apos;What You See Is What You Get&apos;. This term refers to Graphical User Interfaces that present work in a format that is identical to that when printed out. From Faculty-of-Education
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WYSIWYG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/wiz&apos;ee-wig/ adj. [Traced to Flip Wilson&apos;s &quot;Geraldine&quot; character c.1970] Describes a user interface under which &quot;What You See Is What You Get&quot;, as opposed to one that uses more-or-less obscure commands that do not result in immediate visual feedback. True WYSIWYG in environments supporting multiple fonts or graphics is a a rarely-attained ideal; there are variants of this term to express real-world manifestations including WYSIAWYG (What You See Is Almost What You Get) and WYSIMOLWYG (What You See Is More or Less What You Get). All these can be mildly derogatory, as they are often used to refer to dumbed-down user-friendly interfaces targeted at non-programmers; a hacker has no fear of obscure commands (compare WYSIAYG). On the other hand, EMACS was one of the very first WYSIWYG editors, replacing (actually, at first overlaying) the extremely obscure, command-based TECO. See also WIMP environment. [Oddly enough, WYSIWYG has already made it into the OED, in lower case yet. --ESR] From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
WYSIWYG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
What You See Is What You Get (DTP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
wzip
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Lossy compression and denoising The program wzip is a preprocessor for LOSSY data compression. A sequence of ascii floating-point numbers is transformed into a sequence of small integers ready for effective compression with e.g. gzip. The program can also be used for effective but time consuming denoising of measurement data. Wzip was originally written for the processing of EDX-linescans. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossary>
