<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="X">
<title>X</title>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a portable, network-transparent window system From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
See XFree86. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X /X/
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
n. 1. Used in various speech and writing contexts (also in lowercase) in roughly its algebraic sense of `unknown within a set defined by context&apos; (compare N). Thus, the abbreviation 680x0 stands for 68000, 68010, 68020, 68030, or 68040, and 80x86 stands for 80186, 80286, 80386, 80486, 80586 or 80686 (note that a Unix hacker might write these as 680[0-6]0 and 80[1-6]86 or 680?0 and 80?86 respectively; see glob). 2. [after the name of an earlier window system called `W&apos;] An over-sized, over-featured, over-engineered and incredibly over-complicated window system developed at MIT and widely used on Unix systems. From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Extension
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An X extension is program code that extends the X server by adding some significant new functionality missing from the core X protocol, such as direct support for 3-D graphics. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Image Extension
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Provides a mechanism for graphical image management in the client/server environment of X11. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Toolkit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The X Toolkit ( libXt.so) is a widget library that has always come free with X. It is crude-looking by today&apos;s standards. It doesn&apos;t feature 3D (shadowed) widgets, although it is comes free with X. [The excellent xfig application, an X Toolkit application, was in fact used to do the diagrams in this book.]Motif ( libM.so) is a modern, full-featured widget library that had become an industry standard. Motif is, however, bloated, slow, and dependent on the X toolkit. It has always been an expensive proprietary library. Tk (tee-kay, libtk.so) is a library that is primarily used with the Tcl scripting language. It was probably the first platform-independent library (running on Windows, all UNIX variants, and the Apple Mac). It is, however, slow and has limited features (this is progressively changing). Both Tcl and Motif are not very elegant-looking. Around 1996, we saw a lot of widget libraries popping up with different licenses. V, xforms, and graphix come to mind. (This was when I started to write coolwidgets--my own widget library.) There was no efficient, multipurpose, Free, and elegant-looking widget library for UNIX. This was a situation that sucked and was retarding Free software development. From Rute-Users-Guide
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Window System
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical windowing environment for UNIX. The underlying programming required by many user interfaces. (Also, see Desktop, Window Manager and XFree86.) From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Window System
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an advanced, network transparent, windowing, graphical environment, developed at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and first released in 1984. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Window System (X)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An engine and interface for creating graphical desktops and applications. See XFree86. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Windows
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A network windowing environment commony used on UNIX-based workstations. X Windows is a device-independent,  application program interface (API) that can run under operatings systems ranging from disk operating systems to a mainframe operating system. It&apos;s used most frequently on UNIX machines. Unlike Microsoft Windows 95 and other PC-based windowing environments, X Windows is designed for use on a minicomputer-based network. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X Windows
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Windows forms the basis for most GUIs on UNIX. It is based upon a network protocol such that a program can run on one computer but be displayed on another. Conceptually, it is a graphical version of Telnet. Key point: X Windows goes in the &quot;wrong&quot; direction. When you log into an X Windows host, the host opens a connection back to the display. As a consequence, it is very useful as a back-channel. In particular, the program xterm provides a raw command-prompt from which a hacker can interact with just as if they had telnetted to the machine. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-face-el
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XFace utility for GNU Emacs. XFace utility for GNU Emacs. If use on XEmacs then x-face-el suggests MULE supported XEmacs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X-Modem
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
One of the earliest reliable file transfer protocols, Xmodem was written in 1977 by Ward Christiansen. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-pgp-sig-el
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-PGP-Sig mail and news header utility for Emacs. X-PGP-Sig header utility for Emacs. It can be insert/verify PGP signature in X-PGP-Sig: mail/news header. x-pgp-sig.el is for MH(mh-e, Mew and so on), Gnus, Semi-gnus, wl(Wanderlust) VM, cmail etc... (MUA on Emacs). But English Documents is not available. (only Japanese available) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-symbol
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WYSIWYG TeX mode for XEmacs This is a WYSIWYG TeX add-on for [X]Emacs21.  It shows math symbols, sub/super-scripts via special fonts, and figures via imagemagick. Emacs21 support is still BETA. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-terminal-emulator
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
terminal emulator for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-ttcidfont-conf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Configure TrueType and CID fonts for X. This package configures TrueType fonts and CID fonts (as well as CMaps) for X. It generates .scale file and .alias file from TrueType and CID fonts registered to Defoma, and calls mkfontdir (and mkcfm). Both xtt and freetype backends which are used to handle TrueType fonts in X are supported. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-window-manager
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tab Window Manager for the X Window System From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-window-system
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System This metapackage provides substantially all the components of the X Window System as developed by the XFree86 Project, as well as a set of historically popular accessory programs. The development and debugging libraries are not provided by this metapackage. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x-window-system-core
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System core components This metapackage provides the essential components for a standalone workstation running the X Window System.  It provides the X libraries, an X server (except on the S/390 architecture), a set of fonts, and a group of basic X clients and utilities. Higher level metapackages, such as those for desktop environments, can depend on this package and simplify their dependencies. It should be noted that a package providing x-window-manager and a package providing x-terminal-emulator should also be installed to ensure a comfortable X experience. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X-Windows
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A network-based GUI designed for Unix systems, there are thousands of free applications available as source code and compiled executables for X-Windows compatible systems, including PC-based X-terminal emulators. From KADOWKEV
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x10
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Operate X-10 electrical power control modules. X-10 modules are devices that plug into an electrical outlet and allow you to remotely control the power to a lamp or an appliance that is plugged into them. There are also X-10 modules that install in place of wall switches to control lights, and there&apos;s one that can be used to set back a thermostat. This program commands up to 256 X-10 modules via a CP-290 serial-interface controller plugged into any serial port of your system. You can use it to automate your home! It&apos;s also commonly used to provide control over computers and other devices that might need to be powered up or down via a timed command or remote control. The CP-290 controller stores 128 clock-driven events that it will execute when your computer is turned off, so you can even program your computer to turn itself on at a particular time. You can buy the modules and manual controllers in Radio Shack stores, but the CP-290 serial-interface controller used to command them using your Debian system is slightly harder to find. Instructions on where to order one are included in the documentation of this package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x10-automate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GUI interface for x10 power line control utility Tk (wish) based GUI for the &quot;x10&quot; home-control program. With this program you can attach icons to your various X10 devices and see them displayed on a toolbar as well as a floor plan of your own. You can also read, write and edit programs to download to the CP-290 controller. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X11
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Version 11 of the X Window System. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X11
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X window System version 11 (X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x11iraf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X utilities for IRAF (Image Reduction Analysis Facility) Includes the xgterm, ximtool and xtapemon and associated utilities for the Image Reduction and Analysis Facility. WARNING: ximtool requires 8-bit mode or it will fail to start. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x11perf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 server performance test program From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x11perfcomp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 server performance comparison program From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x2vnc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A dual-screen hack - link a MS-Windows and X display This program merges the capabilities of x2x and vncviewer.  It will allow a machine with an X display and a machine with a VNC server running on it&apos;s main screen to act as if they were two displays connected to one machine. When you move your mouse pointer off the screen in a direction of your choosing, the pointer will appear on the other screen instead. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x2x
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Link two X displays together, simulating a multiheaded display x2x joins a pair of X displays together, as if they were a single multiheaded display.  The pointer can be warped between displays, or, depending on how you start x2x, can slide from one display to the other when it runs off the edge of the screen.  Keyboard focus also moves between displays in the way you&apos;d expect, and the X selection propagates around.  At least one of the displays involved (specifically, the one being controlled remotely) must support the XTEST extension. (The servers shipped by Debian support this.) x2x is useful when you have two displays on the same desk, as you can use a single keyboard and mouse to control both.  If you want to propagate your selections between displays which are not sharing a desk, you might be more interested in the package propsel.  Propsel does not link the displays&apos; keyboard and mouse, which would be confusing in some cases, and can propagate between up to 8 displays, whereas x2x can handle only two at a time. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
X3D-PEX
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X3D-PEX, sometimes called PEX-5, is a version of the Phigs 3D graphics library. See X extension. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
x86info
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Display diagnostic information about i386 CPUs x86info displays diagnostic information about the CPUs fitted to i386 systems.  This includes information on the CPU cache configuration, speed and supported features. Some features require the kernel cpuid driver to be available. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Architecture (IBM, VM, ESA, VM/ESA, XC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xa+cv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XCIN Anywhere +CV wrapper for Chinese input in X applications XA+CV (XCIN Anywhere +CV) is a small X library wrapper for XCIN.  Users may use this nifty tool to input and display Chinese (both Big5 and GB) characters in almost any X applications (e.g.  Netscape 4.x), especially for those that do not support the XIM protocol.  Authors: WEI Je-Ren &lt;weijr@magic.math.ntu.edu.tw&gt;           CHENG Yuan-Chung &lt;platin@ms31.hinet.net&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XAA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xfree86 Acceleration Architecture (X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xabacus
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simulation of the ancient oriental calculator This is the non-motif version by David Bagley. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XACT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xante&apos;s Accurate Calibration Technology (Xante), &quot;X*ACT&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xae
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML Authoring Environment for Emacs The XAE is an add-on software package that enables you to use Emacs and your system&apos;s HTML browser to create, transform, and display XML documents. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xalan
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XSLT processor. Command line utility to process XML files using an XSLT stylesheet. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xalex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xalf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Provides feed back while loading X applications Xalf can reliably detect if newly mapped windows are belonging to a particular launched application. It does this by overloading the Xlib function XMapWindow with a version that signals the tracking xalf process. Xalf provides (currently) four different types as &quot;indicators&quot;, described below. Invisible Window:    Xalf creates an invisible window, to be used in conjunction    with a standard task pager like Gnomes tasklist_applet or the    KDE Taskbar. The name of the window is the application name    within parenthesis. The small window icon (KWM_WIN_ICON) is    set to a small hourglass. This indicator is default. Splash screen:    An generic splashscreen is displayed during application    launch. Mouse cursor change:    Xalf adds an hourglass symbol to the mousecursor for the root    window and the Gnome panel. Note that the cursor is not    changed for the Gnome foot-menu windows. Animated star:    An animated indicator resembling the look of that on SGI/Irix    machines (a kind of yellow star blinking while loading a    program). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xamixer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical mixer for ALSA ALSA is an effort to create a modules sound system for Linux, while maintaining full compatibility with OSS/Lite. This package contains a graphical front-end (using the GTK+ toolkit) to the ALSA mixer device. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xandros Linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xandros Desktop OS (formerly Corel&apos;s Debian-based distribution) is a desktop system designed to peacefully co-exist and inter-operate with Windows desktop and server systems. The first version of the Xandros Desktop OS was released October 22, 2002.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xaos
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
real-time interactive fractal zoomer XaoS is a real-time interactive fractal zoomer. It can display the fractals in X, svgalib, and even plain text mode. It displays the Mandelbrot set or one of 8 other fractals and allows you to zoom smoothly into the fractal. Various coloring modes are provided for both the points inside and outside the selected set. In addition, switching between Mandelbrot and Julia fractal types is provided. Other features include autopilot mode, palette changing, image saving, fractal inversion, and a built in fractal tutorial. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XAPIA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X.400 API Association (org., X.400, API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xapm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X program to monitor APM battery status On laptop computers, the Advanced Power Management (APM) support provides access to battery status information and may help you to conserve battery power, depending on your laptop and the APM implementation. This package contains xapm(1), an X11 utility that displays the status of the battery. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xapple2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Apple ][ Emulator This is a fully-functional 100% Apple ][ emulator for X windows. It is partly written in 386 (AT&amp;T) assembler and partly in C. You can switch diskettes using a diskette database through an intuitive interface.  Furthermore, it is possible to trim the speed of the emulator and it runs in full speed (approximately) twice as fast as an standard Apple II+ on a 486DX-50.  It uses the svgalib&apos;s key scancodes and implements the undocumented 6502 instructions (required by at least two games: Bug Attack and MS Pacman). Because the Apple ROMs are copyrighted, they are not included here.  You will have to make copies of them from your old Apple computer.  If you don&apos;t want to mess around with this, you can find a copy at:    http://geta.life.uiuc.edu/~badger/files/apple_II.rom    http://geta.life.uiuc.edu/~badger/files/slot6.rom Transferring your old Apple disks is a bit of work, but you can save yourself the trouble of digging up your old masters by seeing if some kind soul has already done the work for you at:    ftp://ftp.apple.asimov.net/pub/apple_II/images/ Remember, you can only use these ROMs and images _legally_ if you already own the original.  Have fun!   (Ahhh....  What memories!) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xarchon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An X11 version of the game Archon. XArchon is a clone of the classic ARCHON game which was distributed by Electronic Arts around 1985.  It pits the light side against the dark side in a battle for the control of a chess-like playing board. XArchon consists of a strategy mode, in which pieces are moved around the board, and an arcade mode, in which two pieces attempting to occupy the same square battle one another. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xarclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Reversed xclock If clocks had been invented in Argentina (southern hemisphere), they would run counter-clockwise. Down there a sundial runs the other way around! The program is an extension of the standard X clock widget.  New features are: Configurable direction of rotation and font support in analog mode. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xargs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
build and execute command lines from standard input From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xasteroids
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-based asteroids-style arcade game Make big rocks into little ones. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xastir
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Amateur Station Tracking and Information Reporting Xastir is an APRS client for X. APRS is the Automatic Position Reporting System, a system where objects report their position (usually obtained from GPS) on the air; Xastir displays this information graphically. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xauth
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X authority file utility From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xautolock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
start a program if the X session is idle for some time Xautolock monitors input devices under the X Window System, and launches a program of your choice if there is no activity after a user-configurable period of time.  You can use this to automatically start up a screen locker if you have left your computer unattended for some period of time.  The program launched need not be a screen locker such as xlock. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xaw3d
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cute 3D replacement for the X Athena widget set [libc5] Xaw3d is a set of 3-D widgets based on the R6.1 Athena Widget set, which adds a three dimensional appearance on some of the widgets of X11 applications dynamically linked against libXaw. This is the libc5 version of xaw3dg library, provided for compatibility with libc5-based programs linking to Xaw3d. This library doesn&apos;t contain 3D scrollbars (&quot;arrowscrollbars&quot;), either, please read /usr/share/doc/xaw3d/scrollbars for more information. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xaw3d
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xaw3d is an enhanced version of the MIT Athena Widget set for the X Window System. Xaw3d adds a three-dimensional look to applications with minimal or no source code changes. You should install Xaw3d if you are using applications which incorporate the MIT Athena widget set and you want to incorporate a 3D look into those applications. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xaw3dg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xaw3d widget set Xaw3d is a set of 3-D widgets based on the Athena Widget set, which adds a three dimensional appearance on some of the widgets of X11 applications linked with this library. Please note that this package no longer adds a three dimensional appearance on applications dynamically linked against libXaw. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xawtv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 TV application TV application for X11.  Supports video4linux devices and the Xvideo extension. For Xvideo support xawtv must be compiled with the XFree86 4.0+ client libraries installed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbanner
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Beautify your XDM login screen XBanner is a program designed to beautify your XDM login screen. It can draw text and render some effect on it, and it can fill the background with a nice pattern of colors. XBanner can also put an image on the screen for you, as well as do some minimal animation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbase-clients
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
miscellaneous X clients An X client is a program that interfaces with an X server (almost always via the X libraries), and thus with some input and output hardware like a graphics card, monitor, keyboard, and pointing device (such as a mouse). This package provides a miscellaneous assortment of several dozen X clients that ship with the X Window System, including:  - startx and xinit, which initialize X sessions from the command line;  - xauth, a tool for controlling access to the X session;  - xedit, a text editor;  - xbiff, a tool which tells you when you have new email;  - xcalc, a scientific calculator desktop accessory;  - xclipboard, a tool to manage cut-and-pasted text selections;  - xcutsel, which exchanges selection and cut buffer contents;  - xconsole, which monitors system console messages;  - xditview, a viewer for ditroff output;  - xeyes, a demo program in which a pair of eyes track the pointer;  - xfd, a tool that displays all the glyphs in a given X font;  - xfontsel, a tool for browsing and selecting X fonts;  - xhost, a very dangerous program that you should never use;  - xkill, a tool for terminating misbehaving X clients;  - xload, a monitor for the system load average;  - xlogo, a demo program that displays the X logo;  - xmag, which magnifies parts of the X screen;  - xman, a manual page browser;  - xmessage, a tool to display message or dialog boxes;  - xrefresh, a tool that forces a redraw of the X screen;  - xsetroot, a tool for tailoring the appearance of the root window;  - xvidtune, a tool for customizing X server modelines for your monitor;  - xwd, a utility for taking window dumps (&quot;screenshots&quot;) of the X session;  - xwud, a viewer for window dumps created by xwd;  - oclock and xclock, graphical clocks;  - beforelight, a screen saver;  - bitmap, a monochrome bitmap file editor;  - bmtoa, a tool that converts a monochrome bitmap to ASCII text;  - cxpm and sxpm, tools for checking and viewing X pixmap files;  - dpsexec, a Display PostScript program that allows the user to interact    directly with the PostScript interpreter through a command interface  - dpsinfo, a utility for displaying information about the DPS extension    present in an X server or provided by a client-side DPS agent  - glxgears, a GLX demo that draws three rotating gears, and prints    framerate information to standard output  - iceauth, a tool for manipulating ICE protocol authorization records;  - texteroids, a spinning text demo for the DPS extension  - xftcache, a tool that creates an index of FreeType font files in a    directory  - xset, a tool for setting miscellaneous X server parameters;  - xmodmap, a utility for modifying keymaps and pointer button mappings in X;  - xsetmode and xsetpointer, tools for handling X Input devices;  - setxkbmap, xkbbell, xkbcomp, xkbevd, xkbprint, xkbvleds, and xkbwatch,    tools for managing the X keyboard extension (XKB);  - xsm, a session manager for X sessions;  - smproxy, a session manager proxy for X clients that do not use the X    session manager protocol;  - xgamma, a tool for querying and setting a monitor&apos;s gamma correction;  - appres, editres, listres, viewres, and xrdb, which query and update the    X resource database;  - Xmark, x11perf, x11perfcomp, and xieperf, tools for benchmarking    graphical operations under the X Window System;  - fstobdf, which retrieves a font in BDF format from an X font server;  - xcmsdb, a device color characteristic utility for the X Color Management    System;  - xstdcmap, a utility to selectively define standard colormap properties;  - xev, an X event displayer;  - xfindproxy, a tool to locate X proxy services;  - xlsatoms, which lists interned atoms defined on an X server;  - xlsclients, which lists client applications running on an X display;  - xlsfonts, a server font list displayer;  - xprop, a property displayer for X;  - xdpyinfo, a display information utility for X;  - xwininfo, a window information utility for X;  - glxinfo, a GLX extension information utility for X;  - xvinfo, an Xv extension information utility for X;  - ico, an X graphics demo using an animated polyhedron;  - dga, a demo program for the DGA extension; and  - xgc, an (unfinished) X graphics demo program. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A classic shoot-em-up game for X11. Xbat closely resembles the classic arcade game Xevious. While navigating his Solvalou, the player must survive waves of enemy airships, occasionally meeting up with a &quot;boss-ship&quot; at the end of a level. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbatt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Display battery status xbatt is an X11 client which displays the battery status of your notebook computer equipped with APM (Advanced Power Management) BIOS. The status displayed consists of the remaining battery life, the AC line status, and the charging status. This version of xbatt is dockable in WindowMaker&apos;s Docking bar. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbattle
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A concurrent multi-player battle strategy game. xbattle is a concurrent multi-player game which combines elements of strategy with arcade-like action to capture a wide range of military scenarios.  Opponents play from separate displays, with commands being executed concurrently -- the players do not take &quot;turns&quot;, but rather they all issue their commands simultaneously.  There can be any number of players, with each player assigned to a specific team, indicated by marker colors.  The game board is a matrix of cells (square, hexes, etc.) that can be occupied by colored troops, with the goal of the game being to eliminate the enemy from the board by attacking cells occupied by enemy troops.  A wide variety of command line options (and previously configured game files) provide an abundance of different scenarios and gaming environments. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML Bookmark Exchange Language The XML Bookmark Exchange Language (XBEL) is a rich interchange format for &quot;bookmark&quot; data as used by most web browsers. This package contains XBEL DTDs for 1.0 and 1.1 formats as well as documentation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbiff
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
mailbox flag for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbill
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Get rid of those Wingdows Viruses! Ever get the feeling that nothing is going right?  You&apos;re a sysadmin, and someone&apos;s trying to destroy your computers.  The little people running around the screen are trying to infect your computers with Wingdows [TM], a virus cleverly designed to resemble a popular operating system.  Your objective is to click the mouse on them, ending their potential threat. If one of the people reaches a computer, it will attempt to replace your operating system with the virus it carries. It will then attempt to run off the screen with your vital software. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
3-D tetris like game Xbl is a game involving dropping blocks like Xtetris but in 3 dimensions. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xblast
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Multi player blast-the-others game inspired by Dynablaster Features:   - 2 to 6 players   - 1 or 2 players per X-Server   - 95 different levels   - Full color and monochrome support (including true color modes)   - PoV-Ray rendered color graphics You have to install the xblast-sound package if you want sound support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbmbrowser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Browser for Pixmaps and Bitmaps A nice little utility to browse whole directories of X11 pixmaps or bitmaps. A configurable menu allows editing or display on the root window. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xboard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An X Window System Chess Board. XBoard is a graphical chessboard that can serve as a user interface for GNU Chess, for the Internet Chess Server, or for electronic mail correspondence chess. XBoard can also be used by itself. XBoard uses the Helvetica font (located in the xfonts-75dpi and xfonts-100dpi packages) by default. However, other fonts can be specified via a command line option or an X resource. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xboard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xboard is an X Window System based graphical chessboard which can be used with the GNUchess and Crafty chess programs, with Internet Chess Servers (ICSs), with chess via email, or with your own saved games. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbobo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xboing
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Blockout game for X XBoing is a blockout type game where you have a paddle which you control to bounce a ball around the game zone destroying blocks with a proton ball. Each block carries a different point value. The more blocks you destroy, the better your score. The person with the highest score wins. The arena is filled with blocks and other objects. You have a paddle that can move from left to right at the bottom of the arena. You control the paddle so that the proton ball bounces around blowing up blocks and that it does not go past the paddle and out the bottom, much like a pinball game. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbomb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A &apos;minesweeper&apos; game with squares, hexagons or triangles. A test of speed and logic to find the location of bombs hidden in a grid. Offers the standard square grid, plus hexagonal and triangular grids, each in 3 difficulty levels, all games played against the clock, with a high-score table for each combination. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbox-linux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Xbox Linux project aims to create a version of GNU/Linux that runs on the Microsoft Xbox gaming console. Initial version 0.1 was released August 17, 2002. Version 0.2 was released August 26, 2002. Version 11-01-2003 was released January 17, 2003. A &apos;special purpose/mini&apos; distribution. From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XBP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XBase Parts (Xbase/2, OS/2, DB) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbreaky
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a Breakout/Arkanoid clone for X The objective of this arcade game is to break all the bricks with a ball that bounces off the walls and a paddle that you can move. You start by firing out the ball from your paddle, which can be moved left and right parallel to the wall below it. The ball will move and hit the bricks located above, and when it hits a brick it will fall apart (i.e. dissappear), but the ball will bounce back to hit other bricks, sidewalls or the highest wall. If it falls down not hitting the paddle, you lose one life and have to start over. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbrummi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
3-d models and movies of molecules xbs ball-and-sticks plotting program can create still and moving three dimensional models of molecules. X11 and PostScript output are available.  Models can be rotated, scaled, etc.  Various labeling, shading, lighting, coloring options are available. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbubble
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A nice Puzzle Bubble clone XBubble is a Puzzle Bubble / Bust-A-Move clone. Your goal is to remove all the bubbles from the game board. To do this you must aim and shoot bubbles. When you manage to match 3 or more bubbles of the same color, they burst and disappear. All bubbles which hang free now, will fall down and disappear, too. xbubble features single player mode, two player mode and player vs. computer (five difficulty levels of the AI) and has nice graphics, but no sound. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xbuffy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Monitor mailboxes and/or newsgroups Xbuffy is a program that displays how many unread mails you have in your different mailboxes.  You can have different titles for the mailboxes, and define what shall happen when a new mail arrives.  It can beep and invoke a shell command, for example. Xbuffy can also notify you by blinking a keyboard LED when new mail has arrived. If you press mouse button 1 on the title associated with a mail box, a list of From: and Subject: lines of the mails in the mail spool file is shown.  If you press mouse button 2, an arbitrary command is executed.  If you press mouse button 3, the LED blinking is stopped until another mail has arrived. Xbuffy can similarly watch newsgroups via NNTP. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Configuration (IBM, ESA, VM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcal
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a graphical calendar with memos and reminder alarms The &quot;classic&quot; calendar app with memos and alarms, xcal normally sits idle and displays the date.  When clicked on, pops up a `strip&apos; for this month.  Clicking on a day allows you to enter details. Automatically parses times entered, and reminds you 5 minutes before your appointment. Supports daily and weekly repeating events and context-sensitive help. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcalc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
scientific calculator for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcalendar-i18n
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
calendar program on X with i18n support xcalendar is a simple interactive calendar program with a notebook capability. It is built on the X Toolkit and the Athena or Motif Widgets (compile time option). xcalendar-i18n is a modified version of xcalendar with X11R6-style i18n implementation. Resource files for JA and KR are included. JA resource is included in the original xcalendar, not in the i18n patch. KR resource is sent by Changwoo Ryu &lt;cwryu@debian.org&gt; for this Debian package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcall
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Packet radio program for X/GTK Xcall is a packet radio program which supports the AX.25, NET/ROM and Rose protocols. The current features of xcall are:  o Command line history.  o Recording of the session into a file.  o AX.25 port information read from the proc filesystem.  o Changing of the receive window font and colors.  o Dutch and French Language support.  o Basic support for DX Clusters. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Pigeon holes for your cut and paste selections xcb provides easy access to the cut buffers built into every X server. It allows the buffers to be manipulated either via the command line, or with the mouse in a point and click manner. This version is also utf-8 capable. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCCI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Common Client Interface (X-Windows), &quot;X CCI&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcdroast
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X based CD-writer software X-CD-Roast is a full X based CD-Writer-program and is the successor of cdwtools-0.93. It is a frontend for CD related programs like cdwrite and mkisofs. Feature list of 0.98alpha:   - Easy setup and intuitive X11 user interface   - GUI based on GTK+ instead of TCL/TK (100% new C-code)   - Copies most data/mixed-mode/audio-CDs (data also on-the-fly)   - Master data-CDs and rearrange audio-CDs (data also on-the-fly)   - Create your own audio-CDs (full Disk-at-Once support)   - Multisession/Bootable CD creation.   - Supports most SCSI/ATAPI/Parallel-CD-Writers available   - Supports different international languages   - CDDB-Lookups and CD-Text   - Online help   - Administration mode for usage in computer pools.   - Fully themeable via GTK-Themes   - Runs on most common Unix-Operation-Systems     (Primary platforms: Linux and Solaris) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCEM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensions for Control, Engineering and Manufacturing (API, MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xchain
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A strategy game for 2-4 players Chain Reaction is a classic strategy game for 2-4 players. Players take turns to place tokens on an 8x8 board. When a square exceeds it&apos;s maximum value, it explodes, setting off the surrounding squares. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xchat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
IRC client for X similar to AmIRC XChat is a graphical IRC Client with a GTK+ GUI. It has a look and feel similar to AmIRC for the Amiga. Special features include the mIRC extension DCC RESUME and mIRC color, multiple server/channel windows, dialog windows, and a plugin API. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCHS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Cylinder Head Sectors (EIDE) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Chinese input server in X11 This package contains the XCIN Chinese input server, to be used with Chinese Rxvt (provided in the rxvt-ml package) for the X Window System. It supports both Big5 (traditional Chinese) and GB (simplified Chinese) character sets. Currently, the Debian xcin package use the 12x24, taipei24 (zh_TW.Big5) and hanzigb24st (zh_CN.GB2312) fonts, although other fonts may be used. There is also limited support for the new zh_CN.GBK and zh_HK.Big5-HKSCS locales.  More fonts and input methods will be available for Debian in the future.  Home Page: http://xcin.linux.org.tw/  Authors: Edward Der-Hua Liu, Taiwan           Suei-Jeng Wang &lt;vvvv.bbs@cis.nctu.edu.tw&gt;           Tung-Han Hsieh &lt;thhsieh@linux.org.tw&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcin2.3
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Chinese input server (Big5) for XA+CV in X11. This package contains the (old) XCIN2.3 Chinese input server, to be used with Chinese Rxvt (provided in the rxvt-ml package) and XA+CV in X11. It only supports Big5.  Install the xcingb if you want GB support instead. Currently, the Debian xcin package defaults to use the 12x24 and taipei24 fonts from the xfonts-base and xfonts-intl-chinese packages.  Home Page: http://xcin.linux.org.tw/  Authors: Edward Der-Hua Liu, Taiwan           Suei-Jeng Wang &lt;vvvv.bbs@cis.nctu.edu.tw&gt;           Tung-Han Hsieh &lt;thhsieh@linux.org.tw&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcingb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[Obsolete] Chinese input server (GB) for Crxvt in X11. Note: This package is obsolete.  It is provided in case the user       needs it for some old applications.  The user is recommended       to use xcin 2.5.x or chinput 3.x instead. This package contains the XcinGB Chinese input server, as well as its companion crxvt-gb-2.3 (or gbrxvt-2.3) Chinese X terminal for the X Window System.  It supports the GB2312 character set, the standard encoding in Mainland China and other places that use Simplified Chinese characters, Jiantizi.  Home Page: http://xcin.linux.org.tw/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcircuit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Draw circuit schematics or almost anything. xcircuit is a generic drawing program tailored for making circuit diagrams. The graphical interface attempts to maintain consistency between X11 window rendering and the pure PostScript output. xcircuit is mouse, menu and keyboard driven. The emphasis is on single character macros. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xclip
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
command line interface to X selections xclip is a command line utility that is designed to run on any system with an X11 implementation. It provides an interface to X selections (&quot;the clipboard&quot;) from the command line. It can read data from standard in or a file and place it in an X selection for pasting into other X applications. xclip can also print an X selection to standard out, which can then be redirected to a file or another program. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xclipboard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X clipboard client From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xclips
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphic interface to the &quot;C&quot; Language Integrated Production System This package provides a graphical interface to clips that allows user to have access to many functions and easy display of the agenda, instance, facts... From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
analog / digital clock for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCMOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended CMOS (IC, CMOS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Color Management System (X-Windows), &quot;Xcms&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcmsdb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Device Color Characterization utility for X Color Management System From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCOFF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Common Object File Format (Unix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcolors
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display all X11 color names and colors Reads the rgb.txt file that defines the color names the X server knows and displays the colors found. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcolorsel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display colors and names in X xcolorsel is an X utility that displays the contents of the X color list file (/etc/X11/rgb.txt) together with tiles showing how the color looks on your screen.  You can cut the color names/definitions in various formats (suitable for resource files or C source) so they can be pasted directly into source codes or resources. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xconq
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical multi-player strategy game and game design system. Xconq is an Empire-type strategy game, where each player contests for domination of a simulated world.  Unlike most empire-building games, it features a programming language that game designers can use to build a wide variety of games. Games already in the distribution&apos;s library include everything from simple combat, to elaborate world models, to silly but fun games, with time periods ranging from ancient history into the distant future. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xconq-common
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
common Files to Xconq. This package contains common architecture independent files needed by Xconq. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xconsole
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
monitor system console messages with X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xconvers
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Hamradio convers client for X/GTK Xconvers is a client to connect to a convers server (port 3600) over the internet or by packet-radio. In a split-screen session you can type text into the bottom screen. The reply from the server can be seen in the top screen. The current version features: color support, optional saving of the session to a logfile, history for the connect dialog and the send widget and autologin. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcoral
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Extensible mouse-based text editor for X This is a multi-window mouse-based text editor for the X Window System. It is provided with a built-in C/C++/Java browser and an Ansi C Interpreter to dynamically extend the editor&apos;s possibilities (modes, key-bindings). Xcoral also offers facilities to write LaTeX documents and HTML pages. This package install the Xcoral user&apos;s manual in postscript. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcruise
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fly about 3D-formed file system Xcruise allows you fling about the file system by 3D-view. Every file appears as a planets, directory appears as a galaxies,and symbolic link appears as a worm-holes. You could fly about this space world by moving and clicking your mouse From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XCUTS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Commands and Utilities Test Suite (X/Open) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcutsel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
interchange between cut buffer and selection From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xcwcp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Qt frontend to unixcw Xcwcp is an X-based interactive Morse code tutor program. It lets you choose from a number of options for practice, including sending random characters, random words, and characters from the keyboard. It will also receive Morse code that you send using the keyboard or mouse as a Morse keyer, and display the characters it sees. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdaliclock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Melting digital clock The xdaliclock program displays a digital clock; when a digit changes, it &quot;melts&quot; into its new shape. It can display in 12 or 24 hour modes, and displays the date when a mouse button is held down.  It has two large fonts built into it, but it can animate most other fonts that contain all of the digits.  It can also do some funky psychedelic colormap cycling, and can use the &quot;shape&quot; extension so that the window is shaped like the digits. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdelta
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xdelta (X for XCF: the eXperimental Computing Facility at Berkeley) is a binary delta generator (like a diff program for binaries) and an RCS version control replacement library. The Xdelta library performs its work independently of the actual format used to encode the file and is intended to be used by various higher-level programs such as XCF&apos;s Project Revision Control System (PRCS). PRCS is a front end for aversion control toolset. Xdelta uses a binary file delta algorithm toreplace the standard diff program used by RCS. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdemineur
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet another minesweeper for X This one is the most similar to the Windows one in terms of look and feel. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdeview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Smart multi-file multi-part decoder (X11 GUI) This is an X11-based decoder for files encoded with the following formats: uuencode, xxencode, BASE64, quoted printable, and BinHex. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdfcopy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Program to copy and format Xdf disks in Linux TQ From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdfformat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Program to copy and format Xdf disks in Linux TQ From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdialog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 replacement for the text util dialog Xdialog is designed to be a drop-in replacement for the dialog and cdialog programs. It converts any terminal-based program into a program with an X interface. The dialogs are easier to see and use, and Xdialog adds more functionality such as a help button and box, a treeview, an editbox, file and directory selectors, a range box, and a calendar. It uses GTK+, and will match your desktop theme. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdigger
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A XWindow-game like Boulderdash (without scrolling) You are a little (digger-)man and have to collect diamonds. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdiskusage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays a graphic of your disk usage with du xdiskusage is a user-friendly program to show you what is using up all your disk space. It is based on the design of the &quot;xdu&quot; program written by Phillip C. Dykstra. Changes have been made so it runs &quot;du&quot; for you, and can display the free space left on the disk, and produce a PostScript version of the display. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xditview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display ditroff output From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdkcal
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Desktop Calendar for X X Desktop Calendar (xdkcal) is a Calendar for X Window System. It draws calendar on your desktop.  You can customize, fontset, color drawing style.  This application is completely internationalized so it reads locale database and draw locale specific strings, such as name of months or weeks. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XDM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Display Manager (X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Display Manager - users need only to type in their username and password at a friendly prompt, and they are dropped directly into the graphical environment. This is simple and easy to use, and is seen frequently in college campuses, cyber cafes, business environments, anywhere you have users not necessarily familiar with Unix to any great extent. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X display manager xdm manages a collection of X servers, which may be on the local host or remote machines.  It provides services similar to those provided by init, getty, and login on character-based terminals: prompting for login name and password, authenticating the user, and running a session.  xdm supports XDMCP (X Display Manager Control Protocol) and can also be used to run a chooser process which presents the user with a menu of possible hosts that offer XDMCP display management. If the xutils package is installed, xdm can use the sessreg utility to register login sessions to the system utmp file; this, however, is not necessary for xdm to function. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XDM (X Display Manager)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
User-friendly login front end for the X Window System. Often used in a cyber cafi or campus environment where users who are not familiar with UNIX need occasional access. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XDMCP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Display Manager Control Protocol (X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdpyinfo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display information utility for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XDR
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXternal Data Representation (ONC, RPCL, Sun, RFC 1832) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdrawchem
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an open-source version of ChemDraw A linux application that mirrors the abilities of ChemDraw This program has file compatibility with Chemdraw files. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XDS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xeros Data Systems (manufacturer, Xerox) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display the output of &quot;du&quot; in an X window XDU is a program for displaying a graphical tree of disk space utilization as reported by the UNIX utility &quot;du&quot;.  You can navigate up and down in the tree, sort things, and print out information. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xduck
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdvi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
DVI Previewer for the X Window System From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdvi.bin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
DVI Previewer for the X Window System From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xdvi.real
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
DVI Previewer for the X Window System From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xed
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The standard text editor, for X xed is a Tcl/Tk reimplementation of the standard text editor, ed.  It includes a window showing the file you&apos;re editing, but also has the classic efficient text-based interface Unix users have loved for years. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xedit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
simple text editor for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xeji
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Follow the Mouse X demo A man will watch over you. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xemacs21-bin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Editor and kitchen sink -- support binaries A spinoff of the GNU Emacs editor with much better support for X including multiple fonts within the same buffer and images within buffers, but that doesn&apos;t even begin to describe the changes. XEmacs is a full fledged programming language with a mail reader, news reader, info browser, web browser, calendar, specialized editor for more programming languages and other formats than most people encounter in a lifetime, and much much more. After starting it up peruse the Help menu and read more on its origins and what it can do. You will need one of xemacs21-mule, xemacs21-nomule, or xemacs21-mule-canna-wnn to actually run xemacs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xemacs21-gnome-mule
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Editor and kitchen sink -- Mule binary This package contains the actual binary used to run XEmacs.  It depends on the xemacs21-support package for lisp and etc files, and the xemacs21-bin package for supporting binaries.  This binary has been compiled with support for mule, but no input extensions. This version has also been compiled to use features from gtk and gnome. Mule is the extension to (x)emacs that allows for the display of non-European characters (for example Japanese and Korean characters). This version of the package is mainly useful for only the display and reading of international characters.  It does not have any mechanism for entering non-European characters (see the xemacs21-mule-canna-wnn package for that). This package actually contains one of the six xemacs binaries available.  They are xemacs21-nomule, xemacs21-mule, xemacs21-mule-canna-wnn, xemacs21-gnome-nomule, xemacs21-gnome-mule, and xemacs21-gnome-mule-canna-wnn. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xemeraldia
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
not just another tetris clone Another tetris-like falling blocks game. Although it looks like Tetris, it&apos;s not---and figuring out how to make blocks go away is half the fun. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xengine
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A benchmark program for the X Window System. It displays an animation of the moving engine of cars. The r.p.m. of the engine suggests the performance of the X Window System to put dots on the display. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XEROX PARC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/zee&apos;roks park&apos;/ n. The famed Palo Alto Research Center. For more than a decade, from the early 1970s into the mid-1980s, PARC yielded an astonishing volume of groundbreaking hardware and software innovations. The modern mice, windows, and icons style of software interface was invented there. So was the laser printer and the local-area network; and PARC&apos;s series of D machines anticipated the powerful personal computers of the 1980s by a decade. Sadly, the prophets at PARC were without honor in their own company, so much so that it became a standard joke to describe PARC as a place that specialized in developing brilliant ideas for everyone else. The stunning shortsightedness and obtusity of XEROX&apos;s top-level suits has been well anatomized in &quot;Fumbling The Future: How XEROX Invented, Then Ignored, the First Personal Computer&quot; by Douglas K. Smith and Robert C. Alexander (William Morrow &amp; Co., 1988, ISBN 0-688-09511-9). From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XES
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xerox Engineering Systems (Xerox) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xeukleides
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a program to create Euclidean geometry figures. xeukleides is a system for editing and viewing elementary Euclidean geometry figures using a gtk interface. Also included is eukleides which is console based. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xeuklides
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a program to create euclidean geometry figures. xeuklides is a system for editing and viewing elementary euclidean geometry figures using a gtk interface. Also included is euklides which is console based. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xev
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
print contents of X events From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xevil
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A violent side-scrolling game for X XEvil is a 3rd person, side-view, fast-action, kill-them-before-they-kill-you game. Fight against either computer-controlled enemies, or another player. You sinned in life. And now you must pay. Satan pits the recently deceased against each other to fight for rank in Hell. Your skill determines your fate for all eternity. This contest is known as XEvil. XEvil runs on Windows 95/98/NT, and most Unix platforms. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xexec
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Run a simple arbitrary command from X xexec is a program designed to allow quick and easy access for running simple command lines. For example, let&apos;s say you wanted to start Netscape, but didn&apos;t have it on your window manager&apos;s menu. Just run xexec, and type netscape in the text box, press enter, and there you have it.  It is especially useful for allowing access to any available command via one primary menu entry. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xext
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
extensions to XFree86 3.x servers xext provides extensions to XFree86 version 3.x servers.  This presently includes a system for 3D rendering under X called PEX (the PHIGS/PHIGS-PLUS Extension to X, in which PHIGS stands for Programmer&apos;s Hierarchical Interactive Graphics System), XIE (X Image Extension), and XInput, which can manage the following input devices:   * joystick (PC game port type)   * Elographics touch screen   * MicroTouch touch screens (using stylus or finger)   * mouse   * Wacom eraser   * Wacom cursor   * SummaSketch tablet   * AceCad tablet   * CalComp DrawingBoard tablet   * SWITCH virtual device   * SGI button box While this package is installable without an X server on the system, it is only useful in conjunction with an XFree86 3.x X server.  Note that the loadable extension modules in this package are not compatible with, and are not used by, the XFree86 version 4.x X server. If you intend to use the joystick extension (and the joycal joystick calibration program), and are using a Linux kernel version prior to 2.2, you will need the joystick kernel module package. Note that the PEX extension is not supported on the Alpha architecture. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xeyes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a follow the mouse X demo From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xf86cfg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical configuration tool for XFree86 4.0 From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xf86config
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
generate an XF86Config file From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfaces
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays an image for each piece of mail in your mailbox. XFaces is a program that will display an image for each piece of mail in your mail box. This lets you know at a glance who you have mail from. XFaces starts out (when you have no mail) looking like a color xbiff. As you receive mail XFaces becomes a column of mail images. Some of XFaces features: - Both mono and color images. - Optional Shaped window support with both xpm and xbm. - Sound support using the NetAudio protocol. The NetAudio server currently supports Sun&apos;s SparcStation (SunOS 4.1.X and Solaris 2.2), SGI&apos;s Indigo and NCD MCX X terminals running NCDware 3.1 or later. - Face images can be &quot;compressed&quot; so that each image will only show up once on your display. This way, if you receive 30 messages from one user, list or whatever the image will only show up once. - You can use regular expressions to search any headers to choose images and sounds or ignore that mail message completely. This lets you specify an image/sound for mail that comes from a mailing list or ignore mail that you have already seen but left in your system mailbox. - Compatibility support for Rich Burridge&apos;s faces program. This includes the ability to run user command to generate the image list. - Support for POP mailboxes. - XFaces can kick off shell commands based upon mailbox contents.  You could have yourself paged when a high priority item needs your attention. - XFaces can run external filters to convert images into Xpm so that image formats that XFaces does not understand can be used. - The annotations for mail items include username, hostname, count, user@host, the contents of any header. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFCB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Extended File Control Block From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfce
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Cholesterol Free Desktop Environment XFce, previously known as XForms cool environment, is a desktop environment reminiscent of CDE that uses the GTK+ library, and isn&apos;t resource-hungry. XFce includes a window manager, tool bar, file manager, backdrop manager, sound subsystem, clock and calendar, mouse configuration and pager module. Also includes sounds, icons, backgrounds and pixmaps used by the XFce environment and window manager, along with systemwide configuration files and HTML help files. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display all the characters in an X font From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Front End (X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfig
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Facility for Interactive Generation of figures under X11 XFig is a menu-driven tool that allows the user to draw and manipulate objects interactively in an X window.  The resulting pictures can be saved, printed on postscript printers, or converted to a variety of other formats (e.g. to allow inclusion in LaTeX documents or web pages) using the transfig program. This package contains the xfig program itself and the object libraries. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfindproxy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
locate proxy services From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfingerd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
BSD-like finger daemon with qmail support. Yet another finger daemon.  Mimics the output and behavior of the original BSD daemon.  Does not need to be run as root, has support for PGP keys, qmail mailboxes and qmail dash-extended usernames.  Generally paranoid about account probes, while still allows search by full name.  Users can control if they can be fingered or not.  Uses tcpwrappers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfireworks
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fireworks in your root window XFireworks makes fireworks in the root window on X. This is imitation of Japanese &quot;Hanabi Taikai&quot;. It is very popular event in Japanese summer  and  performed  on  some rivers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfishtank
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
turns your X root into an aquarium Enjoy an animated aquarium background on your screen, with a variety of tropical fish swimming in it. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xflip
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
programs to mirror-image or melt your display. Flip your (or your &quot;xhost +&quot; using friend&apos;s) screen on either the vertical or horizontal axis or melt away the graphics on your display. Both commands have a -planes option to independently act on individual bit planes. This version now comes with a new -oblic option which flips horizontally and vertically simultaneously. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X file and application manager Xfm is an file and application manager program for the X Window System, based on the Xaw3d widget set.  It provides virtually all of the features that you would expect in a file manager; move around your directory tree in multiple windows, move, copy or delete files, and launch programs with simple mouse operations.  Directory displays are updated automatically in regular intervals when the contents of the directory change.  The integrated application manager provides a kind of &quot;shelf&quot; onto which you can place your favorite applications, as well as the files and directories you are currently working with.  It also allows you to access different groups of applications and files.  User-definable file types let you specify a command to be executed when double-clicking on a file or dropping other files onto it. Last not least, xfm can automatically mount and unmount special devices like floppies as you open and close the corresponding directories (mount points). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X/open Federated Naming (X/Open) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfontsel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
point and click selection of X11 font names From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFree86
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A free software implementation of the X Window System (X); an interface that communicates between video cards, displays, and the graphical desktop; provides windowing infrastructure and an interface for programming graphical applications. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFree86
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A version of the X Window System for Linux. Used by GNOME, KDE and other Linux user interfaces/window managers. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFree86
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
If you want to install the X Window System (TM) on your machine, you&apos;ll need to install XFree86.The X Window System provides the base technology for developing graphical user interfaces. Simply stated,X draws the elements of the GUI on the user&apos;s screen andbuilds methods for sending user interactions back to the application. X also supports remote application deployment--running an application on another computer while viewing the input/outputon your machine.  X is a powerful environment which supports many different applications, such as games, programming tools, graphics programs, text editors, etc.  XFree86 is the version of X which runs on Linux, as well as other platforms. This package contains the basic fonts, programs and documentationfor an X workstation.  You will also need the XFree86-serverpackage, which contains the program which drives your video hardware. In addition to installing this package, you will need to install the drakxtools package to configure your card using XFdrake. You may also need to install one of the XFree86 fonts packages.And finally, if you are going to develop applications that run asX clients, you will also need to install XFree86-devel. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFree86
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X was developed by the X Consortium as a standard as well as a reference implementation of that standard. There are ports to every platform that supports graphics. The current version of the standard is 11 release 6 (hence the directory /usr/X11R6/). There will probably never be another version. XFree86 &lt;http://www.xfree86.org/&gt; is a free port of X that includes LINUX Intel machines among its supported hardware. X has some peculiarities that are worth noting if you are a Windows user, and XFree86 has some over those. XFree86 has its own versioning system beneath the ``11R6&apos;&apos;. From Rute-Users-Guide
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFree86
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XFree86 is an open source implementation of the X Window System.  It provides the basic low level functionality which full fledged graphical user interfaces (GUIs) such as GNOME and KDE are designed upon. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfree86-common
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System (XFree86) infrastructure xfree86-common contains the filesystem infrastructure required for further installation of the X Window System in any configuration. Those wishing an X server only (with remote font services and clients) will also require the xserver-common package and an X server package (most likely xserver-xfree86). The counterpart to the above configuration is a machine with the X libraries (the xlibs package), xbase-clients, a window manager, some X font packages, and likely many more client packages. Those who desire a standalone X workstation (and/or are fuzzy on the concepts of X servers and X clients) will require both of the above sets of packages. For convenience, the &quot;x-window-system&quot; metapackage will include everything that is required for a standalone X workstation. A number of terms are used to refer to the X Window System, including &quot;X&quot;, &quot;X Version 11&quot;, &quot;X11&quot;, &quot;X11R6&quot;, and &quot;X11R6.4&quot;.  The version of X used in Debian is derived from the version released by the XFree86 Project, Inc., and is thus often also referred to as &quot;XFree86&quot;.  All of the preceding quoted terms are functionally interchangeable in a Debian system. Still confused?  Install this package and then read the files in /usr/share/doc/xfree86-common/ for assistance. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfreecd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a GTK-based CD Player XfreeCD is a X window program that looks like the front panel of a CD player. It has full cddb database support. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfrisk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Server and X11 client for playing risk with humans or AIs xfrisk allows you to play risk against other players over TCP/IP and/or with 3 different AI players. Risk is a board game played on a map of the world. You control a group of armies and attempt to capture large sections of the world and try to stop your opponents from doing the same thing. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XFS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended File System (JFS, SGI, Unix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X font server From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X font server xfs is a daemon that listens on a network port and serves X fonts to X servers (and thus to X clients).  All X servers have the ability to serve locally installed fonts for themselves, but xfs makes it possible to offload that job from the X server, and/or have a central repository of fonts on a networked machine running xfs so that all the machines running X servers on a network do not require their own set of fonts.  xfs may also be invoked by users to, for instance, make available X fonts in user accounts that are not available to the X server or to an already running system xfs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfs-xtt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-TrueType font server This package provide X-TrueType font server. This is compatible  normal X font server, but added X-TrueType font handling scheme support instead of FreeType backend. XFree86 4.0&apos;s font server can handle TrueType too, but it can not handle TTCap. By using TTCap description, support for font transformations, such as slanting, adjusting glyph width, pseudo-bolding, etc. xfs-xtt is a daemon that listens on a network port and serves X fonts to X servers (and thus to X clients).  All X servers have the ability to serve locally installed fonts for themselves, but xfs makes it possible to offload that job from the X server, and/or have a central repository of fonts on a networked machine running xfs so that all the machines running X servers on a network do not require their own set of fonts.  xfs may also be invoked by users to, for instance, make available X fonts in user accounts that are not available to the X server or to an already running system xfs-xtt. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfsdump
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Administrative utilities for the XFS filesystem The xfsdump package contains xfsdump, xfsrestore and a number of other administrative utilities for managing XFS filesystems. xfsdump examines files in a filesystem, determines which need to be backed up, and copies those files to a specified disk, tape or other storage medium.  It uses XFS-specific directives for optimizing the dump of an XFS filesystem, and also knows how to backup XFS extended attributes.  Backups created with xfsdump are &quot;endian safe&quot; and can thus be transfered between Linux machines of different architectures and also between IRIX machines. xfsrestore performs the inverse function of xfsdump; it can restore a full backup of a filesystem.  Subsequent incremental backups can then be layered on top of the full backup.  Single files and directory subtrees may be restored from full or partial backups. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfsinfo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X font server information utility From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfsprogs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Utilities for managing the XFS filesystem A set of commands to use the XFS filesystem, including mkfs.xfs. XFS is a high performance journaling filesystem which originated on the SGI IRIX platform.  It is completely multi-threaded, can support large files and large filesystems, extended attributes, variable block sizes, is extent based, and makes extensive use of Btrees (directories, extents, free space) to aid both performance and scalability. Refer to the documentation at http://oss.sgi.com/projects/xfs/ for complete details.  This implementation is on-disk compatible with the IRIX version of XFS. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfsprogs-bf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A stripped-down versions of xfsprogs, for boot-floppies This package is an xfsprogs package built for a reduced size, so that it can help to save space on installation boot-floppies. Don&apos;t attempt to install this package, it has no support for a couple of features you surely want.  Anyway it should refuse to install. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfstt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
TrueType Font Server for X11 xfstt means &quot;X11 Font Server for TT fonts&quot;. TT fonts are generally regarded to be the best scalable fonts for displays. Applications needing scalable fonts that are to be displayed on a screen benefit most. This server will allow X11 applications to use the exact same fonts as the TrueType fonts used on most Windows Machines. NB: This package contains NO FONTS. They MUST be obtained separately From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xft
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xft is a font rendering library for X. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xftcache
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
create an index of FreeType font files in a directory From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xftp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Athena X interface to ftp. xftp is a X ftp interface. It allows retrieval or transmission of selected files and directory trees. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xfwp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X firewall proxy server The X firewall proxy is an application layer gateway proxy that may be run on a network firewall host to forward X traffic across the firewall.  Used in conjunction with the X server Security extension and authorization checking, xfwp constitutes a safe, simple, and reliable mechanism both to hide the addresses of X servers located on an intranet and to enforce a server connection policy.  Xfwp cannot protect against mischief originating on an intranet; however, when properly configured it can guarantee that only trusted clients originating on authorized external Internet hosts will be allowed inbound access to local X servers. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended General MIDI (Yamaha, MIDI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XGA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Graphics Adapter (IBM, PS/2) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgalaga
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 version of the famous Galaga game A clone of the classic game Galaga for the X Window System. Xgalaga is a space-invader like game with additional features to produce a more interesting game. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgamma
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Alter a monitor&apos;s gamma correction for XFree86 From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgammon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Implementation of backgammon under X. This a nicely implemented backgammon with the following features:    - X11/Xaw interface,    - a simple file selector and saving dialog,    - You can edit positions and perform rollouts.    - Position dump to a mail file in the format used in backgammon newsgroups.    - Easier movement of stones, by simple button clicks.    - You can play against an opponent on a remote X-Terminal. (experimental). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X graphics demo From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgdipc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GnuDIP GTK client A graphical (GTK-based) client for updating your GnuDIP settings From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgdvi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a TeX DVI previewer for X, with a nice GTK+ UI xgdvi is a TeX DVI(DeVice Independent) file previewer for the X Window System. xgdvi features a cool GTK+ frontend, and since it uses DVIlib as its kernel, xgdvi can handle EPS figures and Japanese DVI files. Anti-aliasing is also supported. This is a part of the TeX-Guy distribution. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgettext
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
extract translatable string from given input files From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgmod
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GUI based module player for Ultrasound and SB AWE soundcards XGmod plays MOD/669/MTM/S3M/ULT/XM modules on machines that have an Gravis Ultrasound family sound card or a Soundblaster AWE. This version has a X interface that depends on Qt. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgospel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an Internet Go client xgospel is a client for playing the game of Go (Weiqi, Baduk) on the Internet Go Server (IGS).  Unfortunately, it is somewhat lacking with respect to connecting to other Go servers on the internet, playing Go between two computers, or editing SGF files.  You should probably install cgoban for these purposes.  However, if you intend to play on IGS frequently, xgospel is the perfect choice for you. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xgraph
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Plotting program, reads stdin, allows interactive zooming Accepts data files or stdin in a form similar to the unix program graph and displays line graphs, scatter plots, or bar charts on an X11 display.  Fully annotated with title, axis numbering and labels, and legend.  Zooming with the mouse is supported.  Can generate hardcopy output to Postscript printers and HPGL plotters.  Output can be directly pasted into idraw (drawtool) for further annotation. Particularly useful in shell scripts. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xhangglider
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
hanggliders fly around in your X root window. xhangglider is a demo program for X. Hanggliders and paragliders fly around in your X root window. Enjoy! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xhost
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
server access control program for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XHTML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended HyperText Markup Language (HTML, WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XHTML (extensible Hyper Text Markup Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An enhanced version of HTML that supports programmer-defined extensions like XML. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XID
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[SNA] eXchange IDentifier (SNA) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XIE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Image Extension (X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xieperf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XIE server extension test and demo program From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ximian-setup-tools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Cross-platform configuration utilities. The Ximian Setup Tools are a set of cross-platform configuration utilities for Linux and other Unices. Internally they are divided in frontends and backends. The frontend knows nothing about the underlying system and provides the same user interface across the different types of systems. The backend knows how to read and write configuration information. The Ximian Setup Tools do not impose a new database on the system, they work with the default configuration files so that configuration can still be done by hand or by other tools. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xine-dvdnav
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
xine DVD plugin that is capable of Menus and special features This plugin will eventually be able to play all special features that can be found on DVDs. Currently, it works with most DVDs. Features include: * DVD menus * correctly coloured subtitles * named subtitles and audio channels * forced subtitles (can be overridden) * Copyright warnings From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xine-plugins
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
xine is a free gpl-licensed video player for unix-like systems. This package includes the main plugins for xine, they allow the input from files, Video CDs, network streams and (not encrypted) DVDs inseveral video formats.  For additional plugins (support for DVDsprotected by CSS or for non free codecs) you could try the packages from the Penguin Liberation Front home page:http://plf.zarb.org That page is not connected to MandrakeSoft. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xine-ui
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the xine video player, user interface This is an X11 based GUI for the libxine video player library. It provides xine, a skin based media player that can play all the audio/video formats that libxine supports. Currently, this includes MPEG1/2, some AVI and Quicktime files, some network streaming methods and disc based media (VCD, SVCD, DVD). A more complete list can be found on http://xine.sf.net/. This package contains an additional front end, aaxine, which runs even on the console. aaxine uses aalib to render ASCII art video, or you can tell it to use a framebuffer device. This is more a proof of concept, but you can use it to watch DVDs on your old vt100 terminal, of course. ;-) Most DVDs on the market today are play-protected by the Content Scrambling System (CSS). Xine does not provide any code to descramble those DVDs, because of legal uncertainties. Have a look at /usr/share/doc/xine-ui/README.Debian for more information! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xine-ui
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
xine is a free GPL-licensed video player for UNIX-like systems. User interface for the X Window system. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xinetd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
replacement for inetd with many enhancements xinetd has access control mechanisms, extensive logging capabilities, the ability to make services available based on time, and can place limits on the number of servers that can be started, among other things. It has the ability to redirect TCP streams to a remote host and port. This is useful for those of that use ip masquerading, or NAT, and want to be able to reach your internal hosts. It also has the ability to bind specific services to specific interfaces. This is useful when you want to make services available for your internal network, but not the rest of the world. Or to have a different service running on the same port, but different interfaces. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xinetd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xinetd is a secure replacement for inetd, the Internet services daemon. Xinetd provides access control for all services based on the address of the remote host and/or on time of access and can prevent denial-of-access attacks. Xinetd provides extensive logging, has no limit on the number of server arguments, and lets you bind specific services to specific IP addresses on your host machine. Each service has its own specific configuration file for Xinetd; the files a relocated in the /etc/xinetd.d directory. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xinit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System initializer From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xinitrc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The xinitrc package contains the xinitrc file, a script which is used to configure your X Window System session or to start a window manager. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xinput
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Runtime configuration and test of XInput devices. Runtime configuration and test of XInput devices. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XInput extension
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a standard X extension. The goal of this extension is to allow additional input devices management to the X Window System. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XINU
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XINU Is Not Unix (OS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xinv3d
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
3D space invaders for X XInvaders 3D is a 3D vector-based space-invaders clone for the X Window System. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XIOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Input/Output System (Novell, Netware) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xipmsg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A pop up style message communication software IP Messenger is a pop up style message communication software for multi platforms. It is based on TCP/IP(UDP). Xipmsg is the X11 version of IP Messenger. It can communicate with IP Messengers for Windows/MacOS. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xisdnload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The xisdnload utility displays a periodically updated histogram of theload average over your ISDN connection. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xitalk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Talk intercept utility for X xitalk logs you in on a pseudo terminal.  If you then disable messages in all your xterms, xitalk will receive all talk requests/ writes.  It can then start a [y]talk session, play a sound, etc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xiterm+thai
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
x-terminal program with Thai languague support xiterm+thai is an x-terminal-emulator program with Thai language support. It has built-in Thai keyboard input support. You could also use X11 XKB extension to input Thai character. Thai font is needed to display Thai character. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xjed
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Editor for programmers. (x11 version) Jed offers: Extensible in a language resembling C. Completely customizable. Capable of read GNU info files from within JED&apos;s info browser. A variety of programming modes (with syntax highlighting) are available including Pascal, Java, Perl, C, C++, FORTRAN, TeX, HTML, SH, IDL, DCL, NROFF, PostScript, Basic. Folding support. Edit TeX files with AUC-TeX style editing (BiBTeX support too). Rectangular cut/paste; regular expressions; incremental searches; search replace across multiple files; multiple windows; multiple buffers; shell modes; directory editor (dired); mail; rmail; ispell; and much more. Note: The SLang runtime files are now in the package jed-commono. The source of these files are in jed-sl. Note: In this version, C-h deletes the previous character instead of loading the help menu. Help is now on Esc-?. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xjewel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
match colors on falling columns of blocks Jewel Box is a falling-pieces game like Tetris, only jewels are removed from the board if three or more of the same jewel lie in a straight line. Interesting cascade-like effects can be achieved when the removal of jewels causes another set of jewels to line up. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xjig
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An X11 jigsaw puzzle xjig is a puzzle that tries to replicate a jigsaw puzzle on the screen as closely as possible. Any GIF image may be loaded and cut into pieces. The goal (as with any jigsaw puzzle) is to reassemble the original picture. Tiles may be freely rotated by use of the mouse, flipped (for double-sided puzzles) and even shown as shaped windows on the desktop (fast machine/video card recommended for the latter!). An example image is provided in /usr/lib/games/xjig . From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xjokes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 jokes xjokes contains 4 jokes. yasiti, blackhole, mori1, and mori2. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xjove
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11-Frontend for jove - a compact, powerful editor. This is the X11-Frontend for jove. Jove is a compact, powerful Emacs-style text-editor.  It provides the common emacs keyboard bindings, together with a reasonable assortment of the most popular advanced features (e.g. interactive shell windows, compile-it, language specific modes) while weighing in with CPU, memory, and disk requirements comparable to vi(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xjump
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A jumping game for X. A jumping game for X. The way to play this game is very simple, but nice game. What you do in this game is only to jump, jump and jump up above. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkbcomp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
compile XKB keyboard description From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkbevd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XKB event daemon From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkbprint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
print an XKB keyboard description From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkbsel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tool for defining, selecting, and indicating XKB keyboards. xkbsel is a framework for defining, selecting, and indicating XKB keyboard mappings, without the need to modify X11 distribution in any way. This package contains the xkbsel basic files and binaries, including the Athena keyboard switching applet. Homepage: http://www.penguin.cz/~stano/sk/xkbsel.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkbsel-gnome
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tool for defining, selecting, and indicating XKB keyboards. xkbsel is a framework for defining, selecting, and indicating XKB keyboard mappings, without the need to modify X11 distribution in any way. This package contains the Gnome keyboard switching applet. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkeycaps
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Manipulate X keymaps (for xmodmap) graphically. xkeycaps is a graphical front-end to xmodmap(1). It opens a window that looks like a keyboard; moving the mouse over a key shows what KeySyms and Modifier bits that key generates. Clicking on a key simulates KeyPress/KeyRelease events on the window of your choice. It is possible to change the KeySyms and Modifiers generated by a key through a mouse-based interface. This program can also write an input file for xmodmap to recreate your changes in future sessions. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkeysw
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a keyboard layout switch for the X Window System. Its main features are:    - Per-window switching. You can have different layouts in different windows.    - Unlimited number of layouts.    - Flexible switching. Any layout can have its own &quot;hot keys&quot; for      switching to other layouts. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkill
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
kill a client by its X resource From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xklitze
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xkobo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a game of space battle Destroy all the fortresses and avoid the many enemy ships to advance to the next level in this game of space battle. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlaby
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Collect four items from an xmaze using the mouse to move. xlaby traps your mouse cursor in one of the mazes generated by &quot;maze&quot;, you must move around until you collect all four objects - invisible walls are an option! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlander
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a lunar landing simulation for X The object is to successfully land the craft on the surface of the moon or some other planet.  The program features &quot;out-the-window&quot; 3-d wire-frame graphics and full directional control of the lander.  For further instructions, please, refer to the man page. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlassie
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dockable mail notifier w/ message count &amp; POP3/APOP/IMAP support Enhanced pending mail notifier. Displays the number of waiting messages. Supports local mail spool and POP3/APOP3/IMAP mail servers. Can run a command when clicked upon. Uses plain xlib, so memory footprint is tiny. Can operate as plain app or WindowMaker/KDE dock applet From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlbiff
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Literate Biff. Displays Froms and Subjects of your new mail Xlbiff lurks in the background, monitoring your mailbox file (normally /usr/spool/mail/&lt;yourusername&gt;).  When something shows up there, it invokes the MH scan(1) command and displays the output in a window. If more mail comes in, it scans again and resizes accordingly. Clicking the left mouse button anywhere in the window causes it to vanish.  It will also vanish if you inc(1) and the mailbox becomes empty.  Xlbiff is modeled after xconsole -- its job is to sit invisibly and pop up only when something demands your attention. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Gtk client for linesrv xlc is a Gtk client for linesrv. It let a user to start or stop an internet connection on a masquerader server. It allows to monitor the connection status and to shutdown the box where the server is running From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xless
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A file browsing tool for the X Window System xless allows you to view information in an X window. It allows filename(s) arguments, or input via STDIN. It can print the current buffer and do regular expression searches. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xletters
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Type falling words before they land A typing practice game for X similar to typespeed and tuxtype. Words chosen from the system&apos;s wordlist fall from the top of the screen and must be typed correctly to score.  In a challenge stage, random sequences of characters appear instead of words. Head-to-head networked play is possible with xletters-duel. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlhtml
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program for converting Microsoft Excel Files .xls The xlhtml program will take an Excel 95, or 97 file as input and convert it to highly optimized html. The output is via standard out so it can be re-directed to files or piped to filters or used as a gateway on the internet. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xli
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
view images under X11 Can view the following image types under X11: FBM Image, Sun Rasterfile, CMU WM Raster, Portable Bit Map (PBM, PGM, PPM), Portable Network Graphics (PNG), Faces Project, GIF Image, JFIF style jpeg Image, Utah RLE Image, Windows, OS/2 RLE Image, Photograph on CD Image, X Window Dump, Targa Image, McIDAS areafile, G3 FAX Image, PC Paintbrush Image, GEM Bit Image, MacPaint Image, X Pixmap, X Bitmap. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlib6
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
shared libraries required by libc5 X clients The X libraries are the interface between X client programs and the hardware-oriented X servers, and consist of routines to read input from the keyboard and pointer, draw on the screen, etc., in an abstract manner that is independent of the particular characteristics of the hardware.  The X libraries communicate with X servers by means of the X protocol.  Xlib itself provides the low-level functionality; Xt, the X Toolkit Intrinsics, is often used as a foundation for widget libraries such as Lesstif or Athena.  Xaw, the Athena widget set, provides a rudimentary set of graphical user-interface elements (buttons, scrollbars, text boxes, etc.).  Several more libraries are provided to implement the functions of various X extensions. X clients compiled against libc5 require that the X libraries be compiled against libc5 as well.  xlib6 provides such backward compatibility. To avoid redundancy, this package depends on the current version of the X library packages for various non-binary files used by the X libraries (bitmaps, locale data, etc.). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlibmesa3
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XFree86 version of Mesa 3D graphics library Mesa is a 3D graphics library which presents an API intended to be compatible with OpenGL.  XFree86 maintains its own version of the Mesa library (which is regularly resynchronized with the official one) to permit development of the XFree86 X server&apos;s Direct Rendering Infrastructure (DRI), which makes the 3D acceleration features of many modern video cards available to X client programmers. Chipset-specific DRI modules, if available for your machine architecture, are provided in this package.  (Unlike the modules in the xserver-xfree86 package, the DRI modules are loaded by the Mesa library, not by the X server itself.) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlibosmesa3
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Mesa/XFree86 off-screen rendering library Mesa is a 3D graphics library which presents an API intended to be compatible with OpenGL.  XFree86 maintains its own version of the Mesa library (which is regularly resynchronized with the official one) to permit development of the XFree86 X server&apos;s Direct Rendering Infrastructure (DRI), which makes the 3D acceleration features of many modern video cards available to X client programmers. The off-screen rendering library (OSMesa) is an extension to Mesa, not an implementation of any OpenGL standard; therefore, it is packaged separately, so that any OpenGL-conformant library may be installed on a Debian system, and OpenGL-based programs may depend on any of them.  The OSMesa library, however, specifically depends on the Mesa library. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlibosmesa3-dbg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Mesa/XFree86 off-screen rendering library (unstripped) This package is useful to provide a backtrace with symbol names in a debugger; this facilitates interpretation of core dumps, and aids in finding logic errors in programs using this library (or the library itself).  The library is installed in /usr/lib/debug and can be used by placing that directory in the LD_LIBRARY_PATH environment variable when the code to be debugged is executed. Non-programmers will likely have little use for this package.  See the xlibosmesa3 package for further information. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlibs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System client libraries The X libraries are an interface between X client programs and the hardware-oriented X servers, and consist of routines to read input from the keyboard and pointer, draw on the screen, etc., in an abstract manner that is independent of the particular characteristics of the hardware.  The X libraries, and the programs that use them, communicate with X servers by means of the X protocol. libX11 (a.k.a. Xlib) provides the low-level functionality, dealing mostly with the wire protocol and in terms of basic operations such as opening and closing the X protocol connection, creating graphics contexts, drawing graphics primitives such as lines, arcs, and glyphs, handling events, and so forth. libXpm, the X pixmap library, is a set of routines used to store and retrieve X pixmaps (a data structure comprising a rectangular array of pixels) from files; the xpm file format is an extension of the monochrome bitmap file format in the X11 specification.  (Traditionally, libXpm was maintained and distributed separately from the X Window System, but XFree86 has absorbed this library). libXt, the X Toolkit Intrinsics, is an abstract widget library upon which graphical widget libraries (such as Athena and LessTif) may be developed; the Intrinsics provide a number of useful interfaces to X conventions and protocols, in many cases reducing a long series of Xlib calls to just a couple of Xt calls. libXmu is a set of miscellaneous utility functions useful to client programmers. libXmuu is a very small set of miscellaneous utility functions extracted from Xmu, Xt, and Xaw, for clients that need the occasional useful function from these libraries but do not require the toolkit overhead.  To use libXmuu, simply include the headers for the other libraries in the client and link against Xmuu instead of Xmu, Xt, and Xaw.  Needless to say, if the client uses functions from Xmu, Xt, or Xaw that are not present in Xmuu, it will fail to link. The remainder of the libraries in this package implement the client side of various X protocol extensions:  - libICE, the Inter-Client Exchange extension;  - libPEX5, PEX, a 3D graphics extension now superseded by Mesa/OpenGL;  - libSM, the Session Management extension;  - libXIE, the X Image Extension;  - libXext, a collection of several commonly-used extensions;  - libXft, a FreeType-based font rendering extension;  - libXi, the X Input extension;  - libXp, the X Printing extension; and  - libXrender, an extension for digital image composition;  - libXtst, the X Testing extension. xlibs also contains the XKB keyboard parameter files, locale data, and a set of bitmap and pixmap image files commonly used by X clients. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlife
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
John Conway&apos;s Game of Life, for X11 This is an X11 implementation of &quot;Life&quot;, a classic cellular automaton. Many example cell arrangements are provided. You can also create and save your own. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XLINK
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML LINKing language (XML) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlispstat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a lisp-based environment for statistical computing xlispstat is an environment for statistical computing and interactive graphics.  It was developed by Luke Tierney &lt;luke@stat.umn.edu&gt; from David Betz&apos;s xlisp interpreter. The system is documented in Tierney&apos;s 1990 book, &quot;LISP-STAT: An Object-oriented Environment for Statistical Computing and Dynamic Graphics&quot; published by Wiley. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
system load average display for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xloadimage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphics file viewer under X11 Can view png, jpeg, gif, tiff, niff, sunraster, fbm, cmuraster, pbm, faces, rle, xwd, vff, mcidas, vicar, pcx, gem, macpaint, xpm and xbm files. Can view images, put them on the root window, or dump them. Does a variety of processing, including: clipping, dithering, depth reduction, zoom, brightening/darkening and merging. Includes xsetbg, xview and uufilter. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlockmore
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Lock X11 display until password is entered. xlock locks the X server till the user enters his/her password at the keyboard.  While xlock is running, all new server connections are refused. The mouse cursor is turned off.  The screen is blanked and a changing pattern is put on the screen. If a key or a mouse button is pressed then the user is prompted for the password of the user who started xlock. This version is built without additional OpenGL/MesaGL and XPM modes. The companion package xlockmore-gl contains them. This is the only difference between the two packages. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlockmore
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The xlockmore utility is an enhanced version of the standard xlockprogram, which allows you to lock an X session so that other users can&apos;t access it. Xlockmore runs a provided screensaver until you type in your password. Install the xlockmore package if you need a locking program to secure X sessions. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlockmore-gl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Lock X11 display until password is entered -- GL version xlock locks the X server till the user enters his/her password at the keyboard.  While xlock is running, all new server connections are refused. The mouse cursor is turned off.  The screen is blanked and a changing pattern is put on the screen. If a key or a mouse button is pressed then the user is prompted for the password of the user who started xlock. This version is built with additional OpenGL/MesaGL and XPM modes. The companion package xlockmore does not contain them. This is the only difference between the two packages. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GTK+ Logging program for Shortwave Hamradio Operators xlog is a logging program for amateur radio operators. xlog focuses on hams who operate shortwave on a daily basis. Logs are stored into a text file. QSO&apos;s are presented in a list. Items in the list can be added, deleted or updated. For each contact, dxcc information is displayed and bearings and distance is calculated, both short and long path. When hamlib is enabled through the menu, you can retrieve frequency, mode and signal-strength from you rig over the serial port. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlogmaster
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program to monitor logfiles Xlogmaster can monitor an almost infinite number of logfiles and all devices that can be read via &quot;cat&quot; like the /proc ones. On a regular expression base, you can hide, raise or lower lines in the logfile and set triggers, which can launch scripts or pop-up a window xlogmaster homepage is at http://www.gnu.org/software/xlogmaster/xlogmaster.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlogo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System logo From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlsatoms
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
list interned atoms defined on server From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlsclients
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
list client applications running on a display From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xlsfonts
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
server font list displayer for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xm-tool
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tool to generate docs for PFE This tool is used to generate the HTML documenation for the portable forth environment (PFE) from source.  It is not needed by users of PFE. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmabacus
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simulation of the ancient oriental calculator This is the motif version by David Bagley.  It was compiled with lesstif. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmaddressbook
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-based address book XmAddressbook is a X-based Address Book program. It can convert the old rolo program&apos;s rolodex.dat files into its own format. NOTE: This used to be called XmRolodex. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmag
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
magnify parts of the screen From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmahjongg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
tile-based solitaire game Xmahjongg is a simple solitaire game. The object is to remove all 144 Mah Jongg tiles from the playing area by matching them two at a time. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmailbox
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A version of xbiff with animation and sound effects. It displays an icon, which changes when mail comes in. Normally this involves checking the size of a file, but it can be set to run an arbitrary command to do it, so you can check mail stored on another system. By default it is set to do a colour, shaped, but non-animated, icon: this is apparently possible with xbiff if you tweak the resources. By tweaking the resources of xmailbox you can get animated icons. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmake
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Powerful project making make program XMAKE is similar to other make&apos;s out there, but is specifically designed to allow you to easily construct multiple complex dependencies without getting screwed by default rulesets. XMake contains a number of features specifically designed to trivialize the construction of compilation rules. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmakemol
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program for visualizing atomic and molecular systems XMakemol is a mouse-based program, written using the LessTif widget set, for viewing and manipulating atomic and other chemical systems.  It reads XYZ input and renders atoms, bonds and hydrogen bonds. Features include:  - Animating multiple frame files  - Interactive measurement of bond lengths, bond angles and torsion angles  - Control over atom/bond sizes  - Exporting to Xpm, Encapsulated PostScript and XYZ formats  - Toggling the visibility of groups of atoms  - Editing the positions of subsets of atoms From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmakemol-gl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program for visualizing atomic and molecular systems XMakemol is a mouse-based program, written using the LessTif widget set, for viewing and manipulating atomic and other chemical systems.  It reads XYZ input and renders atoms, bonds and hydrogen bonds. Features include:  - Animating multiple frame files  - Interactive measurement of bond lengths, bond angles and torsion angles  - Control over atom/bond sizes  - Exporting to Xpm, Encapsulated PostScript and XYZ formats  - Toggling the visibility of groups of atoms  - Editing the positions of subsets of atoms This is the OpenGL-enabled XMakemol package. The images are rendered using true 3D graphics primitives, and can be exported using the Xpm format; red/blue stereo images can also be produced. The OpenGL package provides more display options, along with better support for displaying vectors. Ellipses can also be rendered. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xman
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Manual page display program for the X Window System From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMAPI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Messaging Application Program Interface (API) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xmark
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
summarize x11perf results From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmbase-grok
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical Resource Organizer Kit xmbase-grok, formerly just called &quot;grok&quot;, is a simple database manager and UI builder that can -   *  keep phone and address lists (like a rolodex)   *  store phone call logs   *  keep todo lists   *  manage any other database after simple GUI-driven customization   *  customized data export, HTML export built in More precisely, grok is a program for displaying and editing strings arranged in a grid of rows and columns. Each row is presented as a &quot;card&quot; consisting of multiple columns, or &quot;fields&quot;, that allow data entry. The presentation of the data is programmable; a user interface builder that allows the user to arrange fields on a card graphically is part of grok. Grok also supports a simple language that allows sophisticated queries and data retrieval. Grok comes with the above examples and a few others as pre-built applications. Grok is not a general-purpose database program. It was designed for small applications typical for desktop accessories. If you attempt to run your major airline reservation system or your space shuttle project with it, you are guaranteed to be disappointed. By Thomas Driemeyer &lt;thomas@bitrot.in-berlin.de&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmbdfed
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 font editor XmBDFEditor is a Motif-based BDF font editor with the following features:  o  Multiple fonts can be loaded from the command line.  o  Multiple fonts can be open at the same time.  o  Cutting and pasting glyphs between fonts.  o  Multiple glyph bitmap editors can be open at the same time.  o  Cutting and pasting between glyph bitmap editors.  o  Automatic correction of certain metrics when a font is loaded.  o  Generation of XLFD font names for fonts without XLFD names.  o  Update an XLFD font name from the font properties.  o  Update the font properties from an XLFD font name.  o  Font property editor.  o  Font comment editor.  o  Supports unencoded glyphs (ENCODING of -1).  o  Display of glyph encodings in octal, decimal, or hex.  o  Builtin on-line help.  o  Imports PK/GF fonts.  o  Imports Linux console fonts (PSF, CP, and FNT).  o  Imports Sun console fonts (vfont format).  o  Imports fonts from the X server.  o  Imports Windows FON/FNT fonts.  o  Imports TrueType fonts and collections. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmcd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 based CD player Xmcd uses the Motif toolkit (using the free Lesstif libraries) to achieve a pleasing appearance, such that it actually looks and feels like a real CD player for all basic functions, yet takes advantage of the GUI and window system to make programming and CD database functions easy. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmcpustate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Displays CPU/Swap/Memory/Network load A simple program written with Motif to monitor your system activity. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmem
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Visual indicator of amount of memory/swap usage The xmem program, which gives a visual representation of memory usage. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmessage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display a message or query in a window (X-based /bin/echo) From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmeter
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
histogram of data returned by rstat(3) xmeter displays the histograms in one window, and can be told to monitor multiple hosts or multiple statistics on one host. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensible Music Format (MMA, MIDI) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmgr
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An XY plotting tool Xmgr is a point-and-click tool that allows the user to draw X-Y plots. Xmgr has been renamed to Grace. Unless you have old Xmgr graphs that you can&apos;t convert to the new Grace format, you should use Grace instead of Xmgr. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmh
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X interface to the MH mail system xmh provides a graphical user interface to the MH (Message Handler) mail system.  xmh is a very old X client and is not exactly a &quot;living&quot; piece of software.  MH users will probably prefer the exmh package, which serves the same function and continues to be actively developed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmhtml1
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Motif widget for display HTML 3.2 XmHTML is a high performance Motif Widget capable of displaying HTML 3.2 confirming text.  Graphics support, lesstif compatibility and extensive documentation are amongst its many features. This package provides the runtime shared library. The xmhtml-dev package provides the header files, and the static library. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Memory Interconnect (DEC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML Metadata Interchange [format] From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmille
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The classic game of Mille Bourne A card game against the computer in which each player tries to reach 1000 miles.  Each player tries to avoid accidents, flat tires, running out of gas, and break downs while trying to cause these same maladies in the opponent. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xminicom
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
See minicom. From Binh.
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmkmf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
create a Makefile from an Imakefile From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensible Markup Language (WWW, XML) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XML
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensible Markup Language (XML): a powerful new web markup language (ISO approval in February 1999). It is a powerful way of separating web content and style. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XML (Extended Markup Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML is an HTML-like formatting language. Misconception: The recommended advice when developing Internet protocols has been be conservative in what you send and liberal in what you receive. While in the early days this philosophy fostered interoperability, any economist could tell you the long term effect of this. It leads to a large number of slightly incompatible implementations of protocols, all of which mostly work, but none of which interopate well. For example, FTP is one of the oldest Internet protocols, and there are essentially no fully complient clients or servers, and building a fully interopable client/server is extremely difficult, requiring knowledge of all the quirks of all the popular implementations. Therefore, XML has chosen the opposite approach: compliant implementations are supposed to reject all input that isn&apos;t &quot;well-formed&quot;, even when the intent is clear. This not only avoids interoperability errors in the long run, it also dramatically improves security by guaranteeing that there is only one way to interpret things. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XML (eXtensible Markup Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A powerful new markup language for designing Web pages; an alternative to the older HTML, allowing programmers to define their own markup tags, or formatting commands. From I-gloss
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XML (eXtensible Markup Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A widely used system for defining data formats. XML provides a very rich system to define complex documents and data structures such as invoices, molecular data, news feeds, glossaries, inventory descriptions, real estate properties, etc. As long as a programmer has the XML definition for a collection of data (often called a &quot;schema&quot;) then they can create a program to reliably process any data formatted according to those rules. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xml-common
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The xml-common package contains a collection of entities and DTDsthat are useful for processing XML, but that do not need to be included in multiple packages. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xml-resume-library
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A set of tools for writing a resume in XML The XML Resume Library is an XML and XSL based system for marking up, adding metadata to, and formatting resumes and curricula vitae. It consists of these components:    * An XML Document Type Definition (DTD) for describing resumes.    * Three XSL stylesheets to transform an XML resume into:          * Web-ready HTML,          * Print-ready PDF, or          * Plain, unformatted text From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xml-rpc-api2cpp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Generate C++ wrapper classes for XML-RPC servers. A utility for generating C++ wrapper classes based on an XML-RPC API, obtained by interrogating an XML-RPC server. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xml-rpc-api2txt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dump an XML-RPC API as a text file A utility for printing out an XML-RPC API as a text file.  The API is obtained by interrogating an XML-RPC server. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xml2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Convert between XML, HTML, CSV and a line-oriented format xml2 tools are used to convert XML, HTML and CSV to and from a line-oriented format more amenable to processing by classic Unix pipeline processing tools, like grep, sed, awk, cut, shell scripts, and so forth. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmlcatalog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Command line tool to parse and manipulate XML or SGML catalog files. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmllint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
command line XML tool From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmlrpc4r
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XML-RPC support for Ruby XML-RPC provides remote procedure calls over HTTP with XML. It is like SOAP but much easier. For more information see the XML-RPC homepage &lt;URL:http:// www.xmlrpc.com/&gt;. This package provides XML-RPC support for Ruby. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmltex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
TeX package for processing XML files XMLTeX is a non-validating, namespace-aware XML parser written in TeX.  It allows TeX to directly process XML files. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmlto
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This is a package for converting XML files to various formats using XSL stylesheets. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Memory Manager (DOS, LIM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmms
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Versatile X audio player that looks like Winamp XMMS (formerly known as X11Amp) is an X/GTK+ based audio player for various audio formats. It&apos;s able to read and play:  * Audio MPEG layer 1, 2, and 3 (with mpg123 plug-in),  * WAV, RAW, AU (with internal wav plug-in and MikMod plug-in),  * MOD, XM, S3M, and other module formats (with MikMod plug-in),  * CD Audio (with CDAudio plug-in), with CDDB support,  * .cin files, id Software,  * Ogg Vorbis files. It has eSound, OSS, and disk writer support for outputting sound. It looks almost the same as famous Winamp, and includes those neat features like general purpose, visualization and effect plug-ins, several of which come bundled, then spectrum analyzer, oscilloscope, skins support, and of course, a playlist window. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmms
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XMMS is a sound player written from scratch. Since it uses the WinAmp GUI, it can use WinAmp skins, and play mp3s, mods, s3ms, and other formats. It now has support for input, output, and general plugins, and has also been GPLd. This package also provides an effect plugin based on Sox and a shell for xmms in order to command the running xmms from any script/commandline. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMODEM
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An asynchronous file-transfer protocol for personal computers that makes the error-free transmission of files through the telephone system easier. Developed by Ward Christianson for 8-bit computers running Control Program for Microprocessors (CP/M) and placed in the public domain, the XMODEM protocol included   in most personal computer communications programs is included and commonly is used to download files from bulletin boards systems (BBSs). From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmodmap
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
utility for modifying keymaps and pointer button mappings in X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An interactive X protocol monitor Xmon interactively monitors the byte-stream connections between an X server and a number of X clients.  Xmon recognises all requests, events, errors and replies sent between the clients and the server which are part of the core X protocol. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmorph
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
digital image warper (x11) Xmorph loads, saves, warps, and dissolves images, and loads, saves, creates, and manipulates control meshes which determine the warping.  The technique was invented and first used by Industrial Light and Magic, and is commonly called &quot;morphing&quot;. Xmorph uses the Targa image format exclusively.  Other software is needed to convert to other image formats or to movies.  (Due to a bug, Xmorph&apos;s images are unreadable by John Bradley&apos;s XV.) xmorph is a GUI for libmorph, using the X Toolkit; the package also contains a text-only program called morph. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmotd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a message of the day browser for X Xmotd is a message-of-the-day browser for X11 (with additional sysvnews-like support for dumb terminals).  It displays a customizable message box which displays each message-of-the-day until the user has read them all, and then creates a stamp-file. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmountains
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
fractal landscape generator for X Generates random fractal mountains and displays them in a window (even in the X root window). While the program is running the fractal is continuously extended on the right and the image is scrolled from right to left to expose the newly generated area. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmove
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A Pseudoserver for moving programs between displays. xmove lets you change which display an X Window System program renders to - this could be a different monitor or even a different machine. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmovie
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A nice player for uncompressed Quicktime, MPEG streams and more. This is xmovie, a great movie viewer and audio player with support for several formats, including MPEG-1, MPEG-2 streams, MP2/3 audio, AIFF, Quicktime, DVD&apos;s and more. It plays the following Quicktime video types: Motion JPEG A Uncompressed RGB Component video Progressive JPEG PNG YUV 4:2:0 YUV 4:2:2 It also has support for HDTV program and ATSC transport streams. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A module player supporting AWE32, GUS, and software-mixing xmp is a module player for Linux/FreeBSD/Solaris. Initially designed as a XM player, today it recognizes the following module formats:    xm (Fast Tracker II), mod (Noise/Fast/Protracker), s3m (Scream    Tracker 3), stm (Scream Tracker 2), mtm (Multitracker), ptm (Poly    Tracker), okt (Oktalyzer), far (Farandole Composer), wow (Mod&apos;s    Grave), amd (Amusic Adlib Tracker), rad (Reality Adlib Tracker),    669 (Composer 669), alm (Aley&apos;s modules), mod (Soundtracker 15    instruments) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X/open Management Protocol (X/Open, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmpi
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical user interface for MPI program development. MPI is a standard for writing parallel processing programs using a well defined Message Passing Interface. XMPI can acquire and display extensive detail on an application&apos;s MPI communication, including the following:  o process synchronization status: running, system or blocked  o message queue contents  o source, destination, root ranks  o MPI function name  o communicator  o data type  o message count  o tag The above information is acquired from on-demand snapshots of application status using debugging hooks in the MPI implementation or from a trace log of communication activity. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xmpuzzles
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Collection of puzzles for X with LessTif The following puzzles are included (compiled with LessTif):  - Rotational 3D Puzzles: xrubik, xpyraminx, xoct, xskewb, xdino, xmball  - Sliding Block Puzzles: xcubes, xtriangles, xhexagons, xpanex  - Combination: xmlink xmpuzzles conflicts with xpuzzles because they both try to install the same files in app-defaults.  It can be safely used with --force-overwrite when installing over/with xpuzzles. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Memory Specification (DOS, LIM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XMS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Multiprocessor operating System (OS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XN
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXecution Node From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xnamu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xnc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Northern Captain nc/mc-like filemanager for X Two panels show highlighted directory listings and give an easy and simple way for manipulating files on disks, inside various archives or ftp with a Virtual File System.  * Builtin Rxvt terminal to run programs  * Bookmarks for storing HotDirectories and quickly jumping to them  * &quot;Drag and drop&quot; protocol for file operations  * MultiWindow Viewing and Editing system with various image formats  * User menus and file associations  * Different panel layouts, icons  * Hotkeys for all operations  * Setup tool for customizing colors, your own keys, fonts and so on From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xnecview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
NEC structure and gain pattern viewer xnecview allows a representation of a NEC (Numerical Electromagnetics Code) structure, such as an antenna which is to be modelled to be displayed on the screen.  After an NEC run the gain pattern in various formats can also be superimposed.  This can be rotated and translated for viewing from different angles.  Plots of SWR and gain as a function of frequency can also be produced.  In addition to on screen display, Postscript or PNG output can also be produced. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xnest
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a nested X server From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xnest
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
nested X server xnest an X server that is itself an X client.  This allows you to run a server within a server; this is occasionally useful for testing new window managers and other X clients. Xnest relies upon its parent X server for font services. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xnetload
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An Xload for network interfaces packet rates/totals. Xnetload displays a graph and/or count of incoming/outgoing packets on any network interface in /proc/net/dev. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XNS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xerox Network Services / Systems / Standard (Xerox, XNS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XNSCP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[PPP] XNS IDP Control Protocol (RFC 1764, Xerox, XNS, PPP, XNS, IDP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XNSIDP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xerox Network Services - Internet Datagram Protocol (Xerox, Internet, XNS), &quot;XNS-IDP&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XNSITP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xerox Network Services/Internet ??? Protocol (Xerox, XNS), &quot;XNS/ITP&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xodo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an odometer tracking the distance travelled by your mouse xodometer tracks the total distance your cursor and pointing device (typically a mouse) travel.  It also maintains &quot;trip&quot; distance since the application started or since you clicked on a trip reset button. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XOFF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/X-of/ n. Syn. control-S.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XOFF
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXchange OFF (MODEM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xoids
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Asteroids game with powerups and color graphics. A clone of the classic arcade game, Asteroids. Pilot a spaceship and destroy asteroids by shooting them into smaller and smaller pieces while trying to avoid being smashed or shot by UFOs.  Features power ups for your ship and two player modes - either deathmatch or co-operative where the ships are tied together with elastic! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XON
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/X-on/ n. Syn. control-Q.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XON
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXchange ON (MODEM) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
start an X program on a remote machine From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xonix
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Carve up the screen whilst dodging monsters A clone of the Xonix game for DOS: Start with a rectangle, and munch corners off until you get below the winning area: then proceed to the next level. But beware of the roaming aliens! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xonix-jahu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xonix clone for X11 A clone of the Xonix arcade game: Start with a rectangle, and munch corners off until you get below the winning area: then proceed to the next level. but beware of the roaming enemy balls! This version of Xonix lacks the &quot;eater&quot; creature that is in some versions of the game. It features a 3D look and the ability to load .gif files to be the background of the playing field. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xor
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/X&apos;or/, /kzor/ conj. Exclusive or. `A xor B&apos; means `A or B, but not both&apos;. &quot;I want to get cherry pie xor a banana split.&quot; This derives from the technical use of the term as a function on truth-values that is true if exactly one of its two arguments is true.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xor (exclusive-or)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
In computer science, an XOR is a mathematical operation that combines two bits. The resulting value is TRUE if either of the two bits is TRUE, but false if both are equal. In cryptography, one generally talks about doing an XOR combining two strings of bits: plaintext  11100101 01110101key         00001111 00001111            ------------------ciphertext 11101010 01111010XOR has the interesting property that XORing by the same pattern twice results in the original pattern: ciphertext 11101010 01111010key         00001111 00001111            ------------------plaintext  11100101 01110101Therefore, you can think of XOR as an extremely weak encryption algorithm. The above example shows using XOR as a way of encrypting the original data with the 8-bit key of &quot;00001111&quot;. Many products use this technique to obfuscate data. However, it is extremely easy to recover the original key via a known plaintext attack, as show below: ciphertext 11101010 01111010plaintext  11100101 01110101           ------------------key         00001111 00001111Key point: XOR is a common mathematical operation used in cryptographic algorithms. In fact, the only 100% secure form of encryption is XORing against a one-time pad. Also, any hash algorithm can be converted into an encryption algorithm though a clever use of XOR. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xorca
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xosd-bin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X On-Screen Display library - binary files This package contains binary files shipped with the X OSD library: osd_cat - a &apos;cat&apos; like program which will display its output in an           OSD-like window More info can be found on http://www.ignavus.net/software.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xosview
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X based system monitor Xosview is a monitor which displays the status of several system based parameters.  These include  CPU  usage,  load average,  memory  usage,  swap space usage, network usage, interrupts, and serial port status.  Appearance is fully configurable via command line or X resources. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XOT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X.25 Over TCP (Cisco, X.25, TCP, RFC 1613) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xotcl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An object oriented extension for Tcl XOTcl (Extended Object Tcl) is an object-oriented extension which allows read/write introspection of all aspects of the object system, including class/superclass/object relationships. It allows for the use of meta-classes, multiple inheritance  as well as other advanced features:  - Dynamic Object Aggregations.  - Assertions.  - Meta-data, to enhance self-documentation of objects and classes.  - Per-object mixins, gives objects access to several dynamically defined    supplemental classes.  - Per-class mixins.  - Filters as a means of abstractions over method invocations to implement    large program structures, like design patterns.  - Dynamic Component Loading XOTcl integrates the Tcl package loading with    architectural support for integration with object-oriented constructs. For more information: http://www.xotcl.org/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtreme Programming From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpaint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
reasonably versatile X-based image editing tool In addition to the traditional X bitmap and X pixmap image file formats, xpaint also supports JPEGs and PNGs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpaint
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simple Paint program From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpaste
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program to display the contents of the primary paste buffer. Xpaste will create a window containing the current contents of the primary selection buffer. The size of this window is dictated by the length of the longest line in the selection, the number of lines in the selection, and the size of the current font. Variable-width fonts are supported. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpat2
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Generic patience game for X11 xpat2 is a generic patience game which can be used with different rule sets. It does understand the rules of the well-known Spider game, as well as Klondike and others. This program may have difficulties to start if you have an 8-bit or monochrome display. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Performance Characterization [group] (GPC, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpcd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
PhotoCD tool collection: Base This is a PhotoCD tool collection. This packages core application is a command line tool which can read so-called PhotoCD (*.pcd) images and convert them to PPM or JPEG (pcdtoppm). Also included is a PhotoCD viewing frontend for X (xpcd). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpdf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Portable Document Format (PDF) suite xpdf is a suite of tools for Portable Document Format (PDF) files. (These are sometimes called &apos;Acrobat&apos; files after the name of Adobe&apos;s PDF software.) The tools include xpdf, a PDF viewer (in the package xpdf-reader), and PDF converters (including to/from PostScript) (in the package xpdf-utils). This package is intended for compatibility with previous versions of this package only. You can safely remove it from your system. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpdq
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical user interface for the pdq printing system This application allows users and administrators to configure printing and view print jobs for the pdq printing system. Home Page: http://pdq.sourceforge.net/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpenguin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpenguins
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
little penguins walk on your windows Ever wanted cute little penguins walking along the tops of your windows? Ever wanted to send an army of cute little penguins to invade the screen of someone else on your network? Probably not, but why not try this program out anyway, it&apos;s cool! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPFE (Cross Platform Front End)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A suite of technologies used to create applications that will work and look the same on different computer operating systems. A widely used XPFE application is the Netscape web browser in version 7 and later. The primary technologies used in creating XPFE applications are Javascript, Cascading Style Sheets, and XUL. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPG
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X/open Portability Guide (X/Open, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPGR3
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X/open Portability Guide Release 3 (X/Open, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xphoon
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
sets the root window to a picture of the moon xphoon sets the X root window to a picture of the moon in its current phase, including the partial lighting of the dark side by reflected earthlight. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpilot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Multi-player tactical game for X XPilot is a multi-player tactical manoeuvring game for X.  Each player controls their own fighter equipped with a variety of weapons and power-ups.  Players compete as teams or as individuals;  the object of the game is to score points by blasting the opposition, stealing their treasure or by racing round a circuit. WARNING: This game is very addictive. This package has been split into xpilot-client-common, xpilot-client-nosound, xpilot-client-nas, xpilot-client-rplay and xpilot-server.  There is an  additional package (xpilot-extra) containing various free maps and sounds as well as a useful utility program to interrogate the metaserver. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xplanet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
render an image of a planet into an X window From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xplanet
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
render images of the earth xplanet is similar to xearth, where an image of the earth is rendered into the X root window.  Various projection systems are available for display. The user can also popup a window with a globe that can be rotated interactively. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xplanetbg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
render an image of a planet into an X window From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpm2wico
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
an xpm to windows .ico converter I have written this program primarily to help free software programmers like me to not depend on evil proprietary programs to write Windows icons. It currently supports icons with 256 colors or more and well as grayscale images. Later I will probably add support for multiple-icons file output. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpm4.7
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the X PixMap library, compiled with libc5 XPM (X PixMap) is a format for storing and retrieving pixmaps to and from files.  This package includes a runtime library for including, storing, reading and writing the XPM format. This package contains the libc5 shared library, only for backwards compatibility with older programs. Building programs to depend on this version of the library is deprecated, and no longer supported; thus the corresponding xpm4-altdev package no longer exists. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpostit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
simple postit program on X with I18N support XPostIt allows you to create small notes to yourself in windows on the screen, and save them in disk files. I18N patch for X11R6 has been applied. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtrem Processor Platform (MPP) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Printing Panel Graphical substitute for the lp/lpr command.  With xpp, you can control every printing option known to the CUPS print system (the cupsys package). Best results are available with usage of the appropriate PPD file for your printer.  Each user can save their own customized printing preferences. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xprobe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Remote OS identification using ICMP packets Xprobe allows you to determine what operating system is running on a remote host. It sends several packets to a host and analyses the returned ICMP packets. The tool automates a logic of OS fingerprinting methods called &quot;X&quot;. Xprobe&apos;s functionality is comparable to the OS fingerprinting feature in nmap, but has several advantages over it:  - Faster: A maximum of 4 packets are sent to determine the remote OS.  - Can detect whether the host is up, so pinging is no longer necessary.  - Stealthier: Does not send any malformed datagrams.  - Can distinguish between many variants of Microsoft operating systems. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xprop
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
property displayer for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xprt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X print server xprt provides an X server with the print extension and special DDX (Device-Dependent X) implementation. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXPert System (AI, XPS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Parallel Server (DB, Informix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XPSB
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X - Protocol Stream Benchmark (XPC, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpuyopuyo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A puzzle game similar to tetris, played with colored blobs Xpuyopuyo is a Tetris-like puzzle game where you strive to match up four &quot;blobs&quot; of the same color.  Each match gives you points, and also dumps gray rocks on your opponent which  are irritating and troublesome to get rid of.  Multiple matches at one time score more points, and result in more  rocks  being  dumped on the opponent (much to their dismay).  First person to fill up their screen with puyopuyo blobs loses. Supports solitaire, human-vs-AI, human-vs-human, and AI-vs-AI modes, and network play. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpuzzles
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Collection of puzzles for X The following puzzles are included:  - Rotational 3D Puzzles: xrubik, xpyraminx, xoct, xskewb, xdino, xmball  - Sliding Block Puzzles: xcubes, xtriangles, xhexagons, xpanex  - Combination: xmlink xpuzzles conflicts with xmpuzzles because they both try to install the same files in app-defaults.  It can be safely used with --force-overwrite when installing over/with xmpuzzles. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpvm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
graphical console and monitor for PVM XPVM is a graphical console and monitor for PVM.  It provides a graphical interface to the PVM console commands and information, along with several animated views to monitor the execution of PVM programs.  These views provide information about the interactions among tasks in a parallel PVM program, to assist in debugging and performance tuning. For specifics on the various features of XPVM, and how to operate them, please refer to the appropriate on-line pop-up help information. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xpw
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
the Pathetic Writer word-processor The word-processor part of the Siag Office suite, which also contains SIAG and EGON.  Siag Office uses the Offix DND Drag-and-Drop protocol. A WWW browser is needed to read online doc.  A postscript viewer is used for document preview. It can read and write RTF and HTML files for inter-operation with other well-known word-processors. It should read also .doc files with help from catdoc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xqf
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-based Quake Server Browser XQF is a Gtk+ frontend for Qstat, a tool for querying first-person action game servers like Quake, Unreal Tournament, etc. It displays information about the servers and allows configuring and launching some of the games from it. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xracer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A free Wipeout clone for Unix and X. Xracer is a Wipeout clone, distributed under the GPL. It should be able to use any OpenGL 1.1 compliant library. A 3D accelerator card is required. This is the game data and binary. If you want to build new tracks or other game data, you may also want to install the xracer-tools package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xracer-tools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A free Wipeout clone for Unix and X. Xracer is a Wipeout clone, distributed under the GPL. It should be able to use any OpenGL 1.1 compliant library. A 3D accelerator card is required. These are a few tools to design your own game data. In order to play the game, you will need the xracer package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xrdb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X server resource database utility From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xref
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
/X&apos;ref/ v.,n. Hackish standard abbreviation for `cross-reference&apos;.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xrefresh
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
refresh all or part of an X screen From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xringd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Extended Ring Daemon - Monitor phone rings and take action. xringd will monitor a serial line for RING signals and activate various commands when specific &quot;ring-delay sequences&quot; are detected. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XRIP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended ??? Routing Information Protocol (Novell, Netware) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xrn
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-based NNTP news reader. XRN is a Usenet News reader for the X window system. It requires an NNTP server to talk to (i.e., it cannot read news from local disk files), and the NNTP server must support the XHDR command (most servers nowadays do; if yours doesn&apos;t, XRN will complain when you try to run it). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xroach
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
infests X with disgusting cockroaches Xroach displays disgusting cockroaches on your root window. These creepy crawlies scamper around until they find a window to hide under. Whenever you move or iconify a window, the exposed orthoptera again scamper for cover. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xrootconsole
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fancy X console display Xrootconsole redirects its input to a transparent (and optionally shaded) window on the root window. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XRT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensions for Real-Time market data (API, MS, Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xruessel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xruskb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An X localized keyboard switch and autolock. Xrus is a utility for switching the keyboard mode between different layouts.  While it is intended for switching between Latin and Russian keyboards (RUS/LAT), xrus can be configured to use any two layouts provided that the proper modmaps have been loaded. Xrus monitors all keyboard and mouse events, and when a particular hot key combination is pressed, it swaps 1,2 and 3,4 columns of the keyboard map.  When a a specified time period without keyboard and mouse events passes, it starts a locking program. This package also contains several Cyrillic keyboard mapping tables. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsabre
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fighter plane simulator. SABRE is an on-going game development for the Linux Operating System, worked on as a labor of love by flight-simulation enthusiasts. For now, SABRE is focusing on the older jets and piston-engined fighters of the Korean War / Cold War era.  Featured are F-86 SabreJet, MiG-15, F-84 ThunderJet, F-51 Mustang, and Yak-9.  All of the planes in the game can be flown by the player as well as the computer pilots. This package contains the X binary. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsane
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a gtk based X11 frontend for SANE (Scanner Access Now Easy) SANE stands for &quot;Scanner Access Now Easy&quot; and is an application programming interface (API) that provides standardized access to any raster image scanner hardware (flatbed scanner, hand-held scanner, video- and still-cameras, frame-grabbers, etc.). The SANE standard is free and its discussion and development is open to everybody. The current source code is written for UNIX (including Linux) and is available under the GNU public license (commercial application and backends are welcome, too, however). xsane can be run as a stand-alone program or through the GIMP image manipulation program.  In stand-alone mode, xsane can save an image to a file in a variety of image formats, or serve as a frontend to a fax program, or send an image to a printer. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsane
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XSane is an X based interface for the SANE (Scanner Access Now Easy)library, which provides access to scanners, digital cameras, and other capture devices.  XSane is written in GTK+ and provides control for performing the scan and then manipulating the captured image. You may install xsane-gimp if you want the GIMP plug-in. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsane-gimp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This package provides the regular XSane frontend for the SANE scanner interface, but it works as a GIMP plug-in.  You must have GIMP installed to use this package. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscavenger
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A lode-runner-like platform game for X XScavenger is a platform game for the X Window System. From the README: Scavenger is like Lode Runner. You&apos;ve got to run around gathering objects while avoiding enemies. You can dig down through some of the blocks to get at buried objects. After you&apos;ve collected everything, ladders may appear. To finish the level you&apos;ve got to exit through the top of the screen. If an enemy falls into a dug brick, he is stunned for a while. If the brick fills in with him in it, he is killed, and he will reappear at the top of the screen. This version has a level editor for designing your own levels, and a graphics editor for drawing your own artwork. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscorch
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Clone of Scorched Earth Xscorch is a clone of the classic DOS game, &quot;Scorched Earth&quot;. The basic goal is to annihilate enemy tanks using overpowered guns :).  Basically, you buy weapons, you target the enemy by adjusting the angle of your turret and firing power, and you hope to destroy their tank before they destroy yours. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Automatic screensaver for X The purpose of xscreensaver is to display pretty pictures on your screen when it is not in use, in keeping with the philosophy that unattended monitors should always be doing something interesting, just like they do in the movies. The benefit that this program has over the combination of the xlock and xautolock programs is the ease with which new graphics hacks can be installed: you don&apos;t need to recompile this program to add a new display mode, you just change some resource settings.  Any program which can be invoked in such a way that it draws on the root window of the screen can now be used as a screensaver without modification.  The programs that are being run as screensavers don&apos;t need to have any special knowledge about what it means to be a screensaver. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
graphics hack and screen locker, launched when the user is idle From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The xscreensaver package contains a variety of screensavers for your mind-numbing, ambition-eroding, time-wasting, hypnotized viewing pleasure.Install the xscreensaver package if you need screensavers for use with the X Window System. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-command
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
control a running xscreensaver process From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-demo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
interactively control the background xscreensaver daemon From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-getimage
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
put some randomly-selected image on the root window From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-getimage-file
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
put a randomly-selected image on the root window From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-getimage-video
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
put a video frame on the root window From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-gl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GL(Mesa) screenhacks for xscreensaver These are some extra hacks for xscreensaver that use the Mesa OpenGL-compatible library. They are included as an extra package so the base package doesn&apos;t require Mesa. In addition, these hacks function nicely as GL demos for people who want to try out hardware accelerated 3D with XFree86 4.x From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-gnome
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GNOME binaries for xscreensaver This package contains the GNOME enabled xscreensaver-demo and related files. To be useful, it requires the xscreensaver package to be installed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xscreensaver-nognome
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Gtk only binaries for xscreensaver This package contains the Gtk only xscreensaver-demo for people who do not want to install the whole of GNOME to use xscreensaver. To be useful, it requires the xscreensaver package to be installed. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
More than just cat for the X selection. XSel is a command-line program for getting and setting the contents of the X selection. Normally this is only accessible by manually highlighting information and pasting it with the middle mouse button. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xset
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
user preference utility for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsetmode
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
set the mode for an X Input device From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsetpointer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
set an X Input device as the main pointer From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsetroot
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
root window parameter setting utility for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xshipwars
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Dynamic space-oriented gaming system XShipWars is a highly customizable and dynamic space-oriented gaming system designed for play on the net. You create your own universes and build your own vessels with a huge array of customizable settings. Graphics/video/sound themes for XShipWars are created by many talented professional artists. More information can be found at the XShipWars web site http://wolfpack.twu.net/ShipWars/XShipWars/ . From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsiag
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a spreadsheet with an X11 user-interface The spreadsheet part of the Siag Office suite, which also contains EGON and PW.  Siag Office uses the Offix DND Drag-and-Drop protocol. Siag is a spreadsheet based on X and scheme.  Being based on scheme allows any user to expand the functionality of siag in just about any way imaginable. It can read and write 1-2-3 files for inter-operation with other well-know spreadsheet programs. You can enter expressions in several languages: C, guile, SIOD, Tcl. A WWW browser is needed to read online doc.  A postscript viewer is used for document preview. This one uses an X11 user interface based on the Athena toolkit.  You will find a text version in the `tsiag&apos; package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsidplay
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Music player for tunes from C64 and Amiga This is a very sophisticated music player for C64 and Amiga tunes, aka SID tunes. It&apos;s very simple now to change emulation parameters and control tunes and subtunes. Furthermore, the player features a playlist and support for the HVSC song lengths database file. The `README&apos; contains instructions where to download and how to install this file. There is a somewhat `hidden&apos; expert mode, which enables the built-in oscilloscope. Please see `README.Debian&apos; and `README&apos; for more information (and possible problems). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsitecopy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A program for managing a WWW site via FTP, DAV or HTTP(GNOME version) sitecopy is for copying locally stored websites to remote ftp servers. With a single command, the program will synchronize a set of local files to a remote server by performing uploads and remote deletes as required. The aim is to remove the hassle of uploading and deleting individual files using an FTP client.  sitecopy will also optionally try to spot files you move locally, and move them remotely. sitecopy is designed to not care about what is actually on the remote server - it simply keeps a record of what it THINKS is in on the remote server, and works from that. This version is the GNOME frontend to sitecopy. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xskat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
3-player card game &quot;Skat&quot; Xskat lets you play the card game Skat as defined by the official German &quot;Skatordnung&quot;. You can play by sending a window to the other player&apos;s X display, or via an IRC server. The computer can also simulate players. Many unofficial rules like &quot;Ramsch&quot; or &quot;Bock&quot; are supported. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XSL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensible Stylesheet Language (XML, XSL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xslide
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XSL editing mode for Emacs. xslide is a major mode for editing XSL stylesheets.  It supports running an XSL processor on the current buffer and showing the result in another buffer. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XSLT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformations (XSL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsltproc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XSLT command line processor This is a command line tool that allows to transform XML files into other XML files (or HTML, text, ...) using the standard XSLT stylesheet transformation mechanism. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Session Manager From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsmbrowser
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X11 tool for navigating SMB Networks xSMBrowser is a tool for navigating SMB Networks (Samba, SMB, CIFS). It retains the features of the program it was based upon (Microsoft&apos;s Network Neighborhood), but adds convenient features for Unix users. These include mounting, ability to change networks on-the-fly, and conveniences such as a Stop Button. More information can be found at the xsmbrowser web site http://www.public.iastate.edu/~chadspen/ . From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsmc-calc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Smith Chart calculator for X xsmc-calc allows you to perform Smith Chart calculations for RF (radio frequency) circuit design. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XSMD
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Storage Module Driver interface From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsok
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Generic Sokoban game for X11 xsok is a single player strategic game, a superset of the well-known Sokoban game. The target of Sokoban is to push all the objects into the score area of each level using the mouse or the arrow keys. For the other level subsets, there are different kinds of objects, and special effect squares. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsol
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Solitaire This is a simple Motif/Lesstif version of classic solitaire game that runs under X Window System. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsoldier
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
shoot-em up A vertically scrolling shoot-em up with power-ups and end-of-level bosses. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xspecs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X protocol, extension, and library technical specifications A comprehensive collection of manuals (most in both PostScript and text format, but some in text format only) documenting the standard specifications of the X protocol, extensions to the core protocol, and C library interfaces is provided by this package. The manuals provided include:  * X Window System Protocol  * Xlib - C Library Interface  * X Toolkit Intrinsics - C Library Interface  * Athena Widget Set - C Library Interface  * Bitmap Distribution Format (BDF)  * Compound Text Encoding (CTEXT)  * X Display Power Management Signaling (DPMS) Extension Protocol  * X Display Power Management Signaling (DPMS) Extension Library  * The X Font Service Protocol  * Inter-Client Communications Conventions Manual (ICCCM)  * Inter-Client Exchange (ICE) Protocol  * Inter-Client Exchange (ICE) Library  * The RX Document  * X Session Management Library  * X Session Management Protocol  * X Display Manager Control Protocol (XDMCP)  * XIE Sample Implementation Architecture  * X Image Extension Protocol (XIE)  * XIElib Specification  * The Input Method Protocol  * X Logical Font Description Conventions (XLFD)  * Extending X for Double-Buffering, Multi-Buffering, and Stereo  * Double Buffer Extension (DBE) Protocol  * Double Buffer Extension (DBE) Library  * Low Bandwidth X (LBX) Extension  * LBX X Consortium Algorithms  * MIT-SHM - The MIT Shared Memory Extension  * Record Extension Protocol Specification  * X Record Extension Library  * Security Extension Specification  * X Nonrectangular Window Shape Extension Protocol  * X Nonrectangular Window Shape Extension Library  * X Synchronization Extension Protocol  * X Synchronization Extension Library  * XC-MISC Extension  * XTEST Extension Protocol  * XTEST Extension Library  * X Input Device Extension Library  * X11 Input Extension Porting Document  * X11 Input Extension Protocol Specification  * Xmu Library  * Analysis of the X Protocol for Security Concerns  * Description of the Application Group Extension Implementation  * Definition of the Porting Layer for the X v11 Sample Server  * The X Font Library  * Security Extension Server Design  * X11R6 Sample Implementation Frame Work  * X Locale Database Definition  * The XIM Transport Specification  * A Flexible Remote Execution Protocol Based on rsh  * Xlib and X Protocol Test Suite: User Guide for the X Test Suite  * Font Server Implementation Overview  * X Transport Interface  * the Application Group (APPGROUP) extension  * the BIG-REQUESTS extension This package supersedes the xbooks package in older versions of Debian. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsri
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The xsri program allows the display of text, patterns, and images in the root window, so users can customize the XDM style login screen and/or the normal X background. Install xsri if you would like to change the look of your X loginscreen and/or X background. It is also used to display the default background (Red Hat logo). From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xstarfish
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X wallpaper generator. XStarfish generates colourful, tiled images for your background using random numbers fed through mathematical functions. It does not use source image files, so it can generate its images nearly forever without running out of material. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xstdcmap
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X standard colormap utility From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsu
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Allow users to run commands as root, after prompting for password. xsu is an interface for the command `su - username -c command` in Gnome. When the user executes xsu, he/she will be prompted for a command, a username and a password. If the username and password are correct xsu will execute the command as the entered user. So if the username was root, then the command will be executed as root. Of course it&apos;s also possible to predefine the username and the command by using the [-u,--username] and [-c,--command] arguments at the command line of xsu. This can be very useful when using xsu in for example gmenu or the GNOME panel. * Security Gnome Xsu 2.0 uses the standard su binary to gain it&apos;s root access. This way, all security issues should be solved. The security of all older xsu versions was very bad. With xsu version 0.1.0 the use of a pipe to a secured non-Gnome SUID application was introduced. This has been replaced with a special type of pipe to the standard GNU su application from the &apos;login&apos; package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xsysinfo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
display some Linux kernel parameters in graphical form This X client is like a mix of top, free and xload with the difference that the values are shown in form of a horizontal bar.  The displayed values are: CPU load, CPU idle, memory and swap sizes. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A graphical traceroute It traces (on a picture of the Earth) the route your IP packets travel to their destination. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXtended Technology (IBM, PC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xt-catalog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Catalog support and wrapper for XSLT Processor XT This package provides a simple front-end to XT for processing XML source files with XSL stylesheets. SGML catalog support is provided by a modified version of the command-line driver class for XT. A wrapper script for general XT usage is also included. This package works well for processing most DocBook XML sources. Author: Norman Walsh &lt;ndw@nwalsh.com&gt; Homepage: http://www.arbortext.com/Think_Tank/XML_Resources/Issue_Three/body_issue_three.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtail
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
like &quot;tail -f&quot;, but works on truncated files, directories, more xtail watches the growth of files.  It&apos;s like running a &quot;tail -f&quot; on a bunch of files at once.  It notices if a file is truncated and starts from the beginning.  You can specify both filenames and directories on the command line.  If you specify a directory, it watches all the files in that directory.  It will notice when new files are created (and start watching them) or when old files are deleted (and stop watching them). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtalk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
BSD talk compatible X Window System client. xtalk is a visual communication program which copies lines from your terminal to that of another user. This is an X Window System version, written in python. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtartan
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Display Scottish tartans Xtartan is a program that displays Scottish tartans (check patterns) in an X window or the root window. It can write the images to files for use on WWW pages etc. There is a library of over 240 tartan setts included with the program, and you can also add your own. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XTeamLinux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Distribution and website are in Chinese.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xteddy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a cuddly teddy bear (or other image) for your X desktop Normally, xteddy just sits around doing nothing. After all, that&apos;s what teddy bears are for. Look at him, talk to him, place heavy windows on top of him, zap him around until he becomes dizzy, do what you like; he will always be your true (albeit virtual) friend. Now you can load other pixmaps than the nice teddy, too. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xteddy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xteddy_test
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtel
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An X emulator of the French Minitel. This is a lesstif Minitel client that runs on color/black and white X Display and a xteld daemon that can make Minitel connection with one or more modems. The Minitel is a dedicated terminal for accessing the Teletel, the French videotex network. Thus, this package is almost only for French users. This package now supports the 3622 I-Minitel protocol (more informations on http://www.i-minitel.com). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtell
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Simple messaging client and server, sort of networked write Simple messaging client and server, allowing you to send messages from computer running xtell client to computer running xtelld server. Can be used as replacement for write(1). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtend
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
xtend - X10 status monitoring daemon xtend listens to the CM11A controller and will run commands in response to the input.  This allows for motion sensors, water level detectors, alarm switches, and other X10 enabled devices to keep a log of house activity and status.  Scripts can be written to e-mail reports, or update web pages based on X10 Activity. This package does not have transmit capability, if you want to control X10 devices, you need to use the heyu package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XTerm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Graphical application that provides a shell prompt for typing system commands. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xterm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The XTerm program is the standard terminal emulator for the X Window System. It provides DEC VT102/VT220 and Tektronix 4014 compatible terminals for programs that can&apos;t use the window system directly. If the underlying operating system supports terminal resizing capabilities (for example, the SIGWINCH signal insystems derived from 4.3bsd), xterm will use the facilities to notify programs running in the window whenever it is resized. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xterm
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X terminal emulator xterm is a terminal emulator for the X Window System.  It provides DEC VT102 and Tektronix 4014 compatible terminals for programs that cannot use the window system directly.  This version implements ISO/ANSI colors and most of the control sequences used by DEC VT220 terminals. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtermset
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
change the characteristics of an xterm xtermset allows you to change the characteristics of an xterm window from the command line. Most options have the same names as those that you would give xterm at startup. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xtest
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Xtest is a small program used to test X configuration which is used bythe Red Hat Linux installation program &quot;anaconda&quot;. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtet42
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tetris for X, supports one or 2 players. This version of tetris supports single player mode, or 2 player head-to-head play. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XTI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X/open Transport Interface (X/Open, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtide
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
provides tide and current predictions XTide is a package that provides tide and current predictions in a wide variety of formats. Graphs, text listings, and calendars can be generated, or a tide clock can be provided on your desktop. XTide can work with the X window system, plain text terminals, or the web. This is accomplished with three separate programs: the interactive interface (xtide), the non-interactive or command line interface (tide), and the web interface (xttpd). The algorithm that XTide uses to predict tides is the one used by the National Ocean Service in the U.S. It is significantly more accurate than the simple tide clocks that can be bought in novelty stores. However, it takes more to predict tides accurately than just a spiffy algorithm -- you also need data for every location for which you want to predict tides. This package provide a sample data set for only one location so you can try out the package, but anything useful requires the data packaged in the xtide-data package (or downloaded from the XTide ftp site). Web Page: http://www.flaterco.com/xtide/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtokkaetama
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Puzzle Game. xtokkaetama, alias xkaetama, is a tetris-like game. It supports single-player mode and two-players mode. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtoolwait
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Allows to start X applications serially. Xtoolwait notably decreases the startup time of your X sessions, provided that you start a number of X clients automatically during the X session startup.  Xtoolwait starts one X client in the background, waits until it has mapped a window and then exits. Author: Richard Huveneers &lt;richard@hekkihek.hacom.nl&gt; Homepage: http://www.hacom.nl/~richard/software/xtoolwait.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtoys
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XTP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXpress Transport Protocol From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtradius
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Free radius server implementation. XtRadius is a free radius server implementation. The main feature is that it can handle user accounting and authentication information via external fully configurable scripts. The Radius server is based on Cistron Radius 1.6.4. You can write script to make you own auth and/or accounting routines without having to patch the main server. Communication between XtRadius server and external scripts can be made using command line parameters or via environment variables. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtranslate
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
This is a x11-version translate wich will translate the xclipboard This is a X11-version for translate. It writes the contents of the X-selection and the commandline-option in a temporary used environment-variable, calls the script translate and pipes the results in a xmessage window. It will install a menuentry for the debian menusystem. It is possible to make a shortcut in some windowmanagers to use it more quickly. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtris
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
client-server multiplayer X tetris Xtris supports any number of simultaneous players. Features include:  * Integrated chat system.  * Computer-controlled robot players. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtrlock
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Minimal X display lock program xtrlock is a very minimal X display lock program, which uses nothing except the Xlib library.  It doesn&apos;t obscure the screen, it is completely idle while the display is locked and you don&apos;t type at it, and it doesn&apos;t do funny things to the X access control lists. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtron
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Tron game for X Xtron is a simple one or two player version of the old classic TRON. The game is simple: avoid running into walls, your own tail, and that of your opponent. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtrs
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
emulator for TRS-80 Model I/III/4/4P computers xtrs is an X-based emulator for the Tandy/Radio Shack line of Zilog Z-80-based microcomputers popular in the late 1970&apos;s and early 1980&apos;s.  It features cassette, floppy, and hard drive emulation, timer interrupt emulation, file import and export from the host operating system, support for most of the undocumented Z-80 instructions, and a built-in debugger.  Real floppy drives can be used, and, if an OSS-compatible sound driver is available, application-based sound can be played and real cassettes read and written directly through the sound card or via WAVE files.  Several hi-res graphics cards are emulated and, in Model 4/4P mode, mice are supported. There is also real-time clock, sound card, serial port, joystick, and CPU clock speedup emulation. xtrs requires ROM images from the original machines.  The ROMs are copyrighted by Radio Shack and are not freely licensed.  (Exception: in Model 4P mode, a freely licensed boot ROM included with this package can be used to boot a Model 4 operating system from a diskette image.)  Instructions are provided for retrieval of TRS-80 ROM images by those who may legally use them. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xttitle
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Changes X terminal emulator window titles This is a small program that generates escape sequences to change the title of terminal emulator windows under X. It should work with any program that emulates an xterm-like terminal. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xturqstat
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Fidonet and Usenet statistics program for X Turquoise SuperStat is a simple but powerful Fidonet and Usenet message base statistics program that can read messages that are stored in SDM (*.MSG), SquishMail, JAM, FDAPX/w and MyPoint message bases as well as local or remote (NNTP) Usenet news spools. This is the GUI version. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtux
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-Tux. XTux is a multidirectional scrolling game in which you control famous Free Software characters such as Tux, Beastie, or RMS in an attempt to save the World from an evil software company. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtuxxy
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
cuddly teddy bear for your X Windows desktop. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xtv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
View the screen of a remote X11 display View a remote X11 display in a window on your own display, in a continuously updating fashion.  Just like watching the remote display on television! From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XUI
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-windows User Interface (UI, X-Windows) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XUIDL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X-Unique-ID-Listing. (UIDL, POP3), &quot;X-UIDL&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XUL
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
used to define what the user interface will look like for a particular piece of software. XUL is used to define what buttons, scrollbars, text boxes, and other user-interface items will appear, but it is not used to define how those item will look (e.g. what color they are). The most widely used example of XUL use is probably in theMozilla web browser, where the entire user interface is defined using the XUL language. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XUL (eXtensible User-interface Language)
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A markup language similar to HTML and based on XML. From Matisse
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XUMA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXpertensystem UMweltgefaehrlichkeit von Altlasten (XPS) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xutils
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X Window System utility programs xutils provides a set of utility programs shipped with the X Window System that do not require the X libraries; many of these programs are useful even on a system that does not have any X clients or X servers installed. The programs in this package include:  - atobm, a converter from ASCII to X bitmap (.xbm) files;  - bdftopcf, which converts BDF fonts to PCF fonts;  - bdftruncate.pl and ucs2any.pl, tools to generate fonts with various    encodings from ISO 10646-encoded fonts  - ccmakedep, a version of makedepend which &quot;does it right&quot;  - cleanlinks, a program to remove dangling symlinks and empty directories    from a shadow link tree (created with lndir)  - fslsfonts, a tool that lists fonts served by an X font server;  - imake, a C preprocessor interface to the make utility;  - lndir, a tool that creates a shadow directory of symbolic links to    another directory tree;  - makedepend, a tool to create dependencies in makefiles;  - makeg, a tool for making debuggable executables;  - makepsres, a tool that creates PostScript language resource database    files;  - makestrs, a tool that makes string table C source and header(s);  - mkcfm, a tool that create summaries of font metric files in CID font    directories;  - mkdirhier, a tool that creates a directory hierarchy;  - mkfontdir, a program to generate fonts.dir files;  - scanpci, a utility for retrieving information about the PCI bus and    devices on it (not available on all architectures);  - pcitweak, a utility that can be used to examine or change registers in    the PCI configuration space (not available on all architectures);  - pswrap, a tool that creates C procedures from segments of PostScript    language code;  - resize, which prints a shell command for setting the TERM and TERMCAP    environment variables to indicate the current size of the xterm (or    compatible program) window from which the command is run;  - revpath, which generates a relative path that can be used to undo a    change-directory;  - rstart, a remote start client;  - rstartd, a remote start daemon activated by rstart connections;  - sessreg, a simple program for managing utmp/wtmp entries;  - showfont, a font dumper for use with an X font server;  - showrgb, a decompiler for RGB color-name databases;  - xfsinfo, an X font server information utility;  - xmkmf, a tool that creates a Makefile from an Imakefile; and  - xon, a tool that starts an X program on a remote machine. Installation of the xlibs-dev package, which contains the imake template files, is necessary if the imake or xmkmf tools are to be used. Installation of an rsh or ssh daemon (server) is necessary if rstartd is to be used, and installation of an rsh or ssh client is necessary if rstart is to be used. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Xvfb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
virtual framebuffer X server for X Version 11 From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvfb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
virtual framebuffer X server xvfb provides an X server that can run on machines with no display hardware and no physical input devices.  It emulates a dumb framebuffer using virtual memory.  The primary use of this server was intended to be server testing, but other novel uses for it have been found, including testing clients against unusual depths and screen configurations, doing batch processing with Xvfb as a background rendering engine, load testing, as an aid to porting the X server to a new platform, and providing an unobtrusive way to run applications that don&apos;t really need an X server but insist on having one anyway. This package also contains a convenience script called xvfb-run which simplifies the automated execution of X clients in a virtual server environment.  This convenience script requires the use of the xauth program from xbase-clients, hence the suggestion of xbase-clients. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvfb-run
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
run specified X client or command in a virtual X server environment From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvidtune
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
video mode tuner for XFree86 From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvier
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a &quot;Four in a row&quot; game Xvier is a simple X game where you and your opponent alternately throw stones into free columns. The stones pile up in the columns, and the goal is to get four stones in a row, in a column or diagonally. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xviewg
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
XView shared libraries [libc6] This package contains the shared libraries for XView. XView is a user interface toolkit following the look and feel of Sun&apos;s pre-X11 SunView. This package is required by XView-based programs. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvile
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
VI Like Emacs - vi work-alike (X11) X11 version of the vile editor. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvinfo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Print out X-Video extension adaptor information From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvkbd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
software virtual keyboard for X11 xvkbd is a virtual (graphical) keyboard program for X Window System which provides facility to enter characters onto other clients (softwares) by clicking on a keyboard displayed on the screen.  This may be used for systems without a hardware keyboard such as kiosk terminals or handheld devices.  This program also has facility to send characters specified as the command line option to another client. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvmount
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Small graphical utility for mounting devices by users. Users can mount predefined devices with selected permissions from a simple OpenLook based graphical interface. Xvmount recognizes the filesystem types minix, ext, ext2, msdos, vfat, xiafs, and iso9660/High Sierra. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvncviewer
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Virtual network computing client software for X. VNC stands for Virtual Network Computing. It is, in essence, a remote display system which allows you to view a computing `desktop&apos; environment not only on the machine where it is running, but from anywhere on the Internet and from a wide variety of machine architectures. It is implemented in a client/server model. This package provides a client for X, with this you can connect to a vncserver somewhere in the network and display its content in a window. There are vncserver available for X and for Win95/NT. This package is an enhanced version of VNC including TightVNC allowing it to be optimized to work over slow network connections such as low-speed modem links so you can work remotely almost in real time in most environments. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
XVT
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
eXecutive Vector Table (BS2000) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xvt
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
X terminal-emulator similar to xterm, but smaller xvt is an X terminal-emulator that is designed to be more or less compatible with xterm while using much less swap space.  It is mainly intended for use at sites which use large numbers of X terminals but may also be useful on single workstations that are short of memory. The main way that xvt achieves its small size is by avoiding the use of the X toolkit. If you are looking for a more featureful terminal-emulator than xvt, but one which still uses less swap space than xterm, consider rxvt. Features of xterm which xvt does not support include:  - Tektronix 4014 emulation  - Session logging  - Pop-up menus.  The only one of xterm&apos;s popup menu commands that    is provided in xvt is displaying and hiding of the scrollbar    and this is done simply by pressing any mouse key in the window    with the CONTROL key held down.  - Toolkit style configurability.  In particular, xvt does not    allow the user to remap the mouse or keyboard keys. Features which are supported include:  - VT100 emulation.  Most of the main escape sequences are supported --    certainly all those used by the standard screen based UNIX    applications.  - Lines that scroll off the top of the window are saved and can be    scrolled back with a scrollbar.  - Text selection and insertion including double and triple click for    words and lines. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwave
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Wave sound file editor XWave can load and edit several sound files at the same time. You can cut and paste sections from one file to an other. It also includes some effects like: re-sampling, echo, volume change, revert, etc... From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
dump an image of an X window From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwhois
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
RFC954 whois client for the X Window System This package provides a small and fast query tool for the RFC954 whois service, built using the gtk library for the X Window System. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwininfo
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
window information utility for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a collection of simple routines to call some X11 functions xwit is a collection of simple routines to call some X11 functions that don&apos;t already have any utility commands built around them. The reasoning behind this is that loosely every X function should be accessible from a shell script. For example, XWarpPointer() will move the X pointer, but no utility program exists to do so on those rare occasions when you could really use it.  xwit will also resize, iconify, pop, and move windows given by name or id, change an icon, title or name, set the screen saver going, and change individual key autorepeat settings, etc. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwpe
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Programming environment and editor for console and X11 Xwpe is an integrated programming and debugging environment similar to Borland&apos;s Turbo C and Pascal family. It has many features including the ability to start many compilers, linkers and debuggers from a menu-based interface or using keystrokes. Syntax highlighting is included for many programming languages, and any compiler and debugger can easily be used by the program. When compiling from within xwpe, errors in the source code can be jumped to and swiftly corrected. Variables and the stack can be easily displayed. Setting and unsetting breakpoints can be done directly within the source code. Although it is designed to be a tool for programmers (when invoked as wpe or xwpe), it can also be used as an easy to learn text editor (when invoked as we or xwe). From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwrits
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Reminds you to take a break from typing xwrits is a small reminder program designed to let you know it is time to take a break from typing to rest your wrists and prevent any damage to your wrists (or at least make them feel better if you&apos;ve already damaged them). Normally works on the honor system, but if you find yourself unable to stop typing during your break, it can also lock your keyboard. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xwud
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
image displayer for X From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xxd
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
make a hexdump or do the reverse. From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xxdiff
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a graphical file and directories comparison and merge tool A powerful tool for viewing the differences between two or three files, or two directories, and can be used to produce a merged version. The texts of the two or three files are presented side by side with their differences highlighted with colors for easy identification. Among its features are:    * 3-way diffs    * comfortable enabling of various diff options    * merge with:      * cut and paste      * save selected regions    * view merged results    * recursive comparison    * full customizable through resource file From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xxgdb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A X front-end to the GNU debugger gdb xxgdb is a simple but powerful graphical interface to the GNU debugger gdb.  A more powerful (but slower and much bigger) interface is available in the ddd package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xxkb
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Keyboard state indicator and switcher for xkb This program is a keyboard state indicator and switcher for xkb. Features: - shows current xkb group (pixmap in its own window) - allows switch group by mouse click - allows individual state for every window - can install its own button (indicator/mouse switcher) on every window&apos;s   title bar - can restrict keyboard states for every window to only two (&quot;main group&quot; -   &quot;alternative group&quot;) if xkb set up for more than two groups. Bugs: - documentation is partially in Russian (koi8-r charset) only From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xyoubin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The conventional mail arrival notification client for X. This package contains youbin client for X. This look and feel is like xbiff. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xzgv
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Picture viewer for X with a thumbnail-based selector xzgv is a picture viewer for X, with a thumbnail-based file selector. It uses GTK+ and Imlib. Most file formats are supported, and the thumbnails used are compatible with xv, zgv, and the Gimp. It can also be used with `xzgv file(s)&apos;, to effectively bypass the file selector. For more on how xzgv works and how to use it, do `info xzgv&apos; or `man xzgv&apos; once it&apos;s installed. xzgv differs from other picture viewers for X in that it uses one window for both the file selector and viewer, it (unlike xv) allows both scrolling and fit-to-window methods of viewing large pictures, and it (unlike xv and some others) doesn&apos;t ever mangle the picture&apos;s aspect ratio. It also provides extensive keyboard support; if you prefer using the keyboard, this is almost certainly the best viewer for you. But it doesn&apos;t skimp on the mousey stuff, either. Note that this program is written by the author of the svgalib-based &quot;zgv&quot;, and has similar features. Home Page: http://xzgv.browser.org/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xzip
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Interpreter of Infocom-format story-files Xzip interprets story-files (which are usually text adventure games) in the format used by Infocom.  This includes the games published by Infocom, as well as any games produced by compilers to this format, such as Inform. This is an interpreter for X. For text mode, try frotz or jzip. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
xzoom
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
magnify part of X display, with fast updates Like xmag, xzoom magnifies a section of the X display. Xzoom is different because it will continuously update the magnified area as the display changes. It is fast enough to enlarge small animations, for example. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossary>
