<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary id="Y">
<title>Y</title>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Y2K
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
[Year 2000] [problem] (slang) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YAAS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Acronym Server (WWW) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YABA
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Bloody Acronym (slang) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yabasic
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another BASIC interpreter Implements the most common (and simple) elements of the language plus some graphics facilities.  Anyone who has ever written BASIC programs on a C-64 should feel at home. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yacas
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Computer Algebra System Yet Another Computer Algebra System is a small and highly flexible computer algebra language. The syntax is very close to Mathematica. The distribution contains a small library of mathematical functions, but its real strength is in the language in which you can easily write your own symbolic manipulation algorithms. It supports arbitrary precision arithmetic. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Yacc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a &quot;parser&quot;. YACC stands for &quot;Yet Another Compiler Compiler&quot;. This is because this kind of analysis of text files is normally associated with writing compilers. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yacc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
GNU Project parser generator (yacc replacement) From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YACC
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Compiler Compiler (Unix) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yaclc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
check the bug closings in a Debian changelog. yaclc (yet another change log check) queries the Bug Tracking System to see if the bugs closed in a package&apos;s changelog belong to that package. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yada
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Debianisation Aid YADA is a Debian packaging helper.  It parses a special file, debian/packages, in a source package, and generates an appropriate debian/rules to control building of the package. WARNING: YADA is still very experimental!  Use it at your own risk! (And please run Lintian over anything built with yada before uploading.) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YADE
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another DSSSL Engine (DSSSL) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yadex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
WAD file editor for doom-style WADs Yadex is a Doom level (wad) editor for Unix systems running X, including Linux. It supports Doom alpha, Doom beta, Doom, Ultimate Doom, Final Doom, Doom II, Heretic and also, in a more or less limited way, Hexen and Strife. It is available under the terms of the GPL. Yadex is descended from DEU 5.21. Therefore, as you might expect, it&apos;s a rather low-level editor that requires you to take care of a lot of detail but on the flip side allows you to control very precisely what you are doing. In addition, it has many advanced functions that DEU didn&apos;t have, to make certain tedious tasks easy. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yafc
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another FTP Client Yafc is an ftp client intended to be a replacement for the standard ftp(1) program. Features include directory cache, remote filename completion, aliases, colored ls, recursive get/put/ls/rm, nohup mode transfers, tagging (queueing), background downloading, and more. This version is compiled without KTH Kerberos 4/5 authentication. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yank
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
yet another notekeeper Yank is a simple notekeeper and todo-list manager using the gnome and gtk libraries. It feels stable and usable enough to be released to the public but it surely lacks some (not so important) features which might be added later. Excessive tests have shown that yank is fool-proof, irritating and wasting too much memory. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yaps
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Pager Software This software is primary designed to send message to so called pager devices including cellular phones which are able to receive textual messages (sometimes called SMS, short message system/service.) From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yard
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Perl scripts to build rescue disk(s) to revive a system Yard is a suite of Perl scripts for creating custom boot/rescue disks.  Using a compressed filesystem, it can put a standard kernel image plus about 2.4 meg of utilities on a single floppy.  Yard is also useful for creating self-contained Linux-on-a-floppy systems. You specify a basic set of files and utilities for inclusion and Yard handles many of the details.  Features:  - File specs allow absolute and relative filenames, symbolic links,    file replacements and full shell-style globbing.  - Automatically determines necessary libraries and loaders.  - Allows stripping of binaries and libraries during copying.  - Automatically regenerates ld.so.cache  - Checks for broken symlinks  - Checks /etc/{fstab,inittab,termcap,pam.conf} for common errors and    inconsistencies.  - Checks user directories and files mentioned in /etc/passwd  - Checks command files (eg, rc.local and .login) and scripts for    missing binaries and command interpreters.  - Automatically performs filesystem compression and copying.  - Can be used with or without LILO.  - Can make single or double disk sets.  - Extensive checking of user choices and execution errors. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yardradius
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
YARD Radius Auth/Acct Server YARD Radius is a Radius authentication/accounting server which is derived from the original Livingston Enterprise Inc. RADIUS daemon release 2.1. It adds a number of useful features to the LE daemon, i.e. Control of simultaneous logins. Support of Ascend, Cisco and USR boxes. Extended daily/monthly/yearly accounting information on a per-user basis MD5 encrypted passwords support (both in passwd file and/or users file) Expirations in shadow file. Checking based on time-of-day, traffic and connection time. Support of PAM authentication and accounting. Binary form of accounting file. GDBM formats for users and user stats databases. Autoconfiguring capabilities of sources. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yasgml
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Linuxdoc-DTD only SGML mode Yasgml automates typesetting and previewing of SGML and enables completing input of SGML mark-up command such as `&lt;verb&gt;&apos;..`&lt;/verb&gt;&apos;. It is intended to use with LinuxDoc DTD only. You may need linuxdoc-tools package to process Linuxdoc-DTD SGML source. Default is for Japanese text editing. Its keybinding is based on that of YaTeX. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YASOS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Scheme Object System From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YAST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another Setup Tool (Linux, SUSE), &quot;YaST&quot; From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yatex
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet Another LaTeX mode YaTeX automates typesetting and previewing of LaTeX and enables completing input of LaTeX mark-up command such as `\begin{}&apos;..`\end{}&apos;. YaTeX also supports Demacs which runs on MS-DOS(386), Mule (Multi Language Enhancement to GNU Emacs), and latex on DOS. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yc-el
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet another Canna client for Emacsen. Canna client for emacs20, emacs21 or xemacs with MULE support. yc.el is implemented in pure elisp, makes it possible to use Canna on emacsen without direct support for Canna. Canna is a Japanese input method. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YCPS
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yale Center for Parallel Supercomputing (org., USA, HPC) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Yellow Book
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
An Interntional Standards Organisation (1SO) standard that describes the way data is encoded on CD-ROMs. The Yellow Book standard includes CD-XA specifications. YModem A file transfer protocol is an improved version of XMODEM-IK. YMODEM transfers data in 1,024-byte, blocks and performs a cyclic redundancy check (CRC) on each frame. Also, YMODEM supports sending more than over file in sequence. See YMODEM-g and ZMODEM. From QUECID
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Yellow Dog
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yellow Dog Linux is a complete, Red Hat and RPM based operating system for PowerPC computers. YDL may co-exist with Mac OS in a dual-boot environment or replace the Mac OS on &quot;New World ROM&quot; (Blue &amp; White G3s and newer) machines. Simple to install, YDL offers a graphical installer, KDE (an elegant, mature GUI), and over 900 applications to fulfill server, code developer, and home/office needs. YDL 3.0 was released March 19, 2003.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yelp
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yelp is the Gnome 2 help/documentation browser. It is designed to help you browse all the documentation on your system in one central tool. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yencode
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Powerful yEnc decoder/encoder Powerful standards-compliant yEnc encoder/decoder for the Usenet yEnc encoding format for modern UNIX systems From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yes
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Command which outputs a string repeatedly until killed From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Yet Another
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
adj. [From Unix&apos;s yacc(1), `Yet Another Compiler-Compiler&apos;, a LALR parser generator] 1. Of your own work: A humorous allusion often used in titles to acknowledge that the topic is not original, though the content is. As in `Yet Another AI Group&apos; or `Yet Another Simulated Annealing Algorithm&apos;. 2. Of others&apos; work: Describes something of which there are already far too many. See also YA-, YABA, YAUN.  From Jargon Dictionary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yforth
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A small freeware Forth environment in ANSI C. yForth? is an interestingly small implementation of Forth for Linux.  It suffers several deficiencies.  For general Forth programming or learning under Linux, yForth? is not the best choice. From the author&apos;s README: yForth? is a Forth environment written entirely in ANSI C, making it extremely portable. The first thing I want to tell you about yForth? is that it seems a joke compared to other systems such as gForth or PFE. Nevertheless, you could find yForth? nice, in which case you&apos;re invited to explore yForth? It&apos;s yours, you can make anything you want with it. If you want an explanation of the words provided by yForth? please refer to the draft of ANS Forth or something equivalent.  The Net will help you. Do not expect the prompt &quot;ok&quot; to come up when you run yForth?, the standard says that &quot;ok&quot; shall be printed AFTER every successful command execution... From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yh
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yan Huang Chinese Platform, a console Chinese environment Yan Huang Chinese Platform provides Chinese/English text input/output environment.  Users can choose input methods from &quot;Quwei&quot;, &quot;GbkPinYin&quot; and &quot;BiaoXingMa&quot;.  GBK standard Chinese interal encoding and Big5 encoding Chinese text are both supported.    Authors: Red Flag Linux  Home Page: http://www.redflag-linux.com/ From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yiff-server
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Y Sound Server YIFF is a network based and multi client connection system that supports X Window Systems style event and client handling. Internal 3D sound support and client to server IO wrapper code is also available. YIFF is OSS, ALSA, YSound and Y2N compliant. More information can be found at the YIFF web site http://wolfpack.twu.net/YIFF/ . From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yiyantang
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Terminal-based Chinese automatic encoding converter yyt is a pseudo-tty program that converts Chinese terminal output encoded in GB/BIG5 to a preset encoding automatically. It is useful for users who have to work with multiple Chinese encoding in console applications. Now it also converts input to the incoming encoding if the incoming encoding is set explicitly. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yodl
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yet oneOther Document Language. Yodl is a package that implements a pre-document language and tools to process it.  The idea of Yodl is that you write up a document in a pre-language, then use the tools (e.g. yodl2html) to convert it to some final document language.  Current converters are for HTML, ms, man, LaTeX SGML and texinfo, plus a poor-man&apos;s text converter.  Main document types are &quot;article&quot;, &quot;report&quot;, &quot;book&quot; and &quot;manpage&quot;.  The Yodl document language is designed to be easy to use and extensible.  URL: http://www.xs4all.nl/~jantien/yodl/  Authors: Karel Kubat &lt;karel@icce.rug.nl&gt;       Frank Brokken &lt;f.b.brokken@rc.rug.nl&gt;       Jan Nieuwenhuizen &lt;janneke@gnu.org&gt; From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Yoper
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yoper is a high performance operating system which has been carefully optimised for PC&apos;s with either 686 or higher processor types. The binaries that come with Yoper have been built from scratch using the original sources combined with the best features of from the major distros. Yoper is high performance and compact. In fact Yoper is one of the most standardised linux&apos;s that you will find and hardware performance is better than that of any other commercial OS. With Yoper it is possible to import packages from all the other major distributions, including RPM&apos;s, .deb&apos;s, and .tgz packages. Ydesktop-3.2.1 Release Candidate 3 released January 12, 2003.  From LWN Distribution List
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yorick
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
interpreted language and scientific graphics Yorick is an interpreted programming language for:  * scientific simulations or calculations  * postprocessing or steering large simulation codes  * interactive scientific graphics  * reading, writing, and translating large files of numbers The language features a compact syntax for many common array operations, so it processes large arrays of numbers very quickly and efficiently.  Superficially, yorick code resembles C code, but yorick variables are never explicitly declared and have a dynamic scoping similar to many Lisp dialects.  The yorick language is designed to be typed interactively at a keyboard, as well as stored in files for later use. This package includes an emacs-based development environment, which you can launch by typing M-x yorick in emacs. ftp://ftp-icf.llnl.gov/pub/Yorick/doc/index.html From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
youbin
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The conventional mail arrival notification server. Youbin is a kind of biff in the network age. When youbin is used, the mail spool of a certain, specific machine (mail server) is observed to inform the arrival of mail to a user at an arbitrary machine through the network.  On the other hand, the conventional &quot;biff&quot; informs only the user who logs in at the machine with the mail spool. Combining with POP, youbin eliminate a lot of NFS mount of mail spool for mail arrival checking. Since youbin is designed with event driven, the user is promptly informed of status change of mail spool caused by mail arriving and reading. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YP
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yellow Pages(tm), a registered trademark in the UK of British Telecom plc. From NIS HOWTO
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yp-tools
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Network Information Service (NIS) is a system that provides network information (login names, passwords, home directories, group information) to all of the machines on a network. NIS can allow users to log in on any machine on the network, as long as the machine has the NIS client programs running and the user&apos;s password is recorded in the NIS passwd database. NIS was formerly known as Sun Yellow Pages(YP). This NIS implementation is based on FreeBSD&apos;s YP and is a special port for glibc 2.x and libc versions 5.4.21 and later. This package only provides the NIS client programs. In order to use the clients, you need to have an NIS server running on your network. An NIS server is provided in the ypserv package. Install the yp-tools package if you need NIS client programs for machines on your network. You will also need to install the ypbind package on every machine running NIS client programs. If you need an NIS server, you need to install the ypserv package on one machine on the network. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ypbind
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
The Network Information Service (NIS) is a system that provides network information (login names, passwords, home directories, group information) to all of the machines on a network. NIS can allow users to log in on any machine on the network, as long as the machine has the NIS client programs running and the user&apos;s password is recorded inthe NIS passwd database. NIS was formerly known as Sun Yellow Pages(YP). This package provides the ypbind daemon. The ypbind daemon binds NIS clients to an NIS domain. Ypbind must be running on any machines running NIS client programs. Install the ypbind package on any machines running NIS client programs (included in the yp-tools package). If you need an NIS server, youalso need to install the ypserv package to a machine on your network. From Redhat 8.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
YST
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Yukon Standard Time [-0900] (TZ) From VERA
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ytalk
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Enhanced talk program with X support. Ytalk is a multi-user chat program. It works exactly like the UNIX talk program and even communicates with the same talk daemons. Ytalk&apos;s advantages come in it&apos;s ability to allow multiple connections. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
ytree
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A file manager that looks like Xtree Gold(tm) This is a file manager that looks like xtree gold(tm). it has history, colors, configurable file viewers and much more. It works on terminals. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yudit
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
unicode text editor yudit is a unicode text editor for the X Window System. It does not need localized environment or unicode fonts. It supports simultaneous processing of many languages, conversions for local character standards, bidirectional input, has its own input methods. The package includes conversion utilities, and it also has support for postscript printing. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yydecode
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
decode yEnc archives yydecode works almost identically to the infamous uudecode program, but for yEnc encoded archives. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yyextract
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
extract grammar rules from a yacc grammar From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
yyref
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
generate cross-reference for yacc input From whatis
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

</glossary>
