<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
     "http://docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY technology SYSTEM "technology.xml">
<!ENTITY lfiltering SYSTEM "lfiltering.xml">
<!ENTITY sfiltering SYSTEM "sfiltering.xml">
<!ENTITY protocols SYSTEM "protocols.xml">
<!ENTITY references SYSTEM "references.xml">
<!ENTITY faq SYSTEM "faq.xml">
<!ENTITY newbie SYSTEM "newbie.xml">
<!ENTITY glossary SYSTEM "glossary.xml">
<!ENTITY doctitle "Anti-Spam HOWTO"> ]>

<!--
 
 File        :  $Source$

 Purpose     :  Main file for the Anti-Spam-HOWTO

 $Id$

 The Anti-Spam-HOWTO team Welcomes you ;-)

-->

<article id="index">
  <articleinfo>

    <title>Anti-Spam HOWTO</title>

    <author>
       <firstname>Christopher</firstname>
       <surname>Albert</surname>
       <affiliation>
          <!-- Valid email...spamblock/scramble if so desired -->
          <address><email>christopher dot albert at mcgill dot ca</email></address>
       </affiliation>
     </author>
    <author>
       <firstname>Hal</firstname>
       <surname>Burgiss</surname>
       <affiliation>
          <address><email>hal at foobox dot net</email></address>
       </affiliation>
     </author>

     <!-- All dates specified in ISO "YYYY-MM-DD" format -->
     <pubdate>2003-06-07</pubdate>

     <!-- Most recent revision goes at the top; list in descending order -->
     <revhistory>
       <revision>
          <revnumber>0.9</revnumber>
          <date>2002-06-07</date>
          <authorinitials>HB</authorinitials>
          <revremark>first draft, a mere beginning</revremark>
       </revision>
     </revhistory>


     <abstract>
        <para>
         This is just the beginning of a draft of the future Anti-Spam HOWTO.
         Stay tuned.
        </para>
         <para>
          Since this is a mere draft, there are most likely missing sections,
          errors, and other snafus. Please forgive the mess, and check back 
          later. 
         </para>
     </abstract>

  </articleinfo>



<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
 <!-- 
  <para condition="draft">
    This is only draft text, and will only appear when the "draft" profile is
    selected.
  </para>
-->
  <para>
   This HOWTO will address the impact of SPAM on computer users and networks, 
   both large and small. We will look at the problem, as well as the various
   solutions that are available to Linux administrators and users.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="usage">
  <title>Conventions, Usage and Terminology</title>
  <para>
   Spam is a four letter word to all of us. For the sake of our discussion, 
   Spam will simply be <emphasis>unwanted email</emphasis> that is targeted at
   a large number of recipients. Often it is commercial in nature (i.e. trying
   to sell you something), but not always.
  </para>
  <para>
   We will not address mass mailings that are the result of viruses, though
   the techniques used to combat spam are often effective with viruses as
   well.
  </para>
  <para>
   And we will confine our discussion to email Spam only.
  </para>
  <para>
   There is a brief Glossary in the appendix should any of the terminology
   used in the document not be clear.
  </para>
  </sect2>

     <!-- Legal Sections -->
  <sect2 id="copyright">
    <title>Copyright and License</title>

    <!-- The LDP recommends, but doesn't require, the GFDL --> 
    <para>
     This document, <citetitle>&doctitle;</citetitle>,
     is copyrighted &copy; 2003 by <emphasis>Chris Albert</emphasis> and 
     <emphasis>Hal Burgiss</emphasis>. Permission is granted to copy,
     distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free
     Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the
     Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover
     Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is available
     at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">
     http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
     Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="disclaimer">
    <title>Disclaimer</title>

    <para>
     No liability for the contents of this document can be accepted.
     Use the concepts, examples and information at your own risk.
     There may be errors and inaccuracies, that could be damaging to
     your system.  Proceed with caution, and although this is highly
     unlikely, the author(s) do not take any responsibility.
    </para>

    <para>
     All copyrights are held by their by their respective owners,
     unless specifically noted otherwise.  Use of a term in this
     document should not be regarded as affecting the validity of any
     trademark or service mark.  Naming of particular products or
     brands should not be seen as endorsements.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <!-- Give credit where credit is due...very important -->
 <!-- 
  <sect2 id="credits">
    <title>Credits / Contributors</title>

    <para>
     In this document, I have the pleasure of acknowledging:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem> 
        <para>Individual 1 <email>someone1 (at) somewhere.org</email></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem> 
        <para>Individual 2 <email>someone2 (at) somewhere.org</email></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
-->
  <!-- Feedback -->
  <sect2 id="feedback">
    <title>Feedback</title>

    <para>
     Feedback is always welcomed. To send
     your additions, comments and criticisms you can subscribe to the following
     list : <email>Anti-Spam-Howto (at) lists.mcgill.ca</email>. Anyone can subscribe
     to this list, but you must be subscribed to post and get messages.
     To subscribe, first read the information for list users at
     <ulink url="ashowto-list">http://www.mcgill.ca/ncs/email/listserv/users/</ulink>.
     Then send a message to<email>LISTSERV (at) LISTS.MCGILL.CA</email> 
     with an <emphasis>empty</emphasis> subject line , 
     and body without signature containing only the following line:

     <userinput>SUB ANTI-SPAM-HOWTO firstname lastname</userinput>


    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>New Versions</title>
  <para>
   This is a work-in-progress and not ready for prime time. New versions of
   this document will be periodically released through the <ulink
   url="http://tldp.org">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>.
  </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

<sect1 id="reading-guide">
<title>How  to read this Howto</title>
 <para>
	 Since this document is aimed at a wide audience, we make the following recommendations
	 on reading paths depending on your experience with linux and open source software,
	 as well as your needs or responibilities for controlling spam.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
 <listitem>
	 <para>
		 If you are looking for answers to general questions about spam, or
		 some non-technical recommendations on how
		 to reduce the amount of spam you, your group, or your organization 
		 receives you might want to look at our 
		 <link linkend = "faq">FAQ</link>.
	 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
	 <para>
		 If you are new or unexperienced with linux or opensource software
		 you should consult our 
		 <link linkend = "newbie">Getting Started Guide</link>.
	 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
	 <para>
		 If you are a reasonably expreienced linux user familiar with 
		 installing and configuring open source software, and want to
		 set up a local anti-spam solution, you can start at
		 <link linkend = "lfiltering">Local Filtering</link>, which deals with technolgies
		 for filtering your mail locally.
	 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
	 <para>
		 If you are an experienced mail administrator and want to implement 
		 a site-wide anti-spam solution for your group or organization,
		 then the place for you to begin is the following section
		 <link linkend = "sfiltering">Site-Wide Filtering</link>, 
		 which describes how to set up an spam-filtering solution on a mail gateway.
	 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
	 <para>
		 If you are interested in an overview of current anti-spam technology,
		 or want to do some reading and research before implementing a spam-filtering
		 solution you can start reading from section 
		 <link linkend = "technology">Anti-Spam Technology</link>, 
		 which gives an overview of spam filtering methods.
	
	 </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
	 <para>
		 If you think that spam is a larger problem better dealt with at the level of network
		 protocols, or are interested in this prespective, then you might be intested to 
		 start reading at the section entitiled 
		 <link linkend = "protocols">Network Protocols</link>, which talks about
		 some current research into dealing with spam at the level of network protocols.
	 </para>
 </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->
<!--   ~~~~~~~~~~~~	Begin external entities 	~~~~~~~~~~~~~~	-->


<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

&technology;		<!-- Anti-Spam Technology Section -->

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->
<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

&lfiltering;		<!-- Local Filtering Section -->

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->
<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

&sfiltering;		<!-- Site-Wide Filtering Section -->

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->
<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

&protocols;		<!-- Network Protocols Section -->

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->
<!--   ~~~~~~~~       New section Header    ~~~~~~~~~     -->

&references;		<!-- References Section -->

<!--  ~  End section  ~  -->


&glossary;		<!-- Glossary -->

<!-- begin appendicies -->

&newbie;		<!-- Getting Started Guide -->

&faq;			<!-- FAQ -->

<!-- end appendicies -->

<!-- 	~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~	End external entities 	~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~		-->


</article>

