<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>24</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-10-07</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Traffic-Control-HOWTO/">Traffic Control HOWTO</ulink> by Martin A. Brown explains the implementation of queuing, scheduling, shaping and dropping of packets on Linux.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Our German friends translated the <ulink url="http://www.linuxhaven.de/dlhp/HOWTO/DE-LVM-HOWTO.html">LVM HOWTO</ulink> a while ago, apparently, but it only got announced on the Deutsches Linux HOWTO Projekt homepage <ulink url="http://www.linuxhaven.de/dlhp/news.html">last week</ulink>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<para>This section would have been empty again if it wasn't for the
initiative of your weekly news editors ;-)</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>We decided to support Sergiusz Pawlowicz's proposal for
a <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/20030930.html#AEN63">HOWTO stand up
and turn off TV</ulink>.  We would like this document to be a joint
effort, and since you've had some time to think about it, we gather that
by now you probably have to refrain yourselves from sending in a mail to
us to share your ideas ;-)
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Armin would like to find out if anyone can use his <ulink url="http://qwuh.no-ip.com/oracle/">Oracle 6i Forms and Reports Server and Client HOWTO</ulink>.  Have a look and let him know!</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Daniel Nofftz submitted v1.1.0 of his <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5977:200310:laeldocdpphcbljhombk">Athlon
Powersaving HOWTO</ulink>, but requests us to bear with him until it has been reviewed.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Clemens Lee submitted the first version of the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5986:200310:ekpomcffjchcfdnmmlci">Debian Binary Package Building HOWTO</ulink>, which explains how to create <filename>.deb</filename> packages.  However, he's not happy with the title and awaits suggestions to change it.  This is the chance for those readers who are always sighing how they can't contribute anything to Open Source because they're just not the technical kind of person.  You don't have to know anything about Linux in order to help TLDP authors to create good documents.  Sometimes it's enough to just come up with a bit of inspiration for a good title!</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Miroslav Skoric sent in <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5997:200310:akfanghehooklaknddfk">several updates</ulink>: he is the author of the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet Radio mini-HOWTO</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WinNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>.  Don't mix up that last one with Bernd Reichert's <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Linux+NT-Loader.html">NT OS Loader + Linux mini-HOWTO</ulink>!</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>From Ian Ward we received for review the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6001:200310:lgilnlolmnaihmeogdcl">Debian and Windows Shared Printing mini-HOWTO</ulink>, v1.2.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>It is hard to keep track with David Lawyer.  Here is v2.20 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Serial-HOWTO.html">Serial HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Read Eric Raymond's <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Unix-and-Internet-Fundamentals-HOWTO/index.html">Unix and Internet Fundamentals HOWTO</ulink> for a kickstart no-nonsense introduction to computers, Linux and Internet.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>Birthday Wishes from Lars Wirzenius</title>

<para>The formal TLDP 10th anniversary news was <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5068:200309:fhmfikojcekoaemohkge">sent
out</ulink> by Stein Gjoen. Lars Wirzenius seems to recall that <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?7:mss:4076:200310:amkihcbaggglagjflccj">TLDP
started as early as 1992</ulink> and possibly before that.  Is it the said truth of the information age that we forget our history?  Next thing we know, there have always been flying cars and brain plugins around...</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Stale LDP Documents</title>

<para>If you are unhappy about the status of a document that has not
been updated since some time, you should be able to <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5084:200310:mnpkmladkcbfebgdjbbb">replace
the original</ulink>
document after writing if from scratch (for copyright reasons)</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Govt. Support for Linux</title>

<para>Though Off-topic, Shuvam Mishra's <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5080:200310:pocfhjbaeomncpdegppj">
update</ulink> on the Indian government's support for free software is
interesting.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Linux Kernel 0.01 Commentary</title>

<para>If you had problems accessing the Linux Kernel Commentary v0.01 by
Pramode C. E., you should try accessing his <ulink
url="http://pramode2.tripod.com/kerneldocs/">updated URL</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. If you want to help TLDP,
take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/">tasks
page</ulink>, and consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>

