<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>33 and 34</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-12-17</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

<para>Lars Strand is the author of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO/">Mobile IPv6
HOWTO</ulink>.  He describes how to configure mobile computers, such as
laptops and PDAs, for actual mobile use with IPv6.  You need a fully
functional IPv6 network; how to set up one is discussed in the <ulink
url="http://ldp.linux.no/HOWTO/Linux+IPv6-HOWTO/">IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>.
You'll need to patch kernels.  We know the Kernel HOWTO is in review,
but!  1.  Lars gives a step-by-step explanation and 2. you may find the
same information in the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/ACPI-HOWTO/">ACPI HOWTO</ulink>.  Our reviewers are working on the Kernel HOWTO as fast as they can, there's already <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5812:200312:becpbdgagpneamchdggc">a draft for the new Kernel HOWTO</ulink>.</para>
  
</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Peter Tonev wants to write a document on Linux and ergonomics.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Feiyun Wang proposes a study guide annex source commentary for the Linux i386 boot code, and <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6608:200312:eepbbjalleodniadebmk">already has it in XML</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Adrian Offerman wrote an <ulink url="http://www.offerman.net/MMBase-Installation-HOWTO/">MMBase Installation HOWTO</ulink>, describing the installation of the MMBase content management system on RedHat Linux, using the Tomcat application server, integrated with Apache and MySQL.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ralf Holzer notes down his experiences with encrypted file systems and the 2.6 kernel in this <ulink url="http://www.ece.cmu.edu/~rholzer/cryptoloop_mini_howto.html">Cryptoloop Mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The Skoric triplet, we'll call them:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink>, v1.28, covers the installation, configuration and use of the popular packet-radio BBS server software FBB.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>While GRUB is a wonderful thing (<quote>uses a Bash-like interface</quote>), LILO is the most popular Linux boot loader.  The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink> is a supplement to the <ulink url="http://www-user.tu-chemnitz.de/~mibe/linux/lilo/user/">LILO User Guide</ulink>, for those who want a quick start or a short overview.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Details for starting Windows NT from LILO can be found in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Alex Weeks is updating the Linux System Administrator's Guide or SAG.  Here are the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/sag/html/">first results</ulink>, including a new part about NTP, the Network Time Protocol.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Christopher Devine's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Encrypted-Root-Filesystem-HOWTO/">Encrypted Root Filesystem HOWTO</ulink> v1.1 contains information to support GRUB (the GRand Unified Bootloader).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DB2-HOWTO/">DB2 Version 7.1 HOWTO</ulink> contains detailed guidelines for setting up the DB2 Universal Database Version 7.1 on your Linux machine.  Version 1.2.7 of the HOWTO tries to fill the gap towards version 8 of DB2, pointing you to some helpful sites while waiting for a HOWTO that will cover the newer version.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The latest developments in logical volume management are covered in AJ Lewis's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink>, v0.6.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Thomas Marteau published 1.1 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/PA-RISC-Linux-Boot-HOWTO/">PA-RISC/Linux Boot HOWTO</ulink>, in which he explains, among other things, how to use PALO, the bootloader for this type of hardware.  Thomas added a new chapter covering the setup of your Microsoft Windows 2000 server for net-booting your PA/RISC machine.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Daniel Quintiliani added information for Forte Free Agent, Xnews and Dialog in v2.1 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Windows-Newsreaders-under-Linux-HOWTO/">Windows Newsreaders under Linux HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>Linux Gazette and the LDP</title>

<para>Guylhem Aznar <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6191:200312:ekhigcbgkmfeialfacih">wrote</ulink>
to the editors of Linux Gazette asking if it would be possible for
LG.net to submit documents to TLDP in a format that the TLDP could use
to redistribute on its website under a free license. He indicated that a
clear source format with semantic tags (such as docbook or linuxdoc) is
preferable and that mirroring the documents would be a better
opportunity to support LG.net than simply mirroring the website.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item2">
<title>HTML/PDF generation from CVS source</title>

<para>Saqib Ali created a <ulink
url="http://www.xml-dev.com/blog/index.php#88">website</ulink> that can
convert the XML Documents stored in the CVS to HTML/PDF on-the-fly. The
idea is to let the HOWTO authors to view the HTML/PDF output of their
XML source once they commit the source to the CVS. Using the converter
is as simple as going to something like <ulink
url="http://www.xml-dev.com:8080/tldp/http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/*checkout*/LDP/howto/docbook/DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO.xml">http://www.xml-dev.com:8080/tldp/http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/*checkout*/LDP/howto/docbook/DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO.xml</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item3">
<title>WHATIS wiki available</title>

<para>Even thought David Lawyer's concerns regarding the volume of work
associated with a WHATIS series were valid, John R. Daily was reluctant
to forestall a possibly valuable change for years without at least
conducting an experiment. He set up a WHATIS wiki at <ulink
url="http://geekhavoc.com/whatis/">http://geekhavoc.com/whatis/</ulink>.
Feel free to contribute. The WHATIS wiki would be a valuable resource
for reference of certain often used terms within the LDP HOWTOs. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item4">
<title>The LDP HOWTO Generator</title>

<para>Stein Gjoen <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6016:200312:jbdbakjaacfndkmflfhi">announced</ulink>
that the LDP HOWTO Generator was ready for use. The current version is
0.40 at <ulink
url="http://www.nyx.net/~sgjoen/The_LDP_HOWTO_Generator.html">http://www.nyx.net/~sgjoen/The_LDP_HOWTO_Generator.html</ulink>.
A link to this resource has been added to the revised LDP author guide.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="discussions">
<title>Discussions on TLDP lists</title>

<sect2 id="discussion1">
<title>Sponsorship for The LDP</title>

<para>Rahul Sundaram initiated a <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5875:200312:ihpahginmljdgbhooeje">thread</ulink>
for discussing getting sponsorship for the LDP and a reward program like
that of Gnome and Mozilla. During the thread, Saqib Ali said that a
HOWTO about the product of a company could be reviewed by them and the
LDP could place an ad acknowledging the same. David Lawyer however, was
in <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5966:200312:claiepedajakajhoajgg">disagreement</ulink>
with him.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="discussion2">
<title>Right to new maintainer</title>

<para>During the discussion on The LDP document licenses, Guylhem Aznar
<ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6192:200312:nfnlmplgcedgajjaphdf">suggested</ulink>
that we should require authors to automatically grant the right to TLDP
to appoint a new maintainer for their documents when they can no longer
be reached for some time.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="discussion3">
<title>DocBook created html may break links but LinuxDoc OK</title>

<para>In his continued advocacy for LinuxDoc because of its ease of use,
David Lawyer <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6164:200312:claiepedajakajhoajgg">discovered</ulink>
that the conversion of LinuxDoc to HTML and of DocBook to HTML result in
a different naming scheme for chunks. For DocBook, the chunk names are
the same as the label name.  For LinuxDoc, the chunk names are the same
as the title of the doc with a numeric prefix. However, Mark
Komarinski <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6171:200312:nhcmlpmaiihhjanmmgma">said</ulink>
that, reformatting the document will lead to incorrect links even though
the links themselves exist and that the solution (for both formats) is
to make sure your section names make sense and there will be little
reason to rename them. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="discussion4">
<title>Copyright Infringement of Linux Dictionary</title>

<para>Binh Nguyen <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6091:200312:kdlafegngoikhcpbhlid">complained</ulink>
that a certain <ulink
url="http://www.swpearl.com/eng/scripts/aboutus/">PearL Linux
Limited</ulink> created a <ulink
url="http://www.swpearl.com/eng/scripts/dictionary/">database</ulink>
based entirely on the definitions from the Linux Dictionary and did not
acknowledge the original source. </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and Y
Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
