<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>1</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-04-23</pubdate>
  <title>TLDP Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>
<sect1>
  <title>10th Anniversary</title>
<para>
The tenth anniversary of the Linux Documentation Project seemed like a good reason to revive the news section. Happy birthday, LDP! The new editors of this section are blowing the candles and celebrating on behalf of all the volunteers that kept this project going for so long, inviting them to come over for a virtual chat and drink, while swearing dear oaths that they will really do weekly updates. From tomorrow on, after the headaches that'll have joined us in the morning have left ;-)
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>
It has been a good 1.0 week:
</para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linksys-Blue-Box-Router-HOWTO/">Linksys Blue Box Router HOWTO</ulink>, by Eric Steven Raymond, explains how to configure Linksys router and firewall boxes (models BEFSR41 and up) for use on a home DSL connection. Your comments, please.</para></listitem>
    
<listitem><para>Martin A. Brown's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Traffic-Control-tcng-HTB-HOWTO/">Traffic Control using tcng and HTB HOWTO</ulink> discusses traffic shaping on Linux machines using Traffic Control Next Generation with Hierarchical Token Bucket.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Svetoslav Slavtchev submitted the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree local multi-user HOWTO</ulink>, explaining how to set up your system with multiple monitors, keyboards and mouses connected to the local host, allowing multiple local users to log in to the same host simultaneously.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>A document on <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Manuales-LuCAS/doc-instalacion-cluster-alta-disponibilidad/">high-availability clusters with Linux</ulink>, and its difference from a high-performance cluster was released in Spanish.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Cuauhtemoc Pacheco proposed his idea of writing a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4255:200304:ehjkhdkflbkajdlbpclh">Literate Programming HOWTO</ulink> and has had some very positive reactions, but how do you feel about it?</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Derek Black asks for comments on his <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4243:200304:bkaognipcancgnhdlhkj">Redhat AS2.1 HA Cluster mini-HOWTO</ulink> outline.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>A <ulink url="http://ibiblio.org/gferg/ldp/Vb6-to-Tcl.html">VB6 To TCL Cheat-Sheet</ulink>, by Mark Hubbard.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>
<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<para>Plenty of updates this week:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO.html">The Linux Kernel HOWTO</ulink> by Alavoor Vasudevan, check out the v5.4 of the document.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Program-Library-HOWTO/">Program Library HOWTO</ulink> by David A. Wheeler is now at v1.20.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David A. Ranch sent in v2.00.040803 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/IP-Masquerade-HOWTO/">Linux IP Masquerade HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/KDE-GUI-Login-Configuration-HOWTO.html">KDE GUI Login Configuration HOWTO</ulink> v1.3 was sent in by John P. Meshkoff,II.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Your comments are also welcome for the 1.1 release of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Bangla-PDF-HOWTO/">Bangla PDF HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>John Huggins posted v1.4 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Astronomy-HOWTO/">Linux Astronomy HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Last week, David A. Ranch must have had a few spare moments to update his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/docs.html#trinityos">TrinityOS: A Guide to Configuring Your Linux Server</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>An updated <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Tutoriales/Python/">Python Guide</ulink>, v.2.0 is now available in Spanish.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>
                                  
<sect1>
<title>News from the LDP mailing lists</title>

<sect2><title>Discussion on Revival of LDP Weekly News</title>

<para>Greg Ferguson posted a message to the LDP discuss list <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4232:200304:loceblldbelajghaloeg">inviting
volunteers</ulink> for taking over the LDP Weekly News. Machtelt Garrels, Torsten
Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4236:200304:ohdcgmenalgmbedahfkc">responded</ulink> and went on to
<ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4244:200304:nlmglhlkncogglmpofge">discuss</ulink> what should go into the weekly news. A <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4249:200304:ceejnklaecengajdijnf">sample</ulink> was posted to the discuss list and the result is this first issue of the revived
LDP weekly news.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Deciding if Linux is Right for You</title>

<para>Tabatha Persad <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4239:200304:bpablmohaaekmikopbeb">re-posted a request</ulink> for comments on the "Deciding if Linux is Right for You" draft. She was concered about finding the best
place for the document and requested for feedback. Suggestions in
response included <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4245:200304:bpablmohaaekmikopbeb">merging</ulink> the document with the Installation-HOWTO
and a pointer to a related From-DOS/Windows-to-Linux-HOWTO. David Lawyer
<ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4253:200304:bpablmohaaekmikopbeb">preferred different documents</ulink> as that would spread the task of
maintaining to more than one person.</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>HOWTOs and Mini-HOWTOs</title>

<para>The topic comes up for discussion on the LDP discuss list often. David
Lawyer in response to the sample LDP Weekly News put forth his <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4254:200304:blpnkkoapimlbpolbcfb">views
on this issue</ulink> which included suggestions for a high level HOWTO and
several other Mini-HOWTOs along with it. David wanted a better name for
the Mini-HOWTOs that go with the high level HOWTO. Machtelt posted her
<ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4258:200304:bpablmohaaekmikopbeb">views on interlinking</ulink> of HOWTOs and the problems involved and
indicated that she would call the Mini-HOWTOs in question as related
HOWTOs rather than supporting or child HOWTOs.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>Please help us create this weekly newsletter. Seen a site putting in a
story with a link to the LDP? Completed the translation of any HOWTO?
Know of any articles about the LDP published in newspapers or magazines?
We are not curious, just inquisitive ;-). You can help us by sending in
links and information at <email><ulink url="mailto:feedback(at)en.tldp.org">feedback@en.tldp.org</ulink></email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>
</article>
