<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>28</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-11-05</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Niko Sauer has written some interesting things about <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6206:200311:paomefdmeppfbonhpnbd">USB memory sticks</ulink> and would like to know what you think about it.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lars Strand <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5174:200311:abimfngadhibogkclfmk">proposed</ulink>
a Mobile IPv6 HOWTO. A draft version is available at <ulink
url="http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/mipv6/">http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/mipv6/</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Here it is in one-dot-oh!: the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Debian-Jigdo/">Debian Jigdo mini-HOWTO</ulink>, by Peter Jay Salzman.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>After the fashion of the <ulink url="http://koeln.ccc.de/prozesse/writing/artikel/hacker-werden.html">Wie werde ich Hacker HOWTO</ulink> (<ulink url="http://babelfish.altavista.com/">Babelfish</ulink> might be required), TLDP has its own HOWTO-become-a-guru doc, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Reading-List-HOWTO/">Linux Reading List HOWTO</ulink>.  This list is what Eric Steven Raymond considers to be essential reading if you want to become a UNIX/Linux programmer. The list is revision v2.1 now.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Alavoor Vasudevan's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/C-C++Beautifier-HOWTO/">C-C++ Beautifier
HOWTO</ulink> v16.7.  He also tries to keep the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO/">Linux Kernel HOWTO</ulink> up
to date. He sent in an update to his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Vim-HOWTO/">Vim Color Editor HOW-TO</ulink>. </para></listitem> 

<listitem><para>Did you know that Miroslav <quote>Misko</quote> Skoric's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink> contains a section on how to <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB-11.html">communicate with LinFBB in Serbian</ulink>?  Check it out, preferably in the latest version, 1.26.</para>
<para>As usual, Miroslav's updates come in threes: you also get the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink>, v3.15, and the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>, v2.15.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Rick Moen found some more interesting sources of Linux information and listed them in v1.7.3 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/User-Group-HOWTO.html">Linux User Group HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jean-Daniel Dodin's <ulink
url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Partition-Rescue/index.html">Partition-Rescue
HOWTO</ulink> has been converted to docbook and the new version is under the LGPL.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>


<para>Mendel Cooper promises v2.2 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/">Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide</ulink> to be full of exiting new examples demonstrating all the <quote>nifty things</quote> you can do with Bash arrays, and much more!</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>TLDP-ES/LuCAS unreachable</title>

<para>Ismael Olea sent in an update telling us that the Spanish LDP folks are down because of a disk failure and
they are working on fixing it. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>LDP author tools RPM packages</title>

<para>Rodolfo J. Paiz <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5163:200311:ehngfbpnepphojhokgdn">summarized</ulink>
his findings on, what packages form parts of the authoring tools RPM
packages on his RedHat 9 based system. This is his <ulink
url="http://apollo.simpaticus.com/other/docbook.packagelist.shrike.txt">package
list descriptions</ulink> page. On a Debian GNU/Linux based system, the
packages that provide for these capabilities can be installed from the
linuxdoc-tools and the docbook-utils Debian packages. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Linux+XFS HOWTO maintenance</title>

<para>Russel Ingram, the maintainer for the <ulink
url="www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+XFS-HOWTO/">Linux+XFS HOWTO</ulink> feels that
the document is out of its useful life as several linux distributions
offer XFS at installation time. He plans to move the document to the
unmaintained section of the HOWTOs and welcomes anyone who feels they
can turn this back into an up to date and useful document. Contact
Russel at ringram at gargoylecc.com if you are interested. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Linux SAG guide maintenance</title>

<para>Alex Weeks would be maintaining the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/sag/">Linux System Administrator
Guide</ulink> for novices., taking it over from Stephen Stafford. If you would like to help
Alex as a co-maintainer, get in touch with him. </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. If you want to help TLDP,
take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/">tasks
page</ulink>, and consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
