<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>35 and 36</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-12-30</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Feiyun Wang sent in a finalized version of a document he would like to call the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6768:200312:konkimegkjeambdiipla">Linux i386 Boot Code HOWTO</ulink>, a study guide and source commentary to the Linux i386 boot code.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Adrian Offerman submitted a new <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6778:200312:chhbgdgdnpopnokgfpcf">MMBase Installation HOWTO</ulink>, describing the installation of the MMBase content management system on a Red Hat Linux distribution, using the Tomcat application server, and integrating it with MySQL and Apache.  The <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/MMBase.html">current MMBase mini-HOWTO</ulink> describes the setup of the management system on Debian Woody.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Daniel Quintiliani sent in v2.11 of the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6824:200312:dahpibnceeobmhehdekd">Windows Newsreaders under Linux HOWTO</ulink>, which has more info on sounds in Xnews.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>We received v1.4.16 of the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6876:200312:ipgledljmnhigilikgkk">WordPerfect on Linux FAQ</ulink>, maybe in answer to the long discussions about <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6239:200312:bnijmdbhinokiigafgam">TLDP documenting proprietary software</ulink>, and v1.7.4 of the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6877:200312:fmmbocmbfdobkmphigeo">Linux User Group HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Rahul Sundaram has been probing to find co-authors for a really big guide, that would be a sort of always-up-to-date Linux bible, which would connect all TLDP documents, after the example of <ulink url="freebsd.org/handbook">the FreeBSD Handbook</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Chr. Clemens Lee just published v3.0 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Debian-Binary-Package-Building-HOWTO/">Debian Binary Package Building HOWTO</ulink>, which contains minor fixes and applies feedback from readers.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Charles Curley's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-Complete-Backup-and-Recovery-HOWTO/">Linux Complete Backup and Recovery HOWTO</ulink> v1.5 contains notes on Fedora and Grub.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Braun updated the links in v1.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Disk-Encryption-HOWTO/">Disk Encryption HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Binh Nguyen published two updates: v0.63 of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/html/">Linux Filesystem Hierarchy</ulink>, and v0.12 of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/">Linux Dictionary</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>Jamie sets the example</title>
<para>Reviewers are highly in demand, yet we recently had the joy of welcoming a few.  They mysteriously appeared out of nowhere to offer their much-needed services to our project.  One of those new-comers is Jamie Patterson.  Not that long ago, he found the TLDP web site, while looking for Linux documentation.  He must have approved of our system, because he volunteered as a reviewer: <quote>I wanted to help improve and build on the foundation blocks of the ever-expanding Linux Community.</quote></para>
<para>Jamie reviews for content suitability, checks grammar and spelling and, probably the most important thing: ease of reading.  Tabatha, our head-reviewer, thinks he's one of the most faithful reviewers she works with.  However devoted, Jamie can make his voice heard.  As his colleagues say, in an appreciative tone of voice: <quote>He's a little outspoken in his comments.</quote>
</para>
<para>Jamie joined the project only recently, but is already training other reviewers.  Jamie is thirteen years old.  We're told he does a good job.</para>
<para>We also want to welcome the rest of the flock, among others:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Jennifer Riley, with a master's degree in both English and by experience in programming in all kinds of languages, does language review but hopes to start on technical reviewing soon.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emma Jane Hogbin admits that spelling is not her cup of tea, so she does technical reviews.  She is also the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/ACPI-HOWTO/index.html">ACPI HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Doris Cross is getting her own business off the ground, and says that technical editing for TLDP is an asset because it keeps her skills up to date.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="discussions">
<title>Discussions on TLDP lists</title>

<sect2 id="discussion1">
<title>Licensing</title>

<para>As David Lawyer states, the current LDP license contains <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6280:200312:mhljllnlecdgghdoohcl">a loophole</ulink>.</para>
<para>Therefor, Rick Moen wrote a proposal for a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6268:200312:idnijccbcjnijmgbpjbb">new license</ulink> which is now being discussed.  Rick did <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6231:200312:bhlldbihdlbgodochdkp">quite some research</ulink> on the subject of licensing.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="discussion2">
<title>Documenting non-free software?</title>

<para>The <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5875:200312:ihpahginmljdgbhooeje">sponsorship thread</ulink> started last week evolved into a discussion about whether is right to document non-free software, even if it runs on Linux.  However, it was generally agreed that we would have to drop a lot of documents if we were going to be that fierce about the subject.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and Y
Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
