<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>30</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-11-18</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>No new documents this week, but TLDP is preparing for a real freshening up, so be warned!</para>
  
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<para>There were a lot of new proposals this week, for documents (like
the Firewall-HOWTO and the Small Netserver HOWTO) and general structure
of TLDP. A proposal that we got through the feedback mailinglist: Want
to receive TLDP Weekly news issues per E-mail? </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Rick Meyerhoof, whom we know from <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4963:200308:laghddnjpcfalcjhjlal">this
post on the discuss mailinglist</ulink> completed a draft version of the
<ulink
url="http://www.xml-dev.com/xml/LDP/InstallFestHowTo.html">Installfest
HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Larry Lawrence submitted a rather interesting new document, entitled <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6334:200311:lfnabjpfpppbeemhpgcg">Beyond Linux from Scratch Guide</ulink>, which will be a companion guide to the actual <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/lfs/html/index.html">Linux from Scratch Guide</ulink> by Gerard Beekmans.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs and FAQs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>An update of the <ulink url="tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">Linux Documentation Project Reviewer HOWTO</ulink> (v1.2) by David Merrill and Joy Yokley.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Don't throw away old monitors when you upgrade to a bigger one!  Svetoslav Slavtchev explains in his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink> how you can use them to connect up to 16 people to one PC.  v1.3 has some information about installing on Gentoo systems.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Minor editorial updates in v1.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/LDP-FAQ/">LDP FAQ</ulink> by Rahul Sundaram.  If you still don't know what TLDP is about - or if you know people who don't: this is the place to start.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Traffic-Control-HOWTO/">Traffic Control
HOWTO</ulink> updated to v1.0.1 by Martin A. Brown. This version adds a
few links to documentation over v1.0. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Rick Moen sends in the v1.4.15 of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/WordPerfect-Linux-FAQ">WordPerfect on Linux
FAQ</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The two-dot-oh of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Pocket-Linux-Guide/html/">Pocket Linux Guide</ulink> is out.  In this version the GNU coreutils package replaces the fileutils, sh-utils and textutils package.  This and all other packages to build your basic Linux system are compiled from source.  You are guided through the process by David Horton, who takes a step-by-step approach.  You may also expect to find updated version numbers of most source code packages.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>Lampadas update</title>

<para>David Lawyer talked to David Merrill regarding Lampadas. David
Merrill is still working on Lampadas. Lampadas now, is not really
"lampadas" but "plone".  David's lampadas work consists of additions to
plone so that when it's done, lampadas will be part of plone. When it
gets done, we will just need to install plone and we will then have
lampadas. He estimated it will be in Beta in about 6 months from now.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Linuxgazette fork</title>

<para>Thomas Adam on behalf of the editor team of LinuxGazette.net
<ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5279:200311:ceejnklaecengajdijnf">informed
us</ulink> that there was a fork of the popular LinuxGazette magazine
and requested that TLDP should mirror <ulink
url="http://linuxgazette.net">http://linuxgazette.net</ulink>. Rick Moen
<ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5391:200311:pkdleajpekbbaookkgbd">explained</ulink>
the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5357:200311:pkdleajpekbbaookkgbd">reasons</ulink>
for the fork. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Temporary Removal of documents for review</title>

<para>After discussing the quality of Alavoor Vasudevan's HOWTOs, it has
been decided that they should be removed from TLDP collection. Greg
Ferguson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?10:mss:1948:200311:jhkbdaiomgaecfhaaipn">announced</ulink>
the same on the staff mailing list with the mail exchange between TLDP
review coordinator Tabatha and Al Dev. David Lawyer posted a few <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5378:200311:hlplplkejljfgoeoigon">reasons</ulink>
why this was necessary.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>RPM package for LDP author tools</title>

<para>Rodolfo J. Paiz said on <email>docbook@en.tldp.org</email> that
Tom "Spot" Callaway from RedHat would <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?2:mss:605:200311:ehngfbpnepphojhokgdn">help</ulink>
him put together an ldp-author-tools RPM package. This would make it
easier for people running Red Hat, Fedora, Mandrake, or other RPM-based
distros to set up a comfortable working environment to create
documentation for LDP. Rodolfo is interested in feedback regarding the
what the contents of the package should be and can be reached via
<email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Updated LDP-Author-Guide</title>

<para>Emma Jane Hogbin <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5314:200311:ikndjmbepldekebhjjej">posted</ulink>
an update to the LDP Author Guide. The <ulink
url="http://xtrinsic.com/geek/articles/LDP-Author-Guide.html">single
HTML file version</ulink> is available for a week at her site, but the
<ulink
url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/LDP-Author-Guide/">XML
sources</ulink> have been changed again already. The Author Guide is no
longer a <quote>How to write DocBook documents for the LDP</quote>. Emma
spent considerable time working on this and also posted a TODO list for
the guide in her mail. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>TWiki advocacy for TLDP</title>

<para>Randy Kramer posted a long mail about <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5302:200311:ciimdfbjcapnnnjhofpp">Using
A Wiki (TWiki) at LDP</ulink>. Randy wanted to respond to Rodolfo's
questions. His answers are also available in Wiki form at the <ulink
url="http://twiki.org/cgi-bin/view/Wikilearn/TWikiAdvocacyForTheLdp">Wiki
Advocacy For The LDP</ulink> site. </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. If you want to help TLDP,
take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/">tasks
page</ulink>, and consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and Y
Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
