<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>30</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-11-18</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>No new documents this week, but TLDP is preparing for a real freshening up, so be warned!</para>
  
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>
<para>There were a lot of new proposals this week, for documents and general structure of TLDP.  A proposal that we got through the feedback mailinglist: do you want to receive TLDP Weekly news issues per E-mail?  More new ideas that came sprouting up this week in the next sections!
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Rick Meyerhoof, whom we know from <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4963:200308:laghddnjpcfalcjhjlal">this post on the discuss mailinglist</ulink> completed a draft version of the <ulink url="http://www.xml-dev.com/xml/LDP/InstallFestHowTo.html">Installfest HOWTO</ulink>.<para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Larry Lawrence submitted a rather interesting new document, entitled <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6334:200311:lfnabjpfpppbeemhpgcg">Beyond Linux from Scratch Guide</ulink>, which will be a companion guide to the actual <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/lfs/html/index.html">Linux from Scratch Guide</ulink> by Gerard Beekmans.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs and FAQs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>We start off this list with a long-needed update of the <ulink url="tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">Linux Documentation Project Reviewer HOWTO</ulink> (v1.2) by David Merrill and Joy Yokley.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Don't throw away old monitors when you upgrade to a bigger one!  Svetoslav Slavtchev explains in his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink> how you can use them to connect up to 16 people to one PC.  v1.3 has some information about installing on Gentoo systems.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Minor editorial updates in v1.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/LDP-FAQ/">LDP FAQ</ulink> by Rahul Sundaram.  If you still don't know what TLDP is about - or if you know people who don't: this is the place to start.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The two-dot-oh of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Pocket-Linux-Guide/html/">Pocket Linux Guide</ulink> is out.  In this version the GNU coreutils package replaces the fileutils, sh-utils and textutils package.  This and all other packages to build your basic Linux system are compiled from source.  You are guided through the process by David Horton, who takes a step-by-step aproach.  You may also expect to find updated version numbers of most source code packages.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<para>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Discussion Summary 1</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Discussion Summary 2</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>News Item 1</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. If you want to help TLDP,
take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/">tasks
page</ulink>, and consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
