<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>33</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-12-10</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

<para>Lars Starnd is the author of our starring document this week, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO/">Mobile IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>.  He describes how to configure mobile computers, such as laptops and PDAs, for actual mobile use with IPv6.  You need a fully functional IPv6 network; how to set this up is discussed in the <ulink url="http://ldp.linux.no/HOWTO/Linux+IPv6-HOWTO/">IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>.  You'll need to patch kernels.  We know the Kernel HOWTO is in review, but!  1.  Lars gives a step-by-step explanation and 2. you may find the same information in <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/ACPI-HOWTO/">the ACPI HOWTO</ulink>.  Our reviewers are working on the Kernel HOWTO as fast as they can, there's already <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5812:200312:becpbdgagpneamchdggc">a draft for the new Kernel HOWTO</ulink>.</para>
  

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The Skoric tripplet, we'll call them:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink>, v1.28, covers the installation, configuration and use of the popular packet-radio BBS server software FBB.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>While GRUB is a wonderful thing (<quote>uses a Bash-like interface</quote>), LILO is the most popular Linux boot loader.  The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink> is a supplement to the <ulink url="http://www-user.tu-chemnitz.de/~mibe/linux/lilo/user/">LILO User Guide</ulink>, for those who want a quick start or a short overview.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Details for starting Windows NT from LILO can be found in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Alex Weeks is updating the Linux System Administrator's Guide or SAG.  Here are the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/sag/html/">first results</ulink>, including a new part about NTP, the Network Time Protocol.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>Jamie sets the example</title>

<para>Reviewers are highly in demand, yet we recently had the joy of welcoming a few.  They mysteriously appeared out of nowhere to offer their much-needed services to our project.  One of those new-comers is Jamie Patterson.  Not that long ago, he found the TLDP web site, while looking for Linux documentation.  He must have approved of our system, because he volunteered as a reviewer: <quote>I wanted to help improve and build on the foundation blocks of the ever-expanding Linux Community.</quote></para>
<para>Jamie reviews for content suitability, checks grammar and spelling and, probably the most important thing: ease of reading.  Tabatha, our head-reviewer, thinks he's one of the most faithful reviewers she works with.  However devoted, Jamie can make his voice heard.  As his colleagues say, in an appreciative tone of voice: <quote>He's a little outspoken in his comments.</quote>
</para>
<para>Jamie joined the project only recently, but is already training other reviewers.  Jamie is thirteen years old.</para> 
<para>We also want to welcome the rest of the flock, among others:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Jennifer Riley, with a master's degree in both English and by experience in programming in all kinds of languages, does language review but hopes to start on technical reviewing soon.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emma Jane Hogbin admits that spelling is not her cup of tea, so she does technical reviews.  She is also the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/ACPI-HOWTO/index.html">ACPI HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Doris Cross is getting her own business off the ground, and says that technical editing for TLDP is an asset because it keeps her skills up to date.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item2">
<title>News item 2</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item3">
<title>News item 3</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="discussions">
<title>Discussions on TLDP lists</title>

<sect2 id="discussion1">
<title>Discussion topic 1</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="discussion2">
<title>Discussion topic 2</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="discussion3">
<title>Discussion topic 3</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="interview">
<title>Interview with Abc Xyz</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and Y
Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
