<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>13</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-07-22</pubdate>
  <title>TLDP Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The third revision of Howard Shane's <ulink url="http://66.25.191.66/docs/HOWTOS/Scanner/index.html">Scanner HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The SSL section of the HOWTO on <ulink url="http://www.xml-dev.com:8080/cocoon/mount/docbook/Apache-WebDAV-LDAP-HOWTO.html#ssl">Apache based WebDAV Server with LDAP and SSL</ulink> by Saqib N. Ali.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>After much discussions on the mailing lists, having overcome loads of practical problems, Binh Nguyen submitted the Linux Dictionary. The document has been published as one huge section containing an itemized list. <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4751:200307:emedbeghhljpgceecnlp">Discussions</ulink> <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4755:200307:kbpdbbmeddmahbikkfbi">are on</ulink> as to how to make the resource more "usable".
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>If you want to do strange things with strange video hardware, such as working with very high or very low resolutions which are not supported by
default in the standard XFree86 package, Eric Steven Raymond's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/">XFree86 Video Timings HOWTO</ulink> might be helpful.  However, check with <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/obsolete.html">Chapter 2</ulink> first to see whether there's not a more elegant alternative available.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Saqib Ali's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO/">DocBook XML/SGML Processing Using OpenJade</ulink> documentation v2.2.8 now includes additional information for Cocoon, the Apache XML publishing framework, which can be integrated with Tomcat, the Java servlet container, to set up your state-of-the-art application server.  The important thing is to keep your JRE up to date!</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Stephen Darlington's <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Oracle-8-HOWTO.html">Oracle 8i for Linux Installation HOWTO</ulink> is now v1.18.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/mini/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink> by Miroslav "Misko" Skoric is at v1.21</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels updated the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/">Introduction to Linux - A Hands on Guide</ulink> to v1.6 with a few corrections in the initial chapters.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>The LDP Team at Metz 2003</title>

<para>For those who might be interested, Greg Ferguson has sent in a link to a <ulink url="http://externe.net/photos/rmll-2003/tldp_team">picture of the LDP team</ulink> on Guylhem Aznar's site.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>OpenOffice.org 1.1RC & DocBook</title>

<para>Charles Curley installed OpenOffice.org 1.1RC and wrote a very simple test document in OOo's native format and posted his <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4743:200307:fbacfjfdkmpbdhgmbbhp">notes</ulink> regarding the same. While on thread, Chris Karakas <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4746:200307:elfkhmdcfpcflhjkhpgf">said that</ulink> he would document the procedure of writing the entire document in LyX, exporting it to SGML and post-processing to convert it to various formats.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Linux One Stanza Tips (LOST)</title>

<para>The <ulink url="http://lost.sourceforge.net/">LOST (Linux One Stanza Tips)</ulink> project is a series of small Linux related hints and tips and a set of scripts/programs for interfacing the snippets with existing mailers and web pages. The LOST project was born in the Linux-India-Help mailing list in Aug 2001 because the developers of the project felt that as newbies join the list, the same queries are floated time and again.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>
You can help The Linux Documentation Project by:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Reviewing one of the draft versions of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">documents in progress</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Picking up one of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained documents</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Providing assistance with <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/markup.html">markup</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Purchasing a <ulink url="http://www.hackerthreads.com/cgi-bin/SoftCart.100.exe/scstore/tldpstore.htm?E+scstore">TLDP Shirt</ulink>. A part of the amount paid would be donated to the LDP.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Please help us create this weekly newsletter. Seen a site putting
in a story with a link to the LDP? Completed the translation of any
HOWTO?  Know of any articles about the LDP published in newspapers or
magazines? You can update us by sending in links and information at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>
</sect1>
</article>

