<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>32</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-12-03</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
<title>Proposed New Documents</title>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Adrian Offerman <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5788:200312:jlfmbikdfdgefloammhm">proposed</ulink> to submit the Tomcat and MMBase HOWTO that he is working on to The LDP. The document would describe installation on Red Hat, and the integration with Apache and MySQL. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>  

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>If the DocBook/XML/SGML wealth of tags overwhelms you, try David Lawyer's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Howtos-with-LinuxDoc.html">HOWTOs with LinuxDoc mini-HOWTO</ulink>, v0.02.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Diego Bravo Estrada finished the <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Manuales-LuCAS/doc-guia-sendmail/">Tutorial de Sendmail</ulink> (in Spanish), explaining how to get started with sendmail on RedHat-based systems.  Of course, with a bit of inspiration, you will also get other types of Linux to work with sendmail, using the information in this tutorial.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Also new from <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org">es.tldp.org</ulink> is the <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Manuales-LuCAS/doc-gcc-inline/doc-gcc-inline-html/">Gcc Inline Assembly HOWTO</ulink>.  While Martin Gundarra, the author, greatly appreciates the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gcc/onlinedocs/">official GCC documentation</ulink>, he would like to further facilitate access to the GNU Compiler suite with this Spanish document.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Christophe Devine adds sections on support for Grub in his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Encrypted-Root-Filesystem-HOWTO/">Encrypted Root Filesystem HOWTO</ulink> now at v1.1. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>EVMS integrates all aspects of volume management, such as partitioning, logical volume management and multi-disk management in one interface.  And who said Linux is not userfriendly?  For the click-and-pointers there's the EVMS GUI interface and the package offers an ncurses-based GUI for the intermediate system administrator.  Of course, professionals do it with the command line.  Execution of volume management related tasks is explained using these three interfaces.  Version 2.0 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/EVMSUG/html/index.html">EVMS User Guide</ulink> is still maintained by Christine Lorenz, Joy Godreau and Kylie Smith and certainly worth a check.  Unfortunately there's no revision log, but we can see from CVS that a lot of chapters have been updated.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels updated the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/index.html">Introduction to Linux, A Hands on Guide</ulink> to v1.8 with minor modifications. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>WHATIS documents</title>

<para>John R. Daily <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5728:200311:cjacdkoodeefcahlogcd">said</ulink> that there might be value to having small documents available as part of the LDP library that describe key concepts like DNS, the TCP/IP protocol, init scripts, DTDs, shared libraries. The ones that have surely been described repeatedly so that new text need not be invented in the HOWTOs. Martin WHEELER delighted and <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5737:200311:kbpdbbmeddmahbikkfbi">asked</ulink> if someone could setup a wiki somewhere, one page per WHATIS. David Lawyers <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5747:200311:claiepedajakajhoajgg">opinion</ulink> was that there should be a WHATIS co-ordinator and a way to handle many of these WHATIS documents.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. If you want to help TLDP,
take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/">tasks
page</ulink>, and consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and Y
Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
