<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>22</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-09-24</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>Nothing fresh this week.</para>
  
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Kian Spongsveen wrote a HOWTO about the Sybase adaptive Server Enterprise/SQL Server.  Kian is <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5869:200309:fgbnljckgaccipaeaaio">sort of complaining</ulink> that his document did get reviewed by some people, but these reviewers didn't send him any comment.  If you review documents from time to time, please tell the author about it.  Even if it seems a good document that nears publication or that is already published.  Authors like to know about the little things.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Lawyer sent in <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5870:200309:hkdcjikjonpenahbbagh">the Serial HOWTO</ulink>, now v2.19.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>No complaints about Dabiel Quintiliani's proposal to rename his HOWTO.  V2.0 is entitled the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Windows-Newsreaders-under-Linux-HOWTO/">Windows Newsreaders under Linux HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Svetoslav Slavtchev provides us with v 1.2 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If your music files start taking up too much hard disk space, you might want to look into Greg Wierzchowski's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MP3-CD-Burning/">Linux MP3 CD Burning mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Our German collegues finished the <ulink url="http://www.linuxhaven.de/dlhp/HOWTO/DE-Netzwerk-HOWTO.html">translation of the Networking HOWTO</ulink>, v1.7.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels kind of forgot to send us the most recent versions of her guide during the summertime, so here's the official leap to v1.8 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/index.html">Introduction to Linux - A Hands on Guide</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2><title>Miscelleaneous</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>David C. Merrill sent in v2.1.1 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/Linux-FAQ/">Linux FAQ</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Our Spanish collegues have a couple of news items as well, amongs which the transcripts a speech about Open Source in the Administration, that was given at a conference.  Find out more at <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org" />!</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>This week, patentable software will be discussed again in the European Parliament.  The European government wanted to allow patents, but thanks to a lot of volunteers sending protests to their representatives, this has not happened yet.  Still, these are scary days.  This news item was brought to our attention by our Italian colleagues over at <ulink url="http://ildp.pluto.linux.it/" />.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<para>There are a couple of discussions still going on from last week, and some new items.  Join our discussion list for more!</para>

<sect2>
<title>Wikis and copyrights</title>

<para>Chris Karakas, maintainer of the PHP-Nuke HOWTO, wants to put the information he manages in a Wiki clone, but he is afraid he'll have to abandon his copyright if he lets other people edit the same data.  David Lawyer points out that <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5008:200309:ehdpgomfieohmamemmjk">every copyright should have an owner</ulink>.</para>
<para>The idea came up to donate this PHP-Nuke Wiki to the Free Software Foundation and let them have the copyright, but it was decided that this would be too complicated and too much honor for a Wiki.  The <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5023:200309:ehdpgomfieohmamemmjk">concensus now</ulink> is that everybody contributing to the Wiki makes themselves co-owner of the copyright.</para>


</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Tenth anniversary</title>

<para>TLDP staff has been preparing an announcement which will be sent out to a number of organizations, such as the Linux Weekly News, Slashdot and many more.  You have until next Sunday to send in any comments you may have on this announcement.  <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5021:200309:fhmfikojcekoaemohkge">Here is the preview!</ulink></para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. You
can help TLDP by: Reviewing one of the draft versions of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">documents in
progress</ulink>, or picking up one of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained
documents</ulink> and reviving it or providing assistance with <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/markup.html">markup</ulink>. You are
welcome to participate in TLDP discussions by joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. Announcements about TLDP
are made at <email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this weekly newsletter. We need volunteers who
follow the community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and
report events related to The Linux Documentation Project. Please update
us by sending in the information and links to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
