<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>13</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-07-21</pubdate>
  <title>TLDP Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>Nihil nove sub sole (Nothing new under the sun).</para>
  
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>
<para>It's just too hot, I guess...</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>After much discussions on the mailinglists, having overcome loads of practical problems and having sched a lot of blood and sweat, and probably
after some cursing as well, Binh Nguyen submitted the Linux Dictionary.  But however curious you might be (we are, anyway), there's something about the link that makes some browsers crash, so we'd rather wait and have this fixed before linking to this document.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Cluster-HOWTO.html">Cluster HOWTO</ulink>, v1.1 by Ram Samudrala, provides a general view on Linux clustering hardware and software, and discusses basic setup and maintenance of clusters.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If you combine Samba's PDC features with iptables, you get <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO.html">a Samba Authenticated Gateway</ulink>.  The HOWTO by Ricardo Alexandre Mattar is now at v1.1.1.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Svetoslav Slavtchev's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink> is getting over the
child deseases with v1.1.0.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>H&#229;vard Stranden found another way of getting ATI Radeon cards to work with XFree and discusses this in v1.2 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/mini/XFree86-R200/">ATI R200 + XFree86 4.x mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If you want to do strange things with strange video hardware, such as working with very high or very low resolutions which are not supported by
default in the standard XFree86 package, Eric Steven Raymond's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/">XFree86 Video Timings HOWTO</ulink> might be helpful.  However, check with <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Video-Timings-HOWTO/obsolete.html">Chapter 2</ulink> first to see whether there's not a more elegant alternative available.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Saqib Ali's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO/">DocBook XML/SGML Processing Using OpenJade</ulink> documentation v2.2.8 now includes additional information for Cocoon, the Apache XML publishing framework, which can be integrated with Tomcat, the Java servlet container, to set up your state-of-the-art application server.  The important thing is to keep your JRE up to date!</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Stephen Darlington's <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Oracle-8-HOWTO.html">Oracle 8i for Linux Installation HOWTO</ulink> is now v1.18.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Various</title>
<para>Did you know we have <ulink url="http://www.hackerthreads.com/cgi-bin/SoftCart.100.exe/scstore/tldpstore.htm?E+scstore">TLDP T-shirts</ulink>?  From Small to XXL, in white and grey, for all your casual comfort.  If you need to go for
city wear, our penguin poses stylishly on a white or stone-coloured polo shirt.</para>
</sect2>
  

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<para>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Title1</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Title2</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Title3</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>
You can help The Linux Documentation Project by:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Reviewing one of the draft versions of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">documents in progress</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Picking up one of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained documents</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Providing assitance with <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/markup.html">markup</ulink>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>Please help us create this weekly newsletter. Seen a site putting
in a story with a link to the LDP? Completed the translation of any
HOWTO?  Know of any articles about the LDP published in newspapers or
magazines? You can update us by sending in links and information at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>
</sect1>
</article>

