<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>2</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-04-29</pubdate>
  <title>TLDP Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>The one-dot-ohs for this week:</para>
  
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The Deciding-Linux-HOWTO by Rahul Sundaram helps you decide whether Linux is the right operating system for you.  Should you still be in doubt, <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Deciding-Linux-HOWTO/" /> is the place to be.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>A new guide saw the light this week: the Win+BSD+Linux Installation Guide explains how to make these three systems live together on one system.  Subhasish Ghosh is waiting for your comments: <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Win+BSD+Linux-Install/html/" />.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Should there be an <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4294:200304:lpikjdgjjahjolggllhl">international technology base</ulink> for UNIX/POSIX technology?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<para>There were no documents submitted for review this week, so you all have time to look into the updates of existing HOWTOs and guides ;-)</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>
<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ricardo Alexandra Mattar sent in v1.0.2 of the Samba Authenticated Gateway HOWTO, which is now in the HOWTO section at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO.html" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Alavoor Vasudevan now has v.16.3 of the C-C++ Beautifier HOWTO available in DocBook format from <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/C-C++Beautifier-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The Linux Kernel HOWTO was also converted to DocBook, that was v5.5, but v5.6 is the latest now, see <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO by Saqib Ali was released in v2.2.4, read more at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>John Huggins wasn't quite sure of last week's update for the Linux Astronomy HOWTO, so he posted some additions, which you can check out in v1.44 at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Astronomy-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Charles Curley submitted the Linux Complete Backup and Recovery HOWTO, v1.3, which is now available from <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-Complete-Backup-and-Recovery-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Eric S. Raymond must have got a lot of comment on the 1.0 release of the Linksys Blue Box Router HOWTO last week, 'cause here is v1.1: <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linksys-Blue-Box-Router-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The latest version of the openMosix-HOWTO, v0.7 got translated into Spanish, read it at <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Manuales-LuCAS/manual-openMosix-ES/manual-openMosixES_0.7beta-html/" />.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Matthew P. Barnson announced v2.16.3 of the Bugzilla Guide, a comprehensive guide discussing the most popular Open Source bug-tracking system.  Read everything about it at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/bugzilla/Bugzilla-Guide/" />.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>
                                  
<sect1>
<title>News from the LDP mailing lists</title>

<sect2>
	<title>Is the Gnu Free Documentation License (GFDL) free or not?</title>

	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4261:200304:daodcainiabimpblanlg">Sergiusz Pawlowicz</ulink> found a <ulink url="http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=03/04/20/1357236"> discussion on a different list</ulink> on legal issues around the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html">GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL)</ulink> and the Debian project declaring this license non-free.</para>
	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4262:200304:daodcainiabimpblanlg">Colin Watson</ulink> pointed out that this discussion was just affecting version 1.2 of GFDL; not the much more widely used version 1.1. He suggested authors should stick with GFDL 1.1 for the time being.</para>
	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4264:200304:lmhfnpcknmcmihlmfonf">David Lawyer</ulink> mentioned the issue that the license requires a copy of itself to be in any copy of the document that is licensed under it, a practice frequently omitted by the author. But he held that this would usually not be a real-world legal issue as there will be no judge as long as nobody is suing.</para>
	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4265:200304:lmhfnpcknmcmihlmfonf">Charles Curley</ulink>suggested that people who have objections against version 1.2 of GFDL should not only raise them but come up with proposals for amelioration.</para> 

</sect2>

<sect2>
	<title>Full Indic support for Mozilla</title>
	
	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4263:200304:anjffjneljjaddhemmnk">Edward Cherlin</ulink> is working on the <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org">Mozilla project</ulink>. He would like to introduce full Indic support in Mozilla and is therefore looking to get in contact with font developers and probably other people that might be able to help with this.</para>
	</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
	<title>Free Multilingual Technology Base</title>

	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4294:200304:lpikjdgjjahjolggllhl">Alexander Voropay</ulink> is asking if anyone knows about a software to build a free multilingual technology base that would probably serve the LDP translation project as well as other i18n projects very well (and might free all the non-english speakers of sometimes bad to just not understandable translations of terms).</para>
	<para><ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4296:200304:lpikjdgjjahjolggllhl">Binh</ulink> is working on something like that in his/her spare time and has already collected a few 10,000 words, which could be released to the LDP in the near future.</para>
	<para>Note from the editor: How about an international firstname directory that would provide for a gender lookup. There are names I just can't tell if they are male or female. Apologies if the editors of this news ever mess with you first name.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1><title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>Please help us create this weekly newsletter. Seen a site putting in a
story with a link to the LDP? Completed the translation of any HOWTO?
Know of any articles about the LDP published in newspapers or magazines?
We are not curious, just inquisitive ;-). You can help us by sending in
links and information at <email><ulink url="mailto:feedback(at)en.tldp.org">feedback@en.tldp.org</ulink></email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>
</article>
