<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>23</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-09-30</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para></para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Announcing the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Sybase-ASE-HOWTO/">Sybase ASE HOWTO</ulink> v1.0 by Kian Spongsveen.  The full name for this document is the Sybase Adaptive Server Enterprise/SQL Server HOWTO; it describes the installation and basic usage of this database on the Linux platform.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If privacy is an issue for you, check out our second new document this week: the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Encrypted-Root-Filesystem-HOWTO/">Encrypted Root Filesystem HOWTO</ulink> by Christophe Devine.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Pramode C.E. sent in a document entitled <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5924:200309:pgieheipbecfpcodijdd">Linux Kernel Commentary</ulink> and awaits your remarks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Scot W. Stevenson sent in his <ulink
url="http://www.possum.in-berlin.de/scot/mock_mainframe_howto_20030928.html">Mock
Mainframe Mini-HOWTO</ulink>, which would be <quote>A brief description
of a standard way to set up and work with a computer network for a small
group of people that is inexpensive to build, easy to administer, and
relatively safe. It is written for users who might not be completely
familiar with all of the concepts involved</quote>. Scott has requested
for comments on this document</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels submitted the <ulink
url="http://tille.soti.org/training/ldap/">LDAP Operations / Management
HOWTO</ulink> and welcomes any comments you may have.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>We received update v2.19 of David Lawyer's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Serial-HOWTO.html">Serial HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>H&#134;vard Stranden provided us with v1.3.1 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-R200/">ATI R200 + XFree86 4.x mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/User-Group-HOWTO.html">Linux User Group HOWTO</ulink> by Rick Moen is now at v1.6.8.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Svetoslav Slavtchev's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink> was updated to v1.2.1.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Alavoor Vasudevan sent in v6.9 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO/">Kernel HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>David S. Lawyer's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Text-Terminal-HOWTO.html">Text-Terminal-HOWTO</ulink>
is now at v1.32</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Win+BSD+Linux-Install/html/">Windows+BSD+Linux
Installation Guide</ulink> by Subhasish Ghosh has been updated to
v1.1.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>
  
<sect1>
<title>Interview - Sergiusz Pawlowicz</title>

<para>Sergiusz Pawlowicz (or Serek as a few people call him) has been
into Linux and Free Software  ever since 1994, almost ten years.  For nearly as long, he has been one of the thriving forces behind the Polish translation effort.  When he's not administering our mailing-lists or the CVS, he manages his company, <ulink url="http://www.a-k-f.com/" />.</para>
<figure><title>Sergiusz Pawlowicz, CVS and mailing-list administrator</title>
<mediaobject>

<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Sergiusz.eps" format="EPS"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Sergiusz.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
</imageobject>

</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para><emphasis>Q: So, Sergiusz, after all this time, do you remember how you got involved with TLDP?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: I wrote Paul Jones, that I would like to help with LDP,
and I also proposed to switch our document management system to CVS. Because I'm also 
into the development of the <ulink url="http://docs.pld-linux.org/">PLD Linux Distro</ulink>, I was very experienced in using versioning systems in big scale.
As you can see, my proposition was accepted :-)
</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: Apart from TLDP and PLD, you're involved in a number of other Open Source projects: the Free Software Foundation, you translate for the GNU project, ...  And I know from my own experience that you take great care and that people can rely on you.  Do you ever take a day off?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: Yeah, my girlfriend is rather unhappy. It is a real problem.  But community service is stronger than me. It is fascinating
when you have a real influence on political and sociological
aspects of informatics.</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: Is there anything you want to share with the world that you cannot add to one of the Open Source projects you are involved with, such as the Polish Cooking HOWTO, maybe, or the Polish Traditional Woodwork FAQ?  This is your chance to have your deepest wish heard ;-)</emphasis></para>
<para>A: Yeah - <quote>HOWTO to stand up and turn off TV</quote>.  It really gives me the creeps to see that so many people are in an <quote>idle state</quote> and just watch television.  Without adding anything to society, while listening to information prepared
by Public Relations in big concerns, they are empty-headed.</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: In your opinion, what makes TLDP so interesting?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: The most interesting thing in TLDP is that everyone can join us!</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: How do you say <quote>If all else fails, read the HOWTO</quote> in Polish?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: Hehe, you won't believe how strange it sounds, I better not answer this one ;-)</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>Software patents in Europe</title>

<para>Since TLDP provides documentation on free software, a lot of our readers have been concerned about the pushing of software patents in Europe lately.  Thanks to all of you who wrote to their representatives in the European Parliament, the worst case scenario was avoided.  Because of this good news, a lot of Open Source sites have been re-opened last week.  However, the decision has only been postponed, and danger of restriction is still pending.  Read more at <ulink url="http://swpat.ffii.org/" />.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>LDP documentation format</title>

<para>Once in a while, we are reminded of the fact that the LDP caters
to the needs of all the people. The usefulness of the format and clean
design used by LDP
for publishing various HOWTOs has come up yet again <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5040:200309:cejchjflkempalkhifck">in
this mail</ulink> from David Lawyer and <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5035:200309:igepobcinopoifmhjadg">this
one</ulink> from Machtelt Garrels.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Search capability for XML docs using Lucene</title>

<para>Saqib Ali was working on adding search capabilities to an
application that he was working on and <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5053:200309:icjmgahabpdlipbhobhb">wondered</ulink>
if there would any interest if in indexing all TLDP XML documents using
Lucene. He already has an implementation of cocoon running to present
Docbook XML documents as at <ulink
url="http://www.xml-dev.com:8080/cocoon/mount/docbook/Apache-WebDAV-LDAP-HOWTO.html">Apache-WebDAV-LDAP-HOWTO</ulink>
and is planning to add the indexing and search part using Lucene.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. You can help TLDP by:
Reviewing a <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">document in
progress</ulink>, reviving an <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained
document</ulink> or providing assistance with <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/markup.html">markup</ulink>. You are
welcome to participate in TLDP discussions at
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Please send in any such
information to <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
