<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>9</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-06-17</pubdate>
  <title>TLDP Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>History of The LDP</title>
<para>let us see what we can find about 10 years of writing docs by volunteers.</para>
<para>As Matt Welsh, one of the co-founders, puts it: <quote>The history of the LDP is a pretty murky memory these days.</quote>  It started in 1992, before the World Wide Web existed - hard to imagine how we did without HTML, but in those days almost everything was FTP and Usenet, and dial-in to a BBS most likely.  In the beginning, most of the documentation was in one big file, split up in sections, called the <emphasis>Linux FAQ</emphasis>.  But as Linux capabilities grew, it was no longer possible for one person to maintain it, and pretty soon not even for several people to manage the job.  Thus the HOWTOs were born, each describing a part of the original big chunk of information, an easily extendible system that allowed for many authors to contribute their part in their area of specialization.</para>
<para>That effort lead to the use of SGML, allowing for fast generation of all sorts of output formats, including HTML, from one source file or set of files.  The first tests were conducted at Sunsite (a famous server machine at the University of North Carolina), which was the first web site offering information about Linux.  Also when you wanted to download Linux software, sunsite.unc.edu was the place to go.  It still contains some kernel archives - probably by accident, there are also a lot of empty directories these days.</para>
<para>Before the crash last month I was able to find, via FTP, a document referring to two maintainers of the LDP as it was ran by the end of 1994 at UNC.  It pointed to Jon Magid and a mysterious Erik with no last name, who was still at Sunsite in 1996.  Will his last name be revealed in the next edition?  Check it out next week!</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Sven Linker <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4596:200306:giaipgnmlbppaelhfenf">offered</ulink> to translate the Wake-on-LAN-HOWTO into German, and wanted to know if anybody is already doing this.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Emma Jane Hogbin is working on a <ulink url="http://xtrinsic.com/geek/articles/acpi.phtml">ACPI HOWTO</ulink> and is interested in receiving feedback.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Daniel Nofftz submitted an <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5127:200306:ocohcdbfahehmdnmmika">Athlon-Powersaving HOWTO</ulink>, which is ready for comments.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>
<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>We received the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/CSPM-HOWTO/">Complete System Performance Monitor HOWTO</ulink> v2.0, by Chris Lorenz.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Werner Heuser sent in v3.6 of his <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Infrared-HOWTO/">Linux Infrared HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Vivek Venugopalan fixed some dead links in the text of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/REF/CVS-BestPractices/html/">CVS Best Practices</ulink> to update it to v0.6, worth a read if you're using our TLDP CVS system or when setting up your own.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels sent in the v1.5 of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/">Introduction to Linux -
A Hands on Guide</ulink>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>FAQs</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>David Merrill submitted the reorganized <ulink url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/Linux-FAQ/">Linux FAQ</ulink> now at v2.1.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>Italian LDP effort</title>

<para>They have been around for a while, but now they've officially joined the LDP: A warm welcome please, for our Italian colleagues from <ulink url="http://ildp.pluto.linux.it/">ILDP and the Pluto Linux User Group</ulink>!</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Updating LDP XSLT stylesheets</title>

<para>

Dan York sent in a message to the <email>docbook@en.tldp.org</email>
list <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?2:mss:407:200306:cocahfbmmomdmigpcjgm">inviting
volunteers</ulink> for testing and updating the LDP XSLT stylesheets
with the latest version (1.16.2) of the DocBook stylesheets. The LDP
stylesheets are based on version 1.44, which apparently do not work,
because, the way documentation in the standard stylesheets is done has
changed. If you are interested in doing this, you might like
to help David Horton who has <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?2:mss:423:200306:mllcepbomdkmklcadjai">volunteered</ulink>
to do this.

</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>HTML to DocBook equivalents</title>
<para>

If you have just started using DocBook and you are looking for DocBook
equivalents of HTML tags, Martin A.  Brown's <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?2:mss:409:200306:ojenlikbehfnljafjfmh">short
help with examples</ulink> should be useful. The DocBook tags are
of-course available from <ulink
url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/documentation/reference/html/docbook.html">DocBook: The Definitive Guide</ulink>.

</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Update on Lampadas</title>

<para>

David Merrill <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4581:200306:pdldkklajacikgojadpf">sent
in a mail</ulink> inviting an IRC discussion on <ulink
url="http://www.lampadas.org/">Lampadas</ulink> for discussing (1)
<ulink url="http://www.plone.org/">Plone</ulink> work, (2) a possible
resurrection of the old Lampadas mod_python code but with a much more
limited scope and (3) any other concerns you have. David Lawyer <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4590:200306:claiepedajakajhoajgg">was
of the opinion</ulink> that new volunteers could be of help with
Lampadas provided they done some programming in the past. Elsewhere, to
David Merrill's comment that he would like to modify the CMF to use a
plugin system for raw content, Nicolas Chauvat <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4595:200306:nibfaikpkkpacdojonbm">said</ulink>
that David Merrill should not try doing it on his own but needs
co-ordination, because, plone has OpenOffice support and was progressing
at a very fast pace.

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>Please help us create this weekly newsletter. Seen a site putting
in a story with a link to the LDP? Completed the translation of any
HOWTO? Know of any articles about the LDP published in newspapers or
magazines? You can update us by sending in links and information at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>
</sect1>

</article>
