<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>ii</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-09-30</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para></para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>We're proud to announce the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Sybase-ASE-HOWTO/">Sybase ACE HOWTO</ulink> v1.0 by Kian Spongsveen.  The full name for this document is the Sybase Adaptive Server Enterprise/SQL Server HOWTO; it describes the installation and basic usage of this database on the Linux platform.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If privacy is an issue for you, check out our second new document this week: the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Encrypted-Root-Filesystem-HOWTO/">Encrypted Root Filesystem HOWTO</ulink> by Christophe Devine.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Pramode C.E. sent in a document entitled <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:5924:200309:pgieheipbecfpcodijdd">Linux Kernel Commentary</ulink> and awaits your remarks.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels submitted the <ulink url="http://tille.soti.org/training/ldap/">LDAP Operations HOWTO</ulink> or LDAP Management HOWTO (the name is not yet decided on) and welcomes any comments you may have.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>We received update v2.19 of David Lawyer's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Serial-HOWTO.html">Serial HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>H&#134;vard Stranden provided us with v1.3.1 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-R200/">ATI R200 + XFree86 4.x mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/User-Group-HOWTO.html">Linux User Group HOWTO</ulink> by Rick Moen is now at v1.6.8.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Svetoslav Slavtchev's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink> was updated to v1.2.1.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Alavoor Vasudevan sent in v6.9 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Kernel-HOWTO/">Kernel HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Various</title>

<para>Sergiusz Pawlowicz has been into Linux and Open Source ever since 1994, almost ten years.  For nearly as long, he has been one of the thriving forces behind the Polish translation effort.  When he's not administering our mailinglists or the CVS, he manages his company, <ulink url="http://www.a-k-f.com/" />.</para>
<figure><title>Sergiusz Pawlowicz, CVS and mailinglist administrator</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Sergiusz.eps" format="EPS"></imagedata></imageobject><imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Sergiusz.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para><emphasis>Q: So, Sergiusz, after all this time, do you remember how you got involved with TLDP?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: I wrote Paul Jones, that I would like to help with LDP,
and I also proposed to switch our document management system to CVS. Because I'm also 
into the developement of the <ulink url="http://docs.pld-linux.org/">PLD Linux Distro</ulink>, I was very expirienced in using versioning systems in big scale.
As you can see, my proposition was accepted :-)
</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: Apart from TLDP and PLD, you're involved in a number of other Open Source projects: the Free Software Foundation, you translate for the GNU project, ...  And I know from my own experience that you take great care and that people can rely on you.  Do you ever take a day off?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: Yeah, my girlfriend is rather unhappy. It is a real problem.  But community service is stronger than me. It is fascinating
when you have a real influence on political and sociological
aspects of informatics.</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: Is there anything you want to share with the world that you cannot add to one of the Open Source projects you are involved with, such as the Polish Cooking HOWTO, maybe, or the Polish Traditional Woodwork FAQ?  This is your chance to have your deepest wish heard ;-)</emphasis></para>
<para>A: Yeah - <quote>HOWTO to stand up and turn off TV</quote>.  It really gives me the creeps to see that so many people are in an <quote>idle state</quote> and just watch television.  Without adding anything to society, while listening to information prepared
by Public Relations in big concerns, they are empty-headed.</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: In your opinion, what makes TLDP so interesting?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: The most interesting thing in TLDP is that everyone can join us!</para>
<para><emphasis>Q: How do you say <quote>If all else fails, read the HOWTO</quote> in Polish?</emphasis></para>
<para>A: Hehe, you won't believe how strange it sounds, I better not answer this one ;-)</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<para>.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Software patents in Europe</title>

<para>Since TLDP provides documentation on free software, a lot of our readers have been concerned about the pushing of software patents in Europe lately.  Thanks to all of you who wrote to their representatives in the European Parlement, the worst case scenario was avoided.  Because of this good news, a lot of Open Source sites have been re-opened last week.  However, the decision has only been postponed, and danger of restriction is still pending.  Read more at <ulink url="http://swpat.ffii.org/" />.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Discussion Summary 2</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>News Item 1</title>

<para>.</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. You
can help TLDP by: Reviewing one of the draft versions of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">documents in
progress</ulink>, or picking up one of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/unmaint.html">unmaintained
documents</ulink> and reviving it or providing assistance with <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/markup.html">markup</ulink>. You are
welcome to participate in TLDP discussions by joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. Announcements about TLDP
are made at <email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this weekly newsletter. We need volunteers who
follow the community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and
report events related to The Linux Documentation Project. Please update
us by sending in the information and links to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
