<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>1</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-05-06</pubdate>
  <title>TLDP Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<para>One newcomer this week:</para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Raheel Abdul Hameed published the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Web-Browsing-Behind-ISA-Server-HOWTO.html">Web Browsing Behind ISA Server HOWTO</ulink>, which helps out Linux users who have to make their connections from behind a Windows-based ISA server.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Jim Hamilton sent in a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4301:200305:jijofjlebpapjhofcape">proposal to write a <emphasis>Boot from IDE RAID controller</emphasis></ulink> HOWTO or mini-HOWTO.  We didn't see too much reaction on that, I bet this man is still waiting for some opinions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Another interesting idea came from Uday Bhaskar Sarma Seetamraju, who has started on a document <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4303:200305:lichkgnpkkpkmmimkkih">on archiving file systems using CVS</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Lawyer has been breaking his head last week over the LDP Author Guide, which has got quite some critics because it is rather confusing.  Here's David's <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:4310:200305:lcmdapknnkkfdjolmeoa">one page replacement draft</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ralf Spenneberg's IPsec HOWTO is now available for review at <ulink url="http://ibiblio.org/gferg/ldp/IPsec-HOWTO.html" />.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The VideoLAN HOWTO got updated, v1.6 now available from <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/VideoLAN-HOWTO/" />.  The same authors also worked together on the updates of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/REF/VideoLAN-Quickstart/">VideoLAN Quickstart</ulink> document.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Eric S. Raymond sent in v1.2 of his Linksys Blue Box Router HOWTO, which you can check at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linksys-Blue-Box-Router-HOWTO/" />.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David lawyer worked on the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Modem-HOWTO.html">Modem-HOWTO</ulink>, which is now v0.27, and the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Serial-HOWTO.html">Serial HOWTO</ulink>, v2.18.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
<sect2>
<title>Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Joy Goodreau, Kylie Smith and Christine Lorenz have been working on <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/EVMSUG/html/">the EVMS User Guide</ulink>, v2.0.0.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels sent in the monthly updates for the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/">Introduction to Linux</ulink> guide.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Our Spanish colleagues translated the 4.1 version of the <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Manuales-LuCAS/lfs-es/">Linux from Scratch</ulink> guide.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<para>
Editorial Note: Due to unavoidable circumstances, The links in the
discussions point only to <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">http://lists.tldp.org</ulink> and not to the
archive mail link.
</para>

<sect2><title>Comments on LDP Weekly News</title>

<para>
Several people responded to the sample issue of LDP weekly news
suggesting that the news be released to <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">LWN</ulink>, <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">newsforge and linux.com</ulink>. Saqib Ali
<ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">talked</ulink> about RSS feeds.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="ldpag-rep">
<title>One-page replacement for LDP-Author-Guide</title>
<para>David Lawyer felt that the LDP-Author-Guide was too long and
intimidating for most people thinking of writing a HOWTO. He posted a
<ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">one page replacement</ulink> for the
same.  Greg Ferguson posted <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">his
comments</ulink> on the document.</para>

<para>The thread petered out in a different direction when Torsten
Schlabach <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">talked about</ulink>
WYSIWYG editing tools for DocBook but David Lawyer <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">said</ulink> that people
would be turned off if they need to learn a new tool to write for the
LDP. jdd indicated that he was not very pleased by the <quote>switch</quote> from
LinuxDoc to DocBook upon which Greg Ferguson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">clarified</ulink> that LDP still supports
LinuxDoc.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="lampadas">
<title>Status of Lampadas</title>
<para>Derek Hans was <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">wondering</ulink> if Lampadas was still
officially being continued. Guylhem Aznar <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">clarified</ulink> that David Merrill started
a re-design of Lampadas because of serious issues it had. The <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">last update on Lampadas</ulink> was send in
by David long ago.  Nicolas Chauvat <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org">said that</ulink> even though there was some
work going on Lampadas using <ulink
url="http://www.plone.org/">plone</ulink>, David has not had time for it
during the last six months.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="dir-change">
<title>HOWTOs and mini-HOWTOs under one roof</title>
<para> Greg Ferguson <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org">wanted to find
out</ulink> if there were any objections to merging the mini-HOWTOs into
the set of full HOWTOs. The structural boundaries (two sets of tar
files, different directory etc.) are to be removed but authors can still
use the term <quote>mini HOWTO</quote> in titles. People generally
agreed that the two sets of HOWTOs need to be merged into one and that
it would be easy for newbies to search for documentation.</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>Please help us create this weekly newsletter. Seen a site putting
in a story with a link to the LDP? Completed the translation of any
HOWTO?  Know of any articles about the LDP published in newspapers or
magazines?  We are curious ;-). You can help us by sending in links and
information at <email><ulink
url="mailto:feedback(at)en.tldp.org">feedback@en.tldp.org</ulink></email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is edited by
Machtelt Garrels, Torsten Schlabach and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag
with help from several other people.</para>
</sect1>
</article>

