<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2003</volumenum>
  <issuenum>31</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation 
Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2003-11-25</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1>
<title>New documents</title>
<sect2>
  <title>Fresh@LDP</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Lars Strand's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO/">Linux Mobile IPv6
HOWTO</ulink>, describing the software and procedures to set up and use
mobile IPv6 for Linux. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Manoj Warrier, Shishir Deshpande and V. S. Ashoka's
<ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Scientific-Computing-with-GNU-Linux/">Scientific
Computing with Free GNU/Linux Software HOWTO</ulink>. The document aims
to show how a PC running GNU/Linux can be used for scientific computing.
It lists the various available free software and also links on the world
wide web to tutorials on getting started with the tools.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Proposed new documents</title>
<para>From the feedback mailinglist: how about a Windows-Linux Analogy HOWTO?  
This would be a HOWTO describing what to do in order to run your favorite 
Microsoft Windows tasks and programs on a Linux machine.  If you ever had trouble 
migrating and you found solutions, then your input might be of great
value! There is a resource at <ulink
url="http://www.ndeepak.info/stuff/linux/linapps.php">http://www.ndeepak.info/stuff/linux/linapps.php</ulink>
that attempts at helping the users of MS Windows to make an easy transition
from their OS to GNU/Linux.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Submitted for review</title>
<para>It seems there is some confusion about this section.  So, in order to make 
it extra clear for the reader:</para>
<para>The purpose of this section is to help authors gather feedback.  Your 
constructive criticism is <emphasis>very</emphasis> welcome!</para>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Alex Weeks has taken it on him to update the <ulink 
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/sag/index.html">Linux System Administrator's Guide</ulink>.  
He's started cleaning out, and already added a new part about NTP, the Network 
Time Protocol.   The SAG was originally authored by some quite famous people, so 
we would like to wish Alex strength, patience and courage so as to be a worthy 
successor.  He might need your help, however, so please check out the current 
version and let Alex know what else you think is missing.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Werner Heuser submitted a <ulink 
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6396:200311:cancakbdomidilaanpca">new 
edition of the Laptop HOWTO</ulink>.  Since this one, apart from laptops, also 
covers PDA and mobile telephone configuration topics - which presumably made it a lot 
longer, Werner would like to rename his document to be the <quote>Linux Mobile 
Guide</quote>.  Since these are big changes and since we are, after all, on the 
high of a re-styling wave, Tabatha subsequently suggested to give this new 
addition to our Guides collection a <ulink 
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6397:200311:cancakbdomidilaanpca">thorough 
review</ulink>.  <ulink 
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6402:200311:cancakbdomidilaanpca">Werner 
agreed</ulink>, so Tabatha is looking for a volunteer now.  *hint* 
;-)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink 
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6407:200311:abimfngadhibogkclfmk">And this 
post</ulink> proves that we can never have enough volunteers.  Imagine that you, 
like Lars Strand, ask for comments on your work.  You've actively participated 
in other discussions, you are enthusiastic about being a first time author and 
all, but after some days it proves that you get no reaction whatsoever.  So we'd 
like to address a request to our dear readers: our authors do wish to
to hear comments on their documents!  Even if it's just a 
spelling correction, they appreciate that, and will most likely personally tell 
you so.  And then you will have an authentic E-mail, personally directed to you, 
from one of our authors!  And you will be able to honestly brag about your 
participation in an Open Source project ;-)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Artemiy Pavlov submitted the first version of his <ulink 
url="http://linuxdoc.artemio.net/squashfs">SquashFS HOWTO</ulink>.  SquashFS is a 
file system for small Linux implementations, which is for instance needed for 
embedded systems (on a computer chip) or on flash memory.  SquashFS uses a strong 
compression mechanism that squeezes the last drop out of every available bit.  It 
is a read-only file system, so it's ideal for archiving purposes.  If you want 
SquashFS support, you need a kernel patch and maybe the 
<command>mksquashfs</command> command to create these <quote>squashed</quote> file 
systems.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Niko Sauer submitted the <ulink 
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:6441:200311:iddffjjonhgepdhbbfad">USB 
Flash Memory HOWTO</ulink>, a new document.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>  
<title>Updates</title>

<sect2>
<title>HOWTOs</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Ian Ward found a small error having to do with the 
<command>lpadmin</command> command (to administer printers), which he corrected in v1.3 of 
the <ulink 
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Debian-and-Windows-Shared-Printing/index.html">Debian and 
Windows Shared Printing mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David S.Lawyer's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Modem-HOWTO.html">Modem-HOWTO</ulink> has
been updated to v0.31 with the sections on Mgetty dial-in and setserial
re-written. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ari Mäkelä submitted the v2.0.21 of his <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Finnish-HOWTO/">Finnish HOWTO</ulink> with a
lang="fi" attribute to the book element and a few language corrections.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Serial-HOWTO.html">Serial HOWTO</ulink>
written originally by Greg Hankins and now being maintained by David
S.Lawyer has been updated to v2.21 with the Kernel compile USB options for
serial ports and a revised setserial section. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David S. Lawyer sent in v1.33 of his <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Text-Terminal-HOWTO.html">Text-Terminal-HOWTO</ulink>
with a revised setserial section. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
  
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Happenings in the LDP world</title>

<sect2>
<title>LDP Documentation License</title>

<para>Rahul Sundaram was <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5619:200311:ihpahginmljdgbhooeje">looking</ulink>
into <ulink
url="http://people.debian.org/~srivasta/Position_Statement.html">GNU FDL
issues in Debian</ulink> and asked if OPL (Open Publication License
<ulink
url="http://www.opencontent.org/opl.shtml">http://www.opencontent.org/opl.shtml</ulink>) without any restrictions had
any issues and what people think in general about documentation
licenses. David Lawyer <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5625:200311:claiepedajakajhoajgg">said</ulink>
that the LDP needs to create it's own license and prevent documentation
abuse. Andy Oram <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5637:200311:dokpachmpofmkohiengn">suggested</ulink> that the LDP should contact the Creative
Commons for help. Somewhere in the discussion, Colin Watson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:5689:200311:apcdgkbgafajaibhibkf">explained</ulink>
why Rodolfo J. Paiz's ideas of protection of documentation were not in
the spirit of freedom
and how freedom applied to documentation just like it would apply to
software. </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>Feedback and Contributions</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.
Announcements about TLDP are made via
<email>announce-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>. If you want to help TLDP,
take a look at the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/authors/">tasks
page</ulink>, and consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and Y
Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
