<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>30</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-07-28</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

<para>The summer holidays (for some at least) are a very productive season:</para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/guides.html">Linux Kernel Module Programming Guide</ulink> is now split up into two branches, one for the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.4/html/index.html">2.4</ulink> and one for the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html">2.6</ulink> kernels.  Peter Jay Salzman, Ori Pomerantz and Michael Burian have put a lot of work into this, each covering a stable kernel branch starting from the 2.2 kernels.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Our colleagues over at <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/" /> have published a document about Linux/MS Windows integration using OpenLDAP, Samba, CUPS and Python.  It is entitled <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Tutoriales/doc-openldap-samba-cups-python/html/ldap+samba+cups+pykota.html">Integraci&#243;n de redes con OpenLDAP, Samba, CUPS y PyKota</ulink>; other formats are available <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Tutoriales/doc-openldap-samba-cups-python/">here</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The French have translated the Event HOWTO by Mark Komarinski into a document entitled <ulink url="http://www.traduc.org/docs/HOWTO/lecture/Event-HOWTO.html">R&#233;aliser une pr&#233;sentation sur les logiciels libres</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Pawel (McGiwer) Sadowski intends to write a HOWTO about installation modem SpeedTouch 330 USB on Fedora Core 2.  He did not find any document on The LDP site discussing the same.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Trevor Thompson proposed to submit a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9179:200407:kcddneldichebnimjnak">Kernel Compile HOWTO</ulink>; however, Emma Jane suggested to check with Kwan Lowe's <ulink url="http://cvs.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/howto/docbook/Kernel-Build-HOWTO/">start for a Kernel Build HOWTO</ulink> documenting the 2.6 kernel build process.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Chadley Wilson would like to write a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7743:200407:gobnkhhckbaodjmlhcjc">10-page Linux introduction</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>John Tapsell, Thomas Spellman and Matthias Grimm contributed to v.0.09 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Masquerading-Simple-HOWTO/">Masquerading Made Simple HOWTO</ulink>.  This document is a complement to the original <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/IP-Masquerade-HOWTO/index.html">Linux IP Masquerade HOWTO</ulink> by David A. Ranch.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter Jay Salzman published v1.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Debian-Jigdo/">Debian Jigdo HOWTO</ulink>, explaining how you can make your own Debian installation CDs or DVDs, now including info on how to make ISO images on MS Windows machines.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>LQ Wiki to include TLDP docs</para>

<para>Members of the LinuxQuestions Wiki have expressed <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?7:msp:10327:200407:dapncggfnodfolcejkmd">their interest in including TLDP docs</ulink> into the <ulink url="http://wiki.linuxquestions.org/">LQ Wiki</ulink>.  Since many of our documents are published under the free licenses, this initiative can only be encouraged.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Mirror updates</para>

<para>Richard Mitchell lets us know that his New Zealand mirrors will be available at <ulink url="http://ldp.yaksha.ath.cx:8001" /> and <ulink url="http://yaksha.ath.cx:8000/ldp/" /> instead of at http://www.yaksha.co.nz/ldp as previously announced.</para>
<para>Sadit Sathianpaisarn is hosting the second official Thai mirror located in Bangkok at <ulink url="http://pubnet.ngi.nectec.or.th/LDP" />, updated daily, courtesy of NECTEC.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
