<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>14</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-04-07</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Ivan Baldinotti proposes a mini-HOWTO titled <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6933:200404:ocifmoejbolmmmephfkm">From
endnote to LyX</ulink>, which details migration from Endnote or MSWord
to LyX.  There were recent discussions on <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6930:200404:necbnljcfmmpdjhjdohe">whether or not to add a note on LyX to the Author Guide</ulink>. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels proposes to write detailed documentation for the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6910:200404:ihgbeocagoccoafpbbne">creation of presentations using DocBook XML</ulink>.  Though some say this is overkill, she defends the proposal saying that she is looking for two important things: text-mode creation and compatibility with MS Windows users without having to fall back to HTML.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

<para>Join our <ulink url="http://tldp.org/mailinfo.html#maillists">discuss mailinglist</ulink> or mail these people directly to let them know what you think!</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>v2.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Medicine-HOWTO/">Medicine HOWTO</ulink> is now available.  Gerardp Arnaez and Walt Pennington updated the existing links and added new ones to more websites dealing with the subject of Free/Open medical software.  They try out most of the software they discuss, and talk about their experiences, difficulties they encountered and so on.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><quote>Misko's triplet</quote> has been updated again.  This includes the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-Radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink>. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>There were a few typos in Daniel Nofftz's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Athlon-Powersaving-HOWTO/">Athlon Powersaving
HOWTO</ulink>, these have been corrected in v1.1.2.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Postfix-Cyrus-Web-cyradm-HOWTO/">Postfix-Cyrus-Web-cyradm-HOWTO</ulink> guides you through the installation of the Postfix mail transportation agent and the Cyrus IMAP server.  Web-cyradm is a graphical web-based user-administration interface to the system; data is stored in a MySQL database.  Luc de Louw has a whole chapter about virus- and spam protection.  Minor additions and corrections in v1.2.6 of this document.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>It was argued on the discuss mailinglist that the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:msp:6944:200404:jicklkoejglmhimkkill">Author
Guide did not fully reflect TLDP procedures</ulink>, so Emma Jane Hogbin
submitted an <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/">Author Guide update</ulink> (v4.2).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Eric S. Raymond has done some rephrasing in v2.9 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Unix-and-Internet-Fundamentals-HOWTO/">The Unix and Internet Fundamentals HOWTO</ulink>, which explains what your PC does and how it is done in non-technical language.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para>Removal of the Linux Cookbook:</para>
<para>Michael Stutz let us know that he thinks the Linux Cookbook contains too many errors, bugs and licensing issues.  Therefor, as the maintainer of the document, he asked us to remove the Cookbook until he has had time to fix the issues.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Anti-spam measures on the LDP mailing lists:</para>
<para>Sergiusz Pawlowicz announced the start of a test-phase after installing the spamassassin filter on the submit mailinglist on Sunday morning - yes, we work while you sleep/party/have your Sunday-morning soft-boiled egg ;-)</para>
<para>Sergiusz argued before that everybody should have their own E-mail filtering because TLDP didn't have the resources to do it on the server-side, but apparently he has found the hardware to do it.</para>
<para>We hope that if the tests go well, the feedback list will also be filtered.</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
