<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>31 &amp; 32</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-08-11</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Bin Nguyen sent in updates for the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/guides.html">Linux Dictionary</ulink> (v0.15) and for the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/html/index.html">Linux
Filesystem Hierarchy Guide</ulink> (v0.65).  This guide now has updates to describe
the changes incorporated by FHS2.3.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter Jay Salzman sent in the v1.0.2 of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-Gamers-HOWTO/">Linux Gamers HOWTO</ulink>.  The document contains descriptions of available games on Linux,
an overview of gaming libraries, information about your X settings
in order to obtain optimal graphics performance, and details on audio
configuration.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lionel Bouchpan-Lerust-Ju&233;ry submitted updates to the
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SPARC-HOWTO.html">SPARC
HOWTO</ulink>, the document is now at v0.0.7.  Lionel explains that there is more to this story than the Sun implementation of the RISC design and lists Linux distros supporting this platform.  Apart from that, this document contains many tips and tricks for the do-it-yourself reader.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ram Samudrala, one of our authors who works for the acceptance of Linux in enterprise environments, published v1.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Cluster-HOWTO.html">Linux Cluster HOWTO</ulink> and v1.62 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DPT-Hardware-RAID-HOWTO.html">Linux DPT Hardware RAID HOWTO</ulink>.  This last one had a slight name change to better reflect that it is focussing on the DPT RAID controllers - even though the information is fairly applicable on other RAID cards as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The latest evolutions in neural networks, artificial life simulations and intelligent agents can be found in v2.1 of John Eikenberry's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/AI-Alife-HOWTO.html">GNU/Linux AI & Alife HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Lawyer keeps finding new subjects for his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Modem-HOWTO.html">Modem HOWTO</ulink>.  New in v0.33 are some interesting remarks on how your modem is powered and why it says in some manuals that the modem is only supported on MS Windows systems.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>New Malaysian mirror</para>

<para>Ami Shamril volunteered to set up the <ulink url="http://mirror.oscc.org.my/ldp/">second Malaysian mirror site</ulink>.  Five to go and TLDP will have 300 official mirror sites, thanks to the efforts of hundreds of admins locally providing copies.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
