<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>18</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-05-05</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>After months of reviewing, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/">Bash Guide for Beginners</ulink>, by Machtelt Garrels, is finally available.  A lot of readers were waiting for the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/Bash-Beginners-Guide.pdf">PDF version</ulink>, this and other formats can be obtained <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/">here</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Extending the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:msp:6911:200404:ihgbeocagoccoafpbbne">presentations with docbook HOWTO proposal</ulink>, Emma Jane Hogbin suggests a more general <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:msp:7193:200405:aomnmdfohkdjkccmkgfh">Presentations with Linux HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Wim van Dorst updated the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/BogoMips.html">BogoMips mini-HOWTO</ulink> to v36.  For over ten years now this document gives performance info of CPUs running Linux.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If you still want more after finishing the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/">Bash Guide for Beginners</ulink>, Mendel Cooper's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/">Advanced Bash Scripting Guide</ulink> is the place to be.  v2.7 contains more examples and some minor updates.  Mendel keeps the <ulink url="http://personal.riverusers.com/~thegrendel/Change.log">full revision log</ulink> on his personal site.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><quote>Accidents will happen!</quote>  Prepare for the worst with Charles Curley's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-Complete-Backup-and-Recovery-HOWTO/">Linux Complete Backup and Recovery HOWTO</ulink>.  Featuring in v1.6: notes on Knoppix, Syslinux, PPART, QtPart and more info on rescue CDs.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Daniel Nofftz sent in <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9068:200405:jpaoleblmhgecdjeiepd">a
new version</ulink> of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Athlon-Powersaving-HOWTO/">Athlon Power
Saving HOWTO</ulink>.  v1.1.4 incorporates a change in the sis chipset
commandline hack, adds a new sound fix and a new patch for the 2.6.5
kernel. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM
HOWTO</ulink> by AJ Lewis has been updated to v0.11.  This revision has
updated LVM2 FAQ entries. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Introduction to Linux goes to press</para>

<para>The <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/">Introduction to Linux
Guide</ulink> will be available in printed format (264 pages) from
<ulink url="http://fultus.com">http://fultus.com</ulink> from May 20th onwards by Print On Demand (POD).  Fultus also <ulink url="http://store.fultus.com/product_info.php?products_id=65">distributes the book</ulink> via <ulink url="http://amazon.com">Amazon.com</ulink>, <ulink url="http://amazon.co.uk">Amazon.co.uk</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.BarnesAndNoble">Barnes &amp; Noble</ulink>.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Feedback mailinglist protected</para>

<para>Sergiusz has been working quite hard to protect our mailing lists
from spam.  After the submit mailinglist, the protection was extended to
the feedback mailinglist.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>New mirror in Malaysia</para>

<para>Ikmal Ahmad noted that there were no mirrors available for Malaysia and took the initiative to start one.  The new mirror is at <ulink url="http://ldp.leakage.org/" />, is located in Kuala Lumpur and updates several times per day.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Obsolete MSSQL6-Openlink-PHP-ODBC HOWTO</para>

<para>Jean-Philippe Geurard, the HOWTO-French translation coordinator
<ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7191:200405:fgeenikobhbjpinklmbg">wrote
in</ulink> to inform us that the MSSQL6-Openlink-PHP-ODBC HOWTO was
obsolete.  The version of OpenLink that does not seem to be available
anywhere on the Internet and The current version was not free anymore.
</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>AsciiDoc as a new format for submissions</para>

<para><ulink
url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/asciidoc/">AsciiDoc</ulink> is a
GPLed formating system written in Python by Stuart Rackham that can
convert a plain text human readable/writable document format directly to
DocBook.  Scot W. Stevenson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7121:200404:mjolkcjnjbginkhagjki">suggested</ulink>
that the LDP maintainers consider AsciiDoc for document submissions to
reduce the barrier involved in learning DocBook.  Emma Jane Hogbin said
that this was a misconception that the LDP accepts only DocBook
submissions and Scot explained how he thought learning DocBook was
necessary if only at a later point of time.  Gerg Ferguson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7130:200404:ifhbolfhjihbhnkaanhb">was
interested</ulink> in how good AsciiDoc was at doing container elements
and meta-data and that if it can do a good job like WikiText without
DocBook errors, the LDP would be open to such submissions. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP funds and donations</para>

<para>Machtelt Garrels wanted to know what somebody who wanted to give
money to TLDP should be doing.  Paul Jones <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7227:200405:pabolachbpcnijabieho">replied</ulink>
saying that cheques may be sent to: ibiblio.org, campus box 3456, UNC
chapel hill, nc 27599-3456, USA.  They should be made payable to
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a note that the funds
are for the Linux Documentation Project.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
