<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>15</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-04-14</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Emma Jane was still not happy with the Author Guide and after some discussion submitted a <ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/LDP-Author-Guide/">new update</ulink>, merging the contribution section into The LDP publishing process section.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Nico Schottelius wrote a <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9046:200404:gkahgfjmoglaokcaaepk">mini-HOWTO
about Cryptoloop partial security</ulink> and awaits your comments. The
document explains what Cryptoloop is, what it is used for and why it is
only partially secure.  A section also discusses solutions to the
problem. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>David Hinds submitted the v2.118 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/PCMCIA-HOWTO.html">Linux PCMCIA HOWTO</ulink>.  This version features updated lists of supported hardware, updated program version numbers of the discussed software and a whole new section about the kernel PCMCIA support in 2.4 kernels and higher.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Christine Lorenz submitted v2.3.0 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/EVMSUG/html/index.html">EVMS User Guide</ulink>.  She is co-author of this document with Joy Goodreau and Kylie Smith.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Walt Penningtons <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Medicine-HOWTO/">Linux
Medicine-HOWTO</ulink> is now at v2.3. This new release has few minor
updates. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP Feedback</para>

<para>It has been close to an year since The LDP weekly news was
re-started. The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/latest.html">latest
LDPWN</ulink> is available on the web, mailed to the
<email>news@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list and several important news
sources. There is also an <ulink
url="http://www.karakas-online.de/myServices/rssify.php?url=http://tldp.org/ldpwn/latest.html">RSS
feed</ulink> in case you would like to track us with your favorite
aggregator. We take this opportunity to request you for comments and
suggestions for improvement. Please send in your feedback to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email></para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>IRC: Freenode Server #tldp room</para>

<para>The Freenode servers we have a #tldp room for IRC. Connect to one
of the servers at <ulink
url="http://freenode.net/irc_servers.shtml">http://freenode.net/irc_servers.shtml</ulink>
and join #tldp.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Document Licensing Discussion</para>

<para>Rahul Sundaram was <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6964:200404:ihpahginmljdgbhooeje">unhappy</ulink>
that he might be volunteering his work to document authors that restrict
their documentation with a non-free license and indicated what he
thought would be acceptable licenses. Rick Moen <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6965:200404:pkdleajpekbbaookkgbd">described</ulink>
what those licenses were and their problems (like the <ulink
url="http://people.debian.org/~srivasta/Position_Statement.xhtml">DFSG-freeness
of GNU FDL 1.2</ulink>). Rodolfo J. Paiz was of the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6968:200404:ehngfbpnepphojhokgdn">opinion</ulink>
that license of a document is an individual choice and volunteering for
a work with a license that one does not like is not obligatory.  David
Lawyer and Greg Ferguson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6979:200404:claiepedajakajhoajgg">explained</ulink>
the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6982:200404:ifhbolfhjihbhnkaanhb">recommendations</ulink>
of The LDP. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="interview">
<title>Interview with Emma Jane Hogbin</title>

<figure>
<title>Emma Jane Hogbin</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="emma.eps" format="EPS"/>
</imageobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="emma.jpg" format="JPG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Emma Jane Hogbin</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Emma Jane Hogbin, probably the most talkative TLDP volunteer, was very
enthusiastic when we asked her if she would grant us an interview.  <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/20040414.html#interview">Get to know
Emma Jane:</ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><emphasis>Q: The classical question first: how, why and when did you get involved?</emphasis></para>

<para>A: Well I've always been a bit of a docco [Editor's Note: that's a
documentation maniac].  Unlike many of my other technically oriented 
friends, I actually write notes when I'm trying to
install software. And then I go back and check my notes to make sure
things are correctly documented. It makes life a lot easier if I ever
need to install that software again. Just to give an example: In the 
first year that I was running Debian
Linux on my laptop I had to re-install the system about half a dozen times. 
(Yes, I'm as shocked as you are.)  Each time my notes improved and I got a 
little faster at performing each of the required steps.</para>

<para>The first publicly available documentation I wrote for a specific
application was for <ulink url="http://www.htdig.org">ht://dig</ulink> (a great little search engine).  
The document was very well received by my client at the time,
and by the ht://dig community. Although my documentation had always been
appreciated at work, this was the first time I'd received recognition from
a community of users.</para>

<para>My first document accepted to the LDP was the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/ACPI-HOWTO/index.html">ACPI HOWTO</ulink>.  Originally, it was
just notes on the installation process, that I made for myself.  These I
submitted to various mailing lists to confirm their accuracy.  I got lots of
good feedback and
Sebastian Henschel asked me to publish them on-line for the <ulink
url="http://acpi.sourceforge.net/">ACPI4Linux team</ulink>.
Werner Heuser suggested I submit the document to The LDP. Tabatha did my
language review and started sending me really polite emails suggesting that
maybe I'd like to be a technical reviewer. The next thing I knew I'd
volunteered to re-write the Author Guide (a total of about nine months work) and
suddenly I was a full fledged technical and meta data reviewer.</para>

<para>My original ACPI HOWTO now needs a major revamp for the 2.6 kernels, and
I've been gearing up to work on that. Ariel Glenn will be helping me
with the re-write (a process I'm actually looking forward to now).</para>


<para><emphasis>Q: I took the liberty of going through your CV.  As far as your employment is concerned, you seem to do fairly well and in accordance to the subjects you studied while at the university.  But then for TLDP I see you reviewing the USB Flash Memory HOWTO and the BLFS document, and authoring the ACPI HOWTO.  How did you grow an interest for these?</emphasis></para>

<para>A: At this point I'm doing two types of reviews: metadata and technical. 
For the technical reviews I need to know something about the topic that I'm
reviewing. I currently have a USB key chain and a USB camera, so it was a
good match for me to review Niko's <ulink
url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Flash-Memory-HOWTO/index.html">USB Flash Memory HOWTO</ulink>.</para>

<para>The meta data reviews look at a different set of things, specifically the
markup of the
document (does the DocBook/LinuxDoc validate?) and the license the
document is released under. There's a bit more to it than that, but those
are the two things that take the most time on a meta data review. When I'm
doing a meta data review I tend to scan the document for
technical/language inaccuracies as well, but I don't spend a lot of time
on it.</para>

<para>Then I have a third set of responsibilities: authoring documents. I'm
currently an author on three documents at The LDP: ACPI HOWTO, <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/index.html">The Author
Guide</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">Reviewer HOWTO</ulink>. The first (ACPI HOWTO) was simply a document
that I wrote from my own notes on a specific problem that I had to solve.
The second two documents are more "process" documents for The LDP. There
are a lot of volunteers at The LDP, many of whom perform critical roles in
the publication of documents. I've been working on getting some of these
processes documented so that if a volunteer ever wanted help, or decided
to retire, there would be instructions on how to perform that volunteer's
tasks.</para>

<para><emphasis>Q: Did you ever have difficulties or encounter restrictions, being a woman at TLDP?  And the eternal question: What should we do to get more female volunteers?  What should men do to get more women to join this and other Linux projects?</emphasis></para>

<para>A: The only restriction I've found is that I get to do more work! The men on
the list are good at discussing the overall direction of The LDP while the
women seem to be better at processing new documents for their collection
into the LDP (and removing old/out of date documents). When it comes to
processing documents I work primarily with three women and Greg
Ferguson--that's not to say that there aren't any male volunteers! They just
aren't the ones that I do the most work with for the processing of documents.
</para>

<para>Then I look at the work I do on the overall picture and it's mostly men
(and two women). Saqib Ali and David Horton have helped me a great deal with
the tool and document transformations. Greg, as I mentioned above, is
responsible for publishing documents. Stein Gjoen and I have had many
interesting conversations about library-friendly document storage and
meta data. Most of the licensing discussions are headed up by the men on
our team.</para>
                                                                                
<para>As much as I would like to say that it's the men who need to do something
to get more women involved, I think it's really up to the women. Yes,
there are some male bozos out there, but there are some female ones too.
Generally my advice is this: when the bozos behave badly, let them know
what is wrong about their behaviour; then thank them for their help when
they are being good. If a group has an overwhelming number of bozos, find
a new group. There is not a single Linux group that I've quit because of
men behaving badly.</para>

<para>So how do we get more women involved? Good question. I don't have a lot of
tech-oriented female friends. And those who are tech-oriented are too busy
working to consider switching operating systems. It's a long, slow
process, but I think as sophistication of Linux desktop applications grows and
then surpasses the applications available on Windows/Macs we will see more
women involved with Linux. Certainly I came to Unix/Linux fairly late. I was a
Machead growing up, then switched to Windows for university. I tried Linux
in 2000, but the applications I needed weren't stable enough for me at the
time. I tried again in 2002 and have been here ever since.</para>

<para><emphasis>Q: What could TLDP be doing better, according to you?
</emphasis></para>

<para>A: I know how much work is involved because I am a reviewer, but... I would
like to see the entire collection reviewed. I would like to have the
volunteer power to review every document on its one year anniversary. At
that time the document would be either kept in the collection <quote>as
is</quote>,
removed from the collection, or kept with certain conditions (for example
my ACPI HOWTO needs to contain information about the 2.6 series kernels).
The review date would be based on the document's anniversary, not based on
the <quote>last updated</quote> date.</para>
                                                                                
<para>That and having mugs for sale. The <ulink
url="http://www.hackerthreads.com/?page=shop/browse&amp;category_id=ae255697973840ae34ac3dcd028e55ce">t-shirts</ulink> are nice, but what I really
want is a mug.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
