<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>9</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-03-03</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>As proposed a couple of weeks ago, here it is: the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DVD-Playback-HOWTO/">DVD Playback HOWTO</ulink>, by David Jao.  David starts with the basics and explains how to set up the region for your drive, how to check for X Video Overlay support and how to enable DMA drive access.</para>
<para>He continues with the discussion of the DVD playing software:
<application>MPlayer</application>, <application>Xine</application>,
<application>Ogle</application> and <application>VideoLAN</application>.
The HOWTO has information of how to make these work on a variety of Linux distributions.  It also has a troubleshooting section.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>At the <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org">Spanish TLDP</ulink> you can now find two courses about the Andalusian <ulink url="http://www.guadalinex.org/">Guadalinex</ulink> distribution.  The first document is a <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Tutoriales/doc-curso-guadalinex-iesaverroes/html/">guide</ulink> detailing the installation process and explaining how to get started with the system.  It also has an introduction on Internet services and <ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice</ulink>. The second document is <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/Tutoriales/doc-curso-guadalinex-jr/">a beginner's guide</ulink> as well, but it differs from the first one in that it has more on multi-media and didactical applications.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>AJ Lewis sent in an update of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink>. This revision
has updated CVS locations and FTP links along with an added section on
extending a JFS filesystem</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Ravi Kiran asks whether this <ulink
url="http://www.geocities.com/ravikiran_uvs/articles/proc.htm">article
on understanding the proc file system</ulink> would be a good addition
to our collection. Ravi would also like to hear your suggestions on this <ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/ravikiran_uvs/articles/rkfs.html">tutorial on writing a file system</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Eric Raymond's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/UPS-HOWTO/">UPS HOWTO</ulink> v1.1 has a whole new section entitled <quote>An Overview of Power Protection</quote>, explaining the differences between surge suppressors, line conditioners and un-interruptible power supplies.  Furthermore, Eric added a section on the deployment of your UPS.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Also by ESR: v3.0 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Unix-Hardware-Buyer-HOWTO/">Unix Hardware Buyer HOWTO</ulink>.  It has been adapted to the 21st century and the <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/ultimate-linux-box/">Ultimate Linux Box</ulink> articles have been integrated in this HOWTO.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>If you were wondering how to use your Linux box for controlling your telescope, check out the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Astronomy-HOWTO/">Astronomy HOWTO</ulink> (v1.48) by Elwood Downey and John Huggins.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TimePrecision-HOWTO/">Time Precision HOWTO</ulink> v1.0.6 by Avi Alkalay has been <ulink url="http://computerlib.narod.ru/html/linuxtime.htm">translated into Russian</ulink>, thanks to Shaki.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Later on this week, we received another update from Eric Raymond, this one for the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-Demystification-HOWTO/">DocBook Demystification HOWTO</ulink>.  V1.3 features updated links, corrected figures and additional pointers to XML editors.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Eric was in a very productive mood: we also received v1.6 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linksys-Blue-Box-Router-HOWTO/">Linksys Blue Box Router HOWTO</ulink>.  As you recall, this document describes the BEFSR41 models and up of Linksys router/firewall boxes, which are very suitable for use with a home DSL connection.  It also explains firmware upgrades.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/K7s5a-HOWTO.html">K7s5a HOWTO</ulink> v1.8, a combined effort by Sebfrance, Andreas Willenbrink, Alvaro Reguly and Paolo Berva has a new section on making the sensors of this motherboard work with the 2.6 kernel.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>The History of LDP</title>

<para>Machtelt Garrels's article on <ulink
url="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article.php?sid=7433">the history of
LDP</ulink> (A behind-the-scenes look at the evolution of the Linux
Documentation Project) was published by linuxjournal.com. The Dutch
version would be at LinuxMag.nl (a magazine that is published every two
months in both Belgium and The Netherlands).</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
