<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>19</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-05-12</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<para>The discuss mailinglist was teeming with new initiatives this week:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Christian Schnobrich wants to write a HOWTO about <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7221:200405:gcmileclkfhpkbbhmnef">small and silent servers</ulink>.  The focus would be on using old(er) hardware that can be tuned to make less noise, for use in the home office or shared private network.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>All hope is not lost for getting an up to date document into TLDP that discusses Enterprise Java on Linux.  <quote>Chase</quote> <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7206:200405:oijdjcnlaebpnckdlgpa">gives an outline of his ideas</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Steve Kemp <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7252:200405:ecpjlcneojlbednmdldj">has some ideas for a source code auditing HOWTO</ulink>, for which he doesn't find anything comparable in our collection as it is now.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>New in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Athlon-Powersaving-HOWTO/">Athlon Powersaving HOWTO</ulink> v1.1.4, by Daniel Nofftz: sis chipset commandline hack changed, new sound fix, new patch for the 2.6.5 kernel.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>AJ Lewis has updated FAQ entries for LVM2 in v0.11 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Upon <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9071:200405:lbmnkmolejjbeapdhhpb">request of the author</ulink>, Daniel Barlow, the GCC HOWTO has been removed from our collection.  He argues that topics covered in the HOWTO, such as installing GCC, are a non-issue today.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Emma Jane also contacted the maintainer of the 3Dfx HOWTO, Michael Scherer, who <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9072:200405:gjeegggphbeamigcfdfg">asked to move his document into the unmaintained section</ulink>, because it proved to be effort than profit for him.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Linux Documentation: What's There and What's Needed</para>

<para>Andy Oram posted an interesting and well written article titled
<ulink url="http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/wlg/4357">Linux Documentation:
What's There and What's Needed</ulink>.  The web-log entry is a condensed
form of a talk given by Andy at LinuxWorld in January 2004.  The article
discusses the state of Linux Documentation and mentions the LDP in
general terms. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP CD now also at LinuxCentral</para>

<para>The <quote>unofficial</quote>TLDP CD-ROM, for people with low bandwidth or low patience levels can be obtained from <ulink url="http://linuxcentral.com/catalog/index.php3?prod_code=L000-214">LinuxCentral</ulink>.  As Bradley Glonka, long-time contributor to the LinuxCentral project puts it: <quote>We don't expect to make big money with this CD release.  Some people think our project is just the Nth flat commerce initiative, but we really feel that we are part of the community.  We once sent an official copy of Debian to all the Debian developers.</quote></para>
<para>LinuxCentral is donating part of the revenue, accumulated by selling this CD, to the TLDP project.  Thanks, guys!</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Copyright Infringement of Linux Dictionary</para>

<para>The people over at linuxdig.com must have failed to read the copyright notice that comes with our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">Linux Dictionary</ulink>, by Binh Nguyen.  We kindly ask to give credit where credit is due, and to respect our authors.</para>
<para>Binh already <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7247:200405:aeijflemkfkdokbhdenh">sent
a notice to these people</ulink> to bring the matter to their attention,
but so far, nobody reacted.  Binh Nguyen would like to talk to lawyers
and take steps if the copyright violation continues.</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
