<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>6</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-02-11</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

<para></para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Adrian Offerman surprises us with v1.0 of <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MMBase-Inst-HOWTO/">the MMBase Installation HOWTO</ulink>, which describes the installation of this content management system on RedHat Linux using Tomcat as an application server.  He also provides info on how to integrate it with MySQL and Apache.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Steve Peace submitted a document called the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7432:200402:idpiipmjacehkhjeihdh">Qmail-scanner+Clamav HOWTO</ulink>, detailing the installation of the ClamAV GPL'ed anti-virus toolkit on a Qmail server.  Steve awaits your comments on this initial draft.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lars Strand updated his <ulink url="http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/code/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO-v11.tar.bz2">Mobile IPv6 HOWTO</ulink> with new images, two new sections and error fixes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter J. Salzman submitted v1.0.1 of the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7444:200402:hhejdlmpfpjpmpaiafjd">Linux Gamer's HOWTO</ulink>, LG HOWTO for short.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Jao is looking for reviewers for his <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7474:200402:hkpgcgjhacpomnjgoffe">DVD
Playback HOWTO</ulink>. The document describes how to view DVD movies on
a Linux computer with a DVD drive and also helps troubleshoot common
problems.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Lars Strand wrote an Optimized Link State Routing
Protocol <ulink
url="http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/olsr/OLSR-IPv6-HOWTO.html">(OLSR)
IPv6 HOWTO</ulink> for Linux, and would like to submit it to the LDP for
inclusion in the collection. Comments on the above document are welcome.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Lawyer suggested that a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6659:200402:aoajnioenajphdefnbnn">one-page intro to LinuxDoc</ulink> might be a good idea.  Machtelt Garrels offered to write a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6661:200402:ahmedfjihleniifjcpbo">DocBook</ulink> counterpart.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Eric S. Raymond's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Reading-List-HOWTO/">Linux Reading List HOWTO</ulink> has reached v3.0.  Dot-zero always indicates a major update.  From this one all out-of-date books have been removed and a couple of new ones have been added.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>V2.22 of Daniel Quintiliani's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Windows-Newsreaders-under-Linux-HOWTO/">Windows Newsreaders under Linux HOWTO</ulink> contains minor corrections.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/index.html">Introduction to
Linux</ulink> guide by Machtelt Garrels has an ISB Number and a few
formatting changes.  The document is being <ulink
url="http://www.geocities.com/linuxparichay/">translated to
Hindi</ulink> by <ulink
url="http://www.devanaagarii.net/hi/alok/blog/">Alok
Kumar</ulink>.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>Acer Laptop HOWTO removed</title>

<para>Harish Tampi has requested the removal of the Acer Laptop HOWTO due to a lack of time from his part to keep it up to date.  However, info for this brand of portables can be found at <ulink url="http://www.linux-on-laptops.com/acer.html">the Linux on Laptops site</ulink>, section Acer Laptop and Notebook Computers, or at <ulink url="http://www.tuxmobile.org/acer.html">Tuxmobile</ulink>, which hosts a similar page.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item2">
<title>French LDP effort</title>

<para>You might have noticed that the French translation effort, <ulink
url="http://fr.tldp.org/" />, has been pretty motionless for a long
time.  However, the <ulink url="http://www.traduc.org/">Traduc
site</ulink> is quite active. </para>
<para>Apart from regular news updates, this sites features the <emphasis>traduc po</emphasis>, which allows tracking of the state of translations for different packages.  Also worth noticing is the translation to French of the <ulink url="http://www.traduc.org/docs/lgazette/etat_gazette.php?1..2">Linux Gazette</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
