<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>28 &amp; 29</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-07-21</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>David Horton's <ulink url="http://www.happy-monkey.net/LPI/LPI-Self-Study-Guide.html">LPI Certification Self-Study Guide</ulink> was accepted for review.  This work is intended as a quick and most of all <emphasis>inexpensive</emphasis> method for experienced Linux users to prepare for the Linux professional Institute certification exams.  This is no introductory guide, i.e. not for beginners.  Rather, it is a collection of practice questions related to the exam objectives over at <ulink url="http://www.lpi.org/en/lpic.html">the LPI web site</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Tor Slettnes submitted his <ulink url="http://slett.net/spam-filtering-for-mx/">Spam Filtering for Mail Exchangers HOWTO</ulink>.  Originally designed for a specific setup with <application>Exim</application>, he managed to filter out the information that is useful in any mail environment, and published it in this document.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The new release of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MIPS-HOWTO.html">Linux/MIPS HOWTO</ulink> by Ralf B&auml;chle has updated info on related mailinglists and FTP sites, updated links and info about the <ulink url="http://www.linux-mips.org/linux-vr/">Linux-VR project</ulink> and other MIPS-based systems.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Minor changes in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TT-XFree86.html">TrueType Fonts with XFree86 4.x mini-HOWTO</ulink> v1.5 by Bartek Kostrzewa.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Howard Shane added info for the 2.6 kernels in v1.1 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Scanner-HOWTO/">Scanner HOWTO</ulink>, as well as information about the <application>libusb</application> package.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Avi Alkalay encourages people to translate his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TimePrecision-HOWTO/">Time Precision HOWTO</ulink>; v1.0.7 has minor corrections and rephrasings.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels updated the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/">Bash Guide for Beginners</ulink> to have consistent markup; v1.3 is more user-friendly for the blind and a tracer image was added to track usage on the TLDP mirror sites.  A tracer was also added to v1.15 of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/">Introduction to Linux - A hands on Guide</ulink>, and textobjects were added to all images.  Wrong links in the glossary section were corrected and a couple of other items were clarified.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper sent in a new version of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/index.html">Advanced Bash Scripting Guide</ulink>, featuring updates, corrections and new examples.</para></listitem>
                                                                                
<listitem><para>Manoj Warrier, main author of <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Scientific-Computing-with-GNU-Linux/">the Scientific Computing with GNU/Linux HOWTO</ulink> provided us with an update containing additional links and more evaluations of distributions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Emma Jane is proud to announce the <ulink url="http://www.traduc.org/docs/HOWTO/lecture/ACPI-HOWTO.html">French translation of the ACPI HOWTO</ulink>.  She is now also officially the author of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/index.html">LDP Author Guide</ulink>, in which she recently updated the info on how to use our CVS.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>We received v1.2 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Debian-Jigdo/">Debian Jigdo mini-HOWTO</ulink>, by Peter Jay Salzman, which contains minor corrections.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Mirrors: new mirror sites and changes in existing sites</para>

<para>Mary L. Kuss announced that the UK Mirror Service will be transformed into the JISC Mirror Service during summer holidays.  Eduserv, the new responsibles, have <ulink url="http://www.eduserv.org.uk/internet/news">a brief synopsis of the changes here</ulink>.</para>

<para>David Gonzalez changed the URL of his Columbian mirror http://www.skynetbbs.org/LDP/ to <ulink url="http://www.tuxcafe.com/LDP/" />.</para>
<para>New mirror sites:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://mirror3.cs.wisc.edu/pub/mirrors/LDP" /> by Stefan Strandberg, in Madison, Wisconsin, USA.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.indosite.co.id/" /> by Abdussalam Sukarta, Jakarta, Indonesia.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ftp.belnet.be/packages/ldp/" /> (IPv4 and v6) by Bernard Grymonpon, in Belgium.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.yaksha.co.nz/ldp" /> by Richard Mitchell, in Wellington, New Zealand.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Mirror-maintainers: please note that you can replace the <quote>LDP Site Sponsor</quote> logo on the first page with your own.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Check our progress</para>

<para>Ever since the latest round of innovations at TLDP, things are moving.  We'd like to put the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">In Progress Page</ulink> in the spotlight this week.  Here you can find a list of the documents that are proposed and currently being worked on, as well as a list of those that have already been accepted for review and that are undergoing a language or technical review.</para>

<para>We are always looking for reviewers, and even if you are not the technical type of person, you can help in various ways.  Interested in contributing?  Mail <ulink url="mailto:emmajane@tldp.org">Emma Jane</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:tabatha@tldp.org">Tabatha</ulink>, our Review Coordinators, they can tell you how you can make yourself useful.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>LSM Meeting in Bordeaux</para>

<para>You could meet some of our staff at the Libre Software Meeting in Bordeaux, which was held from the 6th to the 10th of July.  The first pictures are floating in, including <ulink url="http://www.sosuemelinux.org/LSM2004/p_France%20093.jpg.html">mad Canadians supporting the European resistance to software patents</ulink>.  This is Emma Jane, possibly jealous that she didn't go to Brussels to get herself such a nice yellow T-shirt ;-)</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP and trudac.org</para>

<para><email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email> has seen a very interesting <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7601:200407:fbbnknekpbeidbolmhjn">discussion</ulink> about the various issues involved in co-operation between the active <ulink url="http://www.trudac.org/">French HOWTO translation effort</ulink> and The LDP.  The discussion also petered out into another <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7707:200407:claiepedajakajhoajgg">thread about licensing issues</ulink>.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Wiki for The LDP</para>

<para>Machtelt Garrels <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7651:200407:ceejnklaecengajdijnf">initiated a discussion</ulink> for changing The LDP volunteer list.  A discussion about maintaining the list ensued, and people went on to discuss the issues in using a Wiki for some parts of The LDP website. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Feedback on proposals</para>

<para>Saqib Ali <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7635:200407:kaoahapddjblcbcdepeb">suggested</ulink> the use of a blog for collecting feedback on proposed documents.  He set up <ulink url="http://tools.tldp.org/blog/">http://tools.tldp.org/blog/</ulink> for the same and listed several <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7641:200407:kaoahapddjblcbcdepeb">XML editors</ulink>.  Emma Jane Hogbin <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7647:200407:jklinmkmkkeoaokicenh">indicated</ulink> that the process outlined in the LDP Author Guide was sufficient for proposals and was in favor of 'canning' the blog. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
