<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>5</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-02-04</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

<para>As Eric S. Raymond, author of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Fedora-Multimedia-Installation-HOWTO/">Fedora Multimedia Installation HOWTO</ulink> puts it, this document explains <quote>how to get various proprietary and restricted multimedia Damned Things working</quote> under Fedora Core.  If you have problems getting MPEG, Flash, Java applications, RealMedia or MP3 to run, here's the place to start.  Eric documents the standard tools and various free packages that you can add to your system.</para>
  
</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Kai Schlachter had troubles upgrading his glibc.  He documented the procedure so as other people won't suffer like he did.  He wants to submit his <ulink url="http://www.murphyslantech.de/linux/glibc-howto/glibcinstall.pdf">Glibc HOWTO</ulink> to our collection and awaits your comments.  David Horton already <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6587:200401:neekgpjhpiplegfacnmj">made some suggestions</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Michael Schlenstedt <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6624:200402:lckloedklkonmleklapa">proposed
to write a Linux ISDN HOWTO</ulink>. Michael's document would give some
background information about ISDN and Linux and explain howto handle
installations of i4l as well as capi. A <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6624:200402:lckloedklkonmleklapa">detailed
table of contents</ulink> was posted to the discuss list. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Steve Peace proposed to document the procedure for
installing and configuring qmail-scanner and ClamAV virus scanner
software as a HOWTO for TLDP. A draft version is <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6633:200402:knaceklpnohmfaichkcf">available
for comment</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Hardware-HOWTO/">Hardware HOWTO</ulink>, by Steven Pritchard, has finally been updated after a long period of inactivity.  Version 3.2.2 contains information on the Athlon64 CPUs; the video card section has been updated; notes are added for the IDE RAID 3ware 8000-series cards; there is more info about SATA (serial ATA or disk controllers in plain English) and a configuration update for Western Digital drives.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jorge Godoy, David Merrill, Mark Komarinski and Emma
Jane Hogbin help you to better help us with v4.1 of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/">LDP Author
Guide</ulink>.  This version has updates on the license recommendations
for docs that you submit to TLDP.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Revision 1.1 of Lars Strand's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO/">Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO</ulink>
comes with information on "Traveling through several foreign LAN's" and
"Returning home" and a few other minor document re-structuring
changes.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>ISBN numbers for TLDP documents</title>

<para>Machtelt Garrels posted the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6625:200402:glmdkngljdhkobgohaja">procedure
for obtaining an ISBN</ulink> number for a document of hers in Belgium.
She hopes this will add to TLDP credentials give it a more serious
look.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
