<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>45 &amp; 46</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-11-17</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Noel Llopis wrote a mini-HOWTO on improving fonts on Mandrake (but his general ideas works on any distribution with KDE).  The  document is up for review at <ulink url="http://convexhull.com/mandrake_fonts.html">http://convexhull.com/mandrake_fonts.html</ulink> and would be submitted to the LDP for inclusion in its collection.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>David S.Lawyer sent in updates to the documents that he maintains:
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Modem-HOWTO.html">Modem-HOWTO</ulink> v0.34 has information on distinctive ring workaround where you want the modem to answer phone calls only for certain types of rings like long, short, long, short, etc.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>The v1.11 of <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Plug-and-Play-HOWTO.html">Plug-and-Play-HOWTO</ulink> has a new sub-section on LPC bus in the "How do I Find Devices and How Are They Configured?" section.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>v2.23 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Serial-HOWTO.html">Serial HOWTO</ulink> has information on serial ports on motherboard likely ISA or LPC and also some quick help added.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>v.1.0.6 of Peter Jay Salzman's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-Gamers-HOWTO/">Linux Gamer's HOWTO</ulink> has new information on OpenAL and libraries.  Few typos have been fixed and the document has also been translated into Hungarian. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper did a few minor updates to his <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/">Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide</ulink> and released v3.1.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Artemiy I. Pavlov's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SquashFS-HOWTO/">SquashFS HOWTO</ulink> v1.6 has been changed to catchup with the SquashFS release 2.0.  There are few minor text corrections as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ram Samudrala submitted v1.31 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Cluster-HOWTO.html">Linux Cluster HOWTO</ulink>.  The document discusses setting up high-performance Linux computing clusters.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The v2.5 of Andries Brouwer's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Large-Disk-HOWTO.html">Large Disk HOWTO</ulink> has more information on disk geometry and the 1024 cylinder and other limits for disks.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP review process</para>

<para>A lot of people had complaints that The LDPs review processes were getting in the way of new documents making their way into the collection.  People suggested watermarking documents that have been reviewed (or the opposite) and distinguishing between the documents that have been through the review process and the documents that have not been.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
