<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>35, 36 &amp; 37</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-09-15</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

<para>It's been a while, sorry to have kept you waiting.  Here is the latest addition to our collection:</para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Tor Slettness contributed the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Spam-Filtering-for-MX/intro-purpose.html">Spam Filtering for MX HOWTO</ulink>.  With all the fuss around the subject of spam, this document comes at the time when we need it the most.  Originally written as a documentation for the <application>Exim</application> MTA, Tor adapted the content to be more widely usable.  Everybody who manages mail exchangers will benefit from reading this guide on weeding out the rubbish and reclaiming your mail servers.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Eric S. Raymond brewed a new HOWTO, the <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/">RPM Builder's Tricks and Traps HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>David Horton is working on an <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7700:200407:jjpmpgdogjgchbhdhcfo">LPI study guide</ulink>.  He already asked around to get some feedback on this initiative, and could certainly use a hand.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>In his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+IPv6-HOWTO/revision-history.html">Linux IPv6 HOWTO</ulink> v0.47, Peter Bieringer added notes on <command>proftpd</command>, <command>vsftpd</command> and other daemons.  There are also more links to related sites.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Is your LUG organizing a Linux installation party?  Check out v1.1 of Eric Meyerhoff's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Installfest-HOWTO/">Installfest HOWTO</ulink> for smooth proceedings.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The Bugzilla Guide has been translated by the people over at <ulink url="http://www.traduc.org">traduc.org</ulink>, it is called <ulink url="http://www.traduc.org/docs/guides/lecture/bugzilla/Bugzilla-Guide.html">Le livre de Bugzilla</ulink> in French (v2.16.4).</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Douglas Gilbert sent in v2.1 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SCSI-2.4-HOWTO/">Linux 2.4 SCSI subsystem HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Vim Macros for Editing DocBook Documents</para>

<para>Linuxjournal has an article on <ulink
url="http://www.linuxjournal.com//article.php?sid=7737">Vim Macros for Editing
DocBook Documents</ulink>.  Mitch Frazier's article discusses Macros for key
mappings, tags and entities that can be used with DocBook/XML and other similar
markup languages in VIm.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Enter the Librarian</para>

<para> Stein Gjoen once proposed that the LDP should get professional help in
(re)structuring and integrating its documents and that it should seek help from
the field of Librarian Sciences.  Stein sent in an email update indicating that
Gerd Berget will be doing a masters project on this very topic at TLDP </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>New mirrors</para>

<para>These new mirrors were added to our collection during the last two weeks:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ralph set up a Hong Kong based mirror at <ulink url="http://linux.com.hk/PenguinWeb/mirrors/LDP/" />;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Christian did one in Buenos Aires, Argentina, at <ulink url="http://tldp.xmundo.net/" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The people over at Zambonet on the Philippines have a mirror at <ulink url="http://www.opensourcecommunity.ph/LDP/" />, in the city of Zamboanga.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mehmet Ackin created a new mirror at <ulink url="http://ldp.cnnet.upr.edu" />, located in San Juan, Puerto Rico.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>From EndNote to LyX</para>

<para>Ivan Baldinotti asked if someone read his howto (from endnote to LyX)
that is now at <ulink
url="http://linuxmafia.com/~rick/FromEndnote.tar.gz">http://linuxmafia.com/~rick/FromEndnote.tar.gz</ulink>.
He thanked Rick Moen for hosting the document and is looking for a web storage
to free the space that Rick offered</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>DB2 For Linux HOWTO</para>

<para>Ian Hakes talked to Dan Scott about the DB2 For Linux HOWTO who allowed
him to take over the DB2 for Linux Howto, with basically a full re-write to
cover DB2's latest release V8.2 on up-to-date enterprise and personal Linux
distributions (RHEL 3, SLES 8, SLES 9, along with Red Hat 8, Fedora Core 2,
SuSE Pro 9.1, and possibly Mandrake 10, Gentoo and maybe even Debian).  This
effort was started by another writer, Rory Hinton, who had to drop off the
project, so Ian would be taking primary responsibility for the document, which
is about 60% complete.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Info hard to find?</para>

<para>ESR had some problems submitting a new document, which was the start of a lengthy <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7900:200409:ngakcbimebpdcbalidmi">thread</ulink> on whether or not info for authors is easily accessible.  Emma rounded of the discussion by asking for suggestions for improvement, if necessary.</para>
<para>On the same lines another discussion was started by Venkat Ramana Enaganti, who submitted his <ulink url="http://www.intraperson.com/autodir/Autodir-HOWTO.html">Autodir HOWTO</ulink>.  He was unsure about the status of this document, and after the technical discussion the issue of <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:msn:7892:200409:ofgjmkpbccmbboabfeie">data flows within TLDP</ulink> came up again.</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
