<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>7</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-02-18</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Kai Schlachter polished up the documentation he wrote
about the installation process of <application>glibc</application>, took
a crash course in docbook and sent in his contribution, which he would
like to call the <ulink
url="http://www.murphyslantech.de/linux/glibc-howto/glibcinstall.docbook">Glibc
mini-HOWTO</ulink>. It's not complete yet: Kai still needs to fine tune
this document to be compliant with the newer versions of
<application>glibc</application>, but comments on the document are
welcome.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lars Strand wrote an <ulink
url="http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/code/OLSR-IPv6-HOWTO-v0.5.tar.bz2">OLSR
(Optimized Link State Routing Protocol) IPv6 HOWTO</ulink> (source XML +
images), describing this routing protocol for mobile ad-hoc networks.
The document has had a technical review, the result of which is now
<ulink url="http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/olsr/">here</ulink>.
Lars is of the opinion that a language review would be valuable.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>


<listitem><para>Michael Schlenstedt is working on an ISDN HOWTO <ulink
url="http://www.schlenn.net/~michael/isdn4linux/EN-TOC.txt">(Table of
contents)</ulink> (<ulink
url="http://www.schlenn.net/~michael/isdn4linux/DE-TOC.txt">German
version</ulink>), explaining ISDN-support in 2.6 kernels. In the new
kernels, a lot has changed and Michael wants to describe installation and
give some background information about CAPI and ISDN4Linux so as to be
able to troubleshoot.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Luigi Bitoni proposed a text documenting the combination
of Apache, Tomcat, Sun's JDK and mod_jk. Luc De Louw (author of a
slightly related <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MMBase-Inst-HOWTO/">MMBase Installation
HOWTO)</ulink>, <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6674:200402">suggested</ulink>
combining the efforts, because he is not a Tomcat and mod_jk
specialist.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper has bug fixes and more examples in the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/">Advanced Bash Scripting Guide</ulink> v2.5.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Major points of attention in v0.7 of the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink> are the
inclusion of a discussion about LVM 2 and the addition of a FAQ section.
Author AJ Lewis handed over the copyright to RedHat.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>Iceland Icenet mirror moved</title>

<para>Albert Ragnarsson let us know that the TLDP mirror over at http://www.eldveggir.com/eldveggur/LDP/ no longer exists because he dropped the domain.  A replacement is available from <ulink url="http://ldp.icenet.is/" />.  This mirror is updated daily.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
