<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>10</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-03-10</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Not actually a new document, but Artemio I. Pavlo thinks
it is now worthy of the version number 1.0, and since all
one-dot-ooooh's come here, his is not exception.  So here is the possibly nearly bug free <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SquashFS-HOWTO/">SquashFS HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Kurt Swendson wants you to have a look at this <ulink
url="http://lam32767.tripod.com/">Beowulf Cluster HOWTO</ulink>.  While
we already have a HOWTO about the same subject, he <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7902:200403:bjbkepfimpgooajojbna">argues</ulink>
that the current document is more of a broad background and introduction
to clustering, it needs a practical addition and his document is truly a
how-to, with step by step instructions. Secure access to the
cluster is not covered yet.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>


<listitem><para>Adrian Offerman's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MMBase-Inst-HOWTO/">MMBase Installation
HOWTO</ulink> v0.2.5 contains minor corrections and the Creative Commons
copyright license has been adjusted.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LDAP-HOWTO/">LDAP HOWTO</ulink> v1.09 by Luiz Ernesto Pinheiro Mal&#232;re covers v2.2.x of the <ulink url="http://www.openldap.org/">OpenLDAP</ulink> package and has some general corrections.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Anthony Lissot provided us with an update of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Partition/">Partition HOWTO</ulink>. V3.4.4
resolves the inconsistencies between the HTML and XML formats and the
sections on LILO placement has been updated along with the swap size
discussion.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Updated code examples in the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/cpg/html/">Custom Linux Porting Guide</ulink> by Shie Erlich.  This guide is intended as a worksheet and general advise to porting Linux to a custom PPC board.
  It highlights pitfalls and critical points in the porting process.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>CONSOL and OSWC</title>

<para>Es.tldp.org links to an article by Ismael Olea that <ulink url="http://listas.hispalinux.es/pipermail/lucas/2004-March/004980.html">summarizes the regional meetings for free documentation in Mexico and Malaga</ulink>.  Ismael was at both meetings and presented some of his work there; you can find the links in the article.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item2">
<title>TLDP editors list</title>

<para>The TLDP reviewers and editors are on their list at
<email>editors@en.tdlp.org</email>. In case you are interested, you can
browse through their archives at the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?9:dds:0:200402">editors mailing
list archives</ulink>. </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
