<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>44</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-11-03</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Matt Barnes would like to start a Linux Documentation - Audio
Video project.  The project aims to convert The LDP documents to wave and mp3
format.  The goal of this exercise is to show that it can be done, and that it
should be done.  The intent is to allow someone to download a media file into a
media player and listen to the information rather than always having to read it
and possibly stream them over the internet.  Contact Matthew S Barnes (mbarnes
at bfinity dot net) if you have more ideas.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>iSCSI-Linux HOWTO:  iSCSI is becoming more popular,
particularly on Linux.  Ben Rockwood was bothered by the massive lack of
documentation available and wrote his own, titled "A Quick Guide to iSCSI on
Linux" (<ulink
url="http://www.cuddletech.com/articles/iscsi/index.html">http://www.cuddletech.com/articles/iscsi/index.html</ulink>).
The document is currently considered as the manual for the iSCSI Enterprise
Target project (http://iscsitarget.sourceforge.net/) and is on of the popular
guides to iSCSI on the net.  Ben intends to update the document and
submit it to The LDP for inclusion as a HOWTO rather than maintain it on his own
site as a paper. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ben Rockwood noticed that the Benchmark HOWTO hasn't been updated since 1997.  The unmaintained list shows a new maintainer for the doc, but an email to him got a failed response from the mail server.  Ben is of the opinion that the document could be a bit more heavy on disk subsystems.  Currently the document is geared towards general systems performance.  Ben was wondering if he should start a new Disk-Benchmarking HOWTO and would like your input.  Email benr@cuddletech.com</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>German SMIL tutorial on Linux: The Computing Center of the
University of Kassel produced a SMIL introduction to Linux (around 4 hours of
video, with subtitles in German and some accompanying figures).  Andreas
Matthias wrote in to offer this to The LDP for integration into The LDP but did
not find any support for non-textual formats in.  The (not yet sufficiently
polished product) is at <ulink
url="http://www.uni-kassel.de/hrz/anwendungen/matthias/unix-kurs/online">http://www.uni-kassel.de/hrz/anwendungen/matthias/unix-kurs/online</ulink>.
He was wondering if someone who understands German and has some talent in
laying out descriptive graphics would help them to complete the project.  Please
contact matthias@hrz.uni-kassel.de if you would like to offer help.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Avi Alkalay's HOWTO for Managing Accurate Date and Time (The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TimePrecision-HOWTO/">TimePrecision-HOWTO</ulink>) has been updated to v1.0.8.  The new version has been translated to Hungarian.  The section on why we need a precise clock and the section on chrony have been updated. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Mirrors Information</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Timothy Anderson wrote to tell us that his TLDP mirror URL has been changed from <ulink url="http://ldp.mirrors.tails.org.ru/">http://ldp.mirrors.tails.org.ru/</ulink> to <ulink url="http://ldp.mirrors.prettysamy.org.ru/">http://ldp.mirrors.prettysamy.org.ru/</ulink>. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Alexandru Bradescu-Popa from Romania is maintaining a copy of TLDP.  The mirror is located at <ulink url="http://www.alexbp.ro/ldp">http://www.alexbp.ro/ldp</ulink> (physical location in Bucharest, Romania) and is updated daily.  </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
