<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>33 &amp; 34</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-08-25</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Diego M. Vadell - UYR send a mail to the discuss list asking The LDP to consider the inclusion of his <ulink url="http://compiling.avsnet.com.ar/">Compiling-HOWTO</ulink> in The LDP collection.  This howto wants to answer the question "How to compile", and also give an lightweight explanation of how does an ELF binary works, how does the shared libraries are found and who are the actors of the compiling process, in order to give a system administrator the tools and knowledge to troubleshoot compiling and general library problems.  Comments on his HOWTO are welcome.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jose Maria Lopez's team at bgSEC wrote a fairly comprehensive <ulink url="http://www.bgsec.com/seguridad-fisica-como-1.0.html">Physical Security HOWTO</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.bgsec.com/files/seguridad-fisica-como-1.0.html.bz2">Compressed with bzip2 for downloading</ulink>).  The document would be included in the <ulink url="http://es.tldp.org/">Spanish LDP collection</ulink> and Jose Maria Lopez would like to see the document translated into English and included with the English LDP collection.  Please contact the team if you would like to  help with the translation. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>If every minute is important for you, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Coffee.html">Coffee Making HOWTO</ulink> is just the thing.  Steadily heading for 1.0, v0.90 introduces a name change and info on Coffee+LAMP, apart from other minor changes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Svetoslav Slavtchev's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree-Local-multi-user-HOWTO/">XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO</ulink> has info about the Mandrake/Debian IsolateDevice for configuring the X server to be used by multiple local users.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Bin Nguyen sent in v0.65 of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Filesystem-Hierarchy/html/index.html">Linux Filesystem Hierarchy</ulink>, in which he tells a bit more about himself and adds two new sections, a.o. one for providing feedback.  Also by Binh: the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">Linux Dictionary</ulink>, v0.16.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>A.J. Lewis has additional info about the boot and root filesystems when using LVM.  Apart from that, minor fixes and updates in v0.13 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Minor bug fixes in v1.4 of David Braun's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Disk-Encryption-HOWTO/">Disk Encryption HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David S. Lawyer updated his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Plug-and-Play-HOWTO.html">Plug and Play HOWTO</ulink>.  It now covers <filename>/proc/isapnp</filename> and <application>sysfs</application> in the 2.6 kernels. Some info about hot pluggable devices and USB has been added as well.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Minor corrections in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MP3-CD-Burning/">Linux MP3 CD Burning mini-HOWTO</ulink> v1.11, submitted by Greg Wierzchowski.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>New mirrors:</para>

<para>Jason T. Hardy set up a <ulink url="http://download.uta.edu/mirror/LDP/">TLDP Mirror in Texas, USA</ulink>, Cong Wu set one up that is reachable via <ulink url="http://202.204.80.47">the 202.204.80.47 address</ulink>, only for the students of the Beijing Institute of Technology in China, Chung-Yen Chang created <ulink url="http://cle.linux.org.tw/LDP/">a new Taiwan mirror site</ulink>.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
