<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>41</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-10-13</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

<para>This week brings us, once again, a new addition to our collection:</para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Venkata Ramana Enaganti finalized the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Autodir-HOWTO/intro.html">Autodir HOWTO</ulink>, which explains <application>autofs</application> and how it can be used to create directories in a transparent manner.  It also details the disadvantage of using the <application>pam_mkhomedir</application> module, as well as where it is different from <application>autofs</application>.</para> <para>According to the author: "Autodir offers a simple and effective means to create directories like home directories in a transparent manner. It relies on the autofs protocol for its operation.  This document explains how to create directories on demand using Autodir in a transparent way to the applications. This document also explains using transparent backup feature that is possible with Autodir without bringing system down for backup purpose for all directories managed by Autodir."  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Miroslav Skoric updated his trio, to note the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ryan Cartwright sent in an updated for the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Windows-LAN-Server-HOWTO.html">Windows LAN server HOW-TO</ulink>, which fixes outdated references.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>WordPerfect for Linux continues to be popular, and is still conditionally available.  Consequently, Rick Moen keeps his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/FAQ/WordPerfect-Linux-FAQ/">WordPerfect on Linux FAQ</ulink> up to date.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>AJ Lewis has updates on LVM2 and on how to move a disk-group to another system in his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Christoph Baumann contributed his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/XFree86-Touch-Screen-HOWTO.html">Linux Touch Screen HOWTO</ulink> under the GNU Free Documentation License.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Problems with WWW-HOWTO</para>

<para>Doug Jensen reported the following problems with the WWW-HOWTO in the current LDP collection:
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>No attribution to the author, Pramod Karnad.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Removal of the Intranet-Server-HOWTO licensing.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Coping of Intranet-Server-HOWTO without proper attribution.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Introduction of a new license (an old version of LDP license).</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Multiple licenses, without clearly stating how they are applied.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Lack of proper maintenance.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
Doug indicated that he would like the HOWTO to be removed and possibly reverted to a version
similar to <ulink url="http://hrast.pef.uni-lj.si/docs/en/www_howto/WWW-HOWTO.html">http://hrast.pef.uni-lj.si/docs/en/www_howto/WWW-HOWTO.html</ulink>.
</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Linux HOWTOs in Swedish</para>

<para>The Linux HOWTOs in Swedish package (doc-linux-sv) in debian has been <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=273702">orphaned</ulink>.  Anybody who is interested in maintaining the package should take a look at <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/devel/wnpp/index.html#howto">http://www.debian.org/devel/wnpp/index.html#howto</ulink> on howto adopt a package properly.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
