<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>17</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-04-28</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/OLSR-IPv6-HOWTO/">OLSR IPv6 HOWTO</ulink> by Lars Strand got through our review procedures.  It describes the software and procedures to set up and use the Optimized Link State Routing Protocol with IPv6.  The document also contains links to IPv6 pages and a FAQ.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para></para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Rajesh Fowkar submitted <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9061:200404:jmelnhencffknbfimmlg">updates to the Ext3 mini-HOWTO</ulink>, correcting some confusing typos.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels submitted the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9063:200404:pfifiedcapeiaknbmogi">Bash Beginner's Guide</ulink>.  This document gets you started with Bash scripting and
bridges the gap between the Bash HOWTO and the Advanced Bash Scripting
Guide.  Everybody who wants to make life easier on themselves, power users
and sysadmins alike, can benefit from reading this practical course.  The
guide contains lots of examples and exercises at the end of each chapter,
demonstrating the theory and helping you practice.  Bash is available on
a wide variety of UNIX, Linux, MS Windows and other systems.
</para>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>AJ Lewis' <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink> contains a basic description of Logical Volume Management and explains how it can be implemented on your Linux system.  v0.10 Has minor corrections.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Tabatha takes a holiday</para>

<para>Tabatha Marshall, our review coordinator, takes some time off from TLDP in order to focus on her own publications - she writes novels for teenagers.  Meanwhile Emma Jane Hogbin takes over Tabatha's tasks.</para>
<para>Talking about holidays, our poor Greg, who published all the documents, and poor Sergiusz, manager of our mailinglists and the CVS, can't take some time off, because there wouldn't be anybody to do their jobs while they are away.  We're looking for some backups here, so as Greg and Ser can also take a holiday this summer.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>News item title 2:</para>

<para>News item 2 body.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>News item title 3:</para>

<para>News item 3 body.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Discussion topic title 1:</para>

<para>Discussion topic 1 body.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Discussion topic title 2:</para>

<para>Discussion topic 2 body.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Discussion topic title 3:</para>

<para>Discussion topic 3 body.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
