<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>13</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-03-31</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Gerardo Arnaez, Walt Pennington and Werner Heuser are the authors of the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Medicine-HOWTO/index.html">Medicine HOWTO</ulink>.  And no, this does not tell you where to purchase the cheapest &lt;insert your favorite spam ad for medicine here &gt; ;-)  Rather, it is a collection of links to important Linux and Open Source sites for doctors and other medical personnel.  The HOWTO also discusses the recording, storage, retrieval, exchange and display of medical data, has pointers to mailinglists, information for veterinarians and discussions of various applications, including medical records and imaging applications.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Haowen Zhang browsed our collection and other resources looking for information about the internals of System V Init.  Because he couldn't find what he was looking for, he asked whether it would be useful to have a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6856:200403:olndaoabiighcgnbkaaj">System V Init HOWTO</ulink>.  There has not been a substantial proposal for the content yet, so if you think this might be interesting, join us on the
discuss mailinglist <email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Even though Eric Raymond posted an <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/let-java-go.html">open letter to Sun, arguing in favour of the release of the Java source code</ulink>, Scott McNealy <ulink url="http://gcn.com/vol1_no1/daily-updates/25400-1.html">said that this won't happen any time soon</ulink>.  Jon Fox, who was working on an Enterprise Java document, <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6881:200403:nohedkmjcfkofpfedgpb">has moral objections</ulink> after hearing about this and fears he's wasting time and energy documenting a non-free platform.  He therefore stops working on the Enterprise Java document.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Floris Lambrechts sent in v0.8 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/User-Authentication-HOWTO/">User Authentication HOWTO</ulink>.  This HOWTO explains how user and group information is stored and used with PAM, the Pluggable Authentication Modules.  The update contains language changes and small bug fixes.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

<note><title>Choose a meaningful subject!</title>
<para>Dear Authors and other users of the submission mailinglist,</para>
<para>As you may have notices, the submission mailinglist is an open list and thus a target for spammers.  For your submissions to stand out, choose a sensible, meaningful subject when posting updates.  Include the name of your HOWTO, Guide or FAQ in the subject.  Otherwise it might pass unnoticed!</para>
</note>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Linux Brochure Project to join TLDP:</para>

<para>Barbara Irwin of the Linux Brochure Project (LBP) indicated that <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6846:200403:ejilbecjpnmoeooninhc">
Guylhem Aznar invited LBP</ulink> to join the LDP </para>
<para>Initially, the project developed as a way for printing a flyer for
the Victoria Linux User Group. LBP is a registered project at <ulink url="http://lbproject.sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</ulink>.  <ulink url="http://lbproject.sourceforge.net/examples.html">Various examples</ulink> for US Letter and A4 paper sizes are available.</para>
<para>Greg Ferguson had questions about what Guylhem had in mind and
wanted to know the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6851:200403:ifhbolfhjihbhnkaanhb">areas
of cooperation</ulink> between the two projects, upon which Barbara
explained that the LBP will become a part of TLDP and that LDP can act
as a repository for completed/processed brochures.
</para>

</listitem>

<listitem><para>Errata: Interview with Fred Stutzman:</para>

<para>Because of problems with the conversion of the TLDP Weekly News source XML to RSS feed, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/20040324.xml#interview">interview with Fred Stutzman</ulink> last week was not spread through our RSS feed. </para>
<para>If you've missed this or any other interview, discussion topic or
news item, don't despair.  You can always <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/">catch up on TLDP Weekly News issues</ulink>
and the latest versions by browsing through our archives.
</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="discussions">
<title>Discussions on TLDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Second TLDP CD-ROM distro:</para>

<para>Bradley Glonka reminded us of the fact that his offer to bring out
a TLDP CD-ROM still stands.  He proposed to publish on demand through <ulink url="http://linuxcentral.com">LinuxCentral</ulink>, who are also hosting a <ulink url="http://linuxcentral.com/linux/LDP/">TLDP mirror</ulink>, and donate part of the revenue to TLDP.  However, Greg argued that <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6873:200403:fpppcopimljgjpbfaoin">there is no need for a second CD provider</ulink> and advises that TLDP sticks to the <ulink url="http://www.embeddedlogic.com/ELSweb/LDPCD_info.html">CD offered by Embedded Logic Systems</ulink>.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem><para>De gustibus et coloribus non disputandum:</para>

<para>The Romans knew it already 2000 years ago: don't discuss colour nor taste.  The discussion about a possible new style for TLDP continues.  While author input about their favorite colours is being waved away with the remark that <quote>DocBook enables authors to concentrate on content, they should not worry about formatting and display</quote>, some are concerned about how their documents will look, especially if an <quote>average</quote> colour is chosen.  As <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6878:200403:apjpihhbjhmiefimbdpl">David Horton suggests</ulink>, the only way out of this thread might well be to concentrate on how a document look in plain black-and-white.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
