<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>26</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-06-30</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Gareth Anderson submitted the <ulink url="http://www.karakas-online.de/gnu-linux-tools-summary/">GNU/Linux tools summary</ulink>, which is an attempt at listing common tools available on a GNU/Linux based system.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Stein Gjoen believes his <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9144:200406:hgbphkommepbpkpkgdin">HOWTO generator</ulink> is now ready for review.  It is meant as a tool for TLDP authors who do not want to learn the DocBook markup but just want to submit content.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Venkat Ramana Enaganti had a problem with automatic creation of home-directories when creating LDAP accounts.  He documents his solution in this <ulink url="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/intraperson/Autodir-HOWTO.html?download">Autodir HOWTO</ulink> and waits for your comments.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Greg Porter inherited some old HP servers and wanted to run Linux on them.  The process of installing Linux, however, required a firmware upgrade, which caused him some trouble.  So he wrote a document discussing the <ulink url="http://www.porterdavis.org/computing/hp_boot/">Hewlett Packard Unix Server Firmware and the HP Boot Sequence</ulink>, which he thinks will make a fine companion for the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/HP-HOWTO/index.html">HP HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ray Benjamin wrote a <ulink url="http://www.raybenjamin.com/linux-help-how-to/index.html">Getting Linux Help HOWTO</ulink> and welcomes your comments.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Tor Slettnes is documenting his setup for spam filtering on incoming mail using a combination of Exim, Exiscan, Spamassassin and Greylistd, but <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:msp:7516:200406:makpkgdefnipepahpgob">realized that theory can be split from practice</ulink> to make his document more useful for general application and inclusion into TLDP.</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Miroslav Skoric added info about a couple of his tutorials in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO</ulink>, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Outdated Cable modem HOWTO</para>

<para>Jess Portnoy has some additions and updates for the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Cable-Modem/index.html">Cable Modem HOWTO</ulink> but can not contact the author, Vladimir Vuksan.  He agreed to take over the HOWTO if the original author can not be contacted within a reasonable period of time, and if the license allows for this.  TLDP is currently checking things out.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Bash guide available in print</para>

<para>Fultus books makes the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/index.html">Bash Guide for Beginners</ulink> available in <ulink url="http://store.fultus.com/product_info.php?products_id=66">print on demand</ulink>, while leaving Machtelt Garrels, the author, and TLDP the rights to publish it on-line.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>HOWTO: Presentations with linux</para>

<para><ulink url="http://xtrinsic.com/">Emma Jane Hogbin</ulink> recently talked about <ulink url="http://xtrinsic.com/newtlug/040622/">HOWTO like Presentations</ulink>.  The purpose of the talk was to help people with their own presentations. The slides of the talk address both the preparation for and the presentation of the topic.  There are a few screen shots of some presentation software but no details. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Parallel Processing HOWTO</para>

<para>Hank Dietz indicated that he would be updating the <ulink url="http://aggregate.org/PPLINUX/">Parallel Processing HOWTO</ulink> and mutate it into a guide. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
