<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>16</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-04-21</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The review of Lars Strand's OLSR IPv6 HOWTO is nearing completion.  OLSR is a routing protocol used in mobile ad-hoc networks.  <ulink url="http://www.gnist.org/~lars/work/insc/code/OLSR-IPv6-HOWTO-v0.5.tar.bz2">Here is a preliminary copy of the OLSR IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>, created with the help of the OLSRd developer.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Emma Jane Hogbin submitted an update of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">Reviewer HOWTO</ulink>.  This document contains information for our editors so that they can streamline the look and feel of TLDP documents.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Nearly there with the <ulink url="http://cvs.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/howto/docbook/Kernel-Build-HOWTO/">Kernel Build HOWTO</ulink> by Kwan Lowe.  A lot of our readers have been complaining about the retirement of the Kernel HOWTO, and about the time it takes to rewrite this document.  Good news: your patience will be rewarded very soon.  Our reviewer team is raising efforts to have the language and technical review ready by the end of this week.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Howard Shane came up with the idea of writing a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:msp:7057:200404:biifelfgnkaocpnpjgoj">Home Office</ulink> HOWTO or FAQ, addressing such questions as <quote>how to print different types of files?</quote> and <quote>Which applications to use to print, FAQ and format files and share them among others with non-Linux systems?</quote>.  He argues that much of the information needed by beginning users is out there, but shattered over tens of different documents and thus hard to find.  Howard awaits your input.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Zeeshan Ali asks whether his <ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/zeelists/video-wall.xml">Video-Wall HOWTO</ulink>, using Xinerama and Gstreamer, would be a good addition to TLDP.  The document has been around for a while, but he now converted it to XML and applies for inclusion in our collection.  Send him your comments!. Emma Jane Hogbin <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7077:200404:nokhehdlcjgfemldedhm">had a few questions</ulink> about the documents content and detail.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Martin Rodgers thinks his <ulink url="http://www.wildcard.demon.co.uk/howto/ameol-wine.html">Ameol/Wine HOWTO</ulink> is finished.  Ameol is the off-line reader for the commercial CIX service.  Martin would appreciate input from Ameol users.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>K. Richard Pixley spent most of last week attempting to get an LDAP server up and running for authenticating both linux and samba and <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7065:200404:ekgmocengagkoejbgelf">found</ulink> that the available HOWTOs were helpful, but insufficient.  Richard floated his idea of a HOWTO for this.  Emma Jane Hogbin <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7080:200404:ikndjmbepldekebhjjej">was of the opinion</ulink> that If the current LDAP HOWTO or the LDAP-Implementation-HOWTO are lacking information, then they should be improved. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>AJ Lewis' <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink> v0.9 features an updated FAQ, info about ext3, an updated links section and an overview of LVM2 commands.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Emma Jane Hogbin updated the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/index.html">LDP Author Guide</ulink>.  The v4.4 comes with an added editor credit requirements to the Using DocBook section.  The submission procedure has also been updated.  New documents can now only be added by one of the review coordinators after the successful completion of each of the required reviews. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO/">Linux Mobile IPv6 HOWTO</ulink> has been updated to v1.2 by Lars Strand.  The new version has updates to the links section and the licence has been changed to GNU FDL with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para>Wanted: Game Server HOWTO maintainer</para>

<para>Anders Jensen-Urstad is looking for somebody to take over the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Game-Server-HOWTO/index.html">Game Server HOWTO</ulink>.  The document describes setup and maintenance of the various Quake servers and the Half-Life and Unreal Tournament servers.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Outdated LDP man page</para>

<para>Very few people know that most Linux systems come with an LDP man page that you can display with the <command>man <parameter>LDP</parameter></command> command.  Unfortunately, this man page contains a lot of old links.  The maintainer has been contacted to put this straight, and we hope it doesn't take too long for all distributions to include the corrected man page.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>In-progress list updated</para>

<para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/authors/inprogress.html">list of documents being reviewed</ulink> has been cleaned out rigidly by Emma Jane, who jumps in while Tabatha takes a much-needed holiday.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
