<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>42 &amp; 43</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-10-27</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

<para>We are pleased to announce addition of two new documents to our collection:</para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/8021X-HOWTO/">802.1X Port-Based Authentication HOWTO</ulink>, describing the software and procedures to set up and use IEEE
  802.1X Port-Based Network Access Control using Xsupplicant as
  Supplicant with FreeRADIUS as a back-end Authentication Server.  This work is authored by Lars Strand, whom you know a.o. from the <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/Mobile-IPv6-HOWTO/index.html">Linux Mobile IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Steve Peace and Gregory L. Porter put together the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Qmail-ClamAV-HOWTO/">Qmail-Scanner and ClamAV HOWTO</ulink>, which is a documentation on how to integrate ClamAV, an anti-virus attachment
  scanner and Qmail-Scanner, an anti-virus message content scanner, 
  with an existing installation of a Qmail email server.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Scientific-Computing-with-GNU-Linux/">Scientific Computing with Free software on GNU/Linux HOWTO</ulink> v1.2 is a joined effort of Manoj Warrier, Shishir Deshpande and V. S. Ashoka.  It lists the various available free software and also links on the world wide web to tutorials on getting started with the tools.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels updated the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/index.html">Bash Guide for Beginners</ulink> to v1.4, which is a consolidated update fixing lots of minor bugs and typos.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Christopher Devine produced v1.2 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Encrypted-Root-Filesystem-HOWTO/">Encrypted Root Filesystem HOWTO</ulink>, which has a lot of minor corrections, new examples and updates on all version numbers of kernels and the likes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO.html">Samba Authenticated Gateway HOWTO</ulink> v1.2.1 has more examples on how to build a firewall/gateway with rules set on a per-user basis, having the users authenticated by a Samba-based PDC.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>On demand of the author, Brian J. Watson, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SSI-UML-HOWTO/index.html">Creating SSI Clusters Using UML HOWTO</ulink> has been moved to the unmaintained section.  Brian J. Watson informed us that OpenSSI clusters of virtual UML machines were not as
useful as they thought would be, so support for the UML
"architecture" deteriorated until it was decided to remove it from
the OpenSSI project altogether.  The people over at OpenSSI are contemplating, however, whether it wouldn't be more useful to write a HOWTO on OpenSSI clustering in general.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>New mirror sites:</para>

<para>We can't stress this enough: try to use a <ulink url="http://tldp.org/mirrors.html">mirror</ulink>!  These are the new once since our last announcement:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.mirrors.tails.org.ru/" />, maintained by Timothy Anderson;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://TLPD.mirrors.activenodes.com/" /> (URL change), maintained by Eduardo Valdes</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>


</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Web based docbook document editor</para>

<para>Saqib Ali sent in a tip to make modifications to your Document
written in DocBook online.  <ulink url="http://www.datamech.com/xmlform/formgenerator4.html">http://www.datamech.com/xmlform/formgenerator4.html</ulink> can be used to do the same by pasting either a link to the XML document or the entire document in the "XML data" text input.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
