<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>21</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-05-26</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Artemio has been working with RTLinux for a while, and
wrote installation instructions to help newbies on the RTLinux mailing
list.  His <ulink
url="http://artemio.net/projects/linuxdoc/rtlinux">RTLinux installation
instructions</ulink> are now also a part of the official RTLinux
package.  Artemio would now like to take over the (out dated) <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/RTLinux-HOWTO.html">RTLinux HOWTO</ulink>
and create a RTLinux Installation HOWTO and RTLinux Programming HOWTO
(or, RTLinux Module Programming HOWTO). </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Teus Benschop <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7342:200405:jkbilkjiphddlmiihkcg">proposed
to write</ulink> a Bible Translation HOWTO.  His HOWTO would cover the
software that is currently available for Linux, explain how VMware was
used to use to run the Bible translation software that is available for
Windows, and detail out how to integrate the two OSes to make the best
of the job, and then call for new software to be written.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/mdw/HOWTO/K7s5a-HOWTO.html">K7s5a HOWTO</ulink> describing the Elite K7s5a motherboard is a joint effort of Sebfrance, Andreas Willenbrink, &#192;lvaro Reguly and Paolo Berva.  Version 2.0 contains corrections sent in by the readers.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ricardo Alexandre Mattar posted v1.2 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO.html">Samba Authenticated Gateway HOWTO</ulink>.  This HOWTO documents the creation of a firewall or gateway that uses rules based on user access, in which the users are authenticated by a Samba Primary Domain Controller.  On the outside, you don't notice too many changes; this version is mainly a cleanup of the source code.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels sent in v1.13 of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/">Introduction to Linux guide</ulink>.  Apart from some minor updates, she added references to rdesktop, updated the glossary and thanks the people who translated the guide into Hindi.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LDP-Reviewer-HOWTO/">Linux Documentation
Project Reviewer HOWTO</ulink> v1.4.2 corrects some spelling mistakes
from v1.4.1. Emma Jane Hogbin sent in this new revision.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Artemiy I. Pavlov released the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SquashFS-HOWTO/">SquashFS HOWTO</ulink> v1.1.
This revision has modifications to the HOWTO to keep it current to
SquashFS release 1.3r3. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>New mirror in Belgrado.</para>

<para>Ljubisa Radivojevic volunteered to set up a mirror of TLDP in Belgrado.  With this, he created the first mirror in the Serbia-Montenegro region.  A complete list of our mirrors can be found at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/mirrors.html" />.  Most are updated daily or even multiple times per day, so choose one near to you!</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Bible Translation HOWTO</para>

<para>Teus Benschop <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7311:200405:jkbilkjiphddlmiihkcg">proposed</ulink>
to write a  Bible Translation HOWTO and requested feedback.  People had
different <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7333:200405:ihpahginmljdgbhooeje">ideas</ulink>
about the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7335:200405:emfgfnelnkndefhfjpim">topic
and the content</ulink> of documents that The LDP should host.  Rodolfo
J Paiz <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7336:200405:ehngfbpnepphojhokgdn">posted
his ideas</ulink> on why Teus Benschop's proposal should be given a
chance.  Greg Ferguson <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7317:200405:ifhbolfhjihbhnkaanhb">said</ulink>
that it would be good if Teus could design this in a generic manner
covering available translation software and then, cover the bible
translation as a "case study".  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
