<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>23 &amp; 24</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-06-09/16</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The language review of the Linux Daemon HOWTO is completed.  You can have a <ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/howto/linuxdoc/Linux-Daemon-HOWTO.sgml?rev=1.2&amp;content-type=text/vnd.viewcvs-markup">preview in our CVS</ulink>.  Thanks to S. Keeling, who also completed the <ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/howto/docbook/Beowulf-HOWTO.xml?rev=1.2&amp;content-type=text/vnd.viewcvs-markup">Beowulf HOWTO</ulink> language review and the <ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/howto/docbook/Win%2bBSD%2bLinux-Install-HOWTO.xml?rev=1.15&amp;content-type=text/vnd.viewcvs-markup">Win+BSD+Linux-Install HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>After some discussion, Teus Benschop included input and remarks from the discuss mailinglist in his <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:9115:200406:obdnpahpamnbgbknfjke">Bible Translation Software on Linux Using Windows Emulators HOWTO</ulink>.  This does not mean that TLDP is getting religious: this HOWTO purely discusses the technical aspects of the software.  Teus also explains why his document is, after all, not conceived as a general translation HOWTO, using the Bible as a practical example.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>S. Keeling came up with the idea of a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7430:200406:nmcomociibbmccbkjhic">Heavy Mail User HOWTO</ulink>, which would discuss high E-mail load from the user's point of view, dealing with the problems caused by being subscribed on multiple mailinglists, having low bandwidth and an under-powered processing system.  The author awaits your comments on the <ulink url="http://www.spots.ab.ca/~keeling/Heavy-MailUser-HOWTO.xml">provisional XML source</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jesse Long proposed to write a <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7382:200406:lccmcephmpahjfjkicec">Bootsplash HOWTO</ulink>.  Bootsplash enables you to configure your
backgrounds for your virtual consoles, using the Linux Kernel's frame buffer
facilities.  V. Alex Brennen <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7383:200406:apmkoaikdifbedjklddi">was of the opinion</ulink> that a Framebuffer and BootSplash HOWTO would be a good addition to The LDP collection and pointed us to the <ulink url="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=49036">Gentoo Forums: Framebuffer and BootSplash HOWTO</ulink>.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>On demand of Gerardo Arnaez, the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Wireless-Link-sys-WPC11/">Link-sys WPC11 Mini-HOWTO</ulink> is obsoleted.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Artemiy Pavlov skipped a couple of official releases and published v1.5 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SquashFS-HOWTO/">SquashFS HOWTO</ulink>.  This version has improved descriptions, instructions for the 2.6 kernels and lots of comparisons between SquashFS 1.x and 2.x.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/">LVM HOWTO</ulink> by AJ Lewis, describing Linux' Logical Volume Manager, has updated FAQ entries in v.0.12.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Jakob &#216;stergaard and Emilio Bueso are co-authoring the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Software-RAID-HOWTO.html">Software RAID HOWTO</ulink>.  New in v1.1: instructions on getting and installing the RAID tools, GRUB setup to boot from a RAID 1 and logical volume management on a RAID configuration.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels sent in an updated version of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/">Bash Guide for Beginners</ulink>.  v1.2 of the document has an added index and more markup in screen sections. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>New mirrors</para>

<para>It's amazing how many people want a local copy of the LDP collection.  These are the new mirrors added last week:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.opensourcemirrors.org" />: set up by John Ellis in Austin, Texas, USA.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://mirror.narfum.org/LDP/" />: by Karel Bemelmans in The Netherlands.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.signal42.com/LDP/" />: by Paul Brown in San Jose, California, USA.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.linuxpowered.com/LDP/" />: by Vidyut Luther in Dallas, Texas, USA.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://cfe.homeunix.org/ldp/" />: by Ernesto Celis in Victoria, Tamaulipas, Mexico.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Libre Software Meeting 2004</para>

<para>TLDP members Emma Jane Hogbin from Canada, Guylhem Aznar from France and Machtelt Garrels from Belgium will attend the <ulink url="http://www.libresoftwaremeeting.org">Libre Software Meeting 2004</ulink> in Bordeaux, France from the 6th to the 10th of July.</para>
<para>Meet them and many other Open developers, techies and supporters at this annual conference that will be held for the 5th time.  This year's program features among many other topics the first open content management systems meeting, FREE (Free Resources for Education in Europe), high-level programming languages for application development, accessibility and a graphics design contest.</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>LDP Manifesto</para>

<para>Christopher Priest was trying to <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7436:200406:cnicoapgfafgabnfphic">understand the purpose of TLDP</ulink>.  David Lawyer <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:7442:200406:claiepedajakajhoajgg">explained</ulink> the original intention and the status.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>HOWTO contribute to The LDP</title>

<para><ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
