<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>11</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-03-17</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>


<para>Niko Sauer finished the procedures for submitting and revising his
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Flash-Memory-HOWTO/">USB Flash Memory
HOWTO</ulink>.  It describes both VFAT and ext2 formatting of the
devices and also has notes on how to support them with a 2.6 kernel.
Nico is the practical sort of person: he includes a section about making
the memory sticks accessible to users and one about maintenance.  You
can try it out immediately on your <ulink
url="http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=04/03/11/139207&amp;mode=thread&amp;tid=159&amp;tid=186">Swiss army knife</ulink>!</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Claudio Cattazzo from the <ulink url="http://it.tldp.org">ILDP</ulink> was so kind as to announce the translations into Italian of the following documents:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Apache-Compile-HOWTO/index.html">The Apache-Compile-HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-Install/index.html">The DocBook-Install HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/DocBook-OpenJade-SGML-XML-HOWTO/index.html">DocBook XML/SGML Processing Using OpenJade</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+IPv6-HOWTO/index.html">The Linux+IPv6-HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/NIS-HOWTO/index.html">The NIS HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Program-Library-HOWTO/index.html">The Program-Library-HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Quota.html">The Quota HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Security-HOWTO/index.html">The Security HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>A big Thank You goes to Michele Ferritto, Giuseppe Briotti, Beatrice Torracca, Daniele Masini, Fabio Zanotti, Riccardo Vianello, Alessio Rolleri and Elisabetta Galli for translating and reviewing these documents.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Ari Makela updated the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Finnish-HOWTO/">Finnish HOWTO</ulink>.  Version 2.0.23 contains instructions for adapting Debian and some minor changes.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Text-Terminal-HOWTO.html">Text Terminal HOWTO</ulink> has been around for quite some time, but it is still useful <emphasis>and</emphasis> maintained, even though it discusses rather archaic hardware.  New in v1.35: info on the Wyse 60 emulator.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ralf H&#246;lzer's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Cryptoloop-HOWTO/">Cryptoloop HOWTO</ulink> v1.2 has a better comparison between Cryptoloop encryption and Loop-AES encryption of a partition, and more explanations on reasons to use either one or the other.  Ralf also announces the deprecation of Cryptoloop in the 2.6 kernels, where it will be replaced by dm-crypt.  While the code for dm-crypt is cleaner, it is still under development and thus far, no user-space tools are available.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels got some more input from readers and
decided it's time to ask publication of v1.12 of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/index.html">Introduction to
Linux</ulink> guide. This version includes notes on running gnome applications
in KDE and vv., A new section on signals and stopping/re-nicing
processes. The Xcdroast pic is deleted and KAudioCreator has been added.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper has an update ready for the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/index.html">Advanced Bash Scripting
Guide</ulink>, another work that keeps on growing. This revision
contains extra entries on different commands, documentation links,
further comments in the examples and stylistic changes. Mendel maintains
a full length <ulink
url="http://personal.riverusers.com/~thegrendel/Change.log">ChangeLog</ulink>
too. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The v1p17 version of the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/NC-HOWTO.html">Linux NetStation
HOWTO</ulink>. Kris Buytaert fixed some links in the document and would
like to thank David Gilles for pointing out the mistakes.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>Mirroring TLDP</title>

<para>The <ulink url="http://tldp.org/mirrors.html">TLDP mirror page</ulink> is now up to date.  After a long period of blocking, Jens Hardings was the first to activate a <ulink url="http://mirrors.csol.org/LDP/">new mirror in Chile</ulink>.</para>
<para>We could do with some extra mirrors, for instance in Costa Rica,
Croatia, French Guiana, Indonesia, Macau, Pakistan, Peru,  Puerto Rico,
Russia and Ukraine, where we have none for the moment (There is a
<ulink
url="http://tille.soti.org/images/tldp-world.jpg">cool world map</ulink>
of the TLDP mirrors).  And we could
certainly do with some extra mirrors in China.  Candidates, anyone?
Contact us through the <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>
address!</para>

<para>Tille <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:6820:200403:ceejnklaecengajdijnf">posted
a summary</ulink> of the update frequency of the mirrors and plans for
weeding out the out-of-date ones. </para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item2">
<title>Spotlight on TLDP</title>

<para>We've certainly know worse times as far as advertisement is concerned:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>LinuxJournal features a 2-page <ulink url="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article.php?sid=7433">article about TLDP history</ulink> entitled <quote>Inside TLDP, a behind-the-scenes look at the evolution of the Linux Documentation Project</quote>, which has been partly published before in TLDP WN issues <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/20030617.html">9/2003</ulink> and <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn/20030701.html">10/2003</ulink>.  The article contains explanations on the name change from LinuxDoc to TLDP and completes the history from the point on where it stopped in our last publication of the matter.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item3">
<title>TLDP Tools Page</title>

<para>Saqib Ali's popular tools for The LDP can be accessed directly
from <ulink url="http://tools.tldp.org/">http://tools.tldp.org</ulink>.
Saqib's Online DocBook XML Validator / Transformer is also linked from
there. </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
