<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2004</volumenum>
  <issuenum>8</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2004-02-25</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ TLDP</title>

  

<para>Feiyun Wang presents us with an interesting study guide annex source commentary in his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-i386-Boot-Code-HOWTO/">Linux i386 Boot Code HOWTO</ulink>.  The document has been designed as a guide to the i386 boot code for <quote>kernel newbies</quote>, explaining the different <filename>Makefile</filename>s, the bootsector, how the compressed image is loaded and so on, all the way to how the kernel is extracted, loaded and activated with the correct settings.</para>
<para>For kernel veterans the document is meant to be an overview and reference to more advanced reading.</para>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-for-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Eric S. Raymond submitted two updates to his documents,
the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7672:200402:llamepbjijfidfififlo">UPS
HOWTO</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7673:200402:ieggnmbilomcfbhojpnd">UNIX Hardware Buyer HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Sébastien François Is working on a HOWTO documenting
the installation of Debian on the Apple iBook G4.  You can look at
<ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7612:200402:oioikpenblidgckodbop">the
first draft here</ulink> - posted to the submit mailinglist in
enthusiasm, but Tabatha <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?5:mss:7623:200402:oioikpenblidgckodbop">indicated</ulink>
to Sébastien that document needs to go through the official procedures first.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Ian Bruntlett wants to do something about bad programming advice and asks for your opinion about this <ulink url="http://www.accu.org/resources/public/terse/learn.htm">HOWTO learn a programming language</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Andrew Schulman proposes this <ulink url="http://home.comcast.net/~andrex/Debian-nVidia/index.html">Debian nVidia HOWTO</ulink> as a replacement for the <ulink url="http://www.madcow404.com/buyle/Nvidia_drivers_Debian_3_0.html">existing mini-HOWTO</ulink> hosted at madcow404.  Your comments will be greatly appreciated.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>John Eikenberry's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/AI-Alife-HOWTO-5.html">AI and Alife HOWTO</ulink> (v2.0 now) takes us on an introductory tour through different systems that simulate intelligence.  John explains about traditional <emphasis>expert systems</emphasis>, neural networks and evolutionary computing, but also touches on the subject of more complex methods such as <emphasis>Alife</emphasis>.  This document is certainly worth looking at if you want something else than everyday application and coding for a change, and contains plenty of links for further reading.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David Horton's <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Pocket-Linux-Guide/html/">Pocket Linux Guide</ulink> v2.1 contains bug fixes, corrections of typo's and other beauty fixes, and adds a couple of useful tips for automation and ease of composition of your own <emphasis>mini-Linux</emphasis>.  According to David, the Pocket Linux Guide is an ideal preparation for those who want to build confidence to explore larger and more complex source-code-only projects later on.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Chris Karakas is proud to announce v2.0 of the <ulink url="http://www.karakas-online.de/EN-Book/">PHP-Nuke HOWTO</ulink>, which is with its 500+ pages actually becoming more of a guide, detailing almost every aspect of PHP-Nuke.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<sect2 id="news-item1">
<title>TLDP Mirrors</title>

<para>Mirror maintenance has been pushed to the background the last year, because our webmaster, Greg Ferguson, was way too overloaded with work to deal with this.  However, new volunteers have offered to take this job off of Greg's shoulders.</para>
<para>All sites mirroring TLDP will be contacted shortly to see if our info is still up to date.  Additionally, new mirror sites will once more be accepted.  Maintainers of mirror sites are encouraged to use <command>rsync</command> and are required to send us the following information:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Maintainer name</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Maintainer E-mail address</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Update frequency</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Location</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Use the <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email> address for more info if you want to become a TLDP mirror site.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="news-item2">
<title>Status of the Kernel HOWTO</title>

<para>It's been a while since the decision to take the Kernel HOWTO off-line for revision.  Since we're getting a lot of requests about this document, we thought an overview of the progress might be appropriate.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The last version of the Kernel HOWTO from Brian Ward can be downloaded from our CVS repository at <ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/howto/linuxdoc/Attic/Kernel-HOWTO.sgml?rev=1.20&only_with_tag=MAIN&hideattic=0&content-type=text/vnd.viewcvs-markup" />.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Kwan Lowe is writing the replacement, which is more or less finished and browseable from <ulink url="http://www.digitalhermit.com/~kwan/kernel.html" />.  Kwan changed the name to <quote>Kernel Rebuild Guide</quote>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Brain Ward, the original author of the Kernel HOWTO, <ulink url="http://www.o--o.net/comp/kernel-howto/">plans to release an alternative document</ulink> for the new kernel.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="feedback">
<title>HOWTO contribute to TLDP</title>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) is working on developing
free, high quality documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system. If
you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.</para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled and edited by Machtelt Garrels and
Y Giridhar Appaji Nag with help from several other people.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
