<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>16</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-04-20</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Clam AV IFrame exploit - False alarm</para>

<para>Clam AV indicates that it detected a few exploits in The LDP
archives in case you are mirroring them.  Specifically, files from the
LDP/LGNET and the LDP/LG directories.  These are false positives and not
a cause for worry.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP Volunteer Database</para>

<para>Martin Wheeler setup a LDP online database of author skillset
profiles.  <ulink url="http://startext.demon.co.uk/tldp/">The DB</ulink>
however, is not restricted to authors and one can go and enlist
themselves if they would like to volunteer for technical reviews,
Docbook conversion, admin tasks, proofing/editing, language reviews,
language translations etc.  There is a <ulink
url="http://startext.demon.co.uk/cgi-bin/htgrep_skillset.cgi?file=SKILLSET&amp;isindex=linguist*&amp;boolean=auto&amp;style=ol&amp;grab=yes">sample
entry</ulink> and also a <ulink
url="http://startext.demon.co.uk/tldp/HOWTOcategories.txt">list of HOWTO
categories</ulink> for reference to volunteers for the above.  This
follows on close heels of the discussion on The LDP discuss list on
subject specialists and subject volunteers. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Choosing an XML editor</para>

<para>The Arts and Humanities Data Service of UK published a <ulink
url="http://ahds.ac.uk/creating/information-papers/xml-editors/">review
of XML editors</ulink> based on technical report titled Benchmarking
XML-editors by Thijs van den Broe.  The report looks at 23 different
editors and benchmarks them against various features (eg, Multilingual
text input and display, Support for different schema languages).  It
also presents the results of an evaluation exercise where different user
groups tried a number of the editors.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Documentation Licensing FAQ</para>

<para>From this week's <ulink
url="http://www.debian.org/News/weekly/2005/16/">Debian weekly
news</ulink>: Jacobo Tarrio <ulink
url="http://lists.debian.org/debian-legal/2005/04/msg00332.html">released</ulink>
a draft <ulink
url="http://jacobo.tarrio.org/Documentation_licensing_FAQ">FAQ</ulink>
on documentation licensing. In this document he summarises several
questions and answers about this topic which should be useful especially
for people who have questions about the <ulink
url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GNU FDL</ulink>. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>LDAP subject matter expert</para>

<para>Machtelt Garrels (Tille) signed up as the LDAP matter expert and
after the spirit of David Lawyer's idea to take responsibility for the
subject for which you are an expert, she will have a go at the current
documents that deal with LDAP: primarily the LDAP HOWTO and LDAP
Implementation HOWTO, but also these HOWTOs which have LDAP as a
sub-subject: Apache Webdav LDAP HOWTO and Apache Compile HOWTO.  Some of
these are quite old, I'll contact the authors and check if they are
still maintaining their document.  As this is a "pilot project", Tille
will keep us posted. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://ldp.pingo.org">http://ldp.pingo.org</ulink> maintained by
igor.mozetic@uni-mb.si in Ljubljana, Slovenia and updated daily.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
