<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>21</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-09-21</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP documents in Linux distros</para>

<para>Machtelt Garrels <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9659:200509:ekigohadccfepdpebdjg">wanted
to know</ulink> which distributions included the LDP documents and
called for volunteers to contact distributions that don't include them
and follow it up with a discussion.  Greg Ferguson indicated that he
talked to a RedHat individual who worked on the docs package and was
told that it took a fair bit of work to package the HOWTOs in a
reasonably sane way and they had limited space on CD.  The RedHat 7.3
errata said that <quote>Several complaints were received concerning the
correctness of the LDP documentation as well as the difference in
procedures between the LDP documentation and the official Red Hat Linux
documentation. Thus, it was decided to no longer provide the LDP
documentation on the Documentation CD</quote> </para>

<para>Among the popular Linux distributions, Debian, SUSE, Slackware and
Ubuntu seem to include the LDP document collection.</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Adrian Offerman sent in a update to his <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MMBase-Inst-HOWTO/">MMBase-Inst-HOWTO</ulink>.
The document, now at 1.0 after the LDP review procedures describes the
installation of the MMBase  content management system on a Red Hat Linux
distribution, using the Tomcat application server, and integrating it
with MySQL and Apache.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://linux.com.hk/PenguinWeb/mirrors/LDP/" /> maintained by
Ralph Lam in Hong Kong and update daily.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.active.co.il/ldp/" /> maintained
by Rami Addady and Gonen Radi of Activetech Ltd.  The mirror server is
collocated in big local ISP, and the server in connected to Israel
Internet backbone</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.linkmost.com" /> maintained by
Maple in Tokyo, Japan and updated daily. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining <email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a
low volume discussion mailing list).  You can also send your suggestions
to <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt
Garrels (Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several
other people.  To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox,
subscribe to the <email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.
Back issues are available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn" />
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
