<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>9 &amp; 10</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-03-09</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Gareth Anderson would like to include the GNU Linux Command
Line Tools Summary document
http://www.karakas-online.de/gnu-linux-tools-summary/introduction.html which
he has been working on since more than two years, in The LDP collection.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Coert wrote a Secure Internet for Small Office / Home Office
HOWTO.  A draft version of the document is available at
http://www.cybcon.com/~coert/linux/siso/index.html.  The HOWTO describes how to
bring up your own Firewall, Wireless Access Point and VPN Server on a single
board computer.  It currently uses the Geode SC1100 and Atheros WiFi NIC, but
could easily be extended to include other hardware, drivers and services.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Zouhir Hafidi wrote a HOWTO about setting up Linux and Windows
Terminal Services in Schools and would like to submit it to TLDP.  A draft
version of the document is available from
http://math.univ-lille1.fr/~hafidi/terminal-services/ and your comments are
most welcome.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>lists@mjhall.org proposed to write a Computational Linguistics
HOWTO.  This HOWTO would briefly survey the major branches of contemporary
computational linguistics and the major types of linguistics software, and then
catalogue Linux software available in each category. An extensive bibliography
and list of resources such as websites and mailing lists would also included.
Some general advice would also be offered on system configuration for
linguistics work.  Martin Wheeler and Rahul Sundaram were excited about the
idea. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Mathieu Deschamps has offered to translate the Linuxbios guide
to English.  If you were waiting for this document to be available in English,
this is some good news.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Version 1.6 (Last updated 20050301 Edition) of Bash Guide for
Beginners http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/ by Machtelt
Garrels has minor problems corrected, more keywords, and info about new Bash
3.0.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Version 1.17 (20050301 Edition) of Machtelt Garrels
"Introduction to Linux, A Hands on Guide"
http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/ has edits for lots of little details
that were outdated, several notes, and some more info about new apps has been
added.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Mirrors</para>
<para>These are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	
	<listitem><para>http://ldp.mirror.nickstallman.net/ - hosted by Nick
	Stallman in Kingston, Massachusetts and updated daily.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>http://ldp.mirror1.wefixtech.co.uk/ - hosted by Tony
	Dodd in Ashburn, VA, USA and updated every other day.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>http://ldp.hosting-concepts.com - hosted by Peter in
	Amsterdam, The Netherlands and updated daily.  </para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>http://ldp.cherryfive.com - hosted by Daniel Prinsloo
	in London, UK and updated weekly.  </para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Gerd Berget's report on The LDP</para>

<para>Gerd Berget's report on The LDP is available for download from
http://www.nyx.net/~sgjoen/rapport.pdf However, the document has not yet been
translate to English.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Modifiability of documentation and software</para>

<para>In a discussion thread concerning modifiability of documentation and
data, Rahul Sundaram commented that most people dont care about whether the
source code is modifiable but that, that doesn't mean we say we dont care about
Free or open source software.  David Lawyer responded indicating that there is
a difference between software and documents.  David said <quote>Software needs
to be free since it's relatively hard to write it and much of it is reusable.
But for documentation, the situation is a lot different.  I've looked at a few
of our old documents that are out-of-date and they mostly need to be entirely
rewritten.  This can be done even if the doc doesn't allow modification.  Why?
Because one uses the info in the obsolete doc plus information in other docs to
write a new doc.  Facts are not copyrighted.</quote>  David was in favour of
modifiable documents, but not as stronly as Rahul was.  An interesting
discussion ensued.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">Back issues</ulink> are available at
http://tldp.org/ldpwn.  </para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
