<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>23</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-06-08</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Proposal for revised license and license requirements.</para>

<para>David Lawyer proposed modifying both the LDP Boilerplate License and the
Manifesto for the purpose of allowing modification to documents in all cases
where the author can't be located.  David, initiating the discussion, said,
<quote>While I support the right of an author (in some cases) to not allow
modification without the author's consent, what about the case where the
document needs revision and author can't be located?  I think our manifesto
needs to be changed to require that any license must allow modification if the
author can't be located after searching on the Internet.</quote>  He said that a
no-modify option to The LDP's Boilerplate License be included with it, to be
effective only if the author selects this option:  Modification would be
prohibited unless the author can't be located.  Furthermore, while LDP would
permit this option we would not encourage it as is currently stated in the
manifesto: "It is not required that the documents be modifiable, but it is
encouraged."  Further, people had comments on David's proposal.  The archive
thread is <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:sss:9369:200506:ajdblngbheknbbnkmcla" />
</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper's <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/index.html">Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide</ulink>, An in-depth exploration of the art of shell scripting is now at v3.5. Plenty of things have changed since the last version v3.4, a complete change log is available from <ulink url="http://personal.riverusers.com/~thegrendel/Change.log" />.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Stephan Reuter has started the translation of the Debian Jigdo mini-HOWTO to German.  The document should be available from Stephan's collection at <ulink url="http://linux.shiningdeath.de/howto-de.shtml" /> very soon. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>In case you have been seeing 404 errors from our mirrors, please check
that things are all set right now.  After the move of our data to another
diskset, some things had been forgotten, and the rsync server configuration was
out of date, but not anymore.  </para>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.mirrors.tailsdiapers.com/" /> maintained by Timothy Anderson in Newport News, VA, US and updated daily.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
