<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>14 &amp; 15</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-04-13</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP documents RPM for Fedora?</para>

<para>Rahul Sundaram indicated that he is planning to package The LDP
docs for Fedora Extras.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Docbook templates?</para>

<para>Jaqui Greenlees was wondering where he can find the template file
for the HOWTOs.  Trevor Harmon replied pointing him to <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/templates-book.html">Links
in the author guide</ulink> to the templates.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>LDP functioning</para>

<para>Rodolfo J. Paiz said, with a <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:sss:9237:200504:bjbgnonlmmobjojdkkop">small
hint of sadness</ulink>, that he will shortly be un-subscribing from the
LDP lists. In the roughly 10 months he has been there, he has not found
the time to make a more significant contribution (for several reasons)
and believed that it is best that he focuses his efforts elsewhere.
People went on to discuss what could be done to address his concerns and
the topic of subject specialists was brought up again, upon which David
Lawyer said, <quote>I just want to remind people that my proposal for
subject specialists was not just for people to list themselves as
specialists, but for them to assume responsibility for all the docs in
their field of specialty.  This responsibility would begin with the
specialist reviewing all the docs in this subject and possibly
suggesting mergers or splits.  Also, if some (or even all) of the docs
are out-of-date, the subject specialist would need to either get the
existing authors to redo them or (in many cases) recruit new authors.
One can use the Internet for recruiting: Find people who discuss the
topic on various mailing lists (and who know what they are writing
about), contact local Linux User Groups, etc.  So, the subject
specialist is both a reviewer, coordinator (merge or split), and
recruiter.  It's a lot of work.  The categories (subjects) need to be
selected so that there will be at least a few docs in that subject.
Also, in some cases, the subject specialist may also be the author of a
doc in that subject area.</quote>.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Trevor Harmon submitted a <ulink
url="http://doc.ece.uci.edu/~tharmon/files/TimeSys-Linux-Install-mini-HOWTO.html">TimeSys
Linux Install mini HOWTO</ulink> for review.  The document is intended
to be a quick-start guide for installing TimeSys Linux on a typical
desktop workstation.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Jim Lieb proposed to write a Kernel Tunable Parameters
HOWTO that would be a reference for all of the tuning parameters
available in the kernel as of version 2.4.22 and 2.6.11.  He already had
a few drafts in place.  Rahul Sundaram said that the right place for
such a dynamic document would probably be the kernel sources in the
Documentation directory.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Rot Hopkins proposed to write a Mounting Windows
partitions HOWTO.  This document came about because he had a dual boot
system with a Chinese version of Windows 2K, which had file names in
both Chinese and Japanese, and these file names weren't displaying
correctly.  The document would talk about (1) umask - The true way in
which it is used to calculate file/dir permissions (2) mount and fstab -
various options required for mounting a vfat partition and (3) timestamp
- Thrown in for those who are interested. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Miroslav "Misko" Skoric updated the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS
mini-HOWTO</ulink>, <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO
mini-HOWTO</ulink> and <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO</ulink>
documents.  They are now at versions v1.33, v3.23 and v2.22
respectively. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Avi Alkalay, Donovan Rebbechi and Hal Burgiss's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Font-HOWTO/">Optimal Use of Fonts on
Linux</ulink> has been updated to v2005-03-31.  Avi's changes for this
version has improved desktop configuration guidelines for higher
resolution screens, and a better layout for authors.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://www.nymphomatic.org/mirror/LDP/">http://www.nymphomatic.org/mirror/LDP/</ulink>
maintained by Marko Crnic in Zagreb, Croatia (Hrvatska) and updated
daily. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://www.linwiz.com/ldp/">http://www.linwiz.com/ldp/</ulink>
maintained by Roland Venter in Auckland, NZ and updated daily as against
twice a week before. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://tldp.attrition.jp">http://tldp.attrition.jp</ulink>
maintained by ryan@attrition.jp in Tokyo, Japan and updated daily.  This
is the first official mirror in Japan.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://opensourcemirrors.org/tldp">http://opensourcemirrors.org/tldp</ulink>
maintained by osm@hostwaydcs.com in Austin, TX, USA and updated daily at
2am. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://tldp.corporacionlinux.cl">http://tldp.corporacionlinux.cl</ulink>
maintained by Rodrigo Henriquez M. in Santiago, Chile and updated daily.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://www.linux.org.py/LDP/">http://www.linux.org.py/LDP/</ulink>
maintained by Oliver (mirror@linux.org.py) in Paraguay and updated
daily. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://ldp.mirrorplus.org">http://ldp.mirrorplus.org</ulink>
maintained by admin@mirrorplus.org of mirrorplus.org in Munich, Germany
and updated daily. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://debian.phys.hacettepe.edu.tr/LDP">http://debian.phys.hacettepe.edu.tr/LDP</ulink>
maintained by Mustafa Mithat Bayramgil in Ankara (Hacettepe University
Physics Eng.  Dept.), Turkey and updated 6 times a day.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://mirror.pacific.net.au/ldp/">http://mirror.pacific.net.au/ldp/</ulink>
maintained by mirror-team@pacific.net.au in Sydney, Australia and
updated 3 times daily.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://ldp.mirrors.asianbaptist.org/">http://ldp.mirrors.asianbaptist.org/</ulink>
maintained by Matthew Isam in Tulsa, Oklahoma, US.  Updated daily.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://viveka.math.hr/LDP/">http://viveka.math.hr/LDP/</ulink> the
only mirror in Croatia, maintained by Vedran Sego in Zagreb, Croatia and
updated daily (at 03:05 local time).  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://ldp.rospot.com/">http://ldp.rospot.com/</ulink> maintained
by Marius David in Timisoara, Romania and updated daily.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
