<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>18</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-05-04</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Local links</para>

<para>Several people already pointed out that our <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/docs.html">docs page</ulink> has absolute
pointers back to iBiblio, whether you use the main site or a mirror.
Because the mirrors do have the complete collection, having absolute
links is rather pointless.  The issue is now being dealt with and local
links will be made available soon.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP history</para>

<para>Greg Ferguson put up an article <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/history.html">TLDP history</ulink> that was
published earlier in LinuxJournal.  Some feedback, however, still needs
to be incorporated to make it accurately reflect what happened during
the last 10 years.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Unmaintained Documents</para>

<para>Guido Gonzato sent in a mail indicating that he doesn't have the
time to maintain the Configuration HOWTO, From DOS/Windows to Linux
HOWTO, From VMS to Linux HOWTO and the Saving Space mini-HOWTO.  If you
would like to maintain any of these documents, send a mail to the
<email>discuss@en.tldp.org</email> list.  Thank you Guido for writing
and maintaining these documents so far.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>OpenSource XML authoring tools</para>

<para>Saqib Ali is covering VEX and ButterflyXML in his article for Free
Software Magazine.  The article might be interesting for HOWTO authors
and editors.  The HTML version is at <ulink
url="http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/free_issues/issue_03/practical_applications_xml/"/>.
</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-released">

<title>New documents @ The LDP</title>

<para></para>
  
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Trevor Harmon finalized the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TimeSys-Linux-Install-HOWTO/">TimeSys Linux
Install mini-HOWTO</ulink>, which is a quick-start guide for installing
TimeSys Linux on a typical desktop workstation.  In the words of the
author <quote>TimeSys Linux is a derivative of Linux created by TimeSys
Corporation. It includes a fully preemptible kernel, a constant-time
scheduler, fully schedulable interrupt handlers, fully schedulable
soft-IRQs, and reduced interrupt disable times. These features reduce
latency to a point where TimeSys Linux can be used as a Real-Time
Operating System (RTOS).</quote>.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Nicolas Dufour prepares submission of the <ulink
url="http://www.nemoworld.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=39&amp;Itemid=70">Linux
Aviation HOWTO</ulink>, listing useful software for private, commercial
and military pilots, airlines, airports and anything having to do with
aeronautics.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels proposes <ulink
url="http://tille.xalasys.com/training/tldp/flowcharts.php">new versions
of the flowcharts explaining TLDP workings</ulink>.  Yaroslaw Fedevych
helped making them more accessible by re-styling the <ulink
url="http://docs.linux.org.ua/stuff/tldp/pubprocess.pdf">Publishing
Process Flowchart</ulink> and the <ulink
url="http://docs.linux.org.ua/stuff/tldp/maint.pdf">Maintenance Process
Flowchart</ulink>.  Yaroslaw's versions are put forward for publication.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>David Ranch updated the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/IP-Masquerade-HOWTO/">Linux IP Masquerade
HOWTO</ulink>.  It has now more comments in the example rulesets.  Apart
from that lots of polishing has been done to streamline this HOWTO.  The
the rc.firewall-iptables-stronger ruleset was updated to fix a typo.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Avi Alkalay updated the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TimePrecision-HOWTO/">Managing Accurate Date
and Time</ulink> to v1.0.9.  This update includes a link to
french translation.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://xsteadfastx.is-a-geek.org/LDP" /> by Marvin Preuss, in Wolfsburg, Germany.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://tldp.attrition.jp/" /> by Ryan, in Tokyo, Japan.  This is our first Japanese mirror, thank you Ryan!</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://tldp.corporacionlinux.cl" /> by Rodrigo Henriquez M., in Santiago, Chili.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.linux.org.py/LDP/" /> by Oliver Schultze, the first mirror in Paraguay.  It is located in the city of Asuncion.  Thank you, Oliver!</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.mirrorplus.org" /> by the admins of MirrorPlus, Munich, Germany.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://debian.phys.hacettepe.edu.tr/LDP" /> by Mustafa Bayramgil, in Ankara, Turkey.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.mirrors.asianbaptist.org/" /> by Matthew Isam, first mirror in the state of Oklahoma, USA.  Congratulations!</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://viveka.math.hr/LDP/" /> by Vedran Sego, in Zagreb, Croatia.  First Croatian mirror, well done!</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://viveka.math.hr/LDP/" /> by Marius David, Timisoara, Romania.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><ulink url="http://gcwilhelm.dynalias.com/ldp/" /> by Gunter Wilhelm, Kirschhausen, Germany. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
