<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>21 &amp; 22</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-06-01</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP job descriptions</para>

<para>The job descriptions that David Horton so diligently prepared for
TLDP are now online a <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/jobdesc/" />.
thanks to David for his efforts and to those volunteers that contributed
content to David.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP tool prototyping</para>

<para>Stein Gjoen silently hacks away at tools that are useful for The
LDP.  Where there may not be a lot of buzz about the same, much of
Stein's TLDP work is located at his home page <ulink
url="http://www.nyx.net/~sgjoen/tarpl.html" />.  Stein indicated that
the web correlator script is now on line and (somewhat) documented, but
not very user friendly.  The program is about 150 lines of AWK script,
takes in apache logs and creates a HTML report.  These reports can be
huge both in terms of size on paper as well as number of bytes.  Sample
is about 180 KB.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP author database</para>

<para>Martin Wheeler let us know that the server the <ulink
url="http://startext.demon.co.uk/tldp/index.html" /> TLDP author
database runs on is going offline soon for a few weeks for a re-vamp,
and he hasn't had the time to transfer it to another machine for the
interim.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>HOWTOs in Debian Sarge</para>

<para>Now that Debian has entered freeze and is on the verge of release,
Stein Gjoen was wondering which documents from TLDP will be included and
how recent these are.  Rick Moen replied pointing Stein to <ulink
url="http://packages.debian.org/testing/doc/doc-linux-text" />, <ulink
url="http://packages.debian.org/testing/doc/doc-linux-html" /> and
<ulink url="http://packages.qa.debian.org/d/doc-linux.html" />.  Frank
Lichtenheld, the Debian package maintainer for the HOWTOs added that he
doesn't plan any further updates until the release since only a few
HOWTOs have been changed since the last one, but that can change if the
release gets delayed or there are many HOWTO updates in the next few
days.  Andrew M.A. Cater on the thread indicated the non-free status of
GNU Free Documentation License for Debian.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>The Compaq Remote Insight Board HOWTO <ulink
url="http://linux.shiningdeath.de/howto-de-compaq_remote_install.shtml"
/> has been translated to German by Stephan Reuter.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David A. Ranch's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/IP-Masquerade-HOWTO/" /> Linux IP Masquerade
HOWTO has been updated to a May 22, 2005 version.  This update has
updated the rc.firewall-iptables-stronger ruleset to 0.87s, removed the
unused drop-and-logit chain and updated the Multiple-IPs FAQ entry a
bit.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Machtelt Garrels updated the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/intro-linux/html/index.html" />
Introduction to Linux - A Hands on Guide, to v1.18.  The changes in
Tille's words <quote>note about pagers, lots of clarifications, removed
quite some RedHat-centric paragraphs, reviewed and updated lots in sound
and video, removed xmms-mp3 stuff, added time zone info because I was
just dealing with date and time, contrary to the title of the section,
removed Mandrake refs.</quote></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/"
/> The Linux Kernel Module Programming Guide authored by Peter Jay
Salzman, Michael Burian, Ori Pomerantz has been updated to v2.6.1.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>In case you intend to mirror The LDP collection, please use
this command:</para>

<screen>rsync -rlptv --delete ftp.ibiblio.org::ldp_mirror /your_path_to/LDP</screen>

<para>Please send an email to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email> in case there is a problem, or if
you successfully mirror the collection, let us know so that we can list
you as a mirror.  </para>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://snolug.ghostwheel-systems.cc/LDP">http://snolug.ghostwheel-systems.cc/LDP</ulink>
maintained by snolug-admin@ghostwheel-systems.cc in Marysville, WA,
U.S.A., and updated daily.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink
url="http://tldp.tuxhilfe.de/">http://tldp.tuxhilfe.de/</ulink>
maintained by mirrors@tuxhilfe.de in Berlin, Germany and updated daily
at 15:37 CE(S)T..  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
