<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>35</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-09-28</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Bash Guide Review</para>

<para>Michael T Kerrisk took a look at the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/index.html">Bash
Beginners Guide</ulink> authored by Machtelt Garrels and said that it
looked fine.  Machtelt Garrels indicated that a review of the document
would be good because she happens to be a non native English speaker.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Benchmark-of-the-filesystems-HOWTO</para>

<para>Svetoslav Chukov's <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?9:mss:269:200509:odhcbkbfccdbmebdhdkg">Benchmark-of-the-filesystems-HOWTO</ulink>
was posted to the editors mailing list calling for volunteers to review
the document.  Pradeep Padala, the author or <ulink
url="http://logfs.sourceforge.net">logfs</ulink>, a log structured file
system for Linux volunteered to look at the document and revert back in
a couple of weeks.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>non-free documentation in Debian main</para>

<para>Frank Lichtenheld <ulink
url="http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel-announce/2005/09/msg00007.html">sent
a mail</ulink> to the debian-devel-announce mailing list indicating how
documentation in Debian's 'main' archive would be removed if it doesn't
meet the Debian Free Software Guidelines.  Things to do, dealing with
non-free documentation in developers individual packages and filing bugs
about non-free documentation has been covered in the announcement. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Steven A sent in his update to the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Quake-HOWTO.html">Linux Quake HOWTO</ulink>.
The document is not an exhaustive HOWTO of setting up any one Quake
program, but a modern guide to GLQuake, a collection of the most useful
tips, and a pointer to the best resources still available on the web -
concentrating on the many engine re-writes and incredible add-ons which
make Quake such a great game. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Status of the Linux-SAN Document</para>

<para>Albretch Mueller <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9688:200509:ciopbonbpdkgbdmldpgd">asked</ulink>
what the status of the <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?7:mss:9986:200404:ciifjaeehkhhbdkkdcle">Linux-SAN
HOWTO or Guide</ulink> that was proposed in Apr 2004 was.  Machtelt
Garrels indicated that The LDP did not hear from the author.  A document
on the said topic would be a very valuable addition to the LDP
collection.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>There haven't been any new mirros or modifications to our existing
mirros, however, Asim from the oracle club in Pakistan indicated that he
would like to have a server for TLDP in Pakistan.  We shall update you
in case there is a new mirror there.  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining <email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a
low volume discussion mailing list).  You can also send your suggestions
to <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt
Garrels (Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several
other people.  To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox,
subscribe to the <email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.
Back issues are available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn" />
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
