<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>2 &amp; 3</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-01-19</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Prospective authors for The LDP are usually pointed to the excellent <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/">LDP Author Guide</ulink>.  However, the guide is big and has a lot of details.  David Laywer's <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:8242:200501:claiepedajakajhoajgg">Draft of very short Authors Guide</ulink> is up for review, and intends to be a quick guide to new authors. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Ari Mäkelä published v2.0.29 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Finnish-HOWTO/">Finnish HOWTO</ulink>, with more details on OpenOffice on Debian and the choice of fonts.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The v1.3 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO.html">Samba Authenticated Gateway</ulink>, by Ricardo Alexandre Mattar, has extended information on how to update your firewall configuration as users connect, including a link to a script that takes the pain off you for implementing this feature.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Howard Shane documents new models and drivers in v1.6 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Webcam-HOWTO/">Webcam HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Getting a bit old-fashioned but still wide-spread: IRC.  In his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/IRC/">IRC HOWTO</ulink>, Frédéric L.W. Meunier explains the basics and lists available Linux applications.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Kurt Swendson asked us to <ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/docs/HOWTO/archive/Beowulf-HOWTO.html">archive</ulink> the existing version of the Beowulf HOWTO, and replace it with a <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Beowulf-HOWTO/">completely revised Beowulf-HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter Bieringer did a few grammatical correction and incorporated minor review comment in the IPv6 IPsec section for v0.48 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+IPv6-HOWTO/">Linux + IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Bryan Henderson updated the example module for 2.6 kernel and mentions dmesg as a way to see kernel messages in his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Module-HOWTO/">Module HOWTO</ulink> and also added info about the dangers of unloading modules.  There is a link to the LKMPG.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Linux MIPS HOWTO</para>

<para>Ralf Bächle announced the replacement of the Linux MIPS HOWTO by a <ulink url="http://www.linux-mips.org/wiki/index.php">wiki</ulink>.  He is looking for advise on translation of the document.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>XML Editors and conversions</para>

<para>Saqib Ali is working on a <ulink url="http://www.xml-dev.com/xml/editors.html">list of XML editors</ulink> categorized by WYSIWYG, WYSIWYM and Text based.  Secondary categorization is done by dividing the editors in Freeware, OpenSource and commercial groups.</para>

<para>Recently we got a couple of documents written in OpenOffice, which needed to be converted to DocBook XML.  There are a couple of possibilities to get there:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>First convert the file to HTML using OO features, then optionally run it through <command>tidy</command> and then through <ulink url="http://freshmeat.net/projects/html2db/">html2db</ulink>.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>There is a tool which is called <command>OOo2dbk</command> and that can be downloaded <ulink url="http://www.indesko.com/sites/fr/telechargements/ooo2dbk___du_docbook/view"> from http://www.indesko.com/sites/fr/telechargements/ooo2dbk___du_docbook/view</ulink>.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">Back issues</ulink> are available at
http://tldp.org/ldpwn.  </para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
