<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>24 &amp; 25</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-06-22</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>New HOWTO Generator</para>

<para>Stein Gjoen announced the first release of the new HOWTO
Generator.  The generator now uses the new set of categories determined
by Gerd Berget, allows up to 3 categories per document, uses CSS,
accessibility has been improved.  Stein indicated that it is
sufficiently flexible that it allows for major rework of chapters with
little effort.  The updates are available from <ulink
url="http://www.nyx.net/~sgjoen/tarpl.html" />. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>LinuxWorld Expo BOF</para>

<para>Andy Oram told us that there will be a BOF on creating
documentation for Linux at the upcoming LinuxWorld Expo in San
Francisco; the BOF is on Wednesday, August 10th, from 5:15pm - 6:45pm.
It was set up and will be moderated by Don Marti, editor in chief of
Linux Journal.  Andy indicated that it would be great to have someone
there who's deeply involved in day-to-day coordination of the LDP.
Edward Cherlin and Rick Moen indicated that they can both attend and
help run that event.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>HOWTO re-licensing</para>

<para>Pradeep Padala asked if his Ncurses Programming HOWTO can be
re-licensed under a different license so that it can be distributed
along with the official Ncurses package (maintained by Thomas Dickey).
Various people stepped in to answer his questions about licensing and
indicated that since he is the sole author of the document, he is free
to license it as he likes, but the original document that was licensed
under a different license will continue to be distributed under the same
license.  Further, updated to the new licensed document will not
probably be available under the old license unless they are explicitly
licensed as such.  </para>

<para>Rick Moen pointed Pradeep to <ulink
url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/Licensing-HOWTO.html" /> and <ulink
url="http://www.rosenlaw.com/oslbook.htm" /> </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>LVM HOWTO <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LVM-HOWTO/"
/>  by AJ Lewis is now at v0.15.  The revision removed references to
xfs_freeze - it is no longer needed; Updated snapshots subsection in
Anatomy of LVM section; Added a couple entries to the LVM2 FAQ and fixed
a couple typos</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter Jay Salzman's Debian Jigdo mini-HOWTO <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Debian-Jigdo/" /> is now at ver 1.5.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David S. Lawyer updated the Modem-HOWTO <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Modem-HOWTO.html" /> to v0.38.  Changes
include: Eliminated section on Digital Modems in appendix since it's
already covered elsewhere. More on cable modems. ISDN serial modems.
Troubleshooting: Can't find winmodems if no driver. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Miroslav "Misko" Skoric sent in minor updates to the FBB
Packet-radio BBS mini-HOWTO <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html"
/> LILO mini-HOWTO <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html" /> and
the Linux+WindowsNT mini-HOWTO <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html" /> </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
