<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>37, 38, 39 &amp; 40 </issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-11-02</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Volunteer for the mirror checkup</para>

<para>Machtelt Garrels is looking for a volunteer to do the mirrors
checkup.  Things to do are: </para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>Check time-stamp on all mirrors
  (http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html), all URLs should have a
  timestamp.txt in the top-level directory.  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Contact the maintainers of mirrors that are not up to
  date, ask if they plan to correct the situation.</para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>Create a list of mirrors that can not be contacted at
  all, those will be removed from
  http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>Get in touch with Tille if you are interested. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>LDP Manifesto "Overview" change</para>

<para>David Lawyer looked at what he had drafted in 2001 for the
"Overview" part of the Manifesto and edited it a little to reflect the
current situation <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9693:200510:claiepedajakajhoajgg"
/>.  The revised version is available for comment and David posted a
version <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9761:200510:ngajkeenpiioblmendee"
/> asking if discuss list is OK with it.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>AsciiDoc and DocBook</para>

<para>Scot Stevenson started <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9709:200510:mjolkcjnjbginkhagjki"
/> started a discussion on why the LDP should start supporting AsciiDoc
as one of the acceptable formats.  Since Scot talked about LinuxDoc,
David Lawyer put down his thoughts on the issue and said that the LDP
could revive LinuxDoc.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>LDP or TLDP</para>

<para>David Lawyer, while discussing the draft of the Introduction to
the LDP Manifesto, said <quote>we did change was our URL from
linuxdoc.org to tldp.org.  But the old URL still works (I just tried
it).  So I'm in favor of continuing to use LDP and to not object if
people call us TLDP.  LDP has a lot of name recognition in printed
books.  If you look at our doc, there's several times more mention of
LDP than TLDP.  So it's not too late to go back to LDP.  LDP is also
used a lot on our website along with TLDP</quote>.  Several people
<ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:sss:9730:200510:pgfjjcaefnhkbdlhllan"
/> were in favour of using LDP and Guylhem P. Aznar said that tldp.org
was choosen because ldp.org was not available.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Alex Nordstrom, the maintainer of the Documentation Workgroup of
the Linux Society of Sweden, sent in a mail to the discuss list <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9700:200510:ddjlkhedkoddjdpcpnpi"
/> outlining the process of translating a document from the Linux 
Documentation Project (LDP) for the Linux Society of Sweden and
requested comments on the translation effort workflow. </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-review">

<title>Documents submitted for review</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Rohit Agarwal submitted a <ulink
url="http://geocities.com/vickys_box/libdc1394howtoVer2.pdf">How To for
libdc1394</ulink>, the document discusses libdc1394 library that is used
for  IEEE1394 camera interfacing.  </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Scot W. Stevenson's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Mock-Mainframe/">Mock Mainframe
Mini-HOWTO</ulink> at v1.2. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Werner Heuser's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Infrared-HOWTO/">Linux Infrared
HOWTO</ulink>.  In version 3.7 technical and a language review have been
done.  Numerous bugs have been fixed and many URLs have been updated.
Some obsolete stuff has been removed. Some documentation about
Linux/IrDA with kernel 2.6 has been added (but there is still work to
do).  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Miroslav "Misko" Skoric sent in updates to the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/FBB.html">FBB Packet-radio BBS
mini-HOWTO</ulink> (v1.36), the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/LILO.html">LILO mini-HOWTO</ulink> (v3.26)
and the <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+WinNT.html">Linux+WindowsNT
mini-HOWTO</ulink> (v2.25).  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter Bieringer's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux+IPv6-HOWTO/">Linux IPv6 HOWTO</ulink>
is now at v0.49.  The new revision adds configuration hints for DHCPv6
and has broken URL cleanups. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Avi Alkalay sent in his <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TimePrecision-HOWTO/">Managing Accurate Date
and Time HOWTO</ulink>.  v2005-10-12 of the document moves the Brazil
zic file out and has been updated.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper's <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/index.html">Advanced
Bash-Scripting Guide</ulink> at v3.7 is a bugfix update and adds some
minor material.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para>David S. Lawyer's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Howtos-with-LinuxDoc.html">Howtos-with-LinuxDoc-mini-HOWTO</ulink>
v0.05.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Rob van der Putten's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Leased-Line/">Leased line Mini HOWTO</ulink>
now at v2.3b7 has information about additional PPPD options and routing.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Charles Curley's <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linux-Complete-Backup-and-Recovery-HOWTO/">Linux
Complete Backup and Recovery HOWTO</ulink> is at v2.0.  The new version
has notes for Fedora Core 4. Notes for older versions of FC and Red Hat
have been removed.  There are changes in the writeup and scripts reflect
using Knoppix instead of tomsrtbt. A few scripts have been changed so
that long lines don't fall off the right side of printed pages.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.nedmirror.nl/" /> maintained by
Wessel Sandkuyl in Amsterdam, The Netherlands and is hosted in a
multi-homed datacentre just under Schiphol.  The mirror is updated
daily.  </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://tldp.hord.ru" /> maintained by
dmitri@gnu.org, knight@uportal.ru in Moscow, Russia and updated daily.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.hoxt.com/" /> maintained by Son
Nguyen in Tampa, FL, USA and update daily. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://howto.hellug.gr" /> maintained by
Apostolos (Greek HOWTOs maintainer) in Athens, Greece and updated daily.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.linuxshop.us/ldp/" /> maintained
by Scott Braynard in NJ, USA and updated daily. </para></listitem>

<listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.linuxnetwork.com" /> maintained
by Jeremiah Tieman in Amsterdam, The Netherlands and updated twice every
day. </para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation
Project</ulink> (TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality
documentation for the GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help
TLDP, consider joining our low volume discussion mailing list
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.  You can also send your
suggestions to <email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt
Garrels (Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several
other people.  To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox,
subscribe to the news mailing list
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email>.  Back issues are available at
<ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink> </para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter.  We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events
related to free software documentation.  Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
