<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>4 to 8 (Jumbo Update)</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-02-23</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Alex Hudson proposed to write a Self-certifying File System
(SFS) HOWTO.  SFS is a network filesystem that makes NFS exports securely
available via the internet. It is a global filesystem, and works on a variety
of free software and non-free software operating systems. This is not to be
confused with the SFS mentioned in the Filesystems HOWTO.  Although it runs
over NFS, SFS is a system of sufficient complexity to warrant its own
documentation. The SFS already have documentation, but it is quite technical
and written in quite terse language, hence Alex proposed to write a HOWTO on
this subject.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Minor updates in Avi Alkalay's <ulink url="  http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Font-HOWTO/">Font HOWTO</ulink>.  Section two of this document, for those who are new to it, contains an excellent read on the difference between printed fonts and the fonts you see on your screen.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>In v2.0 of Eric S. Raymond's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Linksys-Blue-Box-Router-HOWTO/">Linksys Bluebox Router HOWTO</ulink> you will find hints and tips on managing Linksys routers from a Linux system.  This major release describes the changes in 2.x/3.x firmware versions and has more on firmware replacement.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Emma Jane Hogbin added new XML editors in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/">Author Guide</ulink> v4.6, as well as information about DocBook-capable word processors.  There is also more documentation on converting other formats to DocBook.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Peter Jay Salzman, Michael Burian and Ori Pomerantz updated the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html">Linux Kernel Module Programming Guide kernel</ulink> to version 2.6.1.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Adrain Offerman's <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/MMBase-Inst-HOWTO/">MMBase Installation HOWTO</ulink> v0.3.2 has lots of new sections, including detailed instructions on how to set up the latest Java Platform from Sun and how to install multiple Tomcat versions.</para></listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Claudio Cattazzio of the Italian LDP effort updated us that the following documents have been translated to Italian:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Bzip2 mini-HOWTO (translation by Gerardo Di Iorio and revision
by Claudio Cattazzo) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Bzip2.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Bzip2.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Coffee Making HOWTO (translation by Claudio Cattazzo and
Giuseppe Briotti) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Coffee.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Coffee.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Home-Network-mini-HOWTO (translation by Alessio Ciregia and
revision by Daniele Masini) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Home-Network-mini-HOWTO.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Home-Network-mini-HOWTO.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Linux MP3 CD Burning mini-HOWTO (translation by Matteo
Castellini and revision by Beatrice Torracca) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/MP3-CD-Burning/index.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/MP3-CD-Burning/index.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>MS Outlook to Unix Mailbox Conversion mini HOWTO (translation
by Rossella Diomede and revision by Beatrice Torracca) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Outlook-to-Unix-Mailbox.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Outlook-to-Unix-Mailbox.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Smart Card HOWTO (translation by Manuele Rampazzo) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Smart-Card-HOWTO/index.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/Smart-Card-HOWTO/index.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>VPN PPP-SSH Mini-HOWTO (translation by Manuel Spezzani, Alberto
Ronzoni, Daniele Gozzi, Laura Ferretti and Daniela Saladino) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/ppp-ssh/index.html">http://it.tldp.org/HOWTO/ppp-ssh/index.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide 3.1 (translation by Emilio Conti
and revision by Ferdinando Ferranti) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/guide/abs/index.html">http://it.tldp.org/guide/abs/index.html</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Linux From Scratch 5.1.1 (translation by Giulio Daprelà and
revision by Giuseppe Briotti) <ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/lfs/5.1.1/">http://it.tldp.org/lfs/5.1.1/</ulink></para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Linux From Scratch 6.0 (translation by the ILDP-LFS Team)
<ulink
url="http://it.tldp.org/lfs/6.0/">http://it.tldp.org/lfs/6.0/</ulink></para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Mirrors</para>
<para>These are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.irontec.com" />, in Tampa, FL, USA , by Iker Sagasti Markina;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.kgt.org/" />, in Frankfurt, Germany, by Thomas Koeppe;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><ulink url="http://ldp.ausics.net" />, in Brisbane, Australia, by Noel Butler;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.bitpusher.com/mirrors/LDP" />, in San Fransisco, CA, USA, by Michael T. Halligan;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><ulink url="http://ftp.lug.md/pub/mirrors/LDP" />, in Chisinau, Moldavia, by Raileanu Grigore.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

<para>Machtelt Garrels conducted a check of the mirrors and updated <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">the mirrors list</ulink>.  Over 300 official mirrors were checked for accuracy and up-to-date mirroring of the primary site.  97 mirrors were unavailable, out-of-date or did not display the correct content.  Two weeks after contacting the maintainers of those mirrors, almost half of these cases could be resolved.  The other half get two weeks more to correct the errors.  If they have not rectified the situation by then, they will be removed from the mirror list.  Currently, the list has 215 approved mirrors; for 65 mirrors the approval is pending.</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Draft of very short Authors Guide</para>

<para>David Lawyer wrote a very short Authors Guide titled "Writing a LDP Document".  The LDP Authors Guide is a much bigger version with detailed information but the current document is short but useful and easy to comprehend.  The draft with comments from others is available at <ulink url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:sss:8330:200501:llglikfdoinhhhoahfom">http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:sss:8330:200501:llglikfdoinhhhoahfom</ulink>. </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP and Librarian Science</para>

<para>The Linux Documentation Project (TLDP) and the Faculty of Journalism,
Library and Information Science at Oslo University College have joined
forces in an effort to improve the reader experience of the TLDP document
archive.</para>

<para>For more than 10 years TLDP has authored and collected an ever increasing
number of documents. These have been filed in an equally growing document
structure that has shown itself to be less than optimal. An overhaul was
recognised to be overdue and this time it was decided not to "go it alone"
but rather contact the experts on this field: the library and information
scientists.</para>

<para>Oslo University College accepted the invitation from TLDP and soon Gerd
Berget decided to do a professional job of determining an efficient set of
categories as part of a Master's Degree study in library and information
science.  The initial set of categories is available at <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:8391:200502:jbdbakjaacfndkmflfhi">http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:8391:200502:jbdbakjaacfndkmflfhi</ulink>.
But the report itself, being over 100 pages, will take a while to be translated
to english.  </para>

<para>For more information contact:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Tor Arne Dahl, Faculty of Journalism, Library and Information Science, E-mail: Tor-Arne.Dahl(at)jbi.hio.no</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Gerd Berget, Faculty of Journalism, Library and Information Science, E-mail: gerdberget(at)yahoo.no</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Stein Gjoen, TLDP, E-mail: sgjoen(at)mail.nyx.net</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  <ulink
url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">Back issues</ulink> are available at
http://tldp.org/ldpwn.  </para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
