<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
  <volumenum>2005</volumenum>
  <issuenum>11, 12 &amp; 13</issuenum>
  <publisher><publishername>The Linux Documentation Project</publishername></publisher>
  <pubdate>2005-03-30</pubdate>
  <title>The Linux Documentation Project Weekly News</title>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="tldp-world-news">
<title>News in The LDP world</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP Volunteer Responsibility Descriptions</para>

<para>David Horton started on <ulink
url="http://www.happy-monkey.net/tldp/job-descriptions.html">TLDP Job
Descriptions</ulink>.  Currently defined are Author, Chief Coordinator,
Document Publisher, Document Reviewer, Mirror Maintainer, News Contributor,
News Editor and Technical Contributor.  David will be further polling and
charting out the responsibilities of all volunteers; the goal is to include
this documentation on the TLDP site to make it clear to people who want to
contribute to and understand the procedures of the LDP.  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>The LDP publishing process</para>

<para>Machtelt Garrels is working on a graphical representation of the <ulink
url="http://tille.xalasys.com/training/tldp/images/tldp-publishing-flowchart.pdf">
publishing process</ulink> and the <ulink
url="http://tille.xalasys.com/training/tldp/images/tldp-maintenance-flowchart.pdf">maintenance
flowchart</ulink> which is to be included in the <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/html/index.html">Author
Guide</ulink>.  She also proposed to make a flowchart of the relation between
the job responsibilities within TLDP as an addition to David Horton's work.  A
draft of the flowchart is <ulink
url="http://tille.xalasys.com/training/tldp/images/org-flowchart.pdf">available</ulink>.
</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>New German Translations</para>

<para>Stephan Reuter has started the <ulink url="http://linux.shiningdeath.de/">Linux Archive</ulink> site, where you can find HOWTOs and other documents in German.  Among the ever-growing list of translated documents:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><ulink url="http://linux.shiningdeath.de/howto-de-preinstall_checklist.shtml">Pre-Installation-Checklist Howto</ulink></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><ulink url="http://linux.shiningdeath.de/howto-de-linuxinstallation.shtml">Installation HOWTO</ulink></para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><ulink url="http://linux.shiningdeath.de/howto-de-lfs.shtml">Linux from Scratch</ulink></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>TLDP Wikified Mirror</para>

<para>Blake Benthall proposed to set up a <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?7:mss:10670:200503:iomiedbkgnnpmhgcelfk">Wikified
mirror</ulink>.  The proposal was <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:sss:9101:200503:kebchlnjcdnacjalkhnf">discussed
at large</ulink> and Blake setup a preliminary WIKI for testing of his HTML to
WIKI conversion scripts at the site <ulink
url="http://tldp.sys-techs.com/wiki/index.php/Special:Allpages">http://tldp.sys-techs.com/wiki/index.php/Special:Allpages</ulink>.
</para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-discussions">
<title>Discussions on The LDP lists</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>

<para>Modifiability of Documents</para>

<para>Rahul Sundaram wanted to include "modifiability of documents as a
licensing requirement" in the LDP manifesto and also <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:8594:200503:ihpahginmljdgbhooeje">suggested</ulink>
modifying the authors guide.  This led to a discussion on licensing and various
licenses available for documentation.  Emma Jane Hogbin <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:8711:200503:jklinmkmkkeoaokicenh">posted</ulink>
changes to the authors guide and asked for suggestions and comments.  The
thread petered out and went on to discuss how Debian handles documentation and
Emma <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9003:200503:jklinmkmkkeoaokicenh">sent
a mail</ulink> to the maintainers to the doc-linux and doc-linux-nonfree Debian
packages requesting a "a succinct explanation on the distinction so that they
[TLDP authors] may choose the best license for their document".  </para>

</listitem>

<listitem>

<para>Proposed LDP Organization: Subject Specialists</para>

<para>David Lawyer <ulink
url="http://lists.tldp.org/index.cgi?1:mss:9127:200503:claiepedajakajhoajgg">proposed</ulink>
that The LDP partition the existing and expected future LDP docs into say 20-40
categories and find a subject specialist for each category. <quote>She would
first review all the docs on this subject.  If docs were not being adequately
maintained, she would try to find new authors.  She would also try to find
authors for areas covered by the subject but not adequately by any LDP docs.
She would suggest mergers or splits in exiting documents.  New doc proposals
would go to the appropriate subject specialist.</quote>  He said that there
should be a subject specialist coordinator and <quote>the subject specialist
coordinator would need to have good knowledge of all aspects of Linux and have
time to check out the facts when disputes arose.  The subject specialist
coordinator and assistants would initially have to find people to do reviews
for cases where there was no subject specialist to do it.  The subject
specialist coordinator might keep a list of people willing to do technical
reviews</quote>.   People in general thought that this would be a good idea and
went on to discuss it further.  </para>

</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="new-proposed">

<title>New document proposals</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Vikas Singhal proposed to write a Open Source Databases for
Linux HOWTO.  The document will explain installation and configuration of
various open source databases, such as MySQL, PostgreSQL, MaxDB, and Firebird,
on Linux platform. This document will also provide comparison among these
databases. This will not be a very detailed manual but an overview and will
provide pointers for further information.  Rahul Sundaram expressed his
interest in the document and indicated the Vikas should post his proposal and
drafts to the discuss list.  Vivek Varghese Cherian offered help with the
document.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="updated-docs">
<title>Updated HOWTOs, FAQs and Guides</title>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Christophe Devine took the time to update all the package version numbers in the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Encrypted-Root-Filesystem-HOWTO/">Encrypted Root Filesystem HOWTO</ulink> v1.3.  The document is now also available in <ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org">CVS</ulink>.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Another addition to CVS is v0.9 of the <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/BTTV/">BTTV HOWTO</ulink>.  This is the first attempt at rewrite of the document, so comments are welcome!</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Mendel Cooper released v3.3 of the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/">Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide</ulink>, which contains again lots of bug fixes and several new example scripts.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Artemiy I. Pavlov released v1.7 of his <ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/SquashFS-HOWTO/">SquashFS HOWTO</ulink>, this new version has modifications in the document to cover the SquashFS release 2.1.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-mirrors">
<title>Mirror information update</title>

<para>The following are the latest additions to our <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/mirrors.html">list of mirrors</ulink>:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Nels Martens: <ulink url="http://www.codesrc.net/LDP">http://www.codesrc.net/LDP</ulink> in El Segundo, CA, USA and updated daily.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Yevgeniy Skrypets: <ulink url="http://ldp.tolix.org/">http://ldp.tolix.org/</ulink> in Burlingame, CA, USA and updated daily at 1am PST.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tldp-contribute">
<title>The LDP/LDPWN mini-HOWTO</title>

<para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/">The Linux Documentation Project</ulink>
(TLDP) is working on developing free, high quality documentation for the
GNU/Linux operating system.  If you want to help TLDP, consider joining
<email>discuss-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> (a low volume discussion mailing
list).  You can also send your suggestions to
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

<para>The LDP Weekly News is compiled, edited and published by Machtelt Garrels
(Tille) and Y Giridhar Appaji Nag (Giri) with help from several other people.
To receive this newsletter weekly in your mailbox, subscribe to the
<email>news-subscribe@en.tldp.org</email> mailing list.  Back issues are
available at <ulink url="http://tldp.org/ldpwn">http://tldp.org/ldpwn</ulink>
</para>

<para>Help us create this newsletter. We need volunteers who follow the
community (mailing lists, newsgroups, web channels) and report events related
to free software documentation. Write to us at
<email>feedback@en.tldp.org</email>.  </para>

</sect1>

</article>
