<sect1 id="ch09-reboot">
<title>Rebooting the system</title>
<?dbhtml filename="reboot.html" dir="chapter09"?>

<para>Now that all software has been installed, bootscripts have been created, 
it's time to reboot the computer. Before we reboot let's unmount
$LFS/proc and the LFS partition itself by running:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>umount $LFS/proc &amp;&amp;
umount $LFS</userinput></screen></para>

<para>If you decided to create multiple partitions, you need to umount the
other partitions before you umount $LFS, like this:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>umount $LFS/proc &amp;&amp;
umount $LFS/usr &amp;&amp;
umount $LFS/home &amp;&amp;
umount $LFS</userinput></screen></para>

<para>And you can reboot your system by running something like:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>/sbin/shutdown -r now</userinput></screen></para>

<para>At the LILO: prompt make sure that you tell it to boot 
<emphasis>lfs</emphasis> and not the default entry which will boot your
host system again.</para>

<para>After you have rebooted, your LFS system is ready for use and you
can start adding your own software.</para>

<para>One final thing you may want to do is run lilo, now that you are
booted into LFS. This way you will put the LFS version of LILO in the MBR
rather than the one that's there right now from your host system.
Depending on how old your host distribution is, the LFS version may have
more advanced features you need/could use.</para>

<para>Either way, run the following to make the lilo version installed
on LFS active:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>/sbin/lilo</userinput></screen></para>

<para>You may now remove the static directory. If you think you may
need to redo Chapter 5, then you may wish to backup the directory before
removing it. To remove the static directory, type the following
command:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>rm -rf /static</userinput></screen></para>

<para>Now that you have finished installing your LFS system, you may
be wondering how to install additional software, such as a web browser.
Your first stop should be the Beyond Linux From Scratch project, which may
be found at <ulink url="&blfs-root;"/>. The LFS hints may also prove helpful,
and are located at <ulink url="&hints-index;"/>. On a similar note, if you
are not only a newbie to LFS, but also to Linux in general, you may
find the newbie hint at <ulink url="&hints-root;newbie.txt"/> very
interesting.</para>

<para>Remember that there are several LFS mailinglists you may subscribe
to if you are in need of help. See <xref linkend="ch01-maillists"/> for
more information.</para>
 
<para>Again, we thank you for using the LFS Book and hope you found this
book useful and worth your time.</para>

</sect1>
