<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="Partition-Mass-Storage-Definitions-Naming-HOWTO">
	<articleinfo>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jean-Daniel</firstname>
			<surname>Dodin</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<!-- A valid email is required. You may add a spam blocker, or get a Yahoo/Gmail/etc account. -->        <address>
					<email>jdd@dodin.org</email>
				</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>

    <title>Partitions-Mass-Storage-Definitions-Naming-HOWTO</title>
<revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>V0.1</revnumber>
        <date>2009-05-09</date>
        <authorinitials>jdd</authorinitials>
      </revision>

    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Partitions-Mass-Storage-Definitions-Naming-HOWTO</title>
    <para>Copyright (c) 2009 Jean-Daniel Dodin</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Copyright and Licence</title>
    <para>The copyright of this document is to the author,
    Jean-Daniel Dodin, according to the following licence.</para>
    <screen>
      <![CDATA[      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
      Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software
      Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts and
      no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in the
      section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".]]>
</screen>
    <para>
      <ulink url='http://wiki.tldp.org/LdpWikiDefaultLicence#GNUFreeDocumentationLicense'>
      GNU Free Documentation License</ulink>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Mass Storage Involved Here</title>
    <para>Mass storage involved in the present HOWTO are rewritable
    random access ones. Most of them are magnetic rotating disks
    (floppies, Hard Drive) or flash memory (USB key or any kind of
    memory card).</para>
    <para>For example, cdroms and dvds are 
    <emphasis role='strong'>not</emphasis>concerned by this HOWTO (
    <ulink url='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cdrom'>see
    Wikipedia</ulink>). Tapes are not either.</para>
    <para>Mass storage are used by the kernel, so the basic doc can
    be found on 
    <ulink url='http://kernel.org/pub/linux/docs/device-list/devices-2.6+.txt'>
    the kernel Web site</ulink></para>
    <para>Reference site should be 
    <ulink url='http://www.idema.org'>the International Disk drive
    Equipment and Materials Association</ulink>. 
    <emphasis>Should</emphasis>because this Web site is not very
    friendly.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Definitions</title>
    <section>
      <title>Warning</title>
      <para>Many definitions about drives are only virtual. That is
      they are used, but the hardware is often quite different from
      the expected description. Usually this have no odd result,
      any mass storage have to be seen as a 
      <emphasis>black box</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Bytes</title>
      <para>Computers counts with binaries, 1 &amp; 0,
      1111100001110... To be able to read this better, humans uses
      nibbles (4 bits) often shown as Hexadecimal numbers from 0 to
      f (0123456789abcdef). Nibbles are usually grouped by two and
      this gives a byte. The most used memory unit is byte and it's
      multiples, KiB (Kilo Bytes), MiB (Mega Bytes), GiB
      (Gigabytes). The "i" denotes the binary use (0ne Ki is 1024,
      not 1000), the uppercase "B" denotes Bytes, not bits.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sectors</title>
      <para>Sometime, the word 
      <emphasis>block</emphasis>is used in place of 
      <emphasis>sectors</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>Mass storage devices (at least the ones we are dealing
      with here) store bytes in "Sectors" of 512 Bytes. This is
      uneven, because any sector count have to be divided by two to
      have the KiB number, so most partitonning software accepts
      letters k (KiB), m (MiB), g... as options. Wise ones do not
      make any case difference.</para>
      <para>Sector size is the available byte count. The true
      sector is bigger, as it have to include housekeeping data.
      You don't have to worry about that.</para>
      <para>Notice that as of 03-22-2006, the IDEMA annouced a new
      sector size of 4kiB (4096 Bytes): 
      <ulink url='http://www.idema.org/_smartsite/modules/local/data_file/show_file.php?cmd=download&amp;data_file_id=1446' />-
      doc file, can be openned with OpenOffice.org.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Heads</title>
      <para>Rotating mass storage devices uses 
      <emphasis>heads</emphasis>. True heads are the physical
      electromechanical device that writes and read the magnetic
      track. Drives being made of rotating plates, the plates have
      two sides, so disks can have two head by plate. Having two
      plates (frequent) you have four heads.</para>
      <para>Heads are writing through very complex system, see
      detailed info here: 
      <ulink url='http://www.spmtips.com/library/data_storage' />.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tracks</title>
      <para>Plates are rotating. When a head is still, the plate
      rotation and the width of the head are defining a
      track.</para>
      <para>Heads are moving from the external part of the plate to
      the inner part, step by steps. Each step defines a new
      track.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Cylinders</title>
      <para>Heads are moving together, all at the same time. They
      may rotate - on they own center, not the plate center, of
      course. They also may have a linear move. You can see an
      example of linear moving head in any cdreader, looking at the
      move of the laser head. Most disks are as shown by this
      wikipedia image 
      <ulink url='http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/5a/Hard_disk_platters_and_head.jpg/200px-Hard_disk_platters_and_head.jpg' />.</para>
      <para>When you think of all the tracks defined by each head
      at the same time, you have a cylinder. So on a rotating
      drive, all the tracks of the same cylinder are read or
      written at the same time. The actual data is spread on all
      the plates. The way the data is actually written is up to the
      drive manufacturer, not the user.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Disks</title>
      <para>Small disks are used directly as a hole bunch of
      sectors. Basic programs can access data directly on sectors.
      Many do (like dd or any partitionning programm).</para>
      <para>But we live in a world of extremely high capacity mass
      storage. Terabytes is normal nowaday (2009), when a complete
      Linux system can live on a floppy (1440 bytes). So there is a
      need of making several parts from a mass storage device,
      though the partitions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Partitions</title>
      <para>Partitioning is a means to divide a single drive into
      many logical drives. A partition is a contiguous set of
      sectors. To lessen the heads travel, partitions can be
      "aligned" on the cylinder size, that is use an integer number
      of cylinder. This is not always done, but should as it have
      many other advantages for recovery.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Partition Table</title>
      <para>As you can have many partitions, you need to have a
      partition table. This partition table is stored in the very
      beginning of the drive. It's very unlikely that you will have
      to change this table directly writing bytes with an
      hexadecimal editor, so we wont say more on the position of
      the table.</para>
      <para>There are many Operating Systems all around that all
      share similar hardware and as many partition systems. We will
      look only at what one can find in a PC, even if it's not easy
      to define that nowaday. Say, for us, a PC is any computer
      able to run Linux (I know, it's not always true).</para>
      <para>Each of these partition kinds are noted in the table by
      a special flag called "type" ("t" in fdisk). Most known are
      type 83 for Linux partitions and 82 for Linux swap (hex
      numbers).</para>
      <para>Notice that most Operating Systems can share partition
      tables. At least, if a disk is hardware compatible with
      several systems, these systems should be able to see what the
      others have done, not to erase a drive by accident. I can't
      say for sure that its true in the real life.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>File Systems</title>
      <para>Partitions can be accessed directly as sectors, as any
      part of the disk, but are usually filled with a 
      <emphasis role='strong'>file system</emphasis>. File system
      and partitions are related only because a file system is in a
      partition, but that's all. You can have a disk without
      partition but with a file system or have partitions without
      file system (the swap partition beeing the most well known).
      For details on file systems, 
      <ulink url='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File_system'>see
      Wikipedia</ulink>.</para>
      <para>In summary, file systems allow storing data in files
      with human readable names and to sort the files in a friendly
      way, for example as directories, subdirectories, text,
      images...</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Files and Nodes</title>
      <para>Nearly all what you can find on a mass storage
      partition, beside sectors, from an user point of view, is a
      file. But computers are curious geeks and you can treat files
      like disks if you want. Using the "loop" system, default in
      most Linux kernels, one can partition the inside of the file,
      create file systems on it and mount it. This is specially
      handy for experiments.</para>
      <para>Some of these files are 
      <emphasis>devices</emphasis>or 
      <emphasis>nodes</emphasis>. Partitions are not files and are
      accessed via special nodes we will see later. These nodes are
      not created by touch but by 
      <emphasis>mknode</emphasis>. Use with caution. Nodes need a
      type (
      <emphasis>c</emphasis>for "character" or "b" for 
      <emphasis>block</emphasis>) and major and minor numbers. For
      what we need, major numbers are disk numbers and minor
      numbers are partition numbers. The list is visible in
      /proc/partitions</para>
      <screen>
        <![CDATA[cat /proc/partitions
major minor  #blocks  name

   8     0  488386584 sda
   8     1   52436128 sda1
   8     2          1 sda2
   8     5    2104483 sda5
   8     6   20972826 sda6
   8     7   52436128 sda7
   8     8  360434308 sda8]]>
</screen>
      <screen>
        <![CDATA[#mknod b 8 9 /dev/sda9]]>
</screen>
      <para>Creates a /dev/sda9 node of no nuse, given this don't
      create partition, only the node. In a usual Linux
      distribution, nodes are dynamically created at boot time, so
      nobody should have to do so. However, sometime the automatic
      system fails.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Drive Naming in Linux</title>
    <para>There is a special nomenclature that linux uses to refer
    to mass storage that must be understood.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Naming Convention</title>
      <para>Linux used to deal with two kind of drives, depending
      of the electronic interface (controller), IDE and SCSI.
      Oldtimers remember the day where cdwriters where acccessed
      through "SCSI emulation". In fact IDE and SCSI use mostly the
      same low level commands and for 2007 up, with the new "SATA"
      interface, the naming was unified and, in new ditributions,
      all the drives have the same naming. For this part, CD or DVD
      readers/writers are seen like Hard Drives.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Old IDE Names</title>
        <para>By convention, IDE drives where given device names 
        <filename class="devicefile">/dev/hda</filename>to 
        <filename class="devicefile">/dev/hdd</filename>. 
        <emphasis>H</emphasis>ard 
        <emphasis>D</emphasis>rive 
        <emphasis>A</emphasis>(
        <filename class="devicefile">/dev/hda</filename>) is the first drive and 
        <emphasis>H</emphasis>ard 
        <emphasis>D</emphasis>rive 
        <emphasis>C</emphasis>(
        <filename class="devicefile">/dev/hdc</filename>) is the third.</para>
        <para>A typical PC has two IDE controllers, each of which
        can have two drives connected to it. For example, 
        <filename class="devicefile">/dev/hda</filename>is the first drive (master) on the
        first IDE controller and 
        <filename class="devicefile">/dev/hdd</filename>is the second (slave) drive on the
        second controller (the fourth IDE drive in the
        computer).</para>
        <para>So, typically, a computer with IDE controller can
        accomodate 4 drives: /dev/hda (primary master), /dev/hdb
        (primary slave), /dev/hdc (secondary master), /dev/hdd
        (secondary slave). Some (rare) Mother Boards have more than
        two controllers, some addition cards can also have
        controllers, these are numbered following the alphabet, but
        one have to figure out what real names are given for his
        particular hardware.</para>
        <para>You can have drives where ever you want, it's not
        mandatory to fill the gaps. You may have interest to read
        about what drive/cdrom connect to what place, but it's out
        of this document scope.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>New Hard Drives Names</title>
        <para>Now all the rotating hard drives uses the same names
        as the old SCSI controllers, that is "s" in place of "h",
        so /dev/sda, and so on. The number of drives depends on the
        number of controllers on the Mother Board or the extended
        boards. Usually 4 are available. What will be the number of
        a drive is up to the controller card and the way it's read
        by the kernel, so difficult to say at first.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Flash Drives Names</title>
        <para>Flash drives are usually not connected through IDE or
        SATA interfaces and so don't uses the same names. Several
        interfaces are used with each different names. The kernel
        documentations gives the names.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Low level Devices and Extra naming</title>
        <para>You will find in some apps references to lowlevel
        SCSI devices and various naming conventions, for example
        (wodim is the command line cd burner):</para>
        <screen>
          <![CDATA[wodim --scanbus
scsibus1:
        1,0,0   100) *
        1,1,0   101) 'TSSTcorp' 'CD/DVDW TS-L632D' 'ac00' Removable CD-ROM
        1,2,0   102) *
        1,3,0   103) *
        1,4,0   104) *
        1,5,0   105) *
        1,6,0   106) *
        1,7,0   107) *]]>
</screen>
        <para>And you may have to use some sort of 
        <emphasis>SCSI:1,1,0</emphasis>option to access the CDROM.
        try to avoid using this as much as possible, as it's very
        error prone and should be let to programmers only. I only
        mention it because you can't always avoid it.</para>
        <para>If you do "cat /dev/ | more", you can see:</para>
        <screen>
          <![CDATA[lrwxrwxrwx  1 root root             3 mars  9 07:56 scd0 -> sr0
(...)
crw-r-----  1 root disk       21,   0 mars  9 07:56 sg0
crw-rw----+ 1 root disk       21,   1 mars  9 07:56 sg1]]>
</screen>
        <para>These scd, sr, sg devices are lowlevel interface
        (notice the "c" for "character"). Try not using them. 
        <emphasis>dmesg</emphasis>and 
        <emphasis>more /var/log/boot.msg</emphasis>should give you
        the usable sdxx device, like (short summary):</para>
        <screen>
          <![CDATA[<5>sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] 976773168 512-byte hardware sectors: (500GB/465GiB)
<5>sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] Write Protect is off
<7>sd 0:0:0:0: [sda] Mode Sense: 00 3a 00 00]]>
</screen>
        <para>This mean the drive is 
        <emphasis>/dev/sda</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>However these files (given by 
        <emphasis>dmesg</emphasis>and 
        <emphasis>more /var/log/boot.msg</emphasis>) used to be
        easy to read but are no more. Now the kernel starts in
        parallel several drivers, so the messages are mixed, you
        can have</para>
        <screen>
          <![CDATA[<6> sda:<6>USB Universal Host Contr'ller Interface driver v3.0]]>
</screen>
        <para>This don't mean that your sda drive is an usb one,
        but the usb module was started at the same time as the
        drive one and send it's messages simultaneously. You still
        have a 
        <emphasis>/dev/sda</emphasis>drive.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>New Media Names</title>
        <para>Here the dmesg content for inserting an USB
        key:</para>
        <screen>
          <![CDATA[scsi7 : SCSI emulation for USB Mass Storage devices
usb 5-3: New USB device found, idVendor=0951, idProduct=160e
usb 5-3: New USB device strings: Mfr=1, Product=2, SerialNumber=3
usb 5-3: Product: DataTraveler 2.0
usb 5-3: Manufacturer: Kingston
usb 5-3: SerialNumber: 200706200000000059188185
usb-storage: device found at 9
usb-storage: waiting for device to settle before scanning
scsi 7:0:0:0: Direct-Access     Kingston DataTraveler 2.0 1.00 PQ: 0 ANSI: 2
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] 3930112 512-byte hardware sectors: (2.01GB/1.87GiB)
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Write Protect is off
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Mode Sense: 23 00 00 00
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Assuming drive cache: write through
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] 3930112 512-byte hardware sectors: (2.01GB/1.87GiB)
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Write Protect is off
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Mode Sense: 23 00 00 00
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Assuming drive cache: write through
 sdb: sdb1
sd 7:0:0:0: [sdb] Attached SCSI removable disk
sd 7:0:0:0: Attached scsi generic sg2 type 0
usb-storage: device scan complete]]>
</screen>
        <para>You see there all what we where speaking about right
        now! SCSI emulation, scsi, sd and sg names, but also the
        sdb that is most important for us.</para>
        <para>Here are the messages for a high speed SDHC
        card:</para>
        <screen>
          <![CDATA[tifm_core: MMC/SD card detected in socket 0:1
mmc1: new SDHC card at address d555
mmcblk0: mmc1:d555 SD04G 3.79GiB
 mmcblk0: p1

/dev/mmcblk0p1 on /media/H2SD type vfat (rw,nosuid,nodev,noatime,flush,uid=1000,utf8,shortname=lower)]]>
</screen>
        <para>When the two cards are probably the same flash memory
        chip, the USB key uses the USB interface and SCSI
        emulation, the SDHC card uses the PCMCIA slot of the
        laptop, with a special device naming (/dev/mmcblk0). The
        use, as far as partitionning is involved is the
        same.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Disk ID</title>
        <para>In a world where disks are many and removable, it's
        impossible to track what device is used by what disk. So
        there are now many way of using a disk name. This makes it
        extremely difficult to work with basic tools. These are
        "Disk labels" and "Disk UUID", also "Partition Labels". See
        fstab man page for details.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Partition Naming in Linux</title>
    <section>
      <title>Numbers</title>
      <para>Partition naming is thanksfully simpler than drive one.
      Partitions are simply given a number from 0 up (decimal).
      Sometime a "p" is appended on front of the number:</para>
      <screen>
        <![CDATA[cat /proc/partitions
major minor  #blocks  name

   8     0  488386584 sda
   8     1   52436128 sda1
   8     2          1 sda2
   8     5    2104483 sda5
   8     6   20972826 sda6
   8     7   52436128 sda7
   8     8  360434308 sda8
 179     0    3979776 mmcblk0
 179     1    3975680 mmcblk0p1]]>
</screen>
      <para>As you see, partition devices are listed in
      /proc/partition. This file... is not a real file but is
      created on the fly. Don't worry, for what we need it's a
      file.</para>
      <para>Notice the "p1" partition name for the SDHC
      card.</para>
      <para>Max number of partitions is 15 for SCSI and all the
      drives using the new SATA driver, 63 for IDE drives (0 is the
      full drive, 0 to 15 is four bits 0 to 64, 6 bits)</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Meaning of the Numbers</title>
      <para>Not all the numbers have the same meaning. This mess
      come from the PC history. One can divide floppies with
      partitions, but then 4 ones seems sufficient. But then come
      Hard drives :-). So the partitons numbers 1, 2, 3 and 4 are 
      <emphasis>primary</emphasis>partitions. One drive can only
      have 4 primaries.</para>
      <para>To go further, we have to use one of these primary as a
      big one and sub-partition this one, so to have 
      <emphasis>logical</emphasis>partitions. The big 
      <emphasis>extended</emphasis>partition can be any of the
      4.</para>
      <para>So, remember, the primary partitions are inside the
      drive and the logical partitions are inside one of the
      primary, called the 
      <emphasis>extended</emphasis>partition.</para>
      <para>Once the logical partitions are created, it's no more
      recommended to write directly to the extended one. Writing to
      an extended partition would erase the logical ones like
      writing directly to a hard drive erase the partitons. Beware,
      
      <emphasis role='strong'>it's possible</emphasis>!!</para>
      <para>If, after creating 4 primary partitions, all the disk
      space is not used, the remaining space is lost (unusable), so
      most of the time, create the desired primaries, then at last
      the extended one with all the remaining room.</para>
      <para>It's not necessary to create 4 primaries. You could use
      only one extended (Linux only), but there are some advantages
      of using primaries.</para>
      <para>Primaries being 4, the first logical partition is
      always 5. So any partition with number of five and up is a
      logical one.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Device Major and Minor Numbers</title>
    <para>The only important thing with a device file are its major
    and minor device numbers, which are shown instead of the file
    size:</para>
    <screen>
      <![CDATA[$ ls -l /dev/hda
brw-rw---- 1 root disk 8, 0 mars  9 07:56 /dev/sda]]>
</screen>
    <para>Shows permissions (
    <systemitem>brw-rw----</systemitem>), owner (root), group (disk), major
    device number (8), minor device number (0), date (mars 9 -
    french, no year), hour (07:56) and device name (guess
    :-).</para>
    <para>When accessing a device file, the major number selects
    which device driver is being called to perform the input/output
    operation. This call is being done with the minor number as a
    parameter and it is entirely up to the driver how the minor
    number is being interpreted. The driver documentation usually
    describes how the driver uses minor numbers.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Partition Types</title>
    <section>
      <title>Linux Partition Types</title>
      <para>A partition is labeled to host a certain kind of file
      system (not to be confused with a volume label. Such a file
      system could be the linux standard ext3 file system or linux
      swap space, or even foreign file systems like (Microsoft)
      NTFS or (Sun) UFS. There is a numerical code associated with
      each partition type. For example, the code for ext2 is 
      <constant>0x83</constant> and linux swap is 
      <constant>0x82</constant> (0x mean hexadecimal).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Foreign Partition Types</title>
      <para>The partition type codes have been arbitrarily chosen
      (you can't figure out what they should be) and they are
      particular to a given operating system. Therefore, it is
      theoretically possible that if you use two operating systems
      with the same hard drive, the same code might be used to
      designate two different partition types. OS/2 marks its
      partitions with a 0x07 type and so does Windows NT's NTFS.
      MS-DOS allocates several type codes for its various flavors
      of FAT file systems: 0x01, 0x04 and 0x06 are known. DR-DOS
      used 0x81 to indicate protected FAT partitions, creating a
      type clash with Linux/Minix at that time, but neither
      Linux/Minix nor DR-DOS are widely used any more.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Swap Partitions</title>
      <para>Every process running on your computer is allocated a
      number of blocks of RAM. These blocks are called pages. The
      set of in-memory pages which will be referenced by the
      processor in the very near future is called a "working set."
      Linux tries to predict these memory accesses (assuming that
      recently used pages will be used again in the near future)
      and keeps these pages in RAM if possible.</para>
      <para>If you have too many processes running on a machine,
      the kernel will try to free up RAM by writing pages to disk.
      This is what swap space is for. It effectively increases the
      amount of memory you have available. However, disk I/O is
      about a hundred times slower than reading from and writing to
      RAM. Consider this emergency memory and not extra
      memory.</para>
      <para>If memory becomes so scarce that the kernel pages out
      from the working set of one process in order to page in for
      another, the machine is said to be thrashing. Some readers
      might have inadvertenly experienced this: the hard drive is
      grinding away like crazy, but the computer is slow to the
      point of being unusable. Swap space is something you need to
      have, but it is no substitute for sufficient RAM.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Complete List</title>
      <para>From the fdisk help:</para>
      <screen>
        <![CDATA[ 0  Vide            1e  Hidden W95 FAT1 80  Old Minix       bf  Solaris
 1  FAT12           24  NEC DOS         81  Minix / old Lin c1  DRDOS/sec (FAT-
 2  XENIX root      39  Plan 9          82  Linux swap / So c4  DRDOS/sec (FAT-
 3  XENIX usr       3c  PartitionMagic  83  Linux           c6  DRDOS/sec (FAT-
 4  FAT16 <32M      40  Venix 80286     84  OS/2 hidden C:  c7  Syrinx
 5  Extended        41  PPC PReP Boot   85  Linux extended  da  Non-FS data
 6  FAT16           42  SFS             86  NTFS volume set db  CP/M / CTOS / .
 7  HPFS/NTFS       4d  QNX4.x          87  NTFS volume set de  Dell Utility
 8  AIX             4e  QNX4.x 2nd part 88  Linux plein tex df  BootIt
 9  AIX bootable    4f  QNX4.x 3rd part 8e  Linux LVM       e1  DOS access
 a  OS/2 Boot Manag 50  OnTrack DM      93  Amoeba          e3  DOS R/O
 b  W95 FAT32       51  OnTrack DM6 Aux 94  Amoeba BBT      e4  SpeedStor
 c  W95 FAT32 (LBA) 52  CP/M            9f  BSD/OS          eb  BeOS fs
 e  W95 FAT16 (LBA) 53  OnTrack DM6 Aux a0  IBM Thinkpad hi ee  GPT
 f  W95 Etendu (LBA 54  OnTrackDM6      a5  FreeBSD         ef  EFI (FAT-12/16/
10  OPUS            55  EZ-Drive        a6  OpenBSD         f0  Linux/PA-RISC b
11  Hidden FAT12    56  Golden Bow      a7  NeXTSTEP        f1  SpeedStor
12  Compaq diagnost 5c  Priam Edisk     a8  UFS Darwin      f4  SpeedStor
14  Hidden FAT16 <3 61  SpeedStor       a9  NetBSD          f2  DOS secondary
16  Hidden FAT16    63  GNU HURD or Sys ab  Amorce Darwin   fb  VMware VMFS
17  Hidden HPFS/NTF 64  Novell Netware  b7  BSDI fs         fc  VMware VMKCORE
18  AST SmartSleep  65  Novell Netware  b8  BSDI swap       fd  Linux raid auto
1b  Hidden W95 FAT3 70  DiskSecure Mult bb  Boot Wizard hid fe  LANstep
1c  Hidden W95 FAT3 75  PC/IX           be  Amorce Solaris  ff  BBT]]>
</screen>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>How Many Partitions</title>
    <para>The exact number of partitions allowed on a drive is
    fixed by the kernel. So you can find the exact number is the
    kernel documentation, the last version is maintained here 
    <ulink url='http://kernel.org/pub/linux/docs/device-list/' />If
    you have the kernel source installed, you can find your version
    on your computer at
    /usr/src/linux/Documentation/devices.txt.</para>
    <para>Look at "limit on partition". Find yours. Common SATA
    number is 31, SCSI is 15, some are less.</para>
  </section>
</article>


