<chapter>
  <title>General development stuff</title>
  <section id="what-can-i-do">
    <title>What can I do?</title>
    <para>
      A lot! First of all, you can try out all your exciting ideas. You 
      can add everything you ever wanted to have in a distro but couldn't. 
      Of course, if you want to introduce some revolutionary changes, 
      it's a good idea to ask others first.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can start by looking at the .spec files. Having checked out the
      specs from our CVS (<command>cvs up SPECS</command>) look at them 
      and you can easily see
      what needs to be added and modified. You can see the lists of
      available CVS modules at 
      <ulink url="http://cvs.pld-linux.org/">CVSWeb</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can start by adding a new package. We have prepared a template
      which can be a good starting point: check it out from SPECS module in
      our CVS (file template.spec). Ask people for opinion -- on the mailing 
      list or IRC (#pld). Don't worry if you make an error - you can always 
      go back to a previous revision using <literal>-r</literal> option of 
      <command>cvs get/checkout/update</command> commands. If you modify 
      specs made by someone else, be careful not to break anything. Always 
      build before committing (OK, unless you found a typo). If you feel 
      the package should be rebuild and updated on our ftp site (e.g. you 
      have corrected a bug, or there is a typo in an otherwise ready 
      package), remember to increase the release number. 
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="results-of-work">
    <title>I want to see the results of my work!</title>
    <para>
      Be patient. The packages are sent to our building machines. 
      Build logs are available via <ulink 
      url="http://buildlogs.pld-linux.org/">web interface</ulink>, 
      where you can check if building of your package completed 
      successfully.
    </para>
    <para>
      If everything is OK, your package is moved to the i
      <filename>/test</filename> directory, then -- if no one complains, 
      after a couple of days -- to the main tree. 
    </para>
    <para>
      You can see if people use your package when they complain -- and 
      they do! Check out <ulink url="http://bugs.pld.net.pl/">our bugtracking
      system</ulink> to see bug reports. Often these issues are trivial to 
      resolve. Remember to close ticket in BTS after you solved it.
    </para>
  </section>
  &devel-hacking;
  &devel-commit-messages;
</chapter>
