<section id="installer-serial">
	<title>Installing on box without a monitor (a console on a serial port)</title>
	<!-- contributed by Sebastian Zagrodzki -->
	<para>
	  You may install pld on machine that has no monitor. All you need is
	  a null-modem cable and a second computer with terminal emulator
	  (minicom, kermit, HyperTerminal, whatever) or a hardware terminal
	  (like Wyse).
	</para>
	<para>
	  Serial console is very common on big machine farms, with lots of
	  server boxes and without workstations.
	  Some hardware, like Sun SPARCs, Compaq Alphas, many network
	  devices like Cisco, Fore/Marconi or 3Com have a native serial port
	  support (including BIOS prompt). You don't
	  have to keep a monitor or monitors in machine room, you don't
	  have to take it with you every time you go to check why the
	  machine you upgraded last night doesn't respond and so on - you
	  take a notebook (it could be anything, like an old
	  386 or even 8086 with a floppy disk with DOS 3.3 and kermit
	  installed on it) and you don't need anything else.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Make sure you have a full nullmodem cable (with 7 or more
	  wires). If you want to make such a cable by yourself - no
	  problem. You can find pinouts here:
	  <ulink url="http://www.hardwarebook.net">http://www.hardwarebook.net</ulink>
	  Don't forget to check out the Yost page about serial
	  console cables. You'll find there how to make an RJ45
	  to DB9/DB25 adapter:
	  <ulink url="http://Yost.com/Computers/RJ45-serial/">http://Yost.com/Computers/RJ45-serial/</ulink>
	</para>
	<para>
	  You set your terminal to: 9600bps, 8 data bits, none parity, 1
	  stop bit, with no flow control (hardware and software off),
	  VT100 or VT102 emulation.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Run you terminal program and then 
	  insert a PLD bootable floppy or CD-ROM into the target machines
	  drive, and turn power on. If your BIOS does not have serial
	  console support, just wait a moment for a boot - if you didn't
	  set the boot device to be "drive C only", after few moments you
	  should see PLD bootdisk logo. <!-- Hold down <keycap>Shift</keycap> key
	  to get a boot prompt. -->
	</para>
	<para>
	  Type "serial" in boot prompt and press ENTER. If you can't
	  type anything - be sure to check if you turned hardware flow
	  control off. See how the kernel boots, and wait for shell
	  prompt. Voila, now you can do everything like you would when
	  sitting before a monitor.
	</para>
	<para>
	  After installation, don't forget to install getty_ps, and set
	  up a console in inittab:

	  <programlisting>S0:respawn:/sbin/getty ttyS0 9600 vt100</programlisting>

	  When configuring lilo, use:

	  <programlisting>serial=0,9600n8</programlisting>

	  in global configuration, and
	  
	  <programlisting>append="console=ttyS0,9600n8"</programlisting>

	  for every kernel image. This way lilo will prompt you on a
	  serial console, and kernel will use /dev/ttyS0 as /dev/console.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Try it - it really works, and once you start using serial
	  console, you will find it really useful - for example think
	  of remote console access.
	</para>
</section>
