<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix id="About-the-Author">

  <title>About the Author</title>

  <para>
  Binh Nguyen was born 1983, Melbourne, Australia. He studied 
  at St Josephs Marist Brothers College, North Fitzroy until receiving a
  scholarship to St Kevin's College, Toorak.
  </para>

  <para>
  He has degrees in human resourcing, computer science, philosophy,
  international health and is studying for degrees in business management
  and perhaps law and marketing
  </para>

  <para>
  His background is strongly biased towards science and mathematics. 
  Nonetheless, he does have an appreciation for the arts, humanities 
  and sport. He speaks English predominately but is also able to
  communicate in Vietnamese and French. When younger he also possessed
  the ability to communicate in Chinese and Italian.
  </para>

  <para>
  Although brought up as a Buddhist and studying at Catholic/Christian 
  schools all his life as well as studying scripture during his final year of 
  high school he considers himself an atheist.
  </para>

  <para>
  At this moment in time, he works part-time as a (commercial) 
  researcher/developer on Linux related projects with his current 
  focus being on software distribution mechanisms.
  </para>

  <para>
  Two of his technical documents have been incorporated into the 
  Linux Documentation Project ("Linux Dictionary" and "Linux Filesystem 
  Hierarchy", <ulink url="www.tldp.org/guides.html">
  www.tldp.org/guides.html</ulink>). Furthermore, they are being 
  used as reference books in at least ten universities around the world 
  (University of Southern Queensland (Australia), 
  Universidad Michoacana (Mexico), 
  Hong Kong Polytechnic University (Hong Kong),
  Universidade de Sao Paolo (Brazil), 
  University of Southern California (United States of America),
  University of Wales Swansea (United Kingdom),
  University of Ulster (Ireland),
  Universität Duisburg-Essen (Germany),
  Universidad Rey Juan Carlos (Spain),
  Insituto Superior Miguel Torga (Portugal),
  and Universiti Sains Malaysia (Malaysia)). As well as this, he is also a
  Development Lead and Project Administrator of the "Computer Dictionary 
  Project" <ulink url="http://computerdictionary.tsf.org.za/dictionary/index.html">
  http://computerdictionary.tsf.org.za/dictionary/index.html</ulink>
  which is being supported by the Shuttleworth Foundation.
  </para>

  <para>
  He has published articles at linux.com, linmagau.org, desktoplinux.com, 
  newsforge.com, linuxtoday.com, linux.org, pclinuxonline.com, 
  tuxreports.com, etc.... and has a keen interest in the latest innovations 
  in science and technology.
  </para>

  <para>
  The author's homepage is at,
  <ulink url="http://geocities.com/linuxfilesystem/">
  http://geocities.com/linuxfilesystem/</ulink>
  </para> 

</appendix>
