<sect1 id="ARCnet">

<title>ARCnet</title>

<para>
ARCnet, developed in 1977, by Datapoint Corporation, is an older standard
that has largely been replaced by Ethernet in current networks. ARCnet,
uses RG-62 coaxial cable in a star, bus, or hybrid physical topology. This
networking scheme supports active and passive hubs, which must be connected
to an active hub. ARCnet requries 93-ohm terminators at the end of bus
cables, and on unused ports of passive hubs. It supports UTP, coaxial, or
fiber-optic cable. The distance between nodes is 400 feet with UTP cable,
and higher for coaxial or fiber-optic cable.
</para>

<para>
ARCnet uses a token-passing scheme similar to that of token ring. ARCnet
networks support a bandwidth of 2.5 Mbps. Newer standards (ARCnet Plus and
TCNS) support speeds of 20 Mbps and 100 Mbps, but have not really caught on.
</para>

<para>
ARCNet device names are `arc0e', `arc1e', `arc2e' etc. or `arc0s',
`arc1s', `arc2s' etc. The first card detected by the kernel is
assigned `arc0e' or `arc0s' and the rest are assigned sequentially in
the order they are detected. The letter at the end signifies whether
you've selected ethernet encapsulation packet format or RFC1051 packet
format.
</para>

<para>
<screen>	
  Kernel Compile Options:

               Network device support  --->
                   [*] Network device support
                   <*> ARCnet support
                   [ ]   Enable arc0e (ARCnet "Ether-Encap" packet format)
                   [ ]   Enable arc0s (ARCnet RFC1051 packet format)
</screen>
</para>	   

<para>
Once you have your kernel properly built to support your ethernet card
then configuration of the card is easy.
</para>

<para>
Typically you would use something like:
</para>

<para>
<screen>	
          root# ifconfig arc0e 192.168.0.1 netmask 255.255.255.0 up
	  root# route add -net 192.168.0.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 arc0e
</screen>
</para>	   

<para>
Please refer to the /usr/src/linux/Documentation/networking/arcnet.txt
and /usr/src/linux/Documentation/networking/arcnet-hardware.txt files
for further information.
</para>

<para>
ARCNet support on Linux was developed by Avery Pennarun, apenwarr@foxnet.net.
</para>

</sect1>
