<sect1 id="FTP">

  FTP mini-HOWTO
  Matthew Borowski (mkb@yahoo.com )
  v0.2, 9 January 2000

<title>FTP</title>

<para>
File Transport Protocol (FTP) is an efficient way to transfer files between
machines across networks. Clients and servers exist for almost all platforms
making FTP the most convenient (and therefore popular) method of transferring
files.

There are two typical modes of running an FTP server - either anonymously or
account-based. Anonymous FTP servers are by far the most popular; they allow
any machine to access the FTP server and the files stored on it with the same
permissions. No usernames or passwords are transmitted down the wire.
Account-based FTP allows users to login with real usernames and passwords.
While it provides greater access control than anonymous FTP, transmitting real
usernames and password unencrypted over the Internet is generally avoided for
security reasons.

An FTP client is the userland application that provides access to FTP
servers. There are many FTP clients available. Some are graphical, and
some are text-based.

FTP related software (servers and clients) for Linux may be found at:
http://metalab.unc.edu/pub/Linux/system/network/file-transfer/

FTP was first developed by the University of California, Berkeley for
inclusion in 4.2BSD (Berkeley Unix). The RFC (Request for Comments)
documents for the protocol is now known as RFC 959 and is available at
ftp://nic.merit.edu/documents/rfc/rfc0959.txt. 
  
3. Beginner's guide to using ftp
A quick guide to using ftp. 

The standard ftp program is the original ftp client. It comes standard with most Linux 
distributions. It first appeared in 4.2BSD, which was developed by the University of 
California, Berkeley. 


3.1 Running the ftp program 
It's easy to use ftp. Let's say you want to connect to the anonymous ftp site 
metalab.unc.edu, to download the latest Linux kernel source. 

At the command line, type: 

$ ftp metalab.unc.edu

The ftp program will attempt to connect to metalab.unc.edu. Another way to do this is 
to run ftp from the command line with no parameters, and use the open command, with 
the site name as an argument: 

$ ftp
ftp> open metalab.unc.edu

3.2 Logging into an FTP server 
When you connect to an FTP site, it will ask you for a login (pressing enter will 
log in as your local user name, in this case, foo: We log in as anonymous or ftp, 
to get to the public archive. 

220 helios.oit.unc.edu FTP server (Version wu-2.6.0(2) Wed Nov 17 14:44:12
EST 1999) ready.
Name (metalab.unc.edu:foo): 

Now, we enter a complete e-mail address as the password (this is what most public 
FTP sites request). 

331 Guest login ok, send your complete e-mail address as password.
Password:

After a successful login, the following information is given to us: 

Remote system type is UNIX.
Using binary mode to transfer files.
ftp> 

3.3 File transfer types 
After you log in to an ftp site, ftp will print out the file transfer type. In 
our case, it is binary. Binary mode transfers the files, bit by bit, as they 
are on the FTP server. Ascii mode, however, will download the text directly. 
You can type ascii or binary to switch between the types. 

You want to download the kernel source, so you leave the file transfer type at 
binary. The binary type is also what you would use for any non-text files -- 
such as graphic images, zip/gzip archives, executable programs, etc. If in 
doubt, use binary mode. 

3.4 Navigating and listing directories 
You do an ls to see a list of the files. The ls command on ftp servers is 
executed on the remote server, so the command line options that you can use 
with it vary from server to server. The most common options are generally 
available, check the manpage for ls for details. 

ftp> ls
200 PORT command successful.
150 Opening ASCII mode data connection for /bin/ls.
total 33590
-r--r--r--   1 root     other    34348506 Dec 03 03:53 IAFA-LISTINGS
lrwxrwxrwx   1 root     other           7 Jul 15  1997 README -> WELCOME
-rw-r--r--   1 root     other         890 Nov 15 13:11 WELCOME
dr-xr-xr-x   2 root     other         512 Jul 15  1997 bin
dr-xr-xr-x   2 root     other         512 Jul 15  1997 dev
dr-xr-xr-x   2 root     other         512 Jul 18  1997 etc
drwxrwxrwx  11 ftp      20           4608 Nov 28 16:00 incoming
lrwxrwxrwx   1 root     other          13 Jun 04  1998 ls-lR -> IAFA-LISTINGS
dr-xr-xr-x  17 root     root          512 Jun 08 11:43 pub
dr-xr-xr-x   3 root     other         512 Jul 15  1997 unc
dr-xr-xr-x   5 root     other         512 Jul 15  1997 usr
226 Transfer complete.

If the ls command lists so many files that they scroll off the top of the 
screen, you can use Shift-PageUp to scroll up. This works in Linux console 
mode as well as in xterm or rxvt. 

On public FTP archives, the downloadable resources are usually held in the 
/pub directory. In this example, you already know that the kernel sources 
are in the directory /pub/Linux/kernel, so you type the following to get 
into that directory: 

ftp> cd pub/Linux/kernel
250-README for kernel
250-
250-What you'll find here: kernel sources and patches
250-
250-
250 CWD command successful.

The messages you see, which begin with "250", are information messages sent 
by the server. In this case, the ftp server is configured to automatically 
send you the README file when you cd into the directory. 

3.5 Downloading and uploading files 
Now, after doing another ls, you see that you want to cd into the v2.2 
directory. You do yet another ls, and find the file you want to download. 
It is linux-2.2.13.tar.gz. So you type this: 

ftp> get linux-2.2.13.tar.gz
local: linux-2.2.13.tar.gz remote: linux-2.2.13.tar.gz
200 PORT command successful.
150 Opening BINARY mode data connection for linux-2.2.13.tar.gz (15079540
bytes).

The ftp program has started saving the remote file linux-2.2.13.tar.gz as 
the local file linux-2.2.13.tar.gz. 

If you wanted to save it as the local file foo.tar.gz, you could have 
specified it like this: 

ftp> get linux-2.2.13.tar.gz foo.tar.gz
local: foo.tar.gz remote: linux-2.2.13.tar.gz
200 PORT command successful.
150 Opening BINARY mode data connection for linux-2.2.13.tar.gz (15079540
bytes).

If you want to download more than one file at a time, you'll have to use 
the mget (multiple get) command. You can use mget together with a 
space-delimited list of filenames you want to download, or you can use 
wildcards with the mget command. For example: 

ftp> mget linux*

Would get all files starting with the string "linux". Normally, mget will 
prompt you for each file before it downloads it. You can toggle this by 
using the prompt command. 

Now let's say you've written a piece of software, and you want to upload 
it to MetaLab to be included in their Linux software archive. First, 
you'd change to the /incoming directory (most public FTP servers have a 
directory, usually called incoming or uploads, where files can be 
uploaded), then you'd use the put command: 

ftp> cd /incoming
ftp> put foo.tar.gz
local: foo.tar.gz remote: foo.tar.gz
200 PORT command successful.
150 Opening BINARY mode data connection for foo.tar.gz.
226 Transfer complete.
10257 bytes sent in 0.00316 secs (3.2e+03 Kbytes/sec)

The put command works the same way as the get command, so you can use 
mput to upload multiple files at the same time. You can also upload a 
local file with a different filename on the server by specifying the 
remote filename and/or pathname as an argument. 

What if the file foo.tar.gz is not in your current local directory 
when you try to upload it? You can switch local directories by using 
the lcd (local change directory) command: 

ftp> lcd /home/foo/
Local directory now /home/foo

3.6 Running shell commands 
The ftp client supports using the bang (!) to run local commands. For 
example, to get a listing of files in your current local directory, do this: 

ftp> !ls

The way this works is that ftp calls the shell (specified in the $SHELL 
environment variable), and it is the shell which runs ls. Thus, you can 
run any command-line which works with your shell simply by prepending "!" 
to it (the default shell in most Linux distributions is bash, the Bourne 
Again SHell). Please note that !cd does not work as you would expect, 
this is why the lcd command exists. 

3.7 Hash marks and tick 
Wouldn't it be nice if you could watch the progress while you're downloading 
a file with ftp? You can use the hash command to print out hash marks as you 
download a file: 

ftp> hash
Hash mark printing on (1024 bytes/hash mark).

As you can tell, ftp will print a hash mark for every 1024 bytes of data 
you download. 

There is also a tick option. 

ftp> tick           
Tick counter printing on (10240 bytes/tick increment).

This will print something to this effect as you download a file:

Bytes transferred: 11680

3.8 Other ftp commands 
There are many other ftp commands. If you have the permissions to do so 
(which you should, if you are connected to your own private shell account), 
you can make a directory on the remote server using the mkdir command. 
You can remove a file on the remote server using the delete command, or 
rmdir to remove a directory. You can also change file permissions using the 
chmod command. 

For more elaborate information on using ftp, please see the online help in 
the ftp program (accessible by typing help with no arguments for a list of 
commands, or help <commandname> for specific help on a command). You can 
also read the Unix man page for ftp by typing man ftp at your command prompt. 

4. Console FTP clients
The original ftp program was the original ftp client, and it is a good 
investment to learn it. It's the only ftp client that you can be certain 
is available on most systems (even Win32 comes with the ftp command, albeit 
an archaic, braindead version of it). 

There are many other console-mode (text-only) ftp clients available. The 
listing here is by no means comprehensive, but includes the most popular 
ones. Search at FreshMeat to find more. 

4.1 NcFTP 
NcFTP is the all-time favorite ftp client of many Unix users. It comes 
bundled with most Linux distributions, and offers many advanced features such
as tab completion and bookmarks. Version 2 of NcFTP had a curses based 
full-screen mode. This was done away with in Version 3 (now in beta). 

It's not 100% compatible with the commands that standard ftp uses. For example, 
get and put in NcFTP act like mget and mput do in standard ftp. So if you want 
to save a remote file as a different local filename, you'd have to 
do get -z remotename localname. Thankfully, NcFTP has a nice online help system 
to assist you in learning the commands. 

You can get the latest version of NcFTP at http://www.ncftp.com. 

4.2 lukemftp 
A port of the NetBSD FTP client to other systems, lukemftp derives its name 
from the author of most of the enhanced features, which include: 
command-line editing, command-line fetches of FTP and HTTP URLs (including 
via proxies), context-sensitive word completion, dynamic progress bar, 
IPv6 support, modification time preservation, paging of local and remote 
files, passive mode support (with fallback to active mode), SOCKS support, 
TIS FWTK gate-ftp server support, and transfer rate throttling. 

lukemftp is espically good for users who don't want to change to anything 
drastically different from the standard ftp client, but want more advanced features. 

You can get the latest version of lukemftp at 
ftp://ftp.netbsd.org/pub/NetBSD/misc/lukemftp/. 

4.3 lftp 
lftp is a sophisticated command line based FTP client. Like bash, it has job 
control. It uses the GNU readline library for input, so you have command line 
completion and editing. lftp also has bookmarks, mirroring support, and can 
transfer several files in parellel. 

You can get the latest version of lftp at http://ftp.yars.free.net/projects/lftp/. 

Debian packages are available at ftp://ftp.freshmeat.net/pub/debs/lftp/. 

4.4 cftp 
Comfortable FTP (cftp) is a full screen mode client. What it lacks in features, 
it makes up for in ease of use. You browse through the directories using the 
arrow keys and enter. 

You should be able to get the latest version of cftp at 
http://ftp.giga.or.at/pub/nih/cftp/. 

4.5 yafc 
Yafc is a very nice ftp client, with features including directory cache, 
remote filename completion, aliases, colorized ls, recursive get/put/ls/rm, 
nohup mode transfers, tagging (queueing), multiple connections, proxy support 
and more. It has support for Kerberos4 authentication. 

You can get the latest version of yafc from 
http://www.stacken.kth.se/~mhe/yafc/. 

Debian packages are available at 
http://members.home.com/decklin/experimental/. 

Redhat packages are available at 
http://lz.freeservers.com/linux/yafc.html. 

5. X Window FTP clients
There are several graphical FTP clients designed to run on the X Window 
system. These clients offer ease of use for users who are used to 
graphical environments, and sometimes offer versatile options that would 
be hard to implement in a text-based ftp client. 

5.1 gFTP 
gFTP is an FTP client for X Windows written using Gtk. The interface has 
some similarities to the popular WS_FTP software commonly used on a certain 
unstable operating system. 

gFTP features simultaneous downloads, resuming of interrupted file transfers, 
file transfer queues, downloading of entire directories, ftp proxy support, 
remote directory caching, passive and non-passive file transfers, drag-n-drop 
support, a very nice connection manager and more. 

If you are running Red Hat Linux and have the GNOME desktop installed, then 
you probably already have gFTP. If not, you can download gFTP from its 
homepage at http://gftp.seul.org/. 

5.2 WXftp 
WXftp is an FTP client for the X Window System designed to be used mainly 
on Linux workstations. It is written using the WXWindows toolkit, so it 
can be compiled to use either Motif or GTK+ 

It includes an intuitive user interface (much like WS_FTP), a session 
manager, on-line help, a progress bar, and more 

Check out WXftp's homepage at http://www.wxftp.seul.org. 

5.3 LLNL XDIR and XFTP 
LLNL XFTP was one of the first graphical FTP clients for Linux. It supports 
FXP (file transfer between two remote hosts), and has a Motif based interface. 

More information is available at http://www.llnl.gov/ia/xdir_xftp/. 

5.4 guiftp 
Guiftp is a simple ftp client written with the GTK+ toolkit. It's good if 
you don't need many features and want a simple, clean look. 

Guiftp's homepage is at http://www.altern.org/ldufresne/guiftp/. 

6. FTP Servers
6.1 How an FTP Server works 
A traditional FTP server is executed from inetd (the internet superserver 
daemon). The standard FTP port is port 21. When a user tries to log in, the 
FTP server uses a standard system call to check the user name and password 
against the entries in the system password file, or the NIS tables if you 
are using NIS. If the login is correct, the user is given access to the system. 

Anonymous FTP works differently. The user logs in with either the anonymous 
or the ftp username (this can be defined in the config file). He is then 
given access to a directory tree that has been chroot()'ed. This ensures 
that the user can not gain access to directory trees he is not authorized 
for. The chrooted directory tree usually contains a mock filesystem, 
with bin/, etc/, and lib/ directories. The files for download are usually 
put in the pub/ directory. 

The reason for a mock filesystem in an anonymous FTP tree is that the FTP 
daemon runs external commands for ls requests. You can also place additional 
programs in the bin directory, and a user can run them with the SITE command 
in his ftp client. For example, Red Hat's FTP includes the RPM command 
(for users to query RPM packages on the site). 

Some FTP servers work differently. For example, some will allow user accounts 
to be set up independant of the system-wide password file (FTP-only accounts). 
Some servers (ProFTPD and NcFTPd for instance) have built-in ls commands and 
do not need a special directory tree within the chroot structure. Other ftp 
servers stray altogether from the standard ftp concept. FTP4ALL, for example, 
does not use system passwords at all. It uses it's own user and group file, 
and has features such as upload/download ratio and customizable server messages. 

6.2 Help with FTP Servers 
WU-FTPD
WU-FTPD is the ftp daemon included with many Linux distributions, including 
Red Hat and Caldera. You can learn more about WU-FTPD at http://www.wu-ftpd.org. 

The WU-FTPD FAQ can be found on the web at http://www.cetis.hvu.nl/~koos/wu-ftpd-faq.html. 

ProFTPD
ProFTPD is a powerful FTP server that includes Apache-style configuration, 
extensive support for virtual hosts, and internal ls. 

A complete command reference and downloads can be found at http://www.proftpd.org
</para>

</sect1>
