<sect1 id="IPv6">

<title>IPv6</title>


<para>
2.1. What is IPv6?

IPv6, sometimes also referred to as IPng (IP Next Generation)
is a new layer 3 protocol (see [http://www.linuxports.com/howto/
intro_to_networking/c4412.htm#PAGE103HTML] linuxports/howto/
intro_to_networking/ISO - OSI Model) which will supersede IPv4 (also known as
IP). 

It was designed to address many issues including, the shortage of 
available IP addresses, lack of mechanisms to handle time-sensitive 
traffic, lack of network layer security, etc.

IPv4 was designed long time ago ([http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc760.html]
RFC 760 / Internet Protocol from January 1980) and since its inception, there
have been many requests for more addresses and enhanced capabilities. Latest
RFC is [http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2460.html] RFC 2460 / Internet Protocol
Version 6 Specification. Major changes in IPv6 are the redesign of the
header, including the increase of address size from 32 bits to 128 bits.
Because layer 3 is responsible for end-to-end packet transport using packet
routing based on addresses, it must include the new IPv6 addresses (source
and destination), like IPv4. It is anticpated that the larger name space 
and accompanying improved addressing scheme, which will prove to provide
a major improvement on routing performance.

For more information about the IPv6 history take a look at older IPv6 related
RFCs listed e.g. at [http://www.switch.ch/lan/ipv6/references.html] SWITCH
IPv6 Pilot / References.

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------

2.2. History of IPv6 in Linux

The years 1992, 1993 and 1994 of the IPv6 History (in general) are covered by
following document: [http://www.laynetworks.com/users/webs/IPv6.htm#CH3] IPv6
or IPng (IP next generation).

To-do: better time-line, more content...
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------

2.2.1. Beginning

The first IPv6 related network code was added to the Linux kernel 2.1.8 in
November 1996 by Pedro Roque. It was based on the BSD API:
diff -u --recursive --new-file v2.1.7/linux/include/linux/in6.h              
¬ linux/include/linux/in6.h                                                  
--- v2.1.7/linux/include/linux/in6.h Thu Jan 1 02:00:00 1970                 
+++ linux/include/linux/in6.h Sun Nov 3 11:04:42 1996                        
@@ -0,0 +1,99 @@                                                             
+/*                                                                          
+ * Types and definitions for AF_INET6                                       
+ * Linux INET6 implementation                                               
+ * + * Authors:                                                             
+ * Pedro Roque <******>                                                     
+ *                                                                          
+ * Source:                                                                  
+ * IPv6 Program Interfaces for BSD Systems                                  
+ * <draft-ietf-ipngwg-bsd-api-05.txt>                                       
                                                                             

The shown lines were copied from patch-2.1.8 (e-mail address was blanked on
copy&paste).
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------

2.2.2. In between

Because of lack of manpower, the IPv6 implementation in the kernel was unable
to follow the discussed drafts or newly released RFCs. In October 2000, a
project was started in Japan, called [http://www.linux-ipv6.org/] USAGI,
whose aim was to implement all missing, or outdated IPv6 support in Linux. It
tracks the current IPv6 implementation in FreeBSD made by the [http://
www.kame.net/] KAME project. From time to time they create snapshots against
current vanilla Linux kernel sources.
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------

2.2.3. Current

Unfortunately, the [http://www.linux-ipv6.org/] USAGI patch is so big, that
current Linux networking maintainers are unable to include it in the
production source of the Linux kernel 2.4.x series. Therefore the 2.4.x
series is missing some (many) extensions and also does not confirm to all
current drafts and RFCs (see [http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/
ipv6-charter.html] IP Version 6 Working Group (ipv6) Charter). This can cause
some interoperability problems with other operating systems.
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------

2.2.4. Future

[http://www.linux-ipv6.org/] USAGI is now making use of the new Linux kernel
development series 2.5.x to insert all of their current extensions into this
development release. Hopefully the 2.6.x kernel series will contain a true
and up-to-date IPv6 implementation.
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------

</sect1>	
