<sect1 id="ISDN">

<title>ISDN</title>

  <para>
  The Integrated Services Digital Network (ISDN) is a series of
  standards that specify a general purpose switched digital data
  network. An ISDN `call' creates a synchronous point to point data
  service to the destination. ISDN is generally delivered on a high
  speed link that is broken down into a number of discrete channels.
  There are two different types of channels, the `B Channels' which will
  actually carry the user data and a single channel called the `D
  channel' which is used to send control information to the ISDN
  exchange to establish calls and other functions. In Australia for
  example, ISDN may be delivered on a 2Mbps link that is broken into 30
  discrete 64kbps B channels with one 64kbps D channel. Any number of
  channels may be used at a time and in any combination. You could for
  example establish 30 separate calls to 30 different destinations at
  64kbps each, or you could establish 15 calls to 15 different
  destinations at 128kbps each (two channels used per call), or just a
  small number of calls and leave the rest idle. A channel may be used
  for either incoming or outgoing calls. The original intention of ISDN
  was to allow Telecommunications companies to provide a single data
  service which could deliver either telephone (via digitised voice) or
  data services to your home or business without requiring you to make
  any special configuration changes.
  </para>

  <para>
  There are a few different ways to connect your computer to an ISDN
  service. One way is to use a device called a `Terminal Adaptor' which
  plugs into the Network Terminating Unit that you telecommunications
  carrier will have installed when you got your ISDN service and
  presents a number of serial interfaces. One of those interfaces is
  used to enter commands to establish calls and configuration and the
  others are actually connected to the network devices that will use the
  data circuits when they are established. Linux will work in this sort
  of configuration without modification, you just treat the port on the
  Terminal Adaptor like you would treat any other serial device.
  Another way, which is the way the kernel ISDN support is designed for
  allows you to install an ISDN card into your Linux machine and then
  has your Linux software handle the protocols and make the calls
  itself.
  </para>

  <para>
  The Linux kernel has built-in ISDN capabilies. Isdn4linux controls
  ISDN PC cards and can emulate a modem with the Hayes command set ("AT"
  commands). The possibilities range from simply using a terminal
  program to connections via HDLC (using included devices) to full
  connection to the Internet with PPP to audio applications.

    FAQ for isdn4linux: http://ww.isdn4linux.de/faq/
  </para>

  <para>
  <screen>	  
  Kernel Compile Options:

               ISDN subsystem  --->
                       <*> ISDN support
                       [ ] Support synchronous PPP
                       [ ] Support audio via ISDN
                       < > ICN 2B and 4B support
                       < > PCBIT-D support
		       < > Teles/NICCY1016PC/Creatix support
  </screen>
  </para>

  <para>  
  The Linux implementation of ISDN supports a number of different types
  of internal ISDN cards. These are those listed in the kernel
  configuration options:
  </para>
  
    ICN 2B and 4B
    Octal PCBIT-D
    Teles ISDN-cards and compatibles

  <para>
  Some of these cards require software to be downloaded to them to make
  them operational. There is a separate utility to do this with.
  </para>

  <para>
  Full details on how to configure the Linux ISDN support is available
  from the /usr/src/linux/Documentation/isdn/ directory and an FAQ
  dedicated to isdn4linux is available at www.lrz-muenchen.de.  (You can
  click on the english flag to get an english version).
  </para>

  <para>
  A note about PPP. The PPP suite of protocols will operate over either
  asynchronous or synchronous serial lines. The commonly distributed PPP
  daemon for Linux `pppd' supports only asynchronous mode. If you wish
  to run the PPP protocols over your ISDN service you need a specially
  modified version. Details of where to find it are available in the
  documentation referred to above.
  </para>

</sect1>  
