<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://docbook.org/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY About-The-Author SYSTEM "About-the-Author.xml">
<!ENTITY Contributors SYSTEM "Contributors.xml">
<!ENTITY Disclaimer   SYSTEM "Disclaimer.xml">
<!ENTITY Donations SYSTEM "Donations.xml">
<!ENTITY Feedback     SYSTEM "Feedback.xml">
<!ENTITY GFDL         SYSTEM "fdl.xml">
<!ENTITY Foreward SYSTEM "Foreward.xml">
<!ENTITY var SYSTEM "var.xml">
<!ENTITY Glossary SYSTEM "Glossary.xml">
<!ENTITY Sources SYSTEM "Sources.xml">
]>

<book>

<bookinfo>
<title>Linux Networking Study Guide</title>
<subtitle>Version 0.05</subtitle>
<pubdate>2004-10-02</pubdate>

<author>
<firstname>Binh</firstname>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<affiliation>
<address>
<email>linuxfilesystem(at)yahoo(dot)com(dot)au</email>
</address>
</affiliation>
</author>

<abstract>
<para>
Nowadays people take it for granted that we exist in a world in which we are able to transfer
information and messages effortlessly and almost transparently via computers. Little thought
is given to how this is achieved. In most cases, the operating system which forms the core 
for communication on the Internet and other major computer networks are based on Unix or one 
of its variants. The reasoning behind this is mainly due to efficiency, security, and the 
tendency of people to dislike change. Hence, this document will cover the theory behind 
computer networking, as well as its use and implementation under Linux which is one of the 
more popular derivatives of Unix. It is meant to be distribution-independant and to be 
accessible to all members of the Linux community. However, a working knowledge of Linux as 
well as its CLI (Command Line Interface) is assumed. Please note that this guide is not
meant to be an all encompassing guide of networking under Linux and that little consideration
towards security is made. It was only designed to provide an overview of this subject and


For such issues please consult other pieces of documentation such
as those made available at the Linux Documentation Project,
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org"/>http://www.tldp.org</ulink>.
</para>
</abstract>

<legalnotice>
<para>Copyright 2004 Binh Nguyen</para>
<para>Trademarks are owned by their owners.</para>
<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
Version 1.2; with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts,
and with no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in
the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
</legalnotice>
</bookinfo>

<preface><title>Source and pre-formatted versions available</title>
<para>The source code and other machine readable formats
of this book can be found on the Internet at the
Linux Documentation Project home page <ulink
url="http://www.tldp.org">http://www.tldp.org</ulink>
The latest version of this document can be found at
<ulink url="http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/Linux-Networking/">
http://cvsview.tldp.org/index.cgi/LDP/guide/docbook/Linux-Networking/</ulink>
</para>
</preface>

<chapter>
<title>Linux Networking</title>

&Foreward;
&var;
</chapter>

&Glossary;
&Sources;
&About-The-Author;
&Contributors;
&Disclaimer;
&Donations;
&Feedback;
&GFDL;

</book>
