<sect1 id="Media-Types">

<title>Media-Types</title>

<para>

Media Types

Common network media include twisted pair (UTP and STP), coaxial cable, fiber-optic cable, and wireless
transmissions via infrared and radio waves. Network media are usually chosen based on several criteria:
their cost, their vulnerability to EMI and eavesdropping, their bandwidth, and the maximum distance at
which they can be used.

Unshielded Twisted Pair (UTP)

UTP is the most common type of network cable in use today. UTP consits of one or more pairs of insulated
copper wires. The wires are twisted together to reduce crosstalk, and enclosed in a plastic insulator.
UTP is the type of cable used in telephone systems.

UTP cables are generally wires using RJ-45 jacks and plugs. These are 8-conductor connectors similar to
the RJ-11 connectors used in telephone cables. UTP is inexpensive and easy to install compared with other
types of cable, although the differenet types of UTP vary in cost.

Copper wire has a high level of attenuation. YTP cable is limited to transmission distances of 100 meters
or less. UTP is more susceptible to interference (EMI) than mos types of cable, and is vaulnerable to
eavesdropping since its own emissions are not shielded.

Types of UTP cable are defined by the EIA standards, which specify the three categories of cable. Category
3 is the minimum requiredment for networking, and Category 5 is the highest-quality network cable. The UTP
categories and the bandwidth they support are summarized below.

Category	Maximum Data and Transfer Rate	Description
3		10 Mbps					Least expensive network cable, commonly used
4		16 Mbps					Medium quality; rarely used
5		100 Mbps					Highest quality

> Start Binh
5		1000Mbps					Highest Quality
> End Binh


Shielded Twisted Pair (STP)

STP cable is similar to UTP, but inclues a foil or wire mesh shield between the wire pairs and
the outer insulation. The shield is electrically grounded, and reduces emissions and
susceptibility to EMI.

STP cable is used in some Token Ting and AppleTalk networks. STP is more expensive than
UTP, and its thickness and rigidity make it more difficult to install. It also uses grounded
connection connectors, adding to the expense.

STP uses the same copper wires as UTP as the same level of attenuation, and therefore the same
maximum distance of about 100 meters. However, it is much less susceptible to EMI and eavesdropping.
The reduced inteference allows for higher bandwidth, potentially as high as 500 Mbps.

Coaxial

Coaxial Cable consists of a single thick copper wire surrounded by an insulator. A shield surrounding
the insulator is used as the second conductor, and is encased in an outer insulation. One type of
coaxial cable is that used for cable television.

The shielding cable makes coaxial cable less susceptible to EMI and emissions than UTP. The cable used
in most nteworks is either Thick Ethernet (RG-8) or Thin Ethernet (RG-58).

Thin coaxial cable is less expensive than the highest quality (Category 5) UTP, but is more difficult
to install due to its thickness, its lack of flexibility, and the connectors. The generally available types
of coaxial cable are described in the table below.

Type		Impendance		Common Cable
RG-8		50 ohms		Thick Ethernet (thicknet)
RG-11		50 ohms		Thick Ethernet (thicknet)
RG-58		50 ohms		Thin Ethernet (thinnet)
RG-59		75 ohms		Cable TV
RG-62		93 ohms		ARCnet

Fiber Optic

A fiber optic cable consists of a thin glass or clear plastic fiber encased in a protective jacket.
Signals are sent through the cable in form of light.

There are two types of fiber optic cable: single-mode, which uses a single wavelength, and multimode,
which uses multiple multiple wavelengths in the same cable.

Fiber optic cable is completely invulnerable to EMI, and has no detectable emissions, It and its
associated equipment are expensive compared to other types of cable, and the most difficult to install.
Single-mode cable is much more expensive than multimode cable.

The advantages of fiber are high bandwidth (up to 2 Gbps (gigabits per second) and extremely low
attenuation. Fiber cable can reach distances ranging from severak miles for multimode cable to
hundreds of miles for single-mode cable.

Infrared

Wireless infrared networking systems are modulated beams of infrared light
to transmit data. These types of networks require a line of sight, and are generally used for short
distances such as networks within buildings or between nearby buildings.

Infrared communications are not subject to EMI, but are vulnerable to obstructions (such as weather conditions)
and bright light, and suseceptible to eavesdropping. There are two types of infrared networks:

- Point-to-point networks use a focused beam, usually generated by a laser. They are less vulnerable
to dispersion and can theorectically be used for long distance networking, although the need for precise
alignment between receiever and transmitter and the vulneraibility to obstructions often makes it impractical.
Bandwidth can be as high as 16 Mbps.

- Broadcast networks use a less focused beam that disperses rapidly. These systems can transmit to multiple
workstations ar once, but are much more vulnerable to dispersion, limiting their useful distance and bandwidth. 
Bandwidth is usually no more than 1 Mbps.

Radio

The most common type of wireless networks use radio waves. Tdaio-based networks have
a reasonably high bandwidth, but are very sensitve to EMI and eavesdropping. Also,
many radio frequencies are regulated by the FCC and are unavailable for use without a
license. There are three types of radio links:

- Low power single frequency

This type of system is best suited for small ares, such as within a building. It uses
a lower-power transmitter on a single radio frequency. The available range is
approximately 30 meters. This is the lowest-cost method of radio networking. Bandwidth
may be as high as 10 Mbps.

- High power single frequency

This system is also uses a single frequency, but at a higher power. This allows for
a much greater range, often covering an entire metropolitan area. Bandwidth is typically
10 Mbps. The greater range makes this type of network the most vulnerable to eavesdropping.

- Spread-spectrum

These systems use multiple frequencies, primarily to avoid eavesdropping. This is done in
two ways, direct sequence modulation sends packets sequentially over several different
frequencies, while frequency hopping transmission change frequencies at scheduled intervals
known to both ends. Both of these are significantly less vulnerable less vulnerable to EMI
and snooping than other radio networks.

Microwave

Another type of wireless network communications uses microwaves, which are similar to radio
waves but at a higher frequency. Higher frequencies are less vulnerable to interference and
snooping, and can provide greater bandwidth. Two common types of microwave networks are in
use:

- Terrestial

This method provides for line-of-sight communication, usually across a short distance.
Bandwidth can be as high as 10 Mbps. Microwaves are still vulnerable to interference and
eavesropping, although not as much as conventional radio waves.

- Satellite

This method relays microwave transmissions via a satellite, allowing for a nearly global
range. The bandwidth can be as high as 10 Mbps, but the satellite relays cause delays that
may impair real-time communication. These systems are more expensive than wireless
communication.

  9.  Cables and Cabling

  Those of you handy with a soldering iron may want to build your own
  cables to interconnect two linux machines. The following cabling
  diagrams should assist you in this.

  9.1.  Serial NULL Modem cable

  Not all NULL modem cables are alike. Many null modem cables do little
  more than trick your computer into thinking all the appropriate
  signals are present and swap transmit and receive data. This is ok but
  means that you must use software flow control (XON/XOFF) which is less
  efficient than hardware flow control. The following cable provides the
  best possible signalling between machines and allows you to use
  hardware (RTS/CTS) flow control.


       Pin Name  Pin                               Pin
       Tx Data    2  -----------------------------  3
       Rx Data    3  -----------------------------  2
       RTS        4  -----------------------------  5
       CTS        5  -----------------------------  4
       Ground     7  -----------------------------  7
       DTR        20 -\---------------------------  8
       DSR        6  -/
       RLSD/DCD   8  ---------------------------/-  20
                                                \-  6



  9.2.  Parallel port cable (PLIP cable)

  If you intend to use the PLIP protocol between two machines then this
  cable will work for you irrespective of what sort of parallel ports
  you have installed.


       Pin Name    pin            pin
       STROBE      1*
       D0->ERROR   2  ----------- 15
       D1->SLCT    3  ----------- 13
       D2->PAPOUT  4  ----------- 12
       D3->ACK     5  ----------- 10
       D4->BUSY    6  ----------- 11
       D5          7*
       D6          8*
       D7          9*
       ACK->D3     10 ----------- 5
       BUSY->D4    11 ----------- 6
       PAPOUT->D2  12 ----------- 4
       SLCT->D1    13 ----------- 3
       FEED        14*
       ERROR->D0   15 ----------- 2
       INIT        16*
       SLCTIN      17*
       GROUND      25 ----------- 25



  Notes:

  ·  Do not connect the pins marked with an asterisk `*'.

  ·  Extra grounds are 18,19,20,21,22,23 and 24.

  ·  If the cable you are using has a metallic shield, it should be
     connected to the metallic DB-25 shell at one end only.

     Warning: A miswired PLIP cable can destroy your controller card. Be
     very careful and double check every connection to ensure you don't
     cause yourself any unnecessary work or heartache.

  While you may be able to run PLIP cables for long distances, you
  should avoid it if you can. The specifications for the cable allow for
  a cable length of about 1 metre or so. Please be very careful when
  running long plip cables as sources of strong electromagnetic fields
  such as lightning, power lines and radio transmitters can interfere
  with and sometimes even damage your controller. If you really want to
  connect two of your computers over a large distance you really should
  be looking at obtaining a pair of thin-net ethernet cards and running
  some coaxial cable.

  9.3.  10base2 (thin coax) Ethernet Cabling

  10base2 is an ethernet cabling standard that specifies the use of 52
  ohm coaxial cable with a diameter of about 5 millimeters. There are a
  couple of important rules to remember when interconnecting machines
  with 10base2 cabling.  The first is that you must use terminators at
  both ends of the cabling.  A terminator is a 52 ohm resistor that
  helps to ensure that the signal is absorbed and not reflected when it
  reaches the end of the cable. Without a terminator at each end of the
  cabling you may find that the ethernet is unreliable or doesn't work
  at all. Normally you'd use `T pieces' to interconnect the machines, so
  that you end up with something that looks like:
        |==========T=============T=============T==========T==========|
                   |             |             |          |
                   |             |             |          |
                 -----         -----         -----      -----
                 |   |         |   |         |   |      |   |
                 -----         -----         -----      -----



  where the `|' at either end represents a terminator, the `======' rep­
  resents a length of coaxial cable with BNC plugs at either end and the
  `T' represents a `T piece' connector. You should keep the length of
  cable between the `T piece' and the actual ethernet card in the PC as
  short as possible, ideally the `T piece' will be plugged directly into
  the ethernet card.

  9.4.  Twisted Pair Ethernet Cable

  If you have only two twisted pair ethernet cards and you wish to
  connect them you do not require a hub. You can cable the two cards
  directly together.  A diagram showing how to do this is included in
  the Ethernet-HOWTO

</sect1> 
