<sect1 id="Network-Management">

<title>Network-Management</title>

<para>
There is an impressive number of tools focused on network management
and remote administration under Linux. Some interesting remote administration
projects are linuxconf and webmin:
</para>

<para>
·  Webmin <http://www.webmin.com/webmin/>
·  Linuxconf <http://www.solucorp.qc.ca/linuxconf/>
</para>

<para>
Other tools include network traffic analysis tools, network security
tools, monitoring tools, configuration tools, etc. An archive of many
of these tools may be found at Metalab
<http://www.metalab.unc.edu/pub/Linux/system/network/>
</para>

9.2.  SNMP

<para>
The Simple Network Management Protocol is a protocol for Internet
network management services. It allows for remote monitoring and
configuration of routers, bridges, network cards, switches, etc...
There is a large amount of libraries, clients, daemons and SNMP based
monitoring programs available for Linux. A good page dealing with SNMP
and Linux software may be found at : http://linas.org/linux/NMS.html
</para>

10.  Enterprise Linux Networking

<para>
In certain situations it is necessary for the networking
infrastructure to have proper mechanisms to guarantee network
availability nearly 100% of the time. Some related techniques are
described in the following sections. Most of the following material
can be found at the excellent Linas website:
http://linas.org/linux/index.html and in the Linux High-Availability
HOWTO <http://metalab.unc.edu/pub/Linux/ALPHA/linux-ha/High-
Availability-HOWTO.html>
</para>

10.1.  High Availability

<para>
Redundancy is used to prevent the overall IT system from having single
points of failure. A server with only one network card or a single
SCSI disk has two single points of failure. The objective is to mask
unplanned outages from users in a manner that lets users continue to
work quickly. High availability software is a set of scripts and tools
that automatically monitor and detect failures, taking the appropriate
steps to restore normal operation and to notifying system
administrators.
</para>

</sect1>
