<sect1 id="Network-Management">

<title>Network-Management</title>

<para>
  9.1.  Network management applications

  There is an impressive number of tools focused on network management
  and remote administration.  Some interesting remote administration
  projects are linuxconf and webmin:

    Webmin <http://www.webmin.com/webmin/>

    Linuxconf <http://www.solucorp.qc.ca/linuxconf/>

  Other tools include network traffic analysis tools, network security
  tools, monitoring tools, configuration tools, etc. An archive of many
  of these tools may be found at Metalab
  <http://www.metalab.unc.edu/pub/Linux/system/network/>


  9.2.  SNMP

  The Simple Network Management Protocol is a protocol for Internet
  network management services. It allows for remote monitoring and
  configuration of routers, bridges, network cards, switches, etc...
  There is a large amount of libraries, clients, daemons and SNMP based
  monitoring programs available for Linux. A good page dealing with SNMP
  and Linux software may be found at : http://linas.org/linux/NMS.html

  10.  Enterprise Linux Networking

  In certain situations it is necessary for the networking
  infrastructure to have proper mechanisms to guarantee network
  availability nearly 100% of the time. Some related techniques are
  described in the following sections. Most of the following material
  can be found at the excellent Linas website:
  http://linas.org/linux/index.html and in the Linux High-Availability
  HOWTO <http://metalab.unc.edu/pub/Linux/ALPHA/linux-ha/High-
  Availability-HOWTO.html>


  10.1.  High Availability

  Redundancy is used to prevent the overall IT system from having single
  points of failure. A server with only one network card or a single
  SCSI disk has two single points of failure. The objective is to mask
  unplanned outages from users in a manner that lets users continue to
  work quickly. High availability software is a set of scripts and tools
  that automatically monitor and detect failures, taking the appropriate
  steps to restore normal operation and to notifying system
  administrators.


  10.2.  RAID

  RAID, short for Redundant Array of Inexpensive Disks, is a method
  whereby information is spread across several disks, using techniques
  such as disk striping (RAID Level 0) and disk mirroring (RAID level 1)
  to achieve redundancy, lower latency and/or higher bandwidth for
  reading and/or writing, and recoverability from hard-disk crashes.
  Over six different types of RAID configurations have been defined.
  There are three types of RAID solution options available to Linux
  users: software RAID, outboard DASD boxes, and RAID disk controllers.


    Software RAID: Pure software RAID implements the various RAID
     levels in the kernel disk (block device) code.

    Outboard DASD Solutions: DASD (Direct Access Storage Device) are
     separate boxes that come with their own power supply, provide a
     cabinet/chassis for holding the hard drives, and appear to Linux as
     just another SCSI device. In many ways, these offer the most robust
     RAID solution.

    RAID Disk Controllers: Disk Controllers are adapter cards that plug
     into the ISA/EISA/PCI bus. Just like regular disk controller cards,
     a cable attaches them to the disk drives. Unlike regular disk
     controllers, the RAID controllers will implement RAID on the card
     itself, performing all necessary operations to provide various RAID
     levels.

  Related HOWTOs:

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/mini/DPT-Hardware-RAID.html

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Root-RAID-HOWTO.html

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Software-RAID-HOWTO.html

  RAID at linas.org:

    http://linas.org/linux/raid.html


  10.3.  Redundant networking

  IP Address Takeover (IPAT). When a network adapter card fails, its IP
  address should be taken by a working network card in the same node or
  in another node. MAC Address Takeover: when an IP takeover occurs, it
  should be made sure that all the nodes in the network update their ARP
  caches (the mapping between IP and MAC addresses).

  See the High-Availability HOWTO for more details:
  http://metalab.unc.edu/pub/Linux/ALPHA/linux-ha/High-Availability-
  HOWTO.html
</para>

</sect1>  
