<sect1 id="Protocols-and-Standards">

<title>Protocols-and-Standards</title>

<para>
IEEE (Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers) 802 Standards

802.1 Internetworking
802.2 Logical Link Control (LLC)
802.3 CSMA/CD (Ethernet) media access method
802.4 Token bus media access method
802.5 Token Ring Media access method
802.6 Metropolitan Area Netwoks (MANs)
802.7 Broadband technologies
802.8 Fiber optic technologies
802.9 Hybrid (voice and data) networking
802.10 Network security
802.11 Wireless Networking
802.12 High-speed LANs
</para>

>Start 353 Notes
Protocols
So it is clear that data units can be transmitted from a sender Data-link Layer to a (peer) receiver Data-Link ayer. The data unit (DU) is encapsulated in a frame. Each frame contains additional information. The meaning of this additional information and the rules that the sender and receiver must follow when processing this information consitutue the protocol. Hence, the frame constitutes a Protocol Data Unit (PDU). To distinguish between PDU's of different layers the PDU may be referred to as a DPDU (D for Data-link).

Piggy-backing
Each PDU may or may not contain data. In the later case, the PDU is being used expressly for the purpose of the protocol, eg. for the receiver to signal that a frame was corrupted.

Sometimes a PDU used for the purpose of protocol alone is called a control message. Sending an entire PDU without any data can lead to a waste of resources. It is possible to control information in a PDU which contains data. Thisis called piggy-backing and is a commonly used technique to save resources. The drawback is that sometimes there is no data available or ready to be sent, in which case the control message may be delayed until data becomes available.

Utopia protocol
The Utopia protocol assumes that the logical-link and receiver are ideal, e. the logical-link is error free, provides unlimited capacity and the receiver can receive PDU's at any rate. With these assumptions, each DU is transmitted as soon as it is given, without any other mechanisms or support. Similarly the receiver delivers each DU as sson as it arrives without checking for errors, duplicates or out of order delivery.

Out of order delivery is possible, even if the sender sent the frames in order! One possiblity is that an entire frame is lost (never to be received) due to noise. Utopia assumes that this cannot happen.

Stop-and-Wait Protocol
Consider sending frames from a fast machine to a slow machine. What happens if the slow machine is reading the data at half the rate that the fast machine is sending it? Eventually the sent data will be lost, never to be received.

For this reason it is important to provide some kind of flow control.

The Stop-and-Wait protocol requires the receiver to send an acknowledgement PDU in return for every frame received. Such a PDU is often called an ACK. The sender will wait for the ACK before sending the next frame.

Kinds of errors
Three kinds of errors can occur:
- the bits in the frame can be inverted, anywhere within the frame including the data bits or the frame's control bits.
- additional bits can be inserted into the frame, before the frame or after the frame and
- bits can be deleted from the frame
Such errors could cause the entire frame to be deleted. Errors don't necessarily happen because of noise. Sometimes an intermediate device devides to "drop" a frame, because eg. it's buffer may be full. These kinds of errors may lead to frames being mistaken as other frames, to ACK's being lost.... even to ACK's magically appearing!

Echo checking
Clearly, error control is required. Error control can be implemented at all layers with the choice of whn, where and how being made by those who develop the layers.

At the highest layer, the use must implement menual error control, eg. by inspecting the result of a file transfer to ensure that the contents are as expected, or by seeing that the keys typed on the terminal are echoed properly onto the display. In fact, error checking is a simple form of error control. In this case, the receiver sends back (echoes) a copy of the receive data unit, for the sender to check.

Automatic Repeat Request
Echo checking is not feasible when the computer is transmitting long data unit sequences. Typically the error control involves the receiver checking the frame for possible errors (perhaps implementing some amount of error correcting) and then either:

1. sending a positive acknowledgement as a form of receipt or
2. sending a negative acknowledgement (NACK) to request another copy of the frame be sent.

This type of error control is known as automatic repeat request (ARQ). ARQ is used in two ways:
- idle RQ and
- continuous RQ.
In either case, the use of ACK's, NACK's or both is implementation dependent and this can lead to a variety of protocols which differ slightly in their specification/operation. The continuous RQ typically uses one of the following transmission strategies:
- selective repeat or
- go-back-N

Sequence numbers
For all the ARQ error control methods, it is necessary to distinguish between different frames. The principle reason is so that duplicate frames can be avoided and to ensure that all frames are eventually received.

Furthermore, because the sequence number must be recorded as part of the frame it will occupy some number of bytes. For frames with fixed formats, the maximum size of the sequence number is also fiexed. So eg. the sequence number may be designated as 1 bit, 2 bits, 8 bits, etc....

Although a fixed suze sequence number may suggest that only a fixed number of frames can be transmitted, as will be found when examining the protocols, distinguishing each frame from every frame is not necessary and in some caes it is quite possible to have a 1-bit sequence number.

Timers
A timer provides an event after a given time interval. Timers are used to trigger protocol state transitions. Eg. recall the stop-and-wait protocol as previously described. If the ACK is lost then the sender will wait indefinitely. In this case, a timer may be used to trigger the protocol in the extendede absence of an ACK.

Idle RQ
The stop-and-wait protocol given earlier is an incomplete form of idle RQ. The basic RQ uses a timer at the sender and either ACK's only (implicit retransmission) or a combination of ACK's and NACK's (explicit retransmission).

When sending a frame, F(n), the sender starts a timer. The sender waits to receive either an ACK(n) or a NACK(n). If nothing is recieved before the timer expires then the timer is reset and F(n) is retransmitted (implicit). If ACK(n) is received then the sender repeats the process F(n+1). If NACK(n) is received before the timer expires then the sender resets the timer and retransmits F(n) (explicit).

Using a NACK
See that the NACK is used when receiving a corrupted frame and signals the sender to stop the timer and send F(n) immediately. Intuitively this decreases the amount of time wasted, and so increases the link utlization.

Link utilization
Clearly, the use of a NACK increases the use of the link. To quantify this requires first examining the basic link utilization of idle RQ.

See Page 48.

Idle RQ and sequence numbers
Clearly, the sequence numbers for idle RQ may be 1 bit. For example, the sender transmits frame F(0) and does not transmit frame F(1) until F(0) has been acknowledged. At any one time, there is only a single frame in question. The two sequence numbers are required in case that the ACK(0) is lost - the sender times out and resends F(0), however the receiver is now waiting for F(1) and can reject F(0).

In this way, the sender has to buffer only one frame, and the receiver has to record only the sequence number of the frame that was previously received.

Because of this, idle RQ does not require much buffer space and is therefore used when simple devices are communicating, such as between a terminal and a display.

Continuous RQ
In previous slide the idle RQ protocol was shown to provide poor link utilization when the time to transmit a frame was significantly less than the propogatio delay.

A number of physical layer services provide links with significantly long propogation delays, such as satellite communication and high bandwidth Ethernet.

Continuous RQ allows the sender to continue to transmit frames, even though no ACK's may have been received for previously transmitted frames.

Sliding windows
Continuous RQ may require buffering at both the sender and the receiver (as well as seen) and, with finite buffers, it is necessary to ensure that neither the sender's not the receiver's buffer becomes over loaded. A sliding window is a flow control which is used to maintain finite buffers at the sender and receiver.

There are numerous methods of implementing a sliding window. However this subject will introduce and use only one method.

Parameters for a sliding window
Each sliding window uses three parameters:
1. the size of the window K,
2. the lower window edge LWE and
3. the upper window edge UWE.
Normally, K remains as a constant while LWE and UWE vary as frames are transmitted and acknowledged. Both the sender and receiver have their own set of parameters and their own interpretations.

Sequence numbers and window size
The size of the sequence number and the window size are related and the relationship depends on the protocol.

Consider the idle RQ from previous slides. Idle RQ uses 1-bit sequence number which gives two different frame identifiers {0,1}. However the window size is K=1 at both the sender and receiver. The reason for this will be explained during go-back-N protocol (idle RQ is a simplified go-back-N). For now, examine the next slide to see how sequence numbers and sliding windows relate.

Go-back-N protocol
With an understanding of sequence numbers and sliding window it is possible to quickly understand the Go-back-N protocol.

The sender uses a window size of K. The receiver uses a window size of 1.

The receiver sends an ACK for each frame as it is received. If a corrupted frame as it is received. If a corrupted frame, F(n), is received or F(n) is missing (didn't arrive) then the receiver sends a special NACK(n) to request that the sender start restransmitting from frame F(n).

Selective repeat protocol
Selective repeat uses a window size of K at both the sender and receiver.

The protocol can be implemented in one of two ways: either the receiver sends only ACK's and the sender implicitly retransmits NACK's to explicity request a frame retransmission.

The seder buffers out-of-order frames until the missing frames are retransmitted.

As the name suggests, the receiver can "selectively" request retransmission of a frame.

When using ACK's only, the absence of an ACK triggers a retransmission.

When using ACK's only, if an ACK is lost, then a retransmission is triggered, but the retransmission frame is discarded. If NACK's are used, then the NACK explicity triggers a retransmission.

Explicit and implicit strategies
Explicit retransmission strategy uses NACK's. Implicit retransmission strategy does not use NACK's.

For explicit retransmission strategy an ACK(n) is sufficient to acknowledge all frames prior to and including F(n).

For implicit retransmission strategy an ACK(n) does not acknowledge all frames prior to F(n). The reason for this is that the strategy relies on the receiver detecting a missing ACK as the trigger for a retransmission.

Sequence numbers and K for selective repeat

Duplex protocols and lnks
So far we have discussed the operation of protocols that have data being transmitted from a sender to a receiver, called simplex protocols. In most cases these protocols required that some PDU's be sent back to the receiver.

Many links allow for data to be sent in both directions simultaneously. Indeed, a single medium may be divided logically into a send and receive channel using FSM. Such links are called duplex links and the protocols that allow data to flow in both directions simultaneously are duplex protocols.

In contrast, recall the primitive stop-and-wait protocol. At any other time, the link was being used to either send a frame or to receive ackowledgement. In this case it is sufficient for the link to be half-duplex. Duplex protocols can operate over a half-duplex link but with less efficiency.

The concepts are studied further when considering the medium access control sub-layer.

Protocol efficiency
The concept of link utilization does not consider the amount of data actually sent is less than the length of the frame. The protocol efficiency refers to the fraction of total data transmitted that represents the DU's themselves. This value is always less than 1 because each frame contains additional protocol information such as CRC and sequence number.

The link efficiency is further reduced to obtain the protocol efficiency. If the length of the DU is D and the length of the frame is L, then only D/L of the utilized link is actually used to transmit DU's.

Medium Access Control

The protocols given in the previous lectures assumed that the sender had a direct link to the receiver , and also that the link provided duplex communication, ie. so that frames could be sent at the same time that ACK's were being received. Recall that the repeater is a simple Layer 1 device that, any number of repeaters may exist between two data-link layer peers, transparently to the communication.

Also recall that the hub is a general repeater.

Frames from any of the data-link layers will be transmitted to every other data-link layer.

The use of a hub introduces new problems for the protocols because a transmitted frame will potentialy be received by a number of different data-link layers.

So each device needs an address. The address is called the medium access control (MAC) address - it is a unique identifier for every device connected to the shared medium.


The MAC sub-layer

To handle issues of MAC addressing, and other issues to do with avoiding collision of frames transmitted by two or more Layer 2 devices, the Layer 2 is broken into a MAC sub-layer and a Logical Link Contrl (LLC) sub-layer.

The protocols discussed so far are those implmented by the LLC sub-layer. The MAC sub-layer abstracts the complexity of medium access from the LLC sub-layer.

Channels
Recall that the Physical Layer is responsible for transmitting a bit stream on the transmission medium. The Physical Layer may share several bit streams over the one transmission medium using either TDM or FDM. In this way the transmission medium has been divided into a number of channels. For a prticular (shared) tranmission medium, each MAC sub-layer has access to the same set of channels. The problem for the MAC sub-layer is to decide how a particular channel will be shared.

MAC sub-layer protocols

What protocol can the MAC sub-layers implement to ensure that channels are used efficiently? (read Section 4.1 and 4.2 of your textbook)

You will see that the protocol of choice is one which takes into consideration the types of channels and also factors such as the propogation delay, frame length, error rate and the frame rate or load.

Classifying MAC protocols

There are two kinds of MAC protocols:

contention protocols: these protocols allow the possiblity of frames colliding.

contention-less protocols: these protocols don't allow the possibliity of frames colliding.

The choice of a contention or contention-less protocol is mainly made on the basis of the transmission medium. In other words different MAC sub-layer protocols have been developed according to the type of Physical Layer.

Logical Token Bus

Logical Token Bus is a contention-less protocol. With this protocol the MAC sub-layers pass around a token and only the MAC sub-layer with the token can use the channel. When a particular MAC sub-layer has finished sending a frame, it sends the token to the next MAC sub-layer, and so on. If a MAC sub-layer has no frame to transmit then it simply passes the token to the next MAC sub-layer. Clearly the protocol can be applied for both half duplex and full duplex channels.

CSMA

To overcome the low efficiency of the Logical Token Bus protocol the Carrier Sense Multiple Access (CSMA) protocol can be used. In this case devices are allowed to transmit a frame at any time (multiple access). However, each device will not transmit a frame if they are receiving a frame (carrier sense).

For the case of persistent CSMA, if a device detects that a frame is being recieved it will send its own frame immediately after the frame has been received. The the case of non-persistent CSMA the device will wait for some random period before transmitting .

Collisions can occur so this protocol is a contention protocol. If collision detection (CD) is used then colliding frames can be aborted.

ALOHA

ALOHA is a contention protocol and is used when carrier sense is not available. Mainly this i for satellite communication. The protocol allows devices to transmit at any time. Read your textbook to see the analysis of ALOHA for the case when slotted and unslotted ALOHA is used.

>End 353 Notes

  3.8.  Amateur Radio

  The Linux kernel has built-in support for amateur radio protocols.

  Especially interesting is the AX.25 support. The AX.25 protocol offers
  both connected and connectionless modes of operation, and is used
  either by itself for point-point links, or to carry other protocols
  such as TCP/IP and NetRom.

  It is similar to X.25 level 2 in structure, with some extensions to
  make it more useful in the amateur radio environment.

  ·  Amateur radio on Linux web site <http://radio.linux.org.au/>

</sect1>
