<sect1 id="Samba">

  8.11.  SAMBA - `NetBEUI', `NetBios', `CIFS' support.

  SAMBA is an implementation of the Session Management Block protocol.
  Samba allows Microsoft and other systems to mount and use your disks
  and printers.

  SAMBA and its configuration are covered in detail in the SMB-HOWTO.

  5.2.  Windows Environment

  Samba is a suite of applications that allow most Unices (and in
  particular Linux) to integrate into a Microsoft network both as a
  client and a server. Acting as a server it allows Windows 95, Windows
  for Workgroups, DOS and Windows NT clients to access Linux files and
  printing services. It can completely replace Windows NT for file and
  printing services, including the automatic downloading of printer
  drivers to clients. Acting as a client allows the Linux workstation to
  mount locally exported windows file shares.

  According to the SAMBA Meta-FAQ:



       "Many users report that compared to other SMB implementations Samba is more stable,
       faster, and compatible with more clients. Administrators of some large installations say
       that Samba is the only SMB server available which will scale to many tens of thousands
       of users without crashing"

  ·  Samba project home page <http://samba.anu.edu.au/samba/>

  ·  SMB HOWTO <http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/SMB-HOWTO.html>

  ·  Printing HOWTO <http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Printing-
     HOWTO.html>
	
<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Samba
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A free software implementation of the server message block (SMB) network file sharing protocol. Samba is usually implemented on networks that have a mixture of UNIX, Linux, and Windows computers and is designed for interoperable file sharing. From Redhat-9-Glossary
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
samba
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A LanManager like file and printer server for Unix. The Samba software suite is a collection of programs that implements the SMB protocol for unix systems, allowing you to serve files and printers to Windows, NT, OS/2 and DOS clients. This protocol is sometimes also referred to as the LanManager or NetBIOS protocol. This package contains all the components necessary to turn your Debian GNU/Linux box into a powerful file and printer server. Currently, the Samba Debian packages consist of the following:  samba - A LanManager like file and printer server for Unix.  samba-common - Samba common files used by both the server and the client.  smbclient - A LanManager like simple client for Unix.  swat - Samba Web Administration Tool  samba-doc - Samba documentation.  smbfs - Mount and umount commands for the smbfs (kernels 2.0.x and above).  libpam-smbpass - pluggable authentication module for SMB password database  libsmbclient - Shared library that allows applications to talk to SMB servers  libsmbclient-dev - libsmbclient shared libraries  winbind: Service to resolve user and group information from Windows NT servers It is possible to install a subset of these packages depending on your particular needs. For example, to access other SMB servers you should only need the smbclient and samba-common packages. From Debian 3.0r0 APT
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Samba
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
A lot of emphasis has been placed on peaceful coexistence between UNIX and Windows. Unfortunately, the two systems come from very different cultures and they have difficulty getting along without  mediation. ...and that, of course, is Samba&apos;s job. Samba &lt;http://samba.org/&gt; runs on UNIX platforms, but speaks to Windows clients like a native. It allows a UNIX system to move into a Windows ``Network Neighborhood&apos;&apos; without causing a stir. Windows users can happily access file and print services without knowing or caring that those services are being offered by a UNIX host. All of this is managed through a protocol suite which is currently known as the ``Common Internet File System,&apos;&apos; or CIFS &lt;http://www.cifs.com&gt;. This name was introduced by Microsoft, and provides some insight into their hopes for the future. At the heart of CIFS is the latest incarnation of the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol, which has a long and tedious history. Samba is an open source CIFS implementation, and is available for free from the http://samba.org/ mirror sites. Samba and Windows are not the only ones to provide CIFS networking. OS/2 supports SMB file and print sharing, and there are commercial CIFS products for Macintosh and other platforms (including several others for UNIX). Samba has been ported to a variety of non-UNIX operating systems, including VMS, AmigaOS, and NetWare. CIFS is also supported on dedicated file server platforms from a variety of vendors. In other words, this stuff is all over the place. From Rute-Users-Guide
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Samba
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
a suite of programs which work together to allow clients to access to a server&apos;s filespace and printers via the SMB (Session Message Block) protocol. This means that you can redirect disks and printers to Unix disks and printers from Lan Manager clients, Windows for Workgroups 3.11 clients, Windows NT clients, Linux clients and OS/2 clients. From Linux Guide @FirstLinux
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
Samba
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Samba adds Windows-networking support to UNIX. Whereas NFS is the most popular protocol for sharing files among UNIX machines, SMB is the most popular protocol for sharing files among Windows machines. The Samba package adds the ability for UNIX systems to interact with Windows systems. Key point: The Samba package comprises the following: smbd The Samba service allowing other machines (often Windows) to read files from a UNIX machine. nmbd Provides support for NetBIOS. Logically, the SMB protocol is layered on top of NetBIOS, which is in turn layered on top of TCP/IP. smbmount An extension to the mount program that allows a UNIX machine to connect to another machine implicitly. Files can be accessed as if they were located on the local machines. smbclient Allows files to be access through SMB in an explicity manner. This is a command-line tool much like the FTP tool that allows files to be copied. Unlike smbmount, files cannot be accessed as if they were local. smb.conf The configuration file for Samba. From Hacking-Lexicon
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
samba-client
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Samba-client provides some SMB clients, which complement the built-in SMB filesystem in Linux. These allow the accessing of SMB shares, and printing to SMB printers. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry>
<glossterm>
samba-server
</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<para>
Samba-server provides a SMB server which can be used to provide network services to SMB (sometimes called &quot;Lan Manager&quot;) clients. Samba uses NetBIOS over TCP/IP (NetBT) protocols and does NOT need NetBEUI (Microsoft Raw NetBIOS frame) protocol. Samba-2.2 features working NT Domain Control capability andincludes the SWAT (Samba Web Administration Tool) that allows samba&apos;s smb.conf file to be remotely managed using your favourite web browser. For the time being this is being enabled on TCP port 901 via xinetd. SWAT is now included init&apos;s own subpackage, samba-swat. Users are advised to use Samba-2.2 as a Windows NT4 Domain Controller only on networks that do NOT have a WindowsNT Domain Controller. This release does NOT as yet have Backup Domain control ability. Please refer to the WHATSNEW.txt document for fixup information. This binary release includes encrypted password support. Please read the smb.conf file and ENCRYPTION.txt in the docs directory for implementation details. From Mandrake 9.0 RPM
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html">http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Linux-Dictionary/html/index.html</ulink>
</para>
</glossdef>
</glossentry>

	
> From Samba Authenticated Gateway HOWTO
  Samba Authenticated Gateway HOWTO
  Ricardo Alexandre Mattar
  v1.2, 2004-05-21

  This documents intends to show how to build a Firewall/Gateway with
  rules set on user basis having the users authenticated by a Samba Pri­
  mary Domain Controller

  1.  Introduction

  As you can see by the poorness of my language, English is not my
  native language. I am writing this document in English for the sake of
  the Linux community. So, please, excuse me for my poor English.  And,
  please, if you speak Portuguese, address me in this language.


  This document intends to enlighten you (and myself) in the process of
  building a Linux Gateway or Firewall, which modify rules on demand
  when users log in or out from their Windows workstations.


  I should be writing an application, but I am too lazy. Hopefully when
  the idea is out there, people will build a few intelligently
  integrated packages. Meanwhile...


  In this document, I will try to show how to build a gateway to NAT or
  MASQUERADE Windows workstations. Use your imagination to modify it to
  get any level of network management. You may use it to grant or deny
  access to services, servers or entire subnetworks on your network.


  Imagine that you have to build a gateway to let Windows workstation
  access the Internet and that you need to authenticate each user before
  letting them access the external networks. The first solution you
  think about is Squid. It's indeed a great solution, when http and ftp
  access is enough for your users. When it comes to let them access
  other services like pop, smtp, ssh, a database server or whatever
  else, you immediately think about NAT or MASQUERADE. But what happens
  to the user authentication?


  Well, this is my solution. It gives you user authentication and fine
  grain control over their access to the external networks.


  1.1.  Overview

  We know that SAMBA can act as a Domain Controller and so it can
  authenticate users on Windows boxes. As a PDC, SAMBA can push netlogon
  scripts to the Windows workstations. We can use this netlogon scripts
  to force the Windows workstations mounting a given share from our
  Linux PDC. This "forced" share shall have preexec and postexec scripts
  which shall be triggered when the user logs in or out. There is a
  program named smbstatus which lists the shares being used, giving us
  also the username and ip address of the workstation. We just need to
  grep this information from smbstatus output and update our firewall
  rules.


  1.2.  Disclaimer

  No liability for the contents of this document can be accepted.  Use
  the concepts, examples and other content at your own risk. As this is
  a new edition of this document, there may be errors and inaccuracies,
  that may of course be damaging to your system. Proceed with caution,
  and although this is highly unlikely, the author(s) do not take any
  responsibility for that.


  All copyrights are held by their respective owners, unless
  specifically noted otherwise. Use of a term in this document should
  not be regarded as affecting the validity of any trademark or service
  mark.


  Naming of particular products or brands should not be seen as
  endorsements.


  1.3.  New versions

  The newest release of this document can be found at http://ram.eti.br
  <http://ram.eti.br> or at http://www.tldp.org <http://www.tldp.org>


  Related HOWTOs can be found at the Linux Documentation Project
  homepage at http://tldp.org <http://tldp.org>.


  1.4.  Translations

  A Portuguese version is available.


  A French translation by Guillaume Lelarge is available
  athttp://www.traduc.org
  <http://www.traduc.org/docs/HOWTO/lecture/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-
  HOWTO.html>


  A Hungarian translation is available at http://tldp.fsf.hu
  <http://tldp.fsf.hu/HOWTO/Samba-Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO-hu/Samba-
  Authenticated-Gateway-HOWTO-hu.html>


  If you want to contribute with a translation, please do.


  1.5.  Feedback

  Contributions and criticism are both welcome.


  Corrections to my English are also very welcome!


  If you find any bugs in the scripts included, please tell me.


  You can find me at ricardo@ram.eti.br or at ricardo.mattar@bol.com.br


  1.6.  Copyright and trademarks

  Copyright (c) 2002-2003 Ricardo Alexandre Mattar


  Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
  under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or
  any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
  Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
  copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free
  Documentation License".


  1.7.  Acknowledgments and Thanks

  Thanks to Carlos Alberto Reis Ribeiro for introducing me to Linux.


  Thanks to Cesar Bremer Pinheiro for motivating me to write this
  document.


  Thanks to Guillaume Lelarge for the (continuous) help with the
  revision.


  Thanks to Erik Esplund for further language corrections.


  Thanks to Albert Teixidó for code improvements.


  Thanks to Felipe Cordeiro Caetano for helping on my main testing site.


  Thanks to the secure communications company RASEAC
  <http://www.raseac.com.br> for sponsoring my work.


  2.  Requirements

  2.1.  Knowledge

  This document is target at the seasoned systems administrator.


  You must have a fair knowledge about (at least know what these are):



  ·  TCP/IP;

  ·  Linux netfilter;

  ·  A scripting language (bash?);

  ·  SAMBA and Windows networking and domain controllers;

  Fortunately, there is plenty of documentation on these topics on the
  Internet.


  2.2.  Software

  Installed on your server, you will need at least:



  ·  Samba;

  ·  Iptables;

  ·  A scripting language;


  3.  Linux box setup

  This Howto assumes you have a kernel from the 2.4 series as it uses
  iptables. Other than that, there are no known issues why this should
  not work on a 2.2 kernel box with the scripts adapted to ipchains.


  Of course, you need to install the iptables userland tools, an apache
  http server if you want to run a CGI tool to change passwords and
  SAMBA. And you will need a kernel compiled with iptables modules.


  You may wish to use DHCP. If so, it is easy to set up. Remember to
  configure the dhcp server to give the nameserver IP address and the
  gateway IP address as well. The Windows machines will make good use of
  this information.


  3.1.  Basic system setup

  Generally any basic system setup from the common Linux distributions
  will fit in this gateway example. Just check if you have Samba and
  IPTABLES.


  3.2.  Additional directory hierarchy

  The additional directory hierarchy will be required to accomplish the
  example of this howto:


  This is used to keep track of the users and IP addresses:



  /var/run/smbgate/



  This is where I place user specific scripts:



  /etc/smbgate/users/



  And group specific scripts:



  /etc/smbgate/groups/



  Directory for the netlogon share:



  /home/samba/netlogon/



  Directory for the tracking share:


  /home/samba/samba/



  These hierarchies are required by some of the scripts and daemons of
  the example.


  3.3.  Firewall setup

  Its very unlikely that your distribution's kernel won't be compiled
  with Iptables and the userland tools won't be installed either.
  Anyway, if you don't have it, refer to http://www.netfilter.org
  <http://www.netfilter.org> or http://www.iptables.org
  <http://www.iptables.org> to get the software and the documentation.


  You will need a basic firewall setup in order to get the gateway
  working. Take a look at the iptables tutorial at IPTABLES TUTORIAL
  <http://www.netfilter.org/documentation/tutorials/blueflux/iptables-
  tutorial.html>. It's an interesting reading. Anyway, if you have no
  time to spend, the following code is somewhat (very) loose but it may
  fit your needs:



  #!/bin/sh
  IPTABLES=/usr/sbin/iptables
  /sbin/depmod -a
  /sbin/insmod ip_tables
  /sbin/insmod ip_conntrack
  /sbin/insmod ip_conntrack_ftp
  /sbin/insmod ip_conntrack_irc
  /sbin/insmod iptable_nat
  /sbin/insmod ip_nat_ftp
  echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
  echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_dynaddr
  $IPTABLES -P INPUT ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -F INPUT
  $IPTABLES -P OUTPUT ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -F OUTPUT
  $IPTABLES -P FORWARD ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -F FORWARD
  $IPTABLES -t nat -F



  You will notice that this code actually does nothing, but load the
  kernel modules related to nat and firewalling and turns the packet
  routing on. You can (and should) place any rules there to give your
  gateway a standard behavior, but the big magic will be done by scripts
  called by the SAMBA daemon.


  Please, remember that this code doesn't have the least bit of
  security! Don't use these examples in production environments. This
  example intends only to be educational. You have to add a firewall
  configuration that suits your systems.


  You have been warned!



  3.4.  SAMBA setup

  Check if you have Samba installed. If your distribution doesn't come
  with Samba pre-packaged then refer to http://www.samba.org
  <http://www.samba.org> to get the packages and for documentation on
  how to install Samba. Brows around their web site and learn about it.
  The site has plenty of documentation and maybe your LINUX distribution
  also has plenty of SAMBA documentation.


  We will need to setup SAMBA as a Primary Domain Controller. I will
  give an example configuration file here, but you should read the Samba
  HOWTO Collection <http://www.samba.org/samba/docs/man/Samba-HOWTO-
  Collection.html> and learn all you can about a PDC.


  3.4.1.  Basic SAMBA setup.

  Since I do not intend to rewrite the SAMBA documentation, here goes a
  sample smb.conf file:



  # Global parameters
  [global]
  workgroup = DOMAIN
  netbios name = LINUX
  server string = Linux PDC
  encrypt passwords = Yes
  map to guest = Bad Password
  passwd program = /usr/bin/passwd
  unix password sync = Yes
  max log size = 50
  time server = Yes
  socket options = TCP_NODELAY SO_RCVBUF=8192 SO_SNDBUF=8192
  add user script = /usr/sbin/useradd -d /dev/null -g 100 -s /bin/false -M %u
  logon script = netlogon.bat
  domain logons = Yes
  os level = 64
  lm announce = True
  preferred master = True
  domain master = True
  dns proxy = No
  printing = lprng
  [homes]
  comment = Home Directories
  path = /home/%u
  read only = No
  [printers]
  comment = All Printers
  path = /var/spool/samba
  printable = Yes
  browseable = No
  available = No
  [netlogon]
  comment = NetLogon ShARE
  path = /home/samba/netlogon
  guest account =
  [samba]
  comment = login tracking share
  path = /home/samba/samba
  browseable = No
  root preexec = /usr/local/bin/netlogon.sh %u %I
  root postexec = /usr/local/bin/netlogoff.sh %u


  You will have to do with it or read the SAMBA documentation if you
  really want to control your server and network.


  3.4.2.  The netlogon and the tracking shares

  The netlogon share is where the Windows workstations download the
  logon script from. We need this share in order to place there a logon
  script, which will tell the workstation to mount a share that will be
  used to track the users ip addresses.


  As you can see, there must be a line like the following in your
  smb.conf



  logon script = netlogon.bat



  This line will tell your Windows client to download and execute the
  script named netlogon.bat. This script must be placed at the netlogon
  share. So, we will also need a netlogon.bat script to your Windows
  workstations. You can use the following example and place it at the
  netlogon share, in this case: /home/samba/netlogon/NETLOGON.BAT.



  REM NETLOGON.BAT
  net use z: \\linux\samba /yes



  This script will tell the Windows workstation to mount the specified
  share, and so we will be able to keep track of the user and
  workstation through the output of the smbstatus program.


  Quite simple! But not enough...


  As you could see, we will need also a tracking share which, in this
  example, I named samba. You can see the tracking share configuration
  in smb.conf:



  [samba]
  comment = login tracking share
  path = /home/samba/samba
  browseable = No
  root preexec = /usr/local/bin/netlogon.sh %u %I
  root postexec = /usr/local/bin/netlogoff.sh %u



  As you can guess or know if you read the SAMBA documentation, the root
  preexec and the root postexec lines tell SAMBA to run the indicated
  scripts when a user mounts or unmounts the share. In this case, we are
  passing the username to the script as a parameter. Note the %u at the
  end of the lines. These scripts are the beasts which will call a
  script or program to modify our gateway's packet filtering rules.



  Note that the netlogon.sh script must check if the refered workstation
  has already mounted the tracking share.


  Take a look at the netlogon.sh and netlogoff.sh scripts:



  #!/bin/sh
  #
  # netlogon.sh
  #
  # usage:
  # netlogon.sh <username>
  #
  if [ -f /var/run/smbgate/$1 ] ; then
      exit 0
  fi
  echo $2 > /var/run/smbgate/$1
  IPTABLES='/usr/sbin/iptables'
  EXTIF='eth0'
  COMMAND='-A'
  ADDRESS=`cat /var/run/smbgate/$1`
  GROUP=`groups $1 | gawk '// { print $3 }'`
  if [ -f /etc/smbgate/users/$1 ] ; then
      /etc/smbgate/users/$1 $COMMAND $ADDRESS $EXTIF
  else
      if [ -f /etc/smbgate/groups/$GROUP ] ; then
          /etc/smbgate/groups/$GROUP $COMMAND $ADDRESS $EXTIF
      else
          /etc/smbgate/users/default.sh $COMMAND $ADDRESS $EXTIF
      fi
  fi



  This script (netlogon.sh) is intended to run when the user logs in and
  will select the which scripts will be executed based on the user name
  and to which group the user belongs. The user's ip address will be
  written to a file at /var/run/smbgate for tracking purposes.  The file
  will take the user's name and will be later used when the user log
  off. The IP address will be passed as an argument to a script with the
  users' name which will finally update the firewall.


  Notice that this netlogon.sh script tries a user script, then if it
  can't find the user script it tries a group script, and finally if it
  can't find the group script it tries the default.sh script.  You can
  modify this logic and behavior as you wish and need, just remember to
  modify the others accordingly.


  Chances are if the user belong to more than one that these scripts
  will fail. I did not have time to write a better code.



  #!/bin/sh
  #
  # netlogoff.sh
  #
  # usage:
  # netlogoff.sh <username>
  #
  IPTABLES='/usr/sbin/iptables'
  EXTIF='ppp0'
  COMMAND='-D'
  ADDRESS=`cat /var/run/smbgate/$1`
  GROUP=`groups $1 | gawk '// { print $3 }'`
  if [ -f /etc/smbgate/users/$1 ] ; then
      /etc/smbgate/users/$1 $COMMAND $ADDRESS $EXTIF
  else
      if [ -f /etc/smbgate/groups/$GROUP ] ; then
          /etc/smbgate/groups/$GROUP $COMMAND $ADDRESS $EXTIF
      else
          /etc/smbgate/users/default.sh $COMMAND $ADDRESS $EXTIF
      fi
  fi
  rm -f /var/run/smbgate/$1



  This script (netlogoff.sh) is intended to run when the user logs off
  and will get the address from the /var/run/smbgate/user file which
  will be passed as an argument to the /etc/smbgate/users/user script
  which will update the firewall to the state desired when the user is
  not logged in.


  Some versions of Windows, such as Windows 2000, mount the tracking
  share more than once per login. This may cause problems with the
  netlogon.sh and netlogoff.sh, triggering the scripts more the once.
  This can make a real mess. So, you may prefer to use a logout checking
  script at cron instead of a netlogoff.sh script triggered by SAMBA.
  Here is an example:



  #!/bin/sh
  # checklogout.sh
  #
  # usage:
  # intended to run at cron (maybe each 10 minutes)

  TRACKDIR="/var/run/smbgate"
  DIRLENGTH=${#TRACKDIR}
  TRACKSHARE="samba"
  EXTIF='eth0'
  COMMAND='-D'
  if [ -d $TRACKDIR ]; then
    for n in $TRACKDIR/*; do
      [ -d $n ] && continue;
      if [ -f $n ] ; then
        IPADDRESS=`cat $n`
        USERNAME=${n:$DIRLENGTH+1}
        NMS=`smbstatus -u $USERNAME | grep $TRACKSHARE | grep $IPADDRESS | grep -v grep | wc -l`
        if [ $NMS == 0 ] ; then
          rm -f $n
          GROUP=`groups $USERNAME | gawk '// { print $3 }'`
          if [ -f /etc/smbgate/users/$USERNAME ] ; then
            /etc/smbgate/users/$USERNAME $COMMAND $IPADDRESS $EXTIF
          else
            if [ -f /etc/smbgate/groups/$GROUP ] ; then
              /etc/smbgate/groups/$GROUP $COMMAND $IPADDRESS $EXTIF
            else
              /etc/smbgate/users/default.sh $COMMAND $IPADDRESS $EXTIF
            fi
          fi
        fi
      else
        exit 0
      fi
    done
  fi



  In that case you should remove the root postexec clause from the
  tracking share on smb.conf:



  root postexec = /usr/local/bin/netlogoff.sh %u



  The following is a standard /etc/smbgate/users/user script. This is
  the one which will actually modify the firewall rules.



  #!/bin/sh
  #
  COMMAND=$1
  ADDRESS=$2
  EXTIF=$3
  IPTABLES='/usr/sbin/iptables'
  $IPTABLES $COMMAND POSTROUTING -t nat -s $ADDRESS -o $EXTIF -j MASQUERADE



  We should also hase a default.sh script at /etc/smbgate/users/ to give
  the gateway a default behavior.

  #!/bin/sh
  #
  # default.sh
  COMMAND=$1
  ADDRESS=$2
  EXTIF=$3
  IPTABLES='/usr/sbin/iptables'
  #$IPTABLES $COMMAND POSTROUTING -t nat -s $ADDRESS -o $EXTIF -j MASQUERADE
  exit 0



  4.  SSH setup

  You may want to run your PDC on one box and have another box as a
  managed gateway for any reason. If so you must setup your gateway to
  accept rsa authenticated logins without passwords from the PDC.


  Take a look at www.openssh.org <http://www.openssh.org/manual.html>
  for information on how to properly setup your ssh server and client
  for this.


  4.1.  Important

  You should read the ssh documentation and make shure that you fully
  understand what you are doing when you setup rsa or any other kind of
  cryptographic authentication.


  If security isn't an issue, just use my example and go on.


  4.2.  Key pair generation

  To create a key pair issue the following commands on the manchine
  meant to be the PDC:



  pdc:~# ssh-keygen -t rsa



  Answer the questions and copy the resulting public key to the gateway
  it self. Usually the public key goes to "~.ssh/id_rsa.pub"



  pdc:~# cd .ssh
  pdc:~# scp id_rsa.pub root@gateway:/root/.ssh/authorized_keys2



  4.3.  SSH enabled logon script

  The following is a standard /etc/smbgate/users/user script modified to
  use the ssh cryptographic authentication.



  #!/bin/sh
  #
  COMMAND=$1
  ADDRESS=$2
  EXTIF=$3
  IPTABLES='/sbin/iptables'
  ssh root@gateway $IPTABLES $COMMAND POSTROUTING -t nat -s $ADDRESS -o $EXTIF -j MASQUERADE



  Note that the iptables binary in called through ssh at the "gateway".
  Again, make sure that you read the ssh server documentation.


  5.  Windows workstation setup

  5.1.  Introduction

  We will stick to setting up the network, user management and policies
  on the Windows workstations.


  I will not go through all those steps, naming each dialog box.  I will
  presume that if you can read and understand this document you can find
  your way through that mess.


  5.2.  Network protocols

  First, unless you really need, remove all network protocols but
  TCP/IP. Even without their own protocol, Windows machines like to
  broadcast a lot, and this doesn't please anyone. Anyway, with TCP/IP
  who needs anything else?


  5.3.  DHCP setup

  If you setup a DHCP server on your Linux box, remember that Windows
  workstations can get the nameservers and gateway's address besides its
  own IP address from it. So, you don't need to set all these items on
  each workstation.


  5.4.  Join your Linux server domain

  Configure the Windows workstation to log in a Domain, and give the
  domain name of your Linux server. This is essential to the gateway
  work.


  You must know that in order to join some versions of Windows to a
  SAMBA domain controller, you must create machine accounts in your
  Linux PDC. Check the SAMBA documentation on how to setup your PDC to
  the specific version of Windows which you have.


  5.4.1.  Windows 95/98

  These versions seems to need no special configuration to join the
  Linux PDC domain.


  5.4.2.  Windows NT and 2000

  These versions require machine accounts at the Linux box. Again, check
  the SAMBA documentation.
  5.4.3.  Windows XP

  This version needs a machine account at the Linux box and a tweak at
  the registry, as follows.


  Locate the key
  "HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\Netlogon\Parameters\RequireSignOrSeal".
  The default value is 1. Set it to 0 and it will no more complain about
  joining the domain.


  If you have many workstation to configure create a file named
  anything.reg with the following content and use it to modify the
  "faulty" registry.



  Windows Registry Editor Version 5.00

  [HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\Netlogon\Parameters]
  "requiresignorseal"=dword:00000000



  This version also needs an adjust at the NETLOGON.BAT script.
  Sometimes it insists on making the mounting persistent.



  REM NETLOGON.BAT
  net use z: \\linux\samba /yes /persistent:no



  5.5.  Policy editor

  There is a utility named policy editor bundled on the Windows CD. The
  file name is poledit.exe. This tool, as the name suggest, allows to
  create a user and system policy file.


  Unfortunately, this tool does not generate a plain text configuration
  file, so I can't place an example here.


  Use the policy editor to create a policy to your workstations and
  users. You should disable the local password cache and domain cache in
  order to get some security. Save the policy file as config.pol and
  place it at the netlogon share of your Linux server. In this way, your
  Windows workstations will download and use the config.pol file to set
  their policy. Of course this task must be done on a Windows machine.


  If you don't use a config.pol file, your Windows workstations will
  annoy you asking for a Windows password and you will become nuts
  trying to synchronize and manage your Domain and Windows passwords.
  It seems that the OS doesn't know that it joined a domain. You must
  tell it and then you have to slap it in the face so it will believe
  you.


  6.  User management



  6.1.  Adding users

  Adding a Linux user by usual means and setting a samba password using
  smbpasswd will work. If you have any doubt, just refer to the SAMBA
  documentation. This is not a difficult issue.


  6.2.  Password management

  I am issuing this a major topic because I couldn't learn yet how to
  manage users and users' passwords from a Windows workstation without
  using a web interface. I couldn't find and didn't know how to build
  integrated tools to solve this problem. So, I am using a CGI program
  to get it done.


  Try the package at http://changepassword.sourceforge.net
  <http://changepassword.sourceforge.net>, it seems to be a good choice.


  6.3.  Granting or denying access to users

  As you could see in a previous section of this howto, the SAMBA daemon
  will call a netlogon.sh script every time the tracking share is
  mounted. This netlogon.sh script will call a script with the user's
  name giving this script the ip address of the refered workstation as a
  parameter. This user script will apply the desired rules.


  For example if you want to give the user full access to internet:



  #!/bin/sh
  #
  COMMAND=$1
  ADDRESS=$2
  EXTIF=$3
  IPTABLES='/usr/sbin/iptables'
  $IPTABLES $COMMAND POSTROUTING -t nat -s $ADDRESS -o $EXTIF -j MASQUERADE



  If you don't want to change anything to a particular user, just give
  him an empty script:



  #/bin/sh
  #
  exit 0



  Or just don't create any script for the less privileged users, letting
  them have the default.sh script, which would be empty as the previous
  or just give limited access as follows:



  #!/bin/sh
  #
  COMMAND=$1
  ADDRESS=$2
  EXTIF=$3
  EXTIFADDRESS=$4
  IPTABLES='/usr/sbin/iptables'
  $IPTABLES $COMMAND POSTROUTING -t nat -s $ADDRESS -o $EXTIF --dport 25 -j SNAT --to-source $EXTIFADDRESS
  $IPTABLES $COMMAND POSTROUTING -t nat -s $ADDRESS -o $EXTIF --dport 110 -j SNAT --to-source $EXTIFADDRESS



  Remember that this script requires you to modify all the previous
  scripts to include the extra parameter ou just modify the script
  script. And remember that you will go nowhere whis this howto if you
  don't understand iptables.


  7.  Group management

  7.1.  Creating groups

  Just create your user groups in the Linux PDC and add the users to the
  groups. This is it.


  Remember that the example scripts in this howto will probably fail if
  you have users belonging to more than one group. If you need this,
  remember to adjust the scripts.


  7.2.  Group policy

  You will need to define group specific scripts and place them in the
  directory "/etc/smbgate/groups/". Remember that the script must be
  named as the group, at least if you want to follow the examples in
  this howto.


  The default scheme of this howto is to check for a user script, then
  for a group script and finally for the default script. If you want to
  modify this behavior remember to adapt the netlogon.sh, netlogoff.sh
  (or the checklogout.sh) scripts. The whole logic is in these scripts.


  8.  Bibliography

  IPTABLES TUTORIAL
  <http://www.netfilter.org/documentation/tutorials/blueflux/iptables-
  tutorial.html> by Oskar Andreasson


  Samba HOWTO Collection <http://www.samba.org/samba/docs/man/Samba-
  HOWTO-Collection.html> by the SAMBA Team

> From Samba Authenticated Gateway HOWTO

  SMB HOWTO
  David Wood, dwood@plugged.net.au
  v1.3, 20 April 2000

  This is the SMB HOWTO.  This document describes how to use the Server
  Message Block (SMB) protocol, also called the Session Message Block,
  NetBIOS or LanManager protocol, with Linux using Samba.
  ______________________________________________________________________

  Table of Contents


  1. License

  2. Introduction

  3. Further Information

  4. Installation

  5. Running The Daemons

  6. General Configuration (/etc/smb.conf)

  7. Sharing A Linux Drive With Windows Machines

  8. Accessing an SMB Share With Linux Machines

  9. Sharing A Linux Printer With Windows Machines

  10. Sharing A Windows Printer With Linux Machines

  11. Backing Up Windows Machines to a Linux Host

  12. Using Samba Across Routed Networks

  13. Acknowledgements



  ______________________________________________________________________

  1.  License

  Copyright (c)  2000  David Wood.

  Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
  under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
  any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
  Invariant Sections , with no Front-Cover Texts and with no Back-Cover
  Texts.  A copy of the license is available at
  http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html
  <http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html>.


  2.  Introduction

  This is the SMB HOWTO.  This document describes how to use the Server
  Message Block (SMB) protocol, also called the Session Message Block,
  NetBIOS or LanManager protocol, with Linux using Samba.  Although this
  document is Linux-centric, Samba runs on most Unix-like operating
  systems.

  This document is maintained by David Wood (dwood@plugged.net.au).
  Additions, modifications or corrections may be mailed there for
  inclusion in the next release.
  Much more Samba documentation is available at the Samba Web site,
  located at http://www.samba.org/ <http://www.samba.org/>.  There is a
  tremendous amount of information there; please have a look before
  asking for help!  You also might try the comp.protocols.smb newsgroup.

  The SMB protocol is used by Microsoft Windows 3.11, NT and 95/98 to
  share disks and printers.  Using the Samba suite of tools by Andrew
  Tridgell (Andrew.Tridgell@anu.edu.au), UNIX (including Linux) machines
  can share disk and printers with Windows hosts.  The smbfs tools by
  Paal-Kr. Engstad (engstad@intermetrics.com) and Volker Lendecke
  (lendecke@namu01.gwdg.de) enable Unix machines to mount SMB shares
  from Windows or Samba hosts.

  There are four basic things that one can do with Samba:


  1. Share a Linux drive with Windows machines.

  2. Access an SMB share with Linux machines.

  3. Share a Linux printer with Windows machines.

  4. Share a Windows printer with Linux machines.

  All of these are covered in this document, plus a few other odds and
  ends.

  Disclaimer: The procedures and scripts either work for the author or
  have been reported to work by the people that provided them.
  Different configurations may not work with the information given here.
  If you encounter such a situation, please e-mail the author with
  suggestions for improvement in this document.

  Please note that for Windows 3.x machines to access SMB shares, they
  must have a TCP/IP stack and the Win32s DLLs.  Both of these are
  available on Microsoft's Web site (http://www.microsoft.com
  <http://www.microsoft.com>).  As of the writing of this version of the
  HOWTO, Microsoft are reportedly requiring a subscription to the
  Microsoft Software Developers Network (MSDN) to download the TCP/IP-32
  stack for Windows 3.x from their Web site.  Since this software used
  to be free, many older copies are in existance and may be acquired
  from friends and user group contacts.


  3.  Further Information

  This HOWTO attempts to explain how to configure basic SMB file and
  print services on a Linux machine.  Samba is a very complex and
  complete package.  There would be no point in attempting to duplicate
  all of the documentation for Samba here.

  For further information, please see the following documents:

  ·  The Samba documentation, available as part of the Samba
     distribution.  The distribution is available at:
     ftp://ftp.samba.org/ <ftp://ftp.samba.org/>

  ·  The Linux Printing HOWTO.

  ·  Protocol Standard For A NetBIOS Service On A TCP/UDP Transport.

     RFC 1001
        > RFC 1001 - Concepts and Methods.

     RFC 1002
        > RFC 1002 - Detailed Specifications.
  4.  Installation

  First, in order to use Samba your machines must be on a single
  ethernet LAN segment using the TCP/IP protocol.  Samba will not work
  using other network protocols.  This is generally easy since Linux and
  Windows 95/98/NT ship with TCP/IP support.  However, if you are using
  Windows 3.X machines TCP/IP support will need to be added.  One of the
  most common questions that I get asked is why Samba "isn't working"
  when Windows machines are not using TCP/IP.

  In order to setup Windows 95/98 to use TCP/IP, select Control Panel |
  Network, then add and configure Microsoft TCP/IP.  Under Windows NT,
  select Control Panel | Network | Protocols.

  To get the latest source version of Samba, go to this URL and pick the
  closest mirror site to you: ftp://ftp.samba.org/
  <ftp://ftp.samba.org/>.

  In most cases, though, your Linux distribution will already come with
  an installable package containing a recent version of Samba.

  The following two daemons are required for the Samba package.  They
  are typically installed in /usr/sbin and run either on boot from the
  systems startup scripts or from inetd.  Example scripts are shown in
  ``Running the Daemons''.


  ______________________________________________________________________
          smbd (The SMB daemon)
          nmbd (Provides NetBIOS nameserver support to clients)
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Please note that the name service provided by the nmbd daemon is
  different from the name service provided by the Domain Name Service
  (DNS).  NetBIOS name service is a 'Windows-style' name service used
  for SMB.  In other words, having DNS name service tells you nothing
  about the state of the ability for Samba to resolve host names.

  Typically, the following Samba binaries are installed in /usr/bin or
  /usr/local/samba/bin, although the location is optional.


  ______________________________________________________________________
          smbclient       (An SMB client for UNIX machines)
          smbprint        (A script to print to a printer on an SMB host)
          smbprint.sysv   (As above, but for SVR4 UNIX machines)
          smbstatus       (Lists the cuurent SMB connections for the local host)
          smbrun          (A 'glue' script to facilitate runnning applciations
                           on SMB hosts)
  ______________________________________________________________________



  The binaries for smbfs file system support are discussed later in this
  document.

  Additionally, a script called 'print' is included with this HOWTO,
  which serves as a useful front end to the smbprint script.

  The Samba package is simple to install.  Simply retrieve the source
  from the location mentioned above, and read the file README in the
  distribution.  There is also a file called docs/INSTALL.txt in the
  distribution that provides a simple step-by-step set of instructions.

  Following installation, place the daemons in /usr/sbin and the
  binaries in /usr/bin.  Install the man pages in /usr/local/man.

  When you made the Samba package, you would have specified in the
  Makefile the location for the configuration file, smb.conf.  This is
  generally in /etc, but you can put it anywhere you like.  For these
  directions, we will presume that you specified the location of the
  configuration file as /etc/smb.conf, the log file location as log file
  = /var/log/samba-log.%m and the lock directory as lock directory =
  /var/lock/samba.

  Install the configuration file, smb.conf.  Go to the directory where
  Samba was built.  Look in the subdirectory examples/simple and read
  the file README.  Copy the file smb.conf found in that directory to
  /etc.  BE CAREFUL!  If you have a Linux distribution that already has
  Samba installed, you may already have a Samba configuration file in
  /etc.  You should probably start with that one.

  If you don't want to have your configuration file in /etc, put it
  wherever you want to, then put a symlink in /etc:


  ______________________________________________________________________
          ln -s /path/to/smb.conf /etc/smb.conf
  ______________________________________________________________________



  5.  Running The Daemons

  The two SMB daemons are /usr/sbin/smbd and /usr/sbin/nmbd.  Under most
  Linux distributions, these are started, stoped and restarted via the
  startup script located in /etc/rc.d/init.d/smb and symlinked to the
  appropriate runlevels.

  If you choose not to use the standard startup script, you can run the
  Samba daemons from inetd or as stand-alone processes.  Samba will
  respond slightly faster as a standalone daemon than running from
  inetd.

  In either case, you should check the file /etc/services for lines that
  look like this:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       netbios-ns      137/tcp         nbns
       netbios-ns      137/udp         nbns
       netbios-dgm     138/tcp         nbdgm
       netbios-dgm     138/udp         nbdgm
       netbios-ssn     139/tcp         nbssn
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Make sure they are all uncommented.  Depending on your distribution,
  you may even need to add them.   Samba will not be able to bind to the
  appropriate ports unless /etc/services has these entries.

  To run the daemons from inetd, place the following lines in the inetd
  configuration file, /etc/inetd.conf:



  ______________________________________________________________________
      # SAMBA NetBIOS services (for PC file and print sharing)
      netbios-ssn stream tcp nowait root /usr/sbin/smbd smbd
      netbios-ns dgram udp wait root /usr/sbin/nmbd nmbd
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Then restart the inetd daemon by running the command:


  ______________________________________________________________________
      kill -HUP `cat /var/run/inetd.pid`
  ______________________________________________________________________



  To run the daemons from the system startup scripts, put the following
  script in file called /etc/rc.d/init.d/smb (for most distributions)
  and symbolically link it to the files specified in the comments:



  ______________________________________________________________________
      #!/bin/sh

      #
      # /etc/rc.d/init.d/smb - starts and stops SMB services.
      #
      # The following files should be synbolic links to this file:
      # symlinks: /etc/rc.d/rc1.d/K35smb  (Kills SMB services on shutdown)
      #           /etc/rc.d/rc3.d/S91smb  (Starts SMB services in multiuser mode)
      #           /etc/rc.d/rc6.d/K35smb  (Kills SMB services on reboot)
      #

      # Source function library.
      . /etc/rc.d/init.d/functions

      # Source networking configuration.
      . /etc/sysconfig/network

      # Check that networking is up.
      [ ${NETWORKING} = "no" ] && exit 0

      # See how we were called.
      case "$1" in
        start)
          echo -n "Starting SMB services: "
          daemon smbd -D
          daemon nmbd -D
          echo
          touch /var/lock/subsys/smb
          ;;
        stop)
          echo -n "Shutting down SMB services: "
          killproc smbd
          killproc nmbd
          rm -f /var/lock/subsys/smb
          echo ""
          ;;
        *)
          echo "Usage: smb {start|stop}"
          exit 1
      esac
  ______________________________________________________________________



  If when starting Samba you get an error that says something about the
  daemon failing to bind to port 139, then you probably have another
  Samba process already running that hasn't yet shut down.  Check a
  process list (with 'ps auxww | grep mbd') to determine if another
  Samba service is running.



  6.  General Configuration (/etc/smb.conf)

  Samba configuration on a Linux (or other UNIX machine) is controlled
  by a single file, /etc/smb.conf.  This file determines which system
  resources you want to share with the outside world and what
  restrictions you wish to place on them.

  Since the following sections will address sharing Linux drives and
  printers with Windows machines, the smb.conf file shown in this
  section is as simple as you can get, just for introductory purposes.


  Don't worry about the details, yet.  Later sections will introduce the
  major concepts.

  Each section of the file starts with a section header such as
  [global], [homes], [printers], etc.

  The [global] section defines a few variables that Samba will use to
  define sharing for all resources.

  The [homes] section allows a remote users to access their (and only
  their) home directory on the local (Linux) machine).  That is, users
  trying to connect to this share from Windows machines, will be
  connected to their personal home directories.  Note that to do this,
  they must have an account on the Linux box.

  The sample smb.conf file below allows remote users to get to their
  home directories on the local machine and to write to a temporary
  directory.  For a Windows user to see these shares, the Linux box has
  to be on the local network.  Then the user simply connects a network
  drive from the Windows File Manager or Windows Explorer.

  Note that in the following sections, additional entries for this file
  will be given to allow more resources to be shared.



       ______________________________________________________________________
       ; /etc/smb.conf
       ;
       ; Make sure and restart the server after making changes to this file, ex:
       ; /etc/rc.d/init.d/smb stop
       ; /etc/rc.d/init.d/smb start

       [global]
       ; Uncomment this if you want a guest account
       ; guest account = nobody
          log file = /var/log/samba-log.%m
          lock directory = /var/lock/samba
          share modes = yes

       [homes]
          comment = Home Directories
          browseable = no
          read only = no
          create mode = 0750

       [tmp]
          comment = Temporary file space
          path = /tmp
          read only = no
          public = yes
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Having written a new smb.conf, it is useful to test it to verify its
  correctness.  You can test the correctness of a smb.conf file , using
  the 'testparm' utility (man page: testparm); if testparm reports no
  problems, smbd will correctly load the configuration file.

  Here's a good trick:  If your Samba server has more than one ethernet
  interface, the smbd may bind to the wrong one.  If so, you can force
  it to bind to the intended one by adding a line that looks like this
  to the [global] section of /etc/smb.conf:

       ______________________________________________________________________
       interfaces = 192.168.1.1/24
       ______________________________________________________________________



  where you replace the IP address above with the one that is assigned
  to the correct ethernet interface.  The "24" is correct for a Class C
  network, but may have to be recalculated if you have subnetted the
  network.  The number relates to the netmask.  Numbers for other
  classes of networks are given in the IP-Masquerade mini-HOWTO.

  There is now a GUI configuration tool for Samba:  GtkSamba.  See
  http://www.open-systems.com/gtksamba.html <http://www.open-
  systems.com/gtksamba.html>.



  7.  Sharing A Linux Drive With Windows Machines

  As shown in the simple smb.conf above, sharing Linux drives with
  Windows users is easy.  However, like everything else with Samba, you
  can control things to a large degree.  Here are some examples:

  To share a directory with the public, create a clone of the [tmp]
  section above by adding something like this to smb.conf:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       [public]
          comment = Public Stuff
          path = /home/public
          public = yes
          writable = yes
          printable = no
       ______________________________________________________________________



  To make the above directory readable by the public, but only writable
  by people in group staff, modify the entry like this:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       [public]
          comment = Public Stuff
          path = /home/public
          public = yes
          writable = yes
          printable = no
          write list = @staff
       ______________________________________________________________________



  It used to be that easy; you would now be able to start Samba and
  browse the shares from a Windows PC.  However, Microsoft has recently
  made life slightly more difficult for those using Samba.  Windows 98,
  Windows NT (service pack 3 or higher) and later builds of Windows 95
  now use encrypted passwords by default.  Samba uses unencrypted
  passwords by default.  You can't browse servers when either the client
  or server is using encrypted passwords, because a connection cannot be
  made anonymously.

  You can tell if you have a password type mismatch between client and
  server if when you try to connect to a share you see a dialog box
  which reads something like "You are not authorized to access that
  account from this machine".

  You can either configure your Samba server to use encrypted passwords,
  or configure the Windows machines to use unencrypted passwords.

  To get Windows to work with encrypted SMB passwords:

  Windows 95/98 =============

  Using the registry editor (regedit), create the registry setting
  HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\System\CurrentControlSet\Services\VxD\VNETSUP Add a
  new DWORD value: Value Name:  EnablePlainTextPassword Data:
  0x01.

  Windows NT ==========

  Using the registry editor (regedit), create the registry setting
  HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\System\CurrentControlSet\Services\Rdr\Parameters
  Add a new DWORD value: Value Name:  EnablePlainTextPassword Data:
  0x01

  Windows 2000 ============

  Using the registry editor (regedit), create the registry setting
  HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\LanmanWorkStation\Parameters
  Add a new DWORD value: Value Name: EnablePlainTextPassword Data: 0x01

  Once these registry changes have been made, reboot the Windows machine
  and try to map a network drive on the Samba server again.  It should
  work as long as the Samba server is using plain text passwords.

  To configure Samba to use encrypted passwords:

  In the [global] section of /etc/smb.conf, add the following lines:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       encrypt passwords = yes
       smb passwd file = /etc/smbpasswd
       ______________________________________________________________________



  You are highly encouraged to read the files ENCRYPTION.txt, Win95.txt
  and WinNT.txt in the Samba documentation before doing this!

  If your clients and server are using encrypted passwords, you will not
  be able to browse the available shares on the server until an initial
  connection has been made with the appropriate authentication.  To get
  the initial connection, enter the share name manually in the Windows
  File Manager or Explorer dialog box, in the form
  '\\<hostname>\<sharename>'.  Log onto the server with a username and
  password that is valid on the server!

  If you suspect that your NetBIOS name service is not correctly
  configured (perhaps because you get 'host not found' errors when
  trying to connect), try using just the IP address of the server:
  '\\<host ip address>\<sharename>'.
  In order to get filenames to appear correctly, you may also need to
  set some options in the appropriate share section.  These work for
  Windows 95/98/NT clients, but may need to be modified if you have
  Windows 3.X clients:



       ______________________________________________________________________
           ; Mangle case = yes seems to give the correct filenames
           ; for Win95/98/NT.
           mangle case = yes

           ; If samba is case sensitive when looking for files
           case sensitive = no

           ; Default case of files that are created
           default case = lower

           ; Preserve case for all filenames
           preserve case = yes

           ; Preserve case for dos (8.3) filenames
           short preserve case = no
       ______________________________________________________________________



  For other tricks to play with drive shares, see the Samba
  documentation or man pages.



       ______________________________________________________________________
       interfaces = 192.168.1.1/24
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Note:  The bit after the / is a reference to the subnet mask.  "24" is
  the value to use for an unsegmented Class C network.  For more
  information on subnet calculations, you might want to see
  http://www.ralphb.net/IPSubnet/ <http://www.ralphb.net/IPSubnet/>.

  There is a lot more to Samba configuration than this, but this will
  get you started.  If you want to do something more advanced, I refer
  you to the Samba Web site mentioned above.



  8.  Accessing an SMB Share With Linux Machines

  Linux (UNIX) machines can also browse and mount SMB shares.  Note that
  this can be done whether the server is a Windows machine or a Samba
  server!

  An SMB client program for UNIX machines is included with the Samba
  distribution.  It provides an ftp-like interface on the command line.
  You can use this utility to transfer files between a Windows 'server'
  and a Linux client.

  Most Linux distributions also now include the useful smbfs package,
  which allows one to mount and umount SMB shares.  More on smbfs below.

  To see which shares are available on a given host, run:


  ______________________________________________________________________
      /usr/bin/smbclient -L host
  ______________________________________________________________________



  where 'host' is the name of the machine that you wish to view.  this
  will return a list of 'service' names - that is, names of drives or
  printers that it can share with you.  Unless the SMB server has no
  security configured, it will ask you for a password.  Get it the
  password for the 'guest' account or for your personal account on that
  machine.

  For example:


  ______________________________________________________________________
      smbclient -L zimmerman
  ______________________________________________________________________



  The output of this command should look something like this:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       Server time is Sat Aug 10 15:58:27 1996
       Timezone is UTC+10.0
       Password:
       Domain=[WORKGROUP] OS=[Windows NT 3.51] Server=[NT LAN Manager 3.51]

       Server=[ZIMMERMAN] User=[] Workgroup=[WORKGROUP] Domain=[]

               Sharename      Type      Comment
               ---------      ----      -------
               ADMIN$         Disk      Remote Admin
               public         Disk      Public
               C$             Disk      Default share
               IPC$           IPC       Remote IPC
               OReilly        Printer   OReilly
               print$         Disk      Printer Drivers


       This machine has a browse list:

               Server               Comment
               ---------            -------
               HOPPER               Samba 1.9.15p8
               KERNIGAN             Samba 1.9.15p8
               LOVELACE             Samba 1.9.15p8
               RITCHIE              Samba 1.9.15p8
               ZIMMERMAN
       ______________________________________________________________________



  The browse list shows other SMB servers with resources to share on the
  network.

  To use the client, run:

  ______________________________________________________________________
      /usr/bin/smbclient service <password>
  ______________________________________________________________________



  where 'service' is a machine and share name.  For example, if you are
  trying to reach a directory that has been shared as 'public' on a
  machine called zimmerman, the service would be called
  \\zimmerman\public.  However, due to shell restrictions, you will need
  to escape the backslashes, so you end up with something like this:


  ______________________________________________________________________
      /usr/bin/smbclient \\\\zimmerman\\public mypasswd
  ______________________________________________________________________



  where 'mypasswd' is the literal string of your password.

  You will get the smbclient prompt:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       Server time is Sat Aug 10 15:58:44 1996
       Timezone is UTC+10.0
       Domain=[WORKGROUP] OS=[Windows NT 3.51] Server=[NT LAN Manager 3.51]
       smb: \>
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Type 'h' to get help using smbclient:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       smb: \> h
       ls             dir            lcd            cd             pwd
       get            mget           put            mput           rename
       more           mask           del            rm             mkdir
       md             rmdir          rd             prompt         recurse
       translate      lowercase      print          printmode      queue
       cancel         stat           quit           q              exit
       newer          archive        tar            blocksize      tarmode
       setmode        help           ?              !
       smb: \>
       ______________________________________________________________________



  If you can use ftp, you shouldn't need the man pages for smbclient.

  Although you can use smbclient for testing, you will soon tire of it
  for real work.  For that you will probably want to use the smbfs
  package.  Smbfs comes with two simple utilties, smbmount and
  smbumount.  They work just like mount and umount for SMB shares.

  One important thing to note:  You must have smbfs support compiled
  into your kernel to use these utilities!


  The following shows a typical use of smbmount to mount an SMB share
  called "customers" from a machine called "samba1":



       ______________________________________________________________________
       [root@postel]# smbmount "\\\\samba1\\customers" -U rtg2t -c 'mount /customers -u 500 -g 100'
       Added interface ip=192.168.35.84 bcast=192.168.255.255 nmask=255.255.0.0
       Got a positive name query response from 192.168.168.158 ( 192.168.168.158 )
       Server time is Tue Oct  5 10:27:36 1999
       Timezone is UTC-4.0
       Password:
       Domain=[IPM] OS=[Unix] Server=[Samba 2.0.3]
       security=user
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Issuing a mount command will now show the share mounted, just as if it
  were an NFS export:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       [root@postel]# mount
       /dev/hda2 on / type ext2 (rw)
       none on /proc type proc (rw)
       none on /dev/pts type devpts (rw,mode=622)
       //SAMBA1/CUSTOMERS on /customers type smbfs (0)
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Please see the manual pages for smbmount and smbumount for details on
  the above operation.



  9.  Sharing A Linux Printer With Windows Machines

  To share a Linux printer with Windows machines, you need to make
  certain that your printer is set up to work under Linux.  If you can
  print from Linux, setting up an SMB share of the printer is stright
  forward.

  Note that Windows users must have an account on the Linux/Samba server
  in order to print.  Windows 95/98 will attempt to authenticate to the
  print server using the username and password used on login to the
  Windows box.This means that if you clicked 'Cancel' when logging onto
  Windows, you can't print (or connect to other SMB services)!  Windows
  NT allows one to explicitely provide a username and password when
  connecting to a printer.

  See the Printing HOWTO to set up local printing.

  Add printing configuration to your smb.conf:



  ______________________________________________________________________
  [global]
     printing = bsd
     printcap name = /etc/printcap
     load printers = yes
     log file = /var/log/samba-log.%m
     lock directory = /var/lock/samba

  [printers]
     comment = All Printers
     security = server
     path = /var/spool/lpd/lp
     browseable = no
     printable = yes
     public = yes
     writable = no
     create mode = 0700

  [ljet]
     security = server
     path = /var/spool/lpd/lp
     printer name = lp
     writable = yes
     public = yes
     printable = yes
     print command = lpr -r -h -P %p %s
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Make certain that the printer path (in this case under [ljet]) matches
  the spool directory in /etc/printcap!

  The lines:


  ______________________________________________________________________
     printcap name = /etc/printcap
     load printers = yes
  ______________________________________________________________________



  controls whether all the printers in /etc/printcap should be loaded by
  default.  If you do this, there is no reason to set up printers
  individually.  The section [printers] specifies options for the
  printers that you wish to explicitly difine.  If the printing
  subsystem you are using doesn't work this way (BSD), you need to set
  up a fake printcap file (or to use the 'print command' technique, see
  below).  For more information on the printcap system see the Printing
  HOWTO.

  A useful technique to test the network connection is to change the
  print command to:


  ______________________________________________________________________
     print command = cp %S /tmp/print.%P.%S
  ______________________________________________________________________



  The resulting file can then be analyzed.


  NOTE:  There are some problems sharing printers on UNIX boxes with
  Windows NT machines using Samba.  One problem is with NT seeing the
  shared printer properly.  To fix this, see the notes in the Samba
  distribution in the file docs/WinNT.txt.  The other deals with
  password problems.  See the comments in the same file for an annoying
  gain of understanding and failure to fix the problem.

  Oleg L. Machulskiy (machulsk@shade.msu.ru) suggests that a better
  print command to use in the above example would be:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       print command = smb2ps %s | lpr -r -h -P %p
       ______________________________________________________________________



  where 'smb2ps' is a script which transforms the spool file received
  from Windows into usual a usable Postscript file. It must cut off
  first 3 lines and last 2 lines, because these lines contain some PJL
  or PCL codes.

  That approach is only needed if your Windows machine is printing PCL
  and not real Postscript.  I have found that Windows 95/98/NT don't
  have a generic Postscript driver per se, but the "Digital turbo
  Printserver 20" driver acts as a good general Postscript driver for
  most setups.  I have also heard that the "Apple LaserWriter II NTX"
  driver works for this purpose.

  If you are creating a printer spool directory instead of using one
  created by a Linux distribution's installation utility, be careful of
  permissions!  Neil Fraser (neilf@necon.co.za) suggested setting the
  permissions of the spool directory (in his case, /var/spool/lpd/lpr)
  to 4755 (note the suid bit).  This worked for him when the owner of
  the directory was 'root' and the group was 'lp'.

  Jeff Stern (jstern@eclectic.ss.uci.edu) reported that he had to set
  the permissions on his spool directory to 777 in order for non-
  priviledged users to print, although he notes that he could have also
  added users to the 'lp' group.  This is a decision for local systems
  administrators;  if printing security is an issue, then lock it down.
  In home environments, you will probably want everyone to be able to
  print.

  Dr. Michael Langner (langner@fiz-chemie.de) points out that write
  permission problems on the /var/spool/lpd/ tree could be avoided by
  use something like "path = /tmp" and "print command = lpr -r -P%p %s"
  instead.

  Sometimes, a Postscript parsing error will occur with Postscript
  printing from Windows machines that causes an extra page to be printed
  at the end of every print job.  The last page will always have "%%[
  Lastpage ]%%" at the top of it.  This seems to happen with Windows 95
  and 98 only and is because the Postscript is malformed.

  One way to handle that is to use a script to remove that bit of bad
  Postscript from the spooled jobs.  Another way is to try to find a
  better Windows Postscript driver.  Probably the best way is to us
  LPRng instead of Postscript to print to a Samba server.

  Erik Ratcliffe (erik@caldera.com) Caldera tells me that using LPRng
  means that any printer driver can be used from Windows machines.  On
  the Samba server, they used an /etc/printcap entry that looked like
  this:
       ______________________________________________________________________
       raw:\
               :rw:sh:
               :lp=/dev/lp1
               :sd=/var/spool/lpd/raw
               :fx=flp
       ______________________________________________________________________



  LPRng doesn't require :\ at the end of every line.  A printer entry
  will still need to be made in /etc/smb.conf for the physical printer.
  The print command line needs to use the "raw" entry in /etc/printcap
  and data must be sent to the printer in binary form.  Try a print
  command line like this:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       print command = lpr -b -Praw %s
       ______________________________________________________________________



  You may also need to set the spooling on the Windows95 end to print
  directly to the printer instead of spooling.

  If you constantly get a extra page printing at the end of print jobs
  from Windows clients, try adding an "sf" directive in /etc/printcap.
  This will suppress form feeds separating jobs, but will not effect
  form feeds within documents.



  10.  Sharing A Windows Printer With Linux Machines

  To share a printer on a Windows machine, you must do the following:


  1. You must have the proper entries in /etc/printcap and they must
     correspond to the local directory structure (for the spool
     directory, etc).

  2. You must have the script /usr/bin/smbprint.  This comes with the
     Samba source, but not with all Samba binary distributions.  A
     slightly modifed copy is discussed below.

  3. If you want to convert ASCII files to Postscript, you must have
     nenscript, or its equivalent.  nenscript is a Postscript converter
     and is generally installed in /usr/bin.

  4. You may wish to make Samba printing easier by having an easy-to-use
     front end.  A simple perl script to handle ASCII, Postscript or
     created Postscript is given below.

  5. You could also use MagicFilter to do the above.  The details on
     setting up MagicFilter are given below the perl script.
     MagicFilter has advantages because it knows how to automatically
     convert a lot of file formats.

  The /etc/printcap entry below is for an HP 5MP printer on a Windows NT
  host.  The entries are as follows:


  ______________________________________________________________________
          cm - comment
          lp - device name to open for output
          sd - the printer's spool directory (on the local machine)
          af - the accounting file
          mx - the maximum file size (zero is unlimited)
          if - name of the input filter (script)
  ______________________________________________________________________



  For more information, see the Printing HOWTO or the man page for
  printcap.



       ______________________________________________________________________
       # /etc/printcap
       #
       # //zimmerman/oreilly via smbprint
       #
       lp:\
               :cm=HP 5MP Postscript OReilly on zimmerman:\
               :lp=/dev/lp1:\
               :sd=/var/spool/lpd/lp:\
               :af=/var/spool/lpd/lp/acct:\
               :mx#0:\
               :if=/usr/bin/smbprint:
       ______________________________________________________________________



  Make certain that the spool and accounting directories exist and are
  writable.  Ensure that the 'if' line holds the proper path to the
  smbprint script (given below) and make sure that the proper device is
  pointed to (the /dev special file).

  Next is the smbprint script itself.  It is usually placed in /usr/bin
  and is attributable to Andrew Tridgell, the person who created Samba
  as far as I know.  It comes with the Samba source distribution, but is
  absent from some binary distributions, so I have recreated it here.

  You may wish to look at this carefully.  There are some minor
  alterations that have shown themselves to be useful.



  ______________________________________________________________________
  #!/bin/sh -x

  # This script is an input filter for printcap printing on a unix machine. It
  # uses the smbclient program to print the file to the specified smb-based
  # server and service.
  # For example you could have a printcap entry like this
  #
  # smb:lp=/dev/null:sd=/usr/spool/smb:sh:if=/usr/local/samba/smbprint
  #
  # which would create a unix printer called "smb" that will print via this
  # script. You will need to create the spool directory /usr/spool/smb with
  # appropriate permissions and ownerships for your system.

  # Set these to the server and service you wish to print to
  # In this example I have a WfWg PC called "lapland" that has a printer
  # exported called "printer" with no password.

  #
  # Script further altered by hamiltom@ecnz.co.nz (Michael Hamilton)
  # so that the server, service, and password can be read from
  # a /usr/var/spool/lpd/PRINTNAME/.config file.
  #
  # In order for this to work the /etc/printcap entry must include an
  # accounting file (af=...):
  #
  #   cdcolour:\
  #       :cm=CD IBM Colorjet on 6th:\
  #       :sd=/var/spool/lpd/cdcolour:\
  #       :af=/var/spool/lpd/cdcolour/acct:\
  #       :if=/usr/local/etc/smbprint:\
  #       :mx=0:\
  #       :lp=/dev/null:
  #
  # The /usr/var/spool/lpd/PRINTNAME/.config file should contain:
  #   server=PC_SERVER
  #   service=PR_SHARENAME
  #   password="password"
  #
  # E.g.
  #   server=PAULS_PC
  #   service=CJET_371
  #   password=""

  #
  # Debugging log file, change to /dev/null if you like.
  #
  logfile=/tmp/smb-print.log
  # logfile=/dev/null


  #
  # The last parameter to the filter is the accounting file name.
  #
  spool_dir=/var/spool/lpd/lp
  config_file=$spool_dir/.config

  # Should read the following variables set in the config file:
  #   server
  #   service
  #   password
  #   user
  eval `cat $config_file`

  #
  # Some debugging help, change the >> to > if you want to same space.
  #
  echo "server $server, service $service" >> $logfile

  (
  # NOTE You may wish to add the line `echo translate' if you want automatic
  # CR/LF translation when printing.
          echo translate
          echo "print -"
          cat
  ) | /usr/bin/smbclient "\\\\$server\\$service" $password -U $user -N -P >> $logfile
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Most Linux distributions come with nenscript for converting ASCII
  documents to Postscript.  The following perl script makes life easier
  be providing a simple interface to Linux printing via smbprint.


  ______________________________________________________________________
  Usage: print [-a|c|p] <filename>
         -a prints <filename> as ASCII
         -c prints <filename> formatted as source code
         -p prints <filename> as Postscript
          If no switch is given, print attempts to
          guess the file type and print appropriately.
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Using smbprint to print ASCII files tends to truncate long lines.
  This script breaks long lines on whitespace (instead of in the middle
  of a word), if possible.

  The source code formatting is done with nenscript.  It takes an ASCII
  file and foramts it in 2 columns with a fancy header (date, filename,
  etc).  It also numbers the lines.  Using this as an example, other
  types of formatting can be accomplished.

  Postscript documents are already properly formatted, so they pass
  through directly.



  ______________________________________________________________________
  #!/usr/bin/perl

  # Script:   print
  # Authors:  Brad Marshall, David Wood
  #           Plugged In Communications
  # Date:     960808
  #
  # Script to print to a Postscript printer via Samba.
  # Purpose:  Takes files of various types as arguments and
  # processes them appropriately for piping to a Samba print script.
  #
  # Currently supported file types:
  #
  # ASCII      - ensures that lines longer than $line_length characters wrap on
  #              whitespace.
  # Postscript - Takes no action.
  # Code       - Formats in Postscript (using nenscript) to display
  #              properly (landscape, font, etc).
  #

  # Set the maximum allowable length for each line of ASCII text.
  $line_length = 76;

  # Set the path and name of the Samba print script
  $print_prog = "/usr/bin/smbprint";

  # Set the path and name to nenscript (the ASCII-->Postscript converter)
  $nenscript = "/usr/bin/nenscript";

  unless ( -f $print_prog ) {
          die "Can't find $print_prog!";
  }
  unless ( -f $nenscript ) {
          die "Can't find $nenscript!";
  }

  &ParseCmdLine(@ARGV);

  # DBG
  print "filetype is $filetype\n";

  if ($filetype eq "ASCII") {
          &wrap($line_length);
  } elsif ($filetype eq "code") {
          &codeformat;
  } elsif ($filetype eq "ps") {
          &createarray;
  } else {
          print "Sorry..no known file type.\n";
          exit 0;
  }
  # Pipe the array to smbprint
  open(PRINTER, "|$print_prog") || die "Can't open $print_prog: $!\n";
  foreach $line (@newlines) {
          print PRINTER $line;
  }
  # Send an extra linefeed in case a file has an incomplete last line.
  print PRINTER "\n";
  close(PRINTER);
  print "Completed\n";
  exit 0;

  # --------------------------------------------------- #
  #        Everything below here is a subroutine        #
  # --------------------------------------------------- #
  sub ParseCmdLine {
          # Parses the command line, finding out what file type the file is

          # Gets $arg and $file to be the arguments (if the exists)
          # and the filename
          if ($#_ < 0) {
                  &usage;
          }
          # DBG
  #       foreach $element (@_) {
  #               print "*$element* \n";
  #       }

          $arg = shift(@_);
          if ($arg =~ /\-./) {
                  $cmd = $arg;
          # DBG
  #       print "\$cmd found.\n";

                  $file = shift(@_);
          } else {
                  $file = $arg;
          }

          # Defining the file type
          unless ($cmd) {
                  # We have no arguments

                  if ($file =~ /\.ps$/) {
                          $filetype = "ps";
                  } elsif ($file =~ /\.java$|\.c$|\.h$|\.pl$|\.sh$|\.csh$|\.m4$|\.inc$|\.html$|\.htm$/) {
                          $filetype = "code";
                  } else {
                          $filetype = "ASCII";
                  }

                  # Process $file for what type is it and return $filetype
          } else {
                  # We have what type it is in $arg
                  if ($cmd =~ /^-p$/) {
                          $filetype = "ps";
                  } elsif ($cmd =~ /^-c$/) {
                          $filetype = "code";
                  } elsif ($cmd =~ /^-a$/) {
                          $filetype = "ASCII"
                  }
          }
  }

  sub usage {
          print "
  Usage: print [-a|c|p] <filename>
         -a prints <filename> as ASCII
         -c prints <filename> formatted as source code
         -p prints <filename> as Postscript
          If no switch is given, print attempts to
          guess the file type and print appropriately.\n
  ";
          exit(0);
  }

  sub wrap {
          # Create an array of file lines, where each line is < the
          # number of characters specified, and wrapped only on whitespace

          # Get the number of characters to limit the line to.
          $limit = pop(@_);

          # DBG
          #print "Entering subroutine wrap\n";
          #print "The line length limit is $limit\n";

          # Read in the file, parse and put into an array.
          open(FILE, "<$file") || die "Can't open $file: $!\n";
          while(<FILE>) {
                  $line = $_;

                  # DBG
                  #print "The line is:\n$line\n";

                  # Wrap the line if it is over the limit.
                  while ( length($line) > $limit ) {

                          # DBG
                          #print "Wrapping...";

                          # Get the first $limit +1 characters.
                          $part = substr($line,0,$limit +1);

                          # DBG
                          #print "The partial line is:\n$part\n";

                          # Check to see if the last character is a space.
                          $last_char = substr($part,-1, 1);
                          if ( " " eq $last_char ) {
                              # If it is, print the rest.

                              # DBG
                              #print "The last character was a space\n";

                              substr($line,0,$limit + 1) = "";
                              substr($part,-1,1) = "";
                              push(@newlines,"$part\n");
                          } else {
                               # If it is not, find the last space in the
                               # sub-line and print up to there.

                              # DBG
                              #print "The last character was not a space\n";

                               # Remove the character past $limit
                               substr($part,-1,1) = "";
                               # Reverse the line to make it easy to find
                               # the last space.
                               $revpart = reverse($part);
                               $index = index($revpart," ");
                               if ( $index > 0 ) {
                                 substr($line,0,$limit-$index) = "";
                                 push(@newlines,substr($part,0,$limit-$index)
                                     . "\n");
                               } else {
                                 # There was no space in the line, so
                                 # print it up to $limit.
                                 substr($line,0,$limit) = "";
                                 push(@newlines,substr($part,0,$limit)
                                     . "\n");
                               }
                          }
                  }
                  push(@newlines,$line);
          }
          close(FILE);
  }

  sub codeformat {
          # Call subroutine wrap then filter through nenscript
          &wrap($line_length);

          # Pipe the results through nenscript to create a Postscript
          # file that adheres to some decent format for printing
          # source code (landscape, Courier font, line numbers).
          # Print this to a temporary file first.
          $tmpfile = "/tmp/nenscript$$";
          open(FILE, "|$nenscript -2G -i$file -N -p$tmpfile -r") ||
                  die "Can't open nenscript: $!\n";
          foreach $line (@newlines) {
                  print FILE $line;
          }
          close(FILE);

          # Read the temporary file back into an array so it can be
          # passed to the Samba print script.
          @newlines = ("");
          open(FILE, "<$tmpfile") || die "Can't open $file: $!\n";
          while(<FILE>) {
                  push(@newlines,$_);
          }
          close(FILE);
          system("rm $tmpfile");
  }

  sub createarray {
          # Create the array for postscript
          open(FILE, "<$file") || die "Can't open $file: $!\n";
          while(<FILE>) {
                  push(@newlines,$_);
          }
          close(FILE);
  }
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Now the MagicFilter way.  Thanks to Alberto Menegazzi
  (flash.egon@iol.it) for this information.

  Alberto says:

  -------------------------------------------------------------- 1)
  Install MagicFilter with the filter for the printers you need in
  /usr/bin/local but DON'T fill /etc/printcap with the suggestion given
  by the documentation from MagicFilter.

  2) Write the /etc/printcap like this way (it's done for my LaserJet
  4L):

  lp|ljet4l:\ :cm=HP LaserJet 4L:\ :lp=/dev/null:\
  # or /dev/lp1 :sd=/var/spool/lpd/ljet4l:\
  :af=/var/spool/lpd/ljet4l/acct:\ :sh:mx#0:\ :if=/usr/local/bin/main-
  filter:

  You should explain that the lp=/dev/... is opened for locking so
  "virtual" devices one for every remote printer should be used.

  Example creating with : touch /dev/ljet4l


  3) Write the filter /usr/local/bin/main-filter the same you suggest
  using the ljet4l-filter instead of cat.

  Here's mine.

  #! /bin/sh logfile=/var/log/smb-print.log
  spool_dir=/var/spool/lpd/ljet4l ( echo "print -"
  /usr/local/bin/ljet4l-filter ) | /usr/bin/smbclient "\\\\SHIR\\HPLJ4"
  -N -P >> $logfile

  P.S. : here is the quote from the Print2Win mini-Howto about locking
  and why creating virtual printers

  ---Starts here

  Hint from Rick Bressler :

  Good tip sheet.  I use something very similar.  One helpful tip, this
  is not a particularly good idea:

  :lp=/dev/null:\

  lpr does an 'exclusive' open on the file you specify as lp=.  It does
  this in order to prevent multiple processes from trying to print to
  the dame printer at the same time.

  The side effect of this is that in your case, eng and colour can't
  print at the same time, (usually more or less transparent since they
  probably print quickly and since they queue you probably don't notice)
  but any other process that tries to write to /dev/null will break!

  On a single user system, probably not a big problem.  I have a system
  with over 50 printers.  It would be a problem there.

  The solution is to create a dummy printer for each.  Eg: touch
  /dev/eng.

  I have modified the lp entries in the printcap file above to take into
  account Rick's suggestion. I did the following:


  #touch /dev/eng #touch /dev/colour

  ---Ends here

  --------------------------------------------------------------



  11.  Backing Up Windows Machines to a Linux Host

  Adam Neat (adamneat@ipax.com.au) kindly contributed the following
  script to back up Windows machines to a Linux host, using the
  smbclient utility.  Adam says that it is used to backup Windows 3.x
  and NT machines to a Linux based DAT SCSI Drive.

  Adam is not proud of the coding style used here, but it works.  As I
  like to say, "If it works and its stupid, then it is not stupid".

  Another Windows backup script, contributed by Dan Tager
  (dtager@marsala.com), is provided below.  Dan's script also backs up
  Unix machines via rsh, although that could be modified to use ssh
  rather easily.

  In this script, the string 'agnea1' is the username on the Linux
  machine that does the backups.
       ______________________________________________________________________
       #!/bin/bash

       clear
       echo Initialising ...
       checkdate=`date | awk '{print $1}'`

       if [ -f "~agnea1/backup-dir/backup-data" ]; then

               echo "ERROR: No config file for today!"
               echo "FATAL!"
               exit 1
       fi

       if [ -d "~agnea1/backup-dir/temp" ]; then

               echo "ERROR: No tempoary directory found!"
               echo
               echo "Attempting to create"
               cd ~agnea1
               cd backup-dir
               mkdir temp
               echo "Directory Made - temp"
       fi

       if [ "$1" = "" ]; then

               echo "ERROR: enter in a machine name (ie: cdwriter)"
               exit 1
       fi

       if [ "$2" = "" ]; then

               echo "ERROR: enter in a SMB (Lan Manager) Resource (ie: work)"
               exit 1
       fi

       if [ "$3" = "" ]; then

               echo "ERROR: enter in an IP address for $1 (ie:
               130.xxx.xxx.52)" exit 1
       fi


       #############################################################################
       # Main Section
       #
       #############################################################################

       cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp
       rm -r ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp/*
       cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/

       case "$checkdate"
       in
               Mon)
                       echo "Backuping for Monday"
                       cat backup-data | /usr/local/samba/bin/smbclient
                       \\\\$1\\$2 -I$3 -N echo "Complete"

                               if [ -d "~agnea1/backup-dir/Monday" ]; then
                                       echo "Directory Monday Not found ...
                                       making" mkdir
                                       ~agnea1/backup-dir/Monday
                               fi

                  echo "Archiving ..."
                  cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp
                  tar -cf monday.tar *                echo "done ..."
                  rm ~agnea1/backup-dir/Monday/monday.tar
                  mv monday.tar ~agnea1/backup-dir/Monday
                  ;;


          Tue)
                  echo "Backuping for Tuesday"
                  cat backup-data | /usr/local/samba/bin/smbclient
                  \\\\$1\\$2 -I$3 -N echo "Complete"

                          if [ -d "~agnea1/backup-dir/Tuesday" ]; then
                                  echo "Directory Tuesday Not found ...
                                  making" mkdir
                                  ~agnea1/backup-dir/Tuesday
                          fi
                  echo "Archiving ..."
                  cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp
                  tar -cf tuesday.tar *
                  echo "done ..."
                  rm ~agnea1/backup-dir/Tuesday/tuesday.tar
                  mv tuesday.tar ~agnea1/backup-dir/Tuesday
                  ;;

          Wed)
                  echo "Backuping for Wednesday"
                  cat backup-data | /usr/local/samba/bin/smbclient
                  \\\\$1\\$2 -I$3 -N echo "Complete"

                          if [ -d "~agnea1/backup-dir/Wednesday" ]; then
                                  echo "Directory Wednesday Not found
                                  ... making" mkdir
                                  ~agnea1/backup-dir/Wednesday
                          fi
                  echo "Archiving ..."
                  cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp
                  tar -cf wednesday.tar *
                  echo "done ..."
               rm ~agnea1/backup-dir/Wednesday/wednesday.tar
                  mv wednesday.tar ~agnea1/backup-dir/Wednesday
                  ;;

          Thu)
                  echo "Backuping for Thrusday"
                  cat backup-data | /usr/local/samba/bin/smbclient
                  \\\\$1\\$2 -I$3 -N echo "Complete"

                          if [ -d "~agnea1/backup-dir/Thursday" ]; then
                                  echo "Directory Thrusday Not found ...
                                  making" mkdir
                                  ~agnea1/backup-dir/Thursday
                          fi
                  echo "Archiving ..."
                  cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp
                  tar -cf thursday.tar *
                  echo "done ..."
                  rm ~agnea1/backup-dir/Thursday/thursday.tar
                  mv thursday.tar ~agnea1/backup-dir/Thursday
                  ;;


          Fri)
                  echo "Backuping for Friday"
                  cat backup-data | /usr/local/samba/bin/smbclient
                  \\\\$1\\$2 -I$3 -N echo "Complete"

                          if [ -d "~agnea1/backup-dir/Friday" ]; then
                                  echo "Directory Friday Not found ...
                                  making" mkdir
                                  ~agnea1/backup-dir/Friday
                          fi
                  echo "Archiving ..."
                  cd ~agnea1/backup-dir/temp
                  tar -cf friday.tar *
                  echo "done ..."
                  rm ~agnea1/backup-dir/Friday/friday.tar
                  mv friday.tar ~agnea1/backup-dir/Friday
                  ;;

          *)
                  echo "FATAL ERROR: Unknown variable passed for day"
                  exit 1;;

  esac
  ###########
  ______________________________________________________________________



  Here's Dan's backup script:



  ______________________________________________________________________
  #!/bin/bash

  BACKDIR=3D/backup
  WINCMD=3D/usr/bin/smbclient

  function CopyWinHost(){

  # tars and gzips "windows shares" to a local directory using samba's
  # smbclient
  # argument 1 is the remote host window's host name
  # argument 2 is the share name to be backed up

     echo $1,$2,$3
     REMOTE=3D$1
     SHARE=3D$2
     DEST=3D$3

   # create a tarred gzip file using samba to copy direct from a
   # windows pc
   # 12345 is a password.  Needs some password even if not defined on
   # remote system
     $WINCMD \\\\$REMOTE\\$SHARE 12345 -Tc -|gzip > $DEST
     echo `date`": Done backing up "$REMOTE" to "$DEST
     echo
  }

  function CopyUnixHost(){

  # tars and gzips a directory using rsh
  # argument 1 is the name of the remote source host
  # argument 2 is the full path to the remote source directory
  # argument 3 is the name of the local tar-gzip file.  day of week
  #  plus .tgz will be appended to argument 3

     REMOTE=3D$1
     SRC=3D$2
     DEST=3D$3


     if rsh $REMOTE tar -cf - $SRC |gzip > $DEST; then
        echo `date`": Done backing up "$REMOTE":"$SRC" to "$DEST
     else
       echo `date`": Error backing up "$REMOTE":"$SRC" to "$DEST
     fi

  }

  # $1: win=3Dbackup windows machine, unix=3Dbackup unix machine
  case $1 in
     win)
        # $2=3D remote windows name, $3=3Dremote share name,
        # $4=3Dlocal destination directory
        CopyWinHost $2 $3 $4;;
     unix)
        # $2 =3D remote host, $3 =3D remote directory,
        # $4 =3D destination name
        CopyUnixHost $2 $3 $4;;
  esac
  ______________________________________________________________________



  12.  Using Samba Across Routed Networks

  Andrew Tridgell states that SMB host browsing across routers is
  problematic.  Here are his suggestions to allow this:

  -------------------------------------------------------------- For
  cross-subnet (ie. routed) browsing you should do the following. There
  are other methods but they are much more complex are error prone:

  1) all computers that you want visible should use a single WINS server
  (Samba or NT can do this)

  2) the master browser for each subnet must be either NT or Samba.
  (Win9X doesn't communicate cross-subnet browse info correctly)

  3) You should use the same workgroup name on all subnets. This is not
  strictly necessary but it is the simplest way to guarantee success. If
  you can't arrange this then you must organise for a way for browse
  info to propogate between subnets. (It does *not* propogate via WINS).
  It propogates via two mechanisms: i) each browse master notices
  workgroup announcements from other browse masters on the same
  broadcast domain ii) each non-Win9X browse master contacts the global
  DMB for the workgroup (typically the domain controller or a Samba box
  marked as the domain master) and swaps full browse info periodically.
  --------------------------------------------------------------

  Also, Rakesh Bharania points out that Cisco routers can be configured
  to forward SMB traffic in a way that allows browsing.  His suggestion
  is to configure the router interface which hosts SMB clients with a
  command like this:



       ______________________________________________________________________
       ip helper-address x.x.x.x
       ______________________________________________________________________



  where x.x.x.x is the IP address of the SMB server.



  13.  Acknowledgements

  Special thanks to Andrew Tridgell (tridge@linuxcare.com) for starting
  and directing the Samba project and for keeping this document honest.

  Brad Marshall (bmarshall@plugged.net.au) and Jason Parker
  (jparker@plugged.net.au) contributed time, patience, scripting and
  research.

  Adam Neat (adamneat@ipax.com.au) and Dan Tager (dtager@marsala.com)
  contributed the bash scripts used to back up Windows machines to a
  Linux host.

  Matthew Flint () told me about the use of the 'interfaces' option in
  smb.conf.

  Oleg L. Machulskiy (machulsk@shade.msu.ru), Jeff Stern
  (jstern@eclectic.ss.uci.edu), Dr. Michael Langner (langner@fiz-
  chemie.de and Erik Ratcliffe (erik@caldera.com) suggested
  modifications to the section on Sharing A Linux Printer With Windows
  Machines.

  Alberto Menegazzi (flash.egon@iol.it) contributed the MagicFilter
  setup to enable a Linux machine to share a Windows printer.

  Rakesh Bharania (rbharani@cisco.com) contributed the suggestion for
  Cisco router configuration.

  Rich Gregory (rtg2t@virginia.edu) and others suggested that this
  document show some details about the smbfs package and its use.

  Andrea Girotto (icarus@inca.dei.unipd.it) contributed a number of
  valuable suggestions throughout the document.

  Thanks, also, to all of the international translators that have
  brought this HOWTO to the non-English speaking world: Takeo Nakano
  (nakano@apm.seikei.ac.jp), Klaus-Dieter Schumacher (Klaus-
  Dieter.Schumacher@fernuni-hagen.de), Andrea Girotto
  (icarus@inca.dei.unipd.it), Mathieu Arnold (arn_mat@club-internet.fr),
  Stein Oddvar Rasmussen (Stein@kongsberg-energi.no) Nilo Menezes
  (nmenezes@n3.com.br) and many others for whom I don't have contact
  details.

</sect1>
