<sect1 id="VNC">

<title>VNC</title>

  8.13.  Tunnelling, mobile IP and virtual private networks

  The Linux kernel allows the tunnelling (encapsulation) of protocols.
  It can do IPX tunnelling through IP, allowing the connection of two
  IPX networks through an IP only link. It can also do IP-IP tunnelling,
  which it is essential for mobile IP support, multicast support and
  amateur radio. (see
  http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/NET3-4-HOWTO-6.html#ss6.8)

  Mobile IP specifies enhancements that allow transparent routing of IP
  datagrams to mobile nodes in the Internet.  Each mobile node is always
  identified by its home address, regardless of its current point of
  attachment to the Internet.  While situated away from its home, a
  mobile node is also associated with a care-of address, which provides
  information about its current point of attachment to the Internet.
  The protocol provides for registering the care-of address with a home
  agent.  The home agent sends datagrams destined for the mobile node
  through a tunnel to the care-of address.  After arriving at the end of
  the tunnel, each datagram is then delivered to the mobile node.

  Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol (PPTP) is a networking technology
  that allows the use of the Internet as a secure virtual private
  network (VPN). PPTP is integrated with the Remote Access Services
  (RAS) server which is built into Windows NT Server. With PPTP, users
  can dial into a local ISP, or connect directly to the Internet, and
  access their network as if they were at their desks. PPTP is a closed
  protocol and its security has recently being compromised. It is highly
  recomendable to use other Linux based alternatives, since they rely on
  open standards which have been carefully examined and tested.


    A client implementation of the PPTP for Linux is available  here
     <http://www.pdos.lcs.mit.edu/~cananian/Projects/PPTP/>

    More on Linux PPTP can be found here
     <http://bmrc.berkeley.edu/people/chaffee/linux_pptp.html>

     Mobile IP:

    http://www.hpl.hp.com/personal/Jean_Tourrilhes/MobileIP/mip.html

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/NET3-4-HOWTO-6.html#ss6.12

     Virtual Private Networks related documents:


    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/mini/VPN.html

    http://sites.inka.de/sites/bigred/devel/cipe.html


7.4.  VNC

  VNC stands for Virtual Network Computing. It is, in essence, a remote
  display system which allows one to view a computing 'desktop'
  environment not only on the machine where it is running, but from
  anywhere on the Internet and from a wide variety of machine
  architectures. Both clients and servers exist for Linux as well as for
  many other platforms. It is possible to execute MS-Word in a Windows
  NT or 95 machine and have the output displayed in a Linux machine. The
  opposite is also true; it is possible to execute an application in a
  Linux machine and have the output displayed in any other Linux or
  Windows machine. One of the available clients is a Java applet,
  allowing the remote display to be run inside a web browser. Another
  client is a port for Linux using the SVGAlib graphics library,
  allowing 386s with as little as 4 MB of RAM to become fully functional
  X-Terminals.

    VNC web site <http://www.orl.co.uk/vnc/>

<para>
Virtual Network Computing (VNC) allows a user to operate a session running on another machine.
Although Linux and all other Unix-like OSes already have this functionality built in, VNC
provides further advantages because it's cross-platform, running on Linux, BSD, Unix, Win32,
MacOS, and PalmOS. This makes it far more versatile.

For example, let's assume the machine that you are attempting to connect to is running Linux.
You can use VNC to access applications running on that other Linux desktop. You can also use
VNC to provide technical support to users on Window's based machines by taking control of
their desktops from the comfort of your server room. VNC is usually installed as seperate
packages for the client and server, typically named 'vnc' and 'vnc-server'.

VNC uses screen numbers to connect clients to servers. This is because Unix machines allow
multiple graphical sessions to be stated simultaneously (check this out by logging in to a
virtual terminal and typing startx -- :1).

For platforms (Windows, MacOS, Palm, etc) which don't have this capability, you'll connect
to 'screen 0' and take over the session of the existing user. For Unix systems, you'll need
to specify a higher number and receive a new desktop.

If you prefer the Windows-style approach where the VNC client takes over the currently
running display, you can use x0rfbserver - see the sidebox below.

VNC Servers and Clients

On Linux, the VNC server (which allows the machine to be used remotely) is actually
run as a replacement X server. To be able to start a VNC session to a machine, log
into it and run vncserver. You'll be prompted for a password -  in future you can
change this password with the vncpasswd command. After you enter the password, you'll
be told the display number of the newly created machine.

It is possible to control a remote macine by using the vncviewer command. If it is
typed on its own it will prompt for a remote machine, or you can use:
vncviewer [host]:[screen-number]

> The VPN HOWTO, deprecated!!!!
> VPN HOWTO
> Linux VPN Masquerade HOWTO
</para>

  10.  References

  10.1.  Web Sites

  Cipe Home Page <http://sites.inka.de/~bigred/devel/cipe.html>

  Masq Home Page <http://ipmasq.cjb.net>

  Samba Home Page <http://samba.anu.edu.au>

  Linux HQ <http://www.linuxhq.com>  ---great site for lots of linux
  info

  10.2.  Documentation

  cipe.info: info file included with cipe distribution

  Firewall HOWTO, by Mark Grennan, markg@netplus.net

  IP Masquerade mini-HOWTO,by  Ambrose Au, ambrose@writeme.com

  IPChains-Howto, by Paul Russell, Paul.Russell@rustcorp.com.au

</sect1>
