<sect1 id="Web-Serving">

12.5. HTTP, an application protocol

Now let's get back to our example. Web browsers and servers speak an
application protocol that runs on top of TCP/IP, using it simply as a way to
pass strings of bytes back and forth. This protocol is called HTTP
(Hyper-Text Transfer Protocol) and we've already seen one command in it ??
the GET shown above.

When the GET command goes to www.tldp.org's webserver with service number 80,
it will be dispatched to a server daemon listening on port 80. Most Internet
services are implemented by server daemons that do nothing but wait on ports,
watching for and executing incoming commands.

If the design of the Internet has one overall rule, it's that all the parts
should be as simple and human-accessible as possible. HTTP, and its relatives
(like the Simple Mail Transfer Protocol, SMTP, that is used to move
electronic mail between hosts) tend to use simple printable-text commands
that end with a carriage-return/line feed.

This is marginally inefficient; in some circumstances you could get more
speed by using a tightly-coded binary protocol. But experience has shown that
the benefits of having commands be easy for human beings to describe and
understand outweigh any marginal gain in efficiency that you might get at the
cost of making things tricky and opaque.

Therefore, what the server daemon ships back to you via TCP/IP is also text.
The beginning of the response will look something like this (a few headers
have been suppressed):
HTTP/1.1 200 OK                                                              
Date: Sat, 10 Oct 1998 18:43:35 GMT                                          
Server: Apache/1.2.6 Red Hat                                                 
Last-Modified: Thu, 27 Aug 1998 17:55:15 GMT                                 
Content-Length: 2982                                                         
Content-Type: text/html                                                      

These headers will be followed by a blank line and the text of the web page
(after which the connection is dropped). Your browser just displays that
page. The headers tell it how (in particular, the Content-Type header tells
it the returned data is really HTML).
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------
	
<title>Web-Serving</title>

<para>
The World Wide Web provides a simple method of publishing and linking information across the Internet,
and is responsible for popularising the Internet to its current level. In the simplest case, a Web
client (or browser), such as Netscape or Internet Explorer, connects with a Web server using a simple
request/response protocol called HTTP (Hypertext Transfer Protocol), and requests HTML (Hypertext
Markup Language) pages, images, Flash and other objects.

In mode modern situations, the Web server can also geneate pages dynamically based on information
returned from the user. Either way setting up your own Web server is extremely simple. There are
many choices for Web serving under Linux. Some servers are very mature, such as Apache, and are perfect
for small and large sites alike. Other servers programmed to be light and fast, and to have only a
limited feature set to reduce complexity. A search on freshmeat.net will reveal a multitude of servers,
but here we'll just look at two to give you an idea of how performance and features can differ between
them.
</para>

6.2.  Web Servers

  Most Linux distributions include Apache <http://www.apache.org>.
  Apache is the number one server on the internet according to
  http://www.netcraft.co.uk/survey/ . More than a half of all internet
  sites are running Apache or one of it derivatives. Apache's advantages
  include its modular design, stability and speed. Given the appropriate
  hardware and configuration it can support the highest loads: Yahoo,
  Altavista, GeoCities, and Hotmail are based on customized versions of
  this server.

  Optional support for SSL (which enables secure transactions) is also
  available at:

    http://www.apache-ssl.org/

    http://raven.covalent.net/

    http://www.c2.net/

  Related HOWTOs:

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/WWW-HOWTO.html

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Virtual-Services-HOWTO.html

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Intranet-Server-HOWTO.html

    Web servers for Linux
     <http://www.linuxlinks.com/Software/Internet/WebServers/>

  6.3.  Web Browsers

  A number of web browsers exist for the Linux platform. Netscape
  Navigator has been one of the choices from the very beginning and the
  upcoming Mozilla (http://www.mozilla.org) will have a Linux version.
  Another popular text based web browser is lynx. It is fast and handy
  when no graphical environment is available.


    Browser software for Linux
     <http://www.linuxlinks.com/Software/Internet/WebBrowsers/>

    http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/mini/Public-Web-Browser.html

Dynamic Web content generation

Web scripting languages are even more common on Linux than databases - basically, every language is
available. This includes CGI, PHP 3 and 4, Perl, JSP, ASP (via closed source applications from Chill!soft
and Halycon Software) and ColdFusion.

PHP is an open source scripting language designed to churn out dynamically produced Web content ranging
from databases to browsers. This inludes not only HTML, but also graphics, Macromedia Flash and
XML-based information. The latest versions of PHP provide impressive speed improvements, install easily
from packages and can be set up quickly. PHP is the most popular Apache module and is used by over two
million sites, including Amazon.com, US telco giant Sprint, Xoom Networks and Lycos. And unlike most other
server side scripting languages, developers (or those that employ them) can add their own functions into
the source to improve it. Supported databases include those in the Database serving section and most ODBC
compliant databases. The language itself borrows its structure from Perl and C.

</sect1>
