<sect1 id="Web-Serving">
	
<title>Web-Serving</title>

<para>
The World Wide Web provides a simple method of publishing and linking
information across the Internet, and is responsible for popularising
the Internet to its current level. In the simplest case, a Web client
(or browser), such as Netscape or Internet Explorer, connects with a
Web server using a simple request/response protocol called HTTP
(Hypertext Transfer Protocol), and requests HTML (Hypertext Markup
Language) pages, images, Flash and other objects.
</para>

<para>
In mode modern situations, the Web server can also geneate pages
dynamically based on information returned from the user. Either way
setting up your own Web server is extremely simple. There are many
choices for Web serving under Linux. Some servers are very mature,
such as Apache, and are perfect for small and large sites alike.
Other servers programmed to be light and fast, and to have only a
limited feature set to reduce complexity. A search on freshmeat.net
will reveal a multitude of servers.
</para>

<para>
Most Linux distributions include Apache <http://www.apache.org>.
Apache is the number one server on the internet according to
http://www.netcraft.co.uk/survey/ . More than a half of all internet
sites are running Apache or one of it derivatives. Apache's advantages
include its modular design, stability and speed. Given the appropriate
hardware and configuration it can support the highest loads: Yahoo,
Altavista, GeoCities, and Hotmail are based on customized versions of
this server.
</para>

<para>
Optional support for SSL (which enables secure transactions) is also
available at:
</para>

   http://www.apache-ssl.org/
   http://raven.covalent.net/
   http://www.c2.net/

Dynamic Web content generation

<para>
Web scripting languages are even more common on Linux than databases
- basically, every language is available. This includes CGI, 
PHP 3 and 4, Perl, JSP, ASP (via closed source applications from
Chill!soft and Halycon Software) and ColdFusion.
</para>

<para>
PHP is an open source scripting language designed to churn out
dynamically produced Web content ranging from databases to browsers.
This inludes not only HTML, but also graphics, Macromedia Flash and
XML-based information. The latest versions of PHP provide impressive
speed improvements, install easily from packages and can be set up
quickly. PHP is the most popular Apache module and is used by over
two million sites, including Amazon.com, US telco giant Sprint,
Xoom Networks and Lycos. And unlike most other server side scripting
languages, developers (or those that employ them) can add their own
functions into the source to improve it. Supported databases include
those in the Database serving section and most ODBC compliant
databases. The language itself borrows its structure from Perl and C.
</para>

   http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/WWW-HOWTO.html
   http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Virtual-Services-HOWTO.html
   http://metalab.unc.edu/mdw/HOWTO/Intranet-Server-HOWTO.html
   Web servers for Linux
    <http://www.linuxlinks.com/Software/Internet/WebServers/>
  
</sect1>
