<sect1 id="X11">

<title>X11</title>

<para>
The X Window System was developed at MIT in the late 1980s, rapidly
becoming the industry standard windowing system for Unix graphics
workstations. The software is freely available, very versatile, and is
suitable for a wide range of hardware platforms. Any X environment
consists of two distinct parts, the X server and one or more X
clients. It is important to realise the distinction between the server
and the client. The server controls the display directly and is
responsible for all input/output via the keyboard, mouse or display.
The clients, on the other hand, do not access the screen directly -
they communicate with the server, which handles all input and output.
It is the clients which do the "real" computing work - running
applications or whatever. The clients communicate with the server,
causing the server to open one or more windows to handle input and
output for that client.
</para>

<para>
In short, the X Window System allows a user to log in into a remote
machine, execute a process (for example, open a web browser) and have
the output displayed on his own machine. Because the process is
actually being executed on the remote system, very little CPU power is
needed in the local one. Indeed, computers exist whose primary purpose
is to act as pure X servers.  Such systems are called X terminals.
</para>

<para>
A free port of the X Window System exists for Linux and can be found
at: Xfree <http://www.xfree86.org/>. It is included in most Linux
distributions.
<para>

<para>
For further information regarding X please see:
</para>
		
X11, LBX, DXPC, NXServer, SSH, MAS

Related HOWTOs:

 Remote X Apps HOWTO
 Linux XDMCP HOWTO
 XDM and X Terminal mini-HOWTO
 The Linux XFree86 HOWTO
 ATI R200 + XFree86 4.x mini-HOWTO
 Second Mouse in X mini-HOWTO
 Linux Touch Screen HOWTO
 XFree86 Video Timings HOWTO
 Linux XFree-to-Xinside mini-HOWTO
 XFree Local Multi-User HOWTO
 Using Xinerama to MultiHead XFree86 V. 4.0+
 Connecting X Terminals to Linux Mini-HOWTO
 How to change the title of an xterm
 X Window System Architecture Overview HOWTO
 The X Window User HOWTO
     
</sect1>
