<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<appendix id="a">
  <title>Hosting Applications</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Analysis</title>

    <para>An operating system by itself is not much fun. What makes an OS
    great is the applications that can be run on top of it. Unfortunately,
    Pocket Linux currently does not have much room for anything other than
    system programs. Still, it would be nice to expand the system just enough
    to host some cool applications. Obviously a full-blown X-Windows GUI is
    out of the question, but running a small console based program should be
    within our reach.</para>

    <para>Rather than doing a typical "hello world" program as an example,
    application hosting will be demonstrated using a console based audio
    player called mp3blaster. Building mp3blaster offers more technical
    challenge than "hello world" and the finished product should be a lot more
    fun. However, it should not be construed that a console-based jukebox is
    the only application for Pocket Linux. On the contrary, after completing
    this phase the reader should have the knowledge and tools to build almost
    any console-based program he or she desires.</para>

    <para>So what will it take to turn a pocket-sized GNU/Linux system into a
    pocket-sized mp3 player? A few things are listed below.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add support for audio hardware.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Create space for the mp3blaster program.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Provide a convenient way to access audio files.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Design</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Support for audio hardware</title>

      <para>There is a vast proliferation of audio hardware on the market and
      each sound card has its own particular configuration. For details on how
      to set up a particular sound card we can turn to the Sound-HOWTO
      available from <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">The Linux Documentation
      Project</ulink>. In a broader sense, however, we can treat a sound card
      like any other piece of new hardware. To add new hardware to a GNU/Linux
      system we will need configure the kernel to recognize it and configure
      <filename>/dev</filename> files on the root disk to access it.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Kernel support for audio</title>

        <para>In order to support sound cards, a new kernel will have to be
        built. It is very important that audio hardware support be configured
        as built-in, because Pocket Linux is not set up to handle kernel
        modules.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Root disk support for audio</title>

        <para>Searching <filename>devices.txt</filename> for the keyword
        "sound" will list quite a few possible audio devices, but usually only
        <filename>/dev/dsp</filename> and <filename>/dev/mixer</filename> are
        required to get sound from a PC. These two files control the digital
        audio output and mixer controls, respectively.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Creating space for the program</title>

      <para>Probably the easiest way to create more space for the mp3blaster
      program is to mount an additional storage device. There are several
      choices for mount points. So far <filename>/usr</filename>,
      <filename>/home</filename> and <filename>/opt</filename> are all empty
      directories and any one of them could be used to mount a floppy, CD-ROM
      or additional compressed ramdisk image. The <filename>/usr</filename>
      directory is a logical choice for a place to put an application, but
      what about the choice of media? Mp3blaster and its required libraries
      are too big to fit on a 1.44M floppy and burning a CD-ROM seems like a
      lot of work for one little program. So given these constraints, the best
      choice would be to put the program on a compressed floppy.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Mounting additional compressed floppies</title>

        <para>Mounting CD's and uncompressed diskettes is easy, but what about
        loading compressed images from floppy into ramdisk? It will have to be
        done manually, because automatic mounting of compressed floppies only
        works for the root diskette. And using <command>mount
        /dev/fd0</command> will not work because there is no filesystem on the
        diskette, there are only the contents of a gzip file. The actual
        filesystem is contained inside the gzip file. So how can we mount the
        filesystem buried beneath the gzip file? This puzzle can be solved by
        examining at the steps used to create the familiar compressed root
        disk floppy.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A ramdisk is created, mounted and filled with files.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The ramdisk device is unmounted.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The contents of the ramdisk are dumped to an image file
            using <command>dd</command>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The image file is compressed with
            <command>gzip</command>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The compressed image file is written to floppy with
            <command>dd</command>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>If that is how the compressed image makes its way from ramdisk
        to compressed floppy, then going from compressed floppy to ramdisk
        should be as simple as running through the steps in reverse.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The compressed image file is read from floppy with
            <command>dd</command>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The image file is uncompressed with
            <command>gunzip</command>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The contents of the image file are dumped into ramdisk using
            <command>dd</command>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The ramdisk device is mounted.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The files are available.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>We can cut out the intermediate image file by using a pipe to
        combine <command>dd</command> and <command>gunzip</command> like this:
        <command>dd if=/dev/fd0 | gunzip -cq &gt; /dev/ram1</command>. Now the
        compressed floppy goes straight into ramdisk, decompressing on the
        fly.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Root disk support for additional ramdisks</title>

        <para>We already have kernel support for ramdisks, because we are
        using a compressed root disk, but we will need to create more ramdisks
        in <filename>/dev</filename>. Typically the kernel supports eight
        ramdisks on <filename>/dev/ram0</filename> through
        <filename>/dev/ram7</filename> with <filename>ram0</filename> being
        used for the rootdisk. The <filename>devices.txt</filename> file
        included in the Linux source code documentation will be helpful for
        matching devices to their major and minor numbers.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Accessing audio files</title>

      <para>The sample mp3 file that we will be using in our example is small
      enough to fit on an uncompressed floppy disk so that there is no need to
      burn a CD. However, serious music lovers may want to have the capability
      to mount a custom CD-ROM full of tunes and that option will require
      support for additional hardware.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>CD-ROM hardware support</title>

        <para>Most modern CD-ROM drives will use IDE devices like
        <filename>/dev/hdc</filename> or <filename>/dev/hdd</filename>. To
        support these CD-ROM drives we will have to configure IDE support in
        the kernel and create the appropriate device files on the root
        disk.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>CD-ROM filesystem support</title>

        <para>CD-ROM's have different filesystems than hard disks and
        floppies. Most CD burning applications use a filesystem called
        ISO-9660 and have the capability to support joliet or rockridge
        extensions. We will have to include support for these filesystems in
        the kernel in order to mount CD-ROM's.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Other required files</title>

      <para>We will want to have all of mp3blaster's required libraries and
      other supporting files available as part of the compressed
      <filename>/usr</filename> image so that mp3blaster can run correctly.
      The familiar <command>ldd</command> command can be used to determine
      which libraries mp3blaster requires. Any additional libraries can be
      placed in <filename>/usr/lib</filename>. Even though some of the
      libraries may appear in <filename>/lib</filename> on the development
      system, they can still go in <filename>/usr/lib</filename> on the Pocket
      Linux system. The dynamic linker, <filename>ld-linux.so</filename>, is
      smart enough to look in both places when loading libraries.</para>

      <para>Because mp3blaster uses the curses (or ncurses) screen control
      library there is one additional file we need. The curses library needs
      to know the characteristics of the terminal it is controlling and it
      gets that information from the terminfo database. The terminfo database
      consists of all the files under the
      <filename>/usr/share/terminfo</filename> directory and is very large
      compared to our available disk space. But, since Pocket Linux only
      supports the PC console, we only have one terminal type to worry about
      and therefore need only one file. The piece of the terminfo database we
      need is the file <filename>/usr/share/terminfo/l/linux</filename>,
      because we are using a "Linux" terminal. For more information about the
      subject of curses, see John Strang's book entitled "Programming with
      Curses" available from <ulink url="http://www.oreilly.com">O'Reilly
      publishing</ulink>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Summary of tasks</title>

      <para>Between sound cards, ramdisks, CD-ROM's and terminfo there is
      quite a bit to keep track of. So let's take a moment to organize and
      summarize the tasks necessary to make the pocket jukebox a
      reality.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a new kernel disk that includes built-in support for
          audio hardware, IDE devices and CD-ROM filesystems.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create the appropriate <filename>/dev</filename> files on the
          root disk to support audio hardware, additional ramdisks and IDE
          CD-ROM's.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Install the <command>gunzip</command> utility to enable
          decompression of the usr image.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create a startup script to load a compressed image from floppy
          into a ramdisk and mount the ramdisk on
          <filename>/usr</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create a compressed floppy that holds the mp3blaster program,
          its required libraries and terminfo files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Construction</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Create an enhanced boot disk</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Build a new kernel</title>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd /usr/src/linux
bash# make menuconfig</programlisting></para>

        <para>Be sure to configure support for the following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>386 processor</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Floppy disk</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RAM disk</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Second extended (ext2) filesystem</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Virtual console</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Audio hardware</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>CD-ROM hardware</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ISO-9660 and Joliet filesystems</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><programlisting>bash# make dep
bash# make clean
bash# make bzImage</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Copy the kernel to diskette</title>

        <para>Place the boot disk in drive fd0</para>

        <para><programlisting>bash# mount /dev/fd0 /mnt
bash# cp /usr/src/linux/arch/i386/boot/bzImage /mnt/boot/vmlinuz</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Unmount the boot disk</title>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd /
bash# umount /mnt</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Create an enhanced root disk</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Create additional device files</title>

        <sect4>
          <title>IDE CD-ROM</title>

          <para><programlisting>bash# mknod -m640 ~/staging/dev/hdc b 22 0
bash# mknod -m640 ~/staging/dev/hdd b 22 64</programlisting></para>

          <para>Optionally create additional IDE devices.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Ramdisk</title>

          <para><programlisting>bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram1 b 1 1
bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram2 b 1 2 
bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram3 b 1 3
bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram4 b 1 4
bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram5 b 1 5
bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram6 b 1 6
bash# mknod -m 640 ~/staging/dev/ram7 b 1 7</programlisting></para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Audio</title>

          <para><programlisting>bash# mknod -m664 ~/staging/dev/dsp c 14 3
bash# mknod -m664 ~/staging/dev/mixer c 14 0</programlisting></para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Install the gunzip binary</title>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd /usr/src/gzip-1.2.4a
bash# export CC="gcc -mcpu=i386"
bash# ./configure --host=i386-pc-linux-gnu
bash# make
bash# strip gzip
bash# cp gzip ~/staging/bin
bash# ln -s gzip ~/staging/bin/gunzip</programlisting></para>

        <para>Don't forget to verify library requirements, check the ownership
        and check permissions on the gzip binary.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Write a startup script to mount a compressed floppy</title>

        <para>Use a text editor to create the following script and save it as
        <filename>~/staging/etc/init.d/usr_image</filename></para>

        <para><programlisting>#!/bin/sh
#
# usr_image - load compressed images from floppy into ramdisk and
#             mount on /usr.
#
echo -n "Is there a compressed diskette to load for /usr [y/N]? "
read REPLY
if [ "$REPLY" = "y" ] || [ "$REPLY" = "Y" ]; then
  echo -n "Please insert the /usr floppy into fd0 and press &lt;ENTER&gt;."
  read REPLY
  echo "Clearing /dev/ram1."
  dd if=/dev/zero of=/dev/ram1 bs=1k count=4096
  echo "Loading compressed image from /dev/fd0 into /dev/ram1..."
  (dd if=/dev/fd0 bs=1k | gunzip -cq) &gt;/dev/ram1 2&gt;/dev/null
  fsck -fp /dev/ram1
  if [ $(($?)) -gt $((1)) ]; then
    echo "Filesystem errors on /dev/ram1!  Manual intervention required."
  else
    echo "Mounting /usr."
    mount /dev/ram1 /usr
  fi
fi
#
# end of usr_image</programlisting></para>

        <para>Configure the script to run right after root is mounted.</para>

        <para><programlisting>bash# ln -s ../init.d/usr_image ~/staging/etc/rcS.d/S21usr_image</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Create a compressed root disk</title>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd /
bash# dd if=/dev/zero of=/dev/ram7 bs=1k count=4096
bash# mke2fs -m0 /dev/ram7
bash# mount /dev/ram7 /mnt
bash# cp -dpR ~/staging/* /mnt
bash# umount /dev/ram7
bash# dd if=/dev/ram7 of=~/phase8-image bs=1k
bash# gzip -9 ~/phase8-image</programlisting></para>

        <para>Insert the diskette labled "root disk" into drive fd0.</para>

        <para><programlisting>bash# dd if=~/phase8-image.gz of=/dev/fd0 bs=1k</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Create a compressed /usr disk for mp3blaster</title>

      <para>The compressed /usr diskette will be created in using the same
      process that is used to create the compressed root disk. We will copy
      files to a staging area, copy the staging area to ramdisk, compress the
      ramdisk and write it to diskette.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Create a staging area</title>

        <para><programlisting>bash# mkdir ~/usr-staging
bash# cd ~/usr-staging
bash# mkdir bin lib
bash# mkdir -p share/termcap/l</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Install the mp3blaster program</title>

        <para>Download the latest version of mp3blaster source code from its
        home at <ulink
        url="http://www.stack.nl/~brama/mp3blaster/">http://www.stack.nl/~brama/mp3blaster/</ulink>.</para>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd ~/usr/src/mp3blaster-3.2.0
bash# ./configure
bash# make
bash# cp src/mp3blaster ~/usr-staging/bin</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Copy additional libraries and terminfo</title>

        <para>Use <command>ldd</command> to find out which libraries are
        needed for mp3blaster.</para>

        <note>
          <para>The following is an example from the author's development
          system. It is possible that different systems may yield slightly
          different results in terms of library requirements.</para>
        </note>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd ~/usr-staging/lib
bash# ldd ~/usr-staging/bin/mp3blaster
bash# cp /usr/lib/ncurses.so.5.0  .
bash# cp /usr/lib/stdc++.so.3 .
bash# cp /lib/libm.so.6 .
bash# cp /usr/lib/libgcc_s.so.1 .
bash# cd ~/usr-staging/share/terminfo/l
bash# cp /usr/share/terminfo/l/linux .</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Make a compressed image and copy it to diskette</title>

        <para><programlisting>bash# cd /
bash# dd if=/dev/zero of=/dev/ram7 bs=1k count=4096
bash# mke2fs -m0 /dev/ram7
bash# mount /dev/ram7 /mnt
bash# cp -dpR ~/usr-staging/* /mnt
bash# umount /dev/ram7
bash# dd if=/dev/ram7 of=~/mp3blaster-image bs=1k
bash# gzip -9 ~/mp3blaster-image</programlisting></para>

        <para>Insert the diskette labled "mp3blaster" into drive fd0.</para>

        <para><programlisting>bash# dd if=~/mp3blaster-image.gz of=/dev/fd0 bs=1k</programlisting></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Create a data diskette for testing</title>

      <para>Go to the internet site <ulink
      url="http://www.paul.sladen.org">http://www.paul.sladen.org</ulink> and
      download the mp3 file of Linus Torvalds pronouncing "Linux." The direct
      link is: <ulink
      url="http://www.paul.sladen.org/pronunciation/torvalds-says-linux.mp3">http://www.paul.sladen.org/pronunciation/torvalds-says-linux.mp3</ulink>.
      Create a Second Extended (ext2) filesystem on a floppy and copy the mp3
      file onto the diskette.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Implementation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>System Startup</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Boot from the kernel diskette.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Insert the root floppy when prompted.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When prompted for a /usr diskette, say 'Y'.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Insert the mp3blaster diskette and press
          <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Verify that the /usr diskette loaded properly</title>

      <para><programlisting>bash# mount
bash# ls -lR /usr</programlisting></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Check the audio device initialization</title>

      <para><programlisting>bash# dmesg | more</programlisting></para>

      <para>If everything worked there should be a line or two indicating that
      the kernel found the audio hardware. The example below shows how the
      kernel might report a Yamaha integrated sound system.</para>

      <para><screen>ymfpci: YMF740C at 0xf4000000 IRQ 10
ac97_codec: AC97 Audio codec, id: 0x4144:0x5303 (Analog Devices AD1819)
</screen></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Test audio output</title>

      <para><programlisting>bash# echo "Garbage" &gt; /dev/dsp</programlisting></para>

      <para>A short burst of static coming from the PC speakers indicates that
      sound is working.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Play a sample file</title>

      <para>Insert the diskette containing the sample audio file.</para>

      <para><programlisting>mount /dev/fd0 /home
bash# /usr/bin/mp3blaster</programlisting></para>

      <para>Use mp3blaster to select and play the file
      <filename>/home/torvalds-says-linux.mp3</filename>. Use mp3blaster's
      mixer controls to adjust the volume as needed.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>System shutdown</title>

      <para>Bring the system down gracefully with the
      <command>shutdown</command> command.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</appendix>