<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<preface>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>About Pocket Linux</title>

    <para>The Pocket Linux Guide demonstrates how to build a small
    console-based GNU/Linux system using only source code and a couple of
    diskettes. It is intended for Linux users who would like to gain a deeper
    understanding about how their system works beneath the shroud of
    distribution specific features and tools. </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Prerequisite Skills</title>

    <para>This guide is intended for intermediate to advanced Linux users. It
    is not intentionally obscure, but certain assumptions about the readers
    skill level are made. Success with this guide depends in part on being
    able to perform the following tasks: </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use basic shell commands</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Reference man and info pages</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Build a custom Linux kernel</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Compile source code using make and related tools</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Project Format</title>

    <para> The Pocket Linux Guide takes a hands-on approach to learning. The
    guide is written with each chapter building a piece of an overall project.
    Chapters are further broken into sections of Analysis, Design,
    Construction and Implementation. This format is derived from Rapid
    Application Development (RAD) methodology. Without going into detail about
    design methodologies, the sections may be summed up as follows. </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Analysis section gives a high-level overview of what is to
        be accomplished in each chapter. It will introduce the tasks that need
        to be completed and why they are important to the overall
        system.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Design section defines the source code packages, files and
        configuration necessary to address the requirements set forth in the
        Analysis section. Much of the theory of why certain system files exist
        and what their purpose is can be found here.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Construction section is where all the hands-on action takes
        place. This section goes into detail about building source code and
        configuring the system files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Implementation section will test the proper operation of the
        project at the end of each chapter. Often there are a few shell
        commands to perform and samples of expected screen outputs are
        given.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para> Readers interested in learning more about RAD may want to consult a
    textbook covering systems analysis and design or visit the following
    University of California, Davis website on the subject: <ulink
    url="http://sysdev.ucdavis.edu/WEBADM/document/rad-stages.htm">http://sysdev.ucdavis.edu/WEBADM/document/rad-stages.htm</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Help &amp; Support</title>

    <para> Readers are encouraged to visit the Pocket Linux Resource Site at
    <ulink
    url="http://pocket-linux.sourceforge.net">http://pocket-linux.sourceforge.net/</ulink>.
    The resource site is home to: </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Information about the Pocket Linux mailing list.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A web-based troubleshooting forum where readers can ask
        questions and give tips to others.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A collection of diskette images for various chapters.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Additional projects that may be of interest to Pocket Linux
        Guide readers.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Feedback</title>

    <para> For technical questions about Pocket Linux please use the mailing
    list or the troubleshooting forum on the <ulink
    url="http://pocket-linux.sourceforge.net">resource site</ulink>. General
    comments and suggestions may be sent to the mailing list or emailed to the
    author directly.</para>
  </sect1>
</preface>