<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="wrap-up">
  <title>Project Wrap Up</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Celebrating Accomplishments</title>

    <para>As the Pocket Linux Project draws to a close we should take a moment
    to celebrate all of our accomplishments. Some of the highlights are listed
    below:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>We have built a system, from source code only, that fully
        implements all of the commands described in the Filesystem Hierarchy
        Standard requirements for a root filesystem.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>We have learned how to use Internet resources to locate and
        download the source code needed to build a GNU/Linux system.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>We have written basic system startup and shutdown scripts and
        configured them to execute in the proper runlevels.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>We have included support for multiple users on virtual consoles
        and implemented permissions on system files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>But most importantly, we have learned some good design
        techniques and project management skills that will enable us to tackle
        any future projects with ease and confidence.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Planning Next Steps</title>

    <para>The Pocket Linux system is nearly overflowing, so there really is no
    more room to expand the current root diskette to support any additional
    commands and features. This leaves us with a few choices of where to go
    next. We can:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Find a way to expand the current system just enough to host a
        small application. (For more information about hosting applications
        with Pocket Linux, see Appendix A)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Remove multi-user capability and some of the less often used
        commands from the root disk, replacing them with utilities like tar
        and gzip that would be useful for a rescue/restore diskset.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use the techniques we have learned to design and build an entire
        GNU/Linux system and install it on a more spacious hard disk
        partition. (For more infomation about building a larger system, check
        out the GNU/Linux System Architect Toolkit at: <ulink
        url="http://architect.sourceforge.net/">http://architect.sourceforge.net/</ulink>.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Which ever path is chosen, we can move forward confidently, armed
    with the knowledge we need to be successful in our endeavors.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>