<sect1 id="ch01-administrativa">
<title>Resources</title>
<?dbhtml filename="resources.html" dir="chapter01"?>


<sect2 id="ch01-faq">
<title>FAQ</title>

<para>If during the building of your LFS system you encounter any errors, or
have any questions, or think you found a typo in the book, then please first
consult the FAQ (Frequently Asked Questions) at
<ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/faq/"/>.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="ch01-irc">
<title>IRC</title>

<para>Several members of the LFS community offer assistance on our community
IRC server. Before you utilize this mode of support, we ask that you've
at least checked the LFS FAQ and the mailing list archives for the answer to
your question.  You can find the IRC server at
<emphasis>irc.linuxfromscratch.org</emphasis> port 6667.  The support channel
is named #LFS-support.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="ch01-maillists" xreflabel="Chapter 1 - Mailing lists">
<title>Mailing lists</title>

<para>The <emphasis>linuxfromscratch.org</emphasis> server is hosting a number
of mailing lists used for the development of the LFS project. These lists
include, among others, the main development and support lists.</para>

<para>For information on which lists are available, how to subscribe to them,
their archive locations, and so on, visit <ulink
url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/mail.html"/>.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="ch01-newsserver">
<title>News server</title>

<para>All the mailing lists hosted at <emphasis>linuxfromscratch.org</emphasis>
are also accessible via the NNTP server. All messages posted to a mailing list
will be copied to the correspondent newsgroup, and vice versa.</para>

<para>The news server can be reached at
<emphasis>news.linuxfromscratch.org</emphasis>.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="ch01-mirrors" xreflabel="Chapter 1 - Mirror sites">
<title>Mirror sites</title>

<para>The LFS project has a number of mirrors set up world-wide to make
accessing the website and downloading the required packages more convenient.
Please visit the website at <ulink url="http://www.linuxfromscratch.org/"/> for
a list of current mirrors.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="ch01-contactinfo">
<title>Contact information</title>

<para>Please direct your all your questions and comments to one of the LFS
mailing lists (see above).</para>

<para>But if you need to reach Gerard Beekmans personally, send an email to
<ulink url="mailto:gerard@linuxfromscratch.org">gerard@linuxfromscratch.org</ulink>.</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>

