<sect2><title>Contents of Autoconf</title>

<para>Last checked against version &autoconf-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>autoconf, autoheader, autom4te, autoreconf, autoscan, autoupdate and 
ifnames</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>autoconf</title>
<para>autoconf is a tool for producing shell scripts that automatically
configure software source code packages to adapt to many kinds of
Unix-like systems. The configuration scripts produced by autoconf are
independent of autoconf when they are run, so their users do not need to
have autoconf.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>autoheader</title>
<para>The autoheader program can create a template file of C #define
statements for configure to use.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>autom4te</title>
<para>autom4te runs GNU M4 on files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>autoreconf</title>
<para>If there are a lot of autoconf-generated configure scripts, the
autoreconf program can save some work. It runs autoconf and
autoheader (where appropriate) repeatedly to remake the autoconf
configure scripts and configuration header templates in the directory
tree rooted at the current directory.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>autoscan</title>
<para>The autoscan program can help to create a configure.in file for
a software package. autoscan examines the source files in a directory
tree. If a directory is not specified on the command line, then the
current working directory is used. The source files are searched for
common portability problems and a configure.scan file is created to
serve as the preliminary configure.in for that package.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>autoupdate</title>
<para>The autoupdate program updates a configure.in file that calls
autoconf macros by their old names to use the current
macro names.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ifnames</title>
<para>ifnames can help when writing a configure.in for a software
package. It prints the identifiers that the package already uses in C
preprocessor conditionals. If a package has already been set up to
have some portability, this program can help to determine what configure
needs to check. It may fill in some gaps in a configure.in file generated
by autoscan.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
