<sect2><title>Contents of Automake</title>

<para>Last checked against version &automake-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>acinstall, aclocal, aclocal-1.6, automake, automake-1.6,
compile, config.guess, config.sub, depcomp, elisp-comp, install-sh,
mdate-sh, missing, mkinstalldirs, py-compile, ylwrap</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>acinstall</title>
<para>acinstall is a script which installs aclocal-style M4 files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>aclocal, aclocal-1.6</title>
<para>automake includes a number of autoconf macros which can be used in
packages, some of which are needed by automake in certain
situations. These macros must be defined in the aclocal.m4-file
or they will not be seen by autoconf.</para>

<para>The aclocal program will automatically generate aclocal.m4 files
based on the contents of configure.in. This provides a convenient
way to get automake-provided macros without having to search around.
Also, the aclocal mechanism is extensible for use 
by other packages.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>automake, automake-1.6</title>
<para>To create all the Makefile.in's for a package, run the automake
program in the top level directory, with no arguments. automake will
automatically find each appropriate Makefile.am (by scanning
configure.in) and generate the corresponding Makefile.in.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>compile</title>
<para>compile is script which acts as a wrapper for compilers.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>config.guess</title>
<para>config.guess is a script which attempts to guess a canonical system
name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>config.sub</title>
<para>config.sub is a configuration validation subroutine script.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>depcomp</title>
<para>depcomp is a script which compiles a program while generating
dependencies as side-effects.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>elisp-comp</title>
<para>elisp-comp is a script which byte-compiles .el files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>install-sh</title>
<para>install-sh is a script which installs a program, script, or a
datafile.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>mdate-sh</title>
<para>mdate-sh is a script which prints the modification time of a file
or directory.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>missing</title>
<para>missing is a script which acts as a common stub for a few missing
GNU programs during an installation.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>mkinstalldirs</title>
<para>mkinstalldirs is a script which makes a directory
hierarchy.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>py-compile</title>
<para>py-compile is a script which compiles a Python program.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ylwrap</title>
<para>ylwrap is a script which acts as a wrapper for lex/yacc
invocations.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
