<sect2><title>Contents of LFS-bootscripts</title>

<para>Last checked against version &bootscripts-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Scripts</title>

<para>checkfs, cleanfs, functions, halt, ifdown, ifup, loadkeys, localnet,
mountfs, mountproc, network, rc, reboot, sendsignals, setclock, swap,
sysklogd and template</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>checkfs</title>
<para>The checkfs script checks the file systems just before they are
mounted (with the exception of journal and network based file
systems).</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>cleanfs</title>
<para>The cleanfs script removes files that shouldn't be preserved between
reboots, such as /var/run/*, /var/lock/*, it re-creates /var/run/utmp and
removes the possible present /etc/nologin, /fastboot and /forcefsck
files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>functions</title>
<para>The functions script contains shared functions among different
scripts such as error checking, status checking, etc.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>halt</title>
<para>The halt script halts the system.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ifdown, ifup</title>
<para>The ifdown and ifup scripts assist the network script with
network devices.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>loadkeys</title>
<para>The loadkeys script loads the proper keymap table that matches your
keyboard layout.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>localnet</title>
<para>The localnet script sets up the system's hostname and local loopback
device.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>mountfs</title>
<para>The mountfs script mounts all file systems that aren't marked noauto
or aren't network based.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>mountproc</title>
<para>The mountproc script is used to mount the proc filesystem.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>network</title>
<para>The network script sets up network interfaces (such as network cards)
and sets up the default gateway where applicable.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>rc</title>
<para>The rc script is the master runlevel control script which is
responsible for running all the other scripts one-by-one in a specific
sequence.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>reboot</title>
<para>The reboot scripts reboots the system.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>sendsignals</title>
<para>The sendsignals script makes sure every process is terminated before
the system reboots or halts.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>setclock</title>
<para>The setclock scripts resets the kernel clock to localtime in case
the hardware clock isn't set to GMT time.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>swap</title>
<para>The swap scripts enables and disables swap files and
partitions.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>sysklogd</title>
<para>The sysklogd script start and stops the system and kernel log
daemons.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>template</title>
<para>The template script is a template you can use to create your own
bootscripts for your other daemons.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>

