<sect2>
<title>Contents</title>

<para>The e2fsprogs package contains the badblocks, chattr, debugfs, 
dumpe2fs, e2fsck, e2label, fsck, fsck.ext2, lsattr, mke2fs, 
mkfs.ext2, mklost+found, tune2fs and uuidgen programs.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Description</title>

<sect3><title>badblocks</title>
<para>badblocks is used to search for bad blocks on a device (usually a disk 
partition).</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>chattr</title>
<para>chattr changes the file attributes on a Linux second extended file
system. </para></sect3>

<sect3><title>debugfs</title>
<para>The debugfs program is a file system debugger. It can be used  to examine 
and change the state of an ext2 file system.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>dumpe2fs</title>
<para>dumpe2fs prints the super block and blocks group information for the 
filesystem present on a specified device.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>e2fsck and fsck.ext2</title>
<para>e2fsck is used to check a Linux second extended file  system. fsck.ext2
does the same as e2fsck.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>e2label</title>
<para>e2label will display or change the filesystem label on the ext2 
filesystem located on the specified device.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>fsck</title>
<para>fsck is used to check and optionally repair a Linux 
file system.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>lsattr</title>
<para>lsattr lists the file attributes on a second extended 
file system.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>mke2fs and mkfs.ext2</title>
<para>mke2fs is used to create a Linux second extended file system on a device 
(usually a disk partition). mkfs.ext2 does the same as mke2fs.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>mklost+found</title>
<para>mklost+found is used to create a lost+found directory in the current 
working directory on a Linux second extended file system. mklost+found 
pre-allocates disk blocks to the directory to make it 
usable by e2fsck.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tune2fs</title>
<para>tune2fs adjusts tunable filesystem parameters on a Linux second extended 
filesystem.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>uuidgen</title>
<para>The uuidgen program creates a new universally unique identifier (UUID) 
using the libuuid library. The new UUID can reasonably be considered unique 
among all UUIDs created on the local system, and among UUIDs created on other
systems in the past and in the future.</para></sect3>

</sect2>

