<sect2><title>Contents of Gettext</title>

<para>Last checked against version &gettext-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>config.charset, config.rpath, gettext, gettextize, hostname,
msgattrib, msgcat, msgcmp, msgcomm, msgconv, msgen, msgexec, msgfilter,
msgfmt, msggrep, msginit, msgmerge, msgunfmt, msguniq, ngettext, project-id,
team-address, trigger, urlget, user-email and xgettext</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>config.charset</title>
<para>The config.charset script outputs a system-dependent table of
character encoding aliases.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>config.rpath</title>
<para>The config.rpath script outputs a system-dependent set of variables,
describing how to set the run time search path of shared libraries in an
executable.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>gettext</title>
<para>The gettext package is used for internationalization (also known as
i18n) and for localization (also known as l10n). Programs can be
compiled with Native Language Support (NLS) which enable them to output
messages in the user's native language rather than in the default English
language.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>gettextize</title>
<para>The gettextize program copies all standard gettext files into a
directory. It's used to make a package with gettext translations.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>hostname</title>
<para>The hostname program displays a network hostname in various
forms.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgattrib</title>
<para>The msgattrib program filters the messages of a translation catalog
according to their attributes and manipulates the attributes.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgcat</title>
<para>The msgcat program finds messages which are common in several raw
translations.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgcmp</title>
<para>The msgcmp program compares two raw translation files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgcomm</title>
<para>The msgcomm program searches messages which appear in several .po
files. It's used to compare how things are translated.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgconv</title>
<para>The msgconv program converts a translation catalog to a different
character encoding.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgen</title>
<para>The msgen program creates an English translation catalog.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgexec</title>
<para>The msgexec program applies a command to all translations of a
translation catalog.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgfilter</title>
<para>The msgfilter program applies a filter to all translations of a
translation catalog.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgfmt</title>
<para>The msgfmt program compiles raw translation into machine code. It's
used to create the final program/package translation file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msggrep</title>
<para>The msggrep program extracts all messages of a translation
catalog that match a given pattern or belong to some given source
files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msginit</title>
<para>The msginit program creates a new PO file, initializing the
meta information with values from the user's environment.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgmerge</title>
<para>The msgmerge program combines two raw translations into one file.
It's used to update the raw translation with the source extract.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msgunfmt</title>
<para>The msgunfmt program decompiles translation files into raw
translation text. It can only be used if the compiled versions are
available.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>msguniq</title>
<para>The msguniq program unifies duplicate translations in a translation
catalog.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ngettext</title>
<para>The ngettext program displays native language translations of a
textual message whose grammatical form depends on a number.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>project-id</title>
<para>The project-id script prints a package's identification package
version or package.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>team-address</title>
<para>The team-address script prints the team's address to stdout and
outputs additional instructions.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>trigger</title>
<para>The trigger script tests whether the current package is a GNOME or
KDE package.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>urlget</title>
<para>The urlget program gets the contents of a URL.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>user-email</title>
<para>The user-email script prints the user's email address, with
confirmation from the user.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>xgettext</title>
<para>The xgettext program extracts the message lines from the programmers' C
files. It's used to make the first translation template.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

<sect3><title>Library Files</title>
<para>libgettextlib[a,so], libgettextsrc[a,so]</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>libgettextlib</title>
<para>No description is currently available.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>libgettextsrc</title>
<para>No description is currently available.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
