<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Short descriptions</title>

<para><command>addftinfo</command> reads a troff font file and adds some
additional font-metric information that is used by the groff system.</para>

<para><command>afmtodit</command> creates a font file for use with
groff and grops.</para>

<para><command>eqn</command> compiles descriptions of equations embedded
within troff input files into commands that are understood by troff.</para>

<para><command>eqn2graph</command> converts an EQN equation into a cropped
image.</para>

<para><command>grn</command> is a groff preprocessor for gremlin files.</para>

<para><command>grodvi</command> is a driver for groff that produces TeX dvi format.</para>

<para><command>groff</command> is a front-end to the groff document
formatting system. Normally it runs the troff program and a post-processor
appropriate for the selected device.</para>

<para><command>groffer</command> displays groff files and man pages on X
and tty.</para>
<para><command>grog</command> reads files and guesses which of the groff
options -e, -man, -me, -mm, -ms, -p, -s, and -t are required for printing
files, and reports the groff command including those options.</para>

<para><command>grolbp</command> is a groff driver for Canon CAPSL printers
(LBP-4 and LBP-8 series laser printers).</para>

<para><command>grolj4</command> is a driver for groff that produces output
in PCL5 format suitable for an HP Laserjet 4 printer.</para>

<para><command>grops</command> translates the output of GNU troff to
Postscript.</para>

<para><command>grotty</command> translates the output of GNU troff into
a form suitable for typewriter-like devices.</para>

<para><command>gtbl</command> is the GNU implementation of tbl.</para>

<para><command>hpftodit</command> creates a font file for use with
groff -Tlj4 from an HP-tagged font metric file.</para>

<para><command>indxbib</command> makes an inverted index for the
bibliographic databases a specified file for use with refer, lookbib,
and lkbib.</para>

<para><command>lkbib</command> searches bibliographic databases for
references that contain specified keys and reports any references found.</para>

<para><command>lookbib</command> prints a prompt on the standard error
(unless the standard input is not a terminal), reads from the standard input
a line containing a set of keywords, searches the bibliographic databases in
a specified file for references containing those keywords, prints any
references found on the standard output and repeats this process until the
end of input.</para>

<para><command>mmroff</command> is a simple preprocessor for groff.</para>

<para><command>neqn</command> formats equations for ascii output.</para>

<para><command>nroff</command> is a script that emulates the nroff command
using groff.</para>

<para><command>pfbtops</command> translates a Postscript font in .pfb
format to ASCII.</para>

<para><command>pic</command> compiles descriptions of pictures embedded
within troff or TeX input files into commands understood by TeX or troff.</para>

<para><command>pic2graph</command> converts a PIC diagram into a cropped
image.</para>

<para><command>pre-grohtml </command> translates  the output of GNU troff
to html.</para>

<para><command>post-grohtml</command> translates the output of GNU troff
to html.</para>

<para><command>refer</command> copies the contents of a file to the
standard output, except that lines between .[ and .] are interpreted as
citations, and lines between .R1 and .R2 are interpreted as commands about
how citations are to be processed.</para>

<para><command>soelim</command> reads files and replaces lines of the form
<emphasis>.so file</emphasis> by the contents of the mentioned
<emphasis>file</emphasis>.</para>

<para><command>tbl</command> compiles descriptions of tables embedded
within troff input files into commands that are understood by troff.</para>

<para><command>tfmtodit</command> creates a font file for use with
groff -Tdvi.</para>

<para><command>troff</command> is highly compatible with Unix troff.
Usually it should be invoked using the groff command, which will also run
preprocessors and post-processors in the appropriate order and with the
appropriate options.</para>

<para><command>zsoelim</command> is the GNU implementation of soelim.</para>

</sect2>

