<sect2><title>Contents of Groff</title>

<para>Last checked against version &groff-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>addftinfo, afmtodit, eqn, geqn (link to eqn), grn, grodvi, groff, grog,
grolbp, grolj4, grops, grotty, gtbl (link to tbl), hpftodit, indxbib, lkbib,
lookbib, mmroff, neqn, nroff, pfbtops, pic, post-grohtml, pre-grohtml, refer,
soelim, tbl, tfmtodit, troff and zsoelim (link to soelim)</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>addftinfo</title>
<para>addftinfo reads a troff font file and adds some additional font-metric 
information that is used by the groff system.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>afmtodit</title>
<para>afmtodit creates a font file for use with groff and grops.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>eqn</title>
<para>eqn compiles descriptions of equations embedded within troff input files 
into commands that are understood by troff.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>geqn</title>
<para>geqn is the GNU implementation of eqn.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grn</title>
<para>grn is a groff preprocessor for gremlin files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grodvi</title>
<para>grodvi is a driver for groff that produces TeX dvi format.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>groff</title>
<para>groff is a front-end to the groff document formatting system. Normally it 
runs the troff program and a post-processor appropriate for the selected 
device.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grog</title>
<para>grog reads files and guesses which of the groff options -e, -man, -me, 
-mm, -ms, -p, -s, and -t are required for printing files, and prints the groff
command including those options on the standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grolbp</title>
<para>grolbp is a groff driver for Canon CAPSL printers (LBP-4 and LBP-8
series laser printers).</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grolj4</title>
<para>grolj4 is a driver for groff that produces output in PCL5 format suitable 
for an HP Laserjet 4 printer.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grops</title>
<para>grops translates the output of GNU troff to Postscript.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grotty</title>
<para>grotty translates the output of GNU troff into a form suitable for 
typewriter-like devices.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>gtbl</title>
<para>gtbl is the GNU implementation of tbl.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>hpftodit</title>
<para>hpftodit creates a font file for use with groff -Tlj4 from an HP
tagged font metric file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>indxbib</title>
<para>indxbib makes an inverted index for the bibliographic databases a
specified file for use with refer, lookbib, and lkbib.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>lkbib</title>
<para>lkbib searches bibliographic databases for references that contain 
specified keys and prints any references found on the 
standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>lookbib</title>
<para>lookbib prints a prompt on the standard error (unless the standard input 
is not a terminal), reads from the standard input a line containing a set 
of keywords, searches the bibliographic databases in a specified file for
references containing those keywords, prints any references found on the
standard output and repeats this process until the end of input.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>mmroff</title>
<para>mmroff is a simple preprocessor for groff.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>neqn</title>
<para>The neqn script formats equations for ascii output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>nroff</title>
<para>The nroff script emulates the nroff command using groff.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pfbtops</title>
<para>pfbtops translates a Postscript font in .pfb format 
to ASCII.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pic</title>
<para>pic compiles descriptions of pictures embedded within troff or TeX input 
files into commands that are understood by TeX or troff.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pre-grohtml and post-grohtml</title>
<para>pre- and post-grohtml translate the output of GNU troff 
to html.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>refer</title>
<para>refer copies the contents of a file to the standard output, except that 
lines between .[ and .] are interpreted as citations, and lines between .R1 
and .R2 are interpreted as commands about how citations are to be 
processed.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>soelim</title>
<para>soelim reads files and replaces lines of the form 
<emphasis>.so file</emphasis> by the contents of
<emphasis>file</emphasis>.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tbl</title>
<para>tbl compiles descriptions of tables embedded within troff input files 
into commands that are understood by troff.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tfmtodit</title>
<para>tfmtodit creates a font file for use with <userinput>groff
-Tdvi</userinput>.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>troff</title>
<para>troff is highly compatible with Unix troff. Usually it should be invoked 
using the groff command, which will also run preprocessors and 
post-processors in the appropriate order and with the appropriate 
options.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>zsoelim</title>
<para>zsoelim is the GNU implementation of soelim.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
