<sect2><title>Contents of Net-tools</title>

<para>Last checked against version &net-tools-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>

<para>arp, dnsdomainname (link to hostname), domainname (link to
hostname), hostname, ifconfig, nameif, netstat, nisdomainname (link to
hostname), plipconfig, rarp, route, slattach and ypdomainname (link to
hostname)</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>arp</title>
<para>arp is used to manipulate the kernel's ARP cache, usually to add
or delete an entry, or to dump the ARP cache.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>dnsdomainname</title>
<para>dnsdomainname shows the system's DNS domain name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>domainname</title>
<para>domainname shows or sets the system's NIS/YP domain
name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>hostname</title>
<para>hostname prints or sets the name of the current host
system.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ifconfig</title>
<para>The ifconfig command is the general command used to configure network
interfaces.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>nameif</title>
<para>nameif names network interfaces based on MAC
addresses.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>netstat</title>
<para>netstat is a multi-purpose tool used to print the network connections, 
routing tables, interface statistics, masquerade connections and multicast 
memberships.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>nisdomainname</title>
<para>nisdomainname shows or sets system's NIS/YP domain
name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>plipconfig</title>
<para>plipconfig is used to fine-tune the PLIP device parameters, hopefully 
making it faster.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>rarp</title>
<para>Akin to the arp program, the rarp program manipulates the system's 
RARP table.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>route</title>
<para>route is the general utility which is used to manipulate the IP 
routing table.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>slattach</title>
<para>slattach attaches a network interface to a serial line, i.e.. puts a 
normal terminal line into one of several "network" modes.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ypdomainname</title>
<para>ypdomainname shows or sets the system's NIS/YP domain
name.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>

