<sect2><title>Contents of Shadow</title>

<para>Last checked against version &shadow-contversion;.</para>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>chage, chfn, chpasswd, chsh, dpasswd, expiry, faillog, gpasswd, 
groupadd, groupdel, groupmod, groups, grpck, grpconv, grpunconv, lastlog,
login, logoutd, mkpasswd, newgrp, newusers, passwd, pwck, pwconv, pwunconv,
sg (link to newgrp), useradd, userdel, usermod, vigr (link to vipw) and
vipw</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>chage</title>
<para>chage changes the number of days between password changes and the date of 
the last password change.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>chfn</title>
<para>chfn changes a user's full name and other information
(office room number, office phone number, and
home phone number).</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>chpasswd</title>
<para>chpasswd reads a file of user name and password pairs from standard 
input and uses this information to update a group of 
existing users.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>chsh</title>
<para>chsh changes the user login shell.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>dpasswd</title>
<para>dpasswd adds, deletes, and updates dial-up passwords for 
user login shells.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>expiry</title>
<para>expiry checks and enforces a password expiration policy.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>faillog</title>
<para>faillog formats the contents of the failure log,/var/log/faillog, and 
maintains failure counts and limits.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>gpasswd</title>
<para>gpasswd is used to administer the /etc/group file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>groupadd</title>
<para>The groupadd command creates a new group account using the values 
specified on the command line and the default values from 
the system.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>groupdel</title>
<para>The groupdel command modifies the system account files, deleting all 
entries that refer to group.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>groupmod</title>
<para>The groupmod command modifies the system account files to reflect the 
changes that are specified on the command line.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>groups</title>
<para>groups prints the groups which a user is in.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grpck</title>
<para>grpck verifies the integrity of the system authentication 
information.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grpconv</title>
<para>grpunconv converts to shadow group files from normal 
group files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>grpunconv</title>
<para>grpunconv converts from shadow group files to normal 
group files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>lastlog</title>
<para>lastlog formats and prints the contents of the last login log, 
/var/log/lastlog. The login-name, port, and last login time will be 
printed.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>login</title>
<para>login is used to establish a new session with the system.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>logoutd</title>
<para>logoutd enforces the login time and port restrictions specified in 
/etc/porttime.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>mkpasswd</title>
<para>mkpasswd reads a file in the format given by the flags and converts it 
to the corresponding database file format.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>newgrp</title>
<para>newgrp is used to change the current group ID during a 
login session.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>newusers</title>
<para>newusers reads a file of user name and clear text password pairs and uses 
this information to update a group of existing users or to create new 
users.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>passwd</title>
<para>passwd changes passwords for user and group accounts.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pwck</title>
<para>pwck verifies the integrity of the password files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pwconv</title>
<para>pwconv converts the normal password file
to a shadowed password file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pwunconv</title>
<para>pwunconv converts a shadowed password file
to a normal password file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>sg</title>
<para>sg sets the user's GID to that of the given group, or executes a
given command as member of the given group.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>useradd</title>
<para>useradd creates a new user or update default new user 
information.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>userdel</title>
<para>userdel modifies the system account files, deleting all entries that 
refer to a specified login name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>usermod</title>
<para>usermod modifies the system account files to reflect the changes that 
are specified on the command line.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>vipw and vigr</title>
<para>vipw and vigr will edit the files /etc/passwd and /etc/group, 
respectively. With the -s flag, they will edit the shadow versions of 
those files, /etc/shadow and /etc/gshadow, respectively.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

<sect3><title>Library Files</title>
<para>libmisc.[a,so], libshadow.[a,so]</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>libmisc</title>
<para>No description is currently available.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>libshadow</title>
<para>libshadow provides common functionality for the shadow
programs.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
