<sect2><title>Contents of sh-utils-&sh-utils-contversion;</title>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>basename, chroot, date, dirname,
echo, env, expr, factor, false, groups, hostid, hostname, id, logname,
nice, nohup, pathchk, pinky, printenv, printf, pwd, seq, sleep, stty,
su, tee, test, true, tty, uname, uptime, users, who, whoami and
yes</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>basename</title>
<para>basename strips directory and suffixes from filenames.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>chroot</title>
<para>chroot runs a command or interactive shell with special 
root directory.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>date</title>
<para>date displays the current time in a specified format, or sets 
the system date.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>dirname</title>
<para>dirname strips non-directory suffixes from file name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>echo</title>
<para>echo displays a line of text.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>env</title>
<para>env runs a program in a modified environment.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>expr</title>
<para>expr evaluates expressions.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>factor</title>
<para>factor prints the prime factors of all specified 
integer numbers.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>false</title>
<para>false always exits with a status code indicating failure.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>groups</title>
<para>groups prints the groups a user is in.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>hostid</title>
<para>hostid prints the numeric identifier (in hexadecimal) for the current 
host.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>hostname</title>
<para>hostname sets or prints the name of the current host system</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>id</title>
<para>id prints the real and effective UIDs and GIDs of a user or the current
user.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>logname</title>
<para>logname prints the current user's login name.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>nice</title>
<para>nice runs a program with modified scheduling priority.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>nohup</title>
<para>nohup runs a command immune to hangups, with output to a 
non-tty</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pathchk</title>
<para>pathchk checks whether file names are valid or portable.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pinky</title>
<para>pinky is a lightweight finger utility which retrieves information about
a certain user</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>printenv</title>
<para>printenv prints all or part of the environment.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>printf</title>
<para>printf formats and prints data (the same as the printf C 
function).</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pwd</title>
<para>pwd prints the name of the current/working directory</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>seq</title>
<para>seq prints numbers in a certain range with a certain 
increment.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>sleep</title>
<para>sleep delays for a specified amount of time.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>stty</title>
<para>stty changes and prints terminal line settings.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>su</title>
<para>su runs a shell with substitute user and group IDs</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tee</title>
<para>tee reads from standard input and writes to standard output and 
files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>test</title>
<para>test checks file types and compares values.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>true</title>
<para>True always exits with a status code indicating success.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tty</title>
<para>tty prints the file name of the terminal connected to standard 
input.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>uname</title>
<para>uname prints system information.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>uptime</title>
<para>uptime tells how long the system has been running.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>users</title>
<para>users prints the user names of users currently logged in to the 
current host.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>who</title>
<para>who shows who is logged on.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>whoami</title>
<para>whoami prints the user's effective userid.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>yes</title>
<para>yes outputs a string repeatedly until killed.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>

