<sect2><title>Contents of textutils-&textutils-contversion;</title>

<sect3><title>Program Files</title>
<para>cat, cksum, comm, csplit, cut, expand,
fmt, fold, head, join, md5sum, nl, od, paste, pr, ptx, sort, split, sum,
tac, tail, tr, tsort, unexpand, uniq and wc</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>Descriptions</title>

<sect4><title>cat</title>
<para>cat concatenates file(s) or standard input to 
standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>cksum</title>
<para>cksum prints CRC checksum and byte counts of each specified
file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>comm</title>
<para>comm compares two sorted files line by line.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>csplit</title>
<para>csplit outputs pieces of a file separated  by (a) pattern(s) to files
xx01, xx02, ..., and outputs byte counts of each piece to standard 
output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>cut</title>
<para>cut prints selected parts of lines from specified files to standard 
output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>expand</title>
<para>expand converts  tabs in files to spaces, writing to standard 
output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>fmt</title>
<para>fmt reformats each paragraph in the specified file(s), writing to 
standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>fold</title>
<para>fold wraps input lines in each specified file (standard input by default),
writing to standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>head</title>
<para>Print first xx (10 by default) lines of each specified file to standard 
output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>join</title>
<para>join joins lines of two files on a common field.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>md5sum</title>
<para>md5sum prints or checks MD5 checksums.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>nl</title>
<para>nl writes each specified file to standard output, with line numbers
added.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>od</title>
<para>od writes an unambiguous representation, octal bytes by default, of a
specified file to standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>paste</title>
<para>paste writes lines consisting of the sequentially corresponding
lines from each specified file, separated by TABs, 
to standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>pr</title>
<para>pr paginates or columnates files for printing.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>ptx</title>
<para>ptx produces a permuted index of file contents.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>sort</title>
<para>sort writes sorted concatenation of files to standard 
output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>split</title>
<para>split outputs fixed-size pieces of an input file to 
PREFIXaa, PREFIXab, ...</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>sum</title>
<para>sum prints checksum and block counts for each specified 
file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tac</title>
<para>tac writes each specified file to standard output, last line
first.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tail</title>
<para>tail print the last xx (10 by default) lines of each specified file to 
standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tr</title>
<para>tr translates, squeezes, and/or deletes characters from standard
input, writing to standard output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>tsort</title>
<para>tsort writes totally ordered lists consistent with the partial ordering 
in specified files.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>unexpand</title>
<para>unexpand converts spaces in each file to tabs, writing to standard
output.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>uniq</title>
<para>Uniq removes duplicate lines from a sorted file.</para></sect4>

<sect4><title>wc</title>
<para>wc prints line, word, and byte counts for each specified file, and a
total line if more than one file is specified.</para></sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
