<sect1 id="ch01-how">
<title>How things are going to be done</title>
<?dbhtml filename="how.html" dir="chapter01"?>

<para>We are going to build the LFS system by using an already installed Linux
distribution such as Debian, SuSe, Slackware, Mandrake, RedHat, etc. There
is no need to have any kind of bootdisk. We will use an existing Linux
system as the base (since we need a compiler, linker, text editor, and
other tools).</para>

<para>After you have downloaded the necessary packages that make up an LFS
system you will create a new Linux native partition onto which the LFS system
will be installed.</para>

<para>The next step, chapter 5, will be the installation of a number of
packages that are statically linked and installed on the LFS partition.
These packages form a basic development suite which will be used to
install the actual system, and are also needed to resolve circular
dependencies. Examples of circular dependencies are: you need a compiler 
to install a compiler. You need a shell in order to install a shell. And
so on.</para>

<para>Chapter 6 installs the actual base system. We use the chroot program 
to start a new shell whose root directory will be set to the LFS
partition. This, in essence, is the same as rebooting and having the
kernel mount the LFS partition as the root partition. The reason that
we don't actually reboot, but instead chroot, is that this way you can
still use your host system. While software is being installed you can
simply switch to a different VC (Virtual Console) or X desktop and
continue using your computer as you normally would.</para>

<para>When all the software is installed, chapter 7 will setup the boot
scripts. Chapter 8 will setup the Linux boot loader and in chapter 9
there are some pointers what you can do after you finish the book. Then
you can finally reboot your system into your new LFS system, and start
to really use it.</para>

<para>This is the process in a nutshell. Detailed information on the steps
you are taking are provided in the chapters as you go through them. If
something isn't completely clear yet, don't worry. It will become very
clear shortly.</para>

<para>Please read chapter 2 carefully as it explains a few important things
you need to be aware of before you work your way through chapters 5 and
above.</para>

</sect1>

