<sect1 id="ch05-tcl">
<title>Installing Tcl-&tcl-version;</title>
<?dbhtml filename="tcl.html" dir="chapter05"?>

<screen>Estimated build time:           &tcl-time-tools; 
Estimated required disk space:  &tcl-compsize-tools;</screen>

&aa-tcl-shortdesc;
&aa-tcl-dep;

<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Installation of Tcl</title>

<para>This package and the next two are only installed to be able to run the 
test suites for GCC and Binutils. Installing three packages just for testing 
purposes may seem like overkill, but it is very reassuring, if not essential, 
to know that our most important tools are working properly.</para>

<para>Prepare Tcl for compilation:</para>

<screen><userinput>cd unix
./configure --prefix=/tools</userinput></screen>

<para>Build the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen>

<para>This package has a test suite available which can perform a number of
checks to ensure it built correctly. However, the Tcl test suite in this
chapter is known to experience failures under certain host conditions that are
not fully understood. Therefore, test suite failures here are not surprising,
but are not considered critical. Should you choose to run the test suite, the
following command will do so:</para>

<screen><userinput>TZ=UTC make test</userinput></screen>

<para>The meaning of the make parameter:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><userinput>TZ=UTC</userinput>: This sets the time zone to
Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) also known as Greenwich Mean Time (GMT), but
only for the duration of the test suite run. This ensures the clock tests are
exercised correctly. More information on the TZ environment variable is
available later on in <xref linkend="chapter07"/>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Sometimes, package test suites will give false failures.  You can
consult the LFS Wiki at <ulink url="http://wiki.linuxfromscratch.org/"/>
to verify that these failures are normal.  This applies to all tests
throughout the book.</para>

<para>Install the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make install</userinput></screen>

<important><para><emphasis>Do not remove</emphasis> the
<filename>tcl&tcl-version;</filename> source directory yet, as the next package
will need its internal headers.</para></important>

<para>Make a necessary symbolic link:</para>

<screen><userinput>ln -s tclsh8.4 /tools/bin/tclsh</userinput></screen>

</sect2>

</sect1>

